okay
good afternoon uh soundcheck
yep we can hear you all good okay okay
great uh good afternoon good evening
good morning
wherever you are um so today i want to
talk about uh lab
two a and b and this is really a
question and answering session
uh so feel free to interrupt any time uh
ask questions as much as you like
uh it's really uh this today's lecture
is really dedicated to
to your questions i summarized uh
many of the questions that came up or
either once or multiple times in the
email on the on the right side here of
this
on the board and hopefully
we'll get through them as i uh
walk through uh my solutions and
so i'm gonna basically cover four topics
related to the solution one i'm going to
first talk a little bit about voting
where like the voting code basically the
heartbeats
and then i'll talk about start and
commit
and this sort of follows i think the
suggestion that we made in the lab like
how you should get started like first
get go voting to work you know then get
heartbeats to work once you've got
heartbeat to work
you can actually start taking commands
from clients and then of course in the
end
you got to commit them to supply them on
the applied channel
so this is roughly the order that i'm
planning to go through but again feel
free to
interrupt at any particular time um
so before diving or looking at my
particular solutions or the solutions i
wrote this year
i want to talk a little bit about
debugging because that was the
probably the question that came up most
in the the um
in all your in the submission in the
submitted questions
so let me talk a little bit at a very
high level about debugging
um and this is a clearly a topic
that we could spend a whole lecture on
uh and
uh but i'm just gonna give you sort of
my high level approach that you know i
typically use
to address uh um you know to basically
pass the labs
and basically start to have i just
always start basically with running the
first test case
and of course if i have not written any
code i'm going to fail it
but at least now i have some you know
starting point where i can uh
start writing some code for and so you
know think about the first test case you
know start
writing uh look at the hints and write
some code
and while writing the code um yeah i
found it you know
convenient uh in this lab to or at least
the set of labs actually any lap in the
824 to
log all messages
and you know typically use you know that
dprinf
function in neutral logo and i'm pretty
pretty systematic of logging messages
and the reason that i do this uh uh
isn't for debugging purposes
um and so i'll write encode
run the test code fails write some code
to actually
try to pass the test case and uh
you know there's sort of two scenarios
you know one you know i pass
which then i immediately move on to the
next you know test case
or i fail um and
in that case um the first thing i do
is you know study the test case a little
bit more in detail and try to figure out
like what actually the test case is
trying to test
and you know the name of the test case
is often very suggestive of
like what the particular scenario or
what sort of sets of scenarios uh
the test case is trying to cover and
then i try to sort of formulate for
myself
and hypothesis is not why you know my
code might not
you know test that past that test case
um and so basically this is sort of a
moment of like reflection and thinking
uh and uh
to sort of like understand what the
constructing my head the scenario that
you know seems to fit the test case you
know think about my code
or whether that actually uh could be
your problem and once i have a sort of a
hypothesis then the next thing to do is
like study you know basically
try to confirm uh the hypothesis
uh whether you know my explanation of ry
and passing the test case might be
uh right or wrong and so to do that then
basically i study the log
so if i have a print you know a trace of
all the messages you know being sent to
the part of the protocol
i can look at the you know trace and you
know
to see you know where things go wrong
and sort of work where our back works
and
you know in that way sort of test and
refine
my hypothesis about why my code you know
might be wrong
um sometimes you know that might you
require uh
you know going back and basically run
the test datacast to basically get more
detailed
uh log output although uh
early on i tend to be very systematic
and you know don't really have to add
any uh print statements but
in some cases that's necessary um and
then
you know that gives me that more
information and i can sort of really
zoom in
on a scenario that you know my
code doesn't handle and once i sort of
have a hypothesis
i've verified with the log that there
are indeed that hypothesis seems to be
correct and that is a source or a bug in
my code
i can just go fix the code
and then run the test case and so
this is the iterative process run test
case
you fail study test case and study log
you know to formulate hypothesis
you know try to confirm the hypothesis
and then move on uh fix the code and
then move on to the next one
uh and that tends to be reasonable
systematic in this um
um and so for example often i will
actually write down in a
in some file and text file what my
hypothesis is and sort of try to collect
evidence
or counter evidence you know to either
prove or disprove my hypothesis i really
have a
good reason to fix the code
i think you know any approach that
basically is not very systematic you
know for example you know you think
something is not really 100 right
you know maybe you'll change that and
then see if you pass the test cases
uh tends to be not work that well i
think that takes a lot of time
because you might be wrong or and worse
you might be wrong and actually pass the
test case and think you're right
uh but it turned out like you know
basically you just shifted the bug from
one corner to another corner and it will
show up later again
so at a very high level uh this is the
sort of the approach
uh that i take um and you can see what
the
the key here is really logging the
messages
um any questions
or comments on
this this approach and i know it's a
very high level but at least give you
some sense about like how i approach
this
uh so the messages here are the rpc yes
all the rpcs
okay
okay so uh so some so do another quick
question yeah
go ahead sir so what's a good like
approach
for deciding the granularity of what to
log and what not to log
ah that's a very good exact great
question i was hoping someone was asking
um i tend to be logged things on the
pretty fine grain
uh glamour nelly and log everything and
uh then i use you know whatever i
pulled uh you know basically log in an
editor or uh
and you use unix utilities like crap to
basically pull out the things that are
actually really interested in
um and the reason i'm doing that is you
know just you know sometimes i don't
know about level granularity
uh i want to study something and uh
i don't want to go back and run the test
case again and i just collect everything
and then you know
filter the stuff out that i don't that i
care about and this brings me on
uh so some people write quite a bit of
infrastructure
for debugging uh the using the logs or
making logs more
easier to uh understand
i'm pretty primitive you know deep train
f and lots of information
although the i i structure my printouts
in
sort of a clear manner so like i can see
what the source what the destination is
and what the the rpc itself is and so i
can sort of
figure uh grab the filter very quickly
because all the text lines have a
particular format
some people spent quite a bit of time
building some infrastructure to
make it all easier i think one of the
tas the
jose when he took the class he actually
built some
software to make a decision with a
little bit of a pearl screen a python
script sex make it easier to actually
partial walks and
i thought it may be interesting to see
what he did
so i'm gonna stop sharing and then ask
jose to share
and maybe demo like how his uh log
uh structure works sorry uh i have a
follow-up question yeah
so how do you make the debugging prints
go into a log rather than
the standard out oh usually bigger than
to an an output to a
file so so do you just pipe everything
into a file
yes i pipe everything into a file got it
thank you
so i guess you just closed a screen and
jose go ahead
you can hear me again yeah i can hear
you okay awesome
um so yeah as i kind of agree you know a
bunch of points i i this
thing is very similar to like how franz
was describing them pretty aggressive
vloggers i
try to kind of just lock every single
event
that is going on and again i also have
like a kind of like a
format that i follow and what i'm gonna
show is kind of how
went about making my life easier going
and passing through the logs
the high level idea is i do very simple
structuring in go
and then i usually dump that the
standard out or to a file and then i use
python scripts to actually do the kind
of like all the coloring and the
structuring
since that's much easier to do in python
than in that it got
and so here's for example what i get out
of when i run
a testing go so when i enable the
verbosity
i just get like an output that looks
something like this
and here what i'm logging is kind of
like the number of milliseconds
is the first column and that's fairly
useful when you are trying to debug
timer events things like that or trying
to see how long
an rpc takes to fail then the second
column
is what i like to call topics they are
not levels because they are no
there's no hierarchy between them
they're just related to different events
incredi probably a lot of you by now
have
realized that in rather there's a lot of
things going on
like timers there's elections there's
like logs
things being applied communication with
the state machine
and all of those events happen with the
slightly different frequencies
so if you want to later just like select
some of them
or like decide to ignore the more versed
ones
it's really handy to just have like that
um
category there and then the third column
probably a lot of you have
something like this is which server like
who is saying this message because
without that it's really hard to
question about what is going on
and the rest is just like a free form
message that explains
kind of like what this message is about
and even though this is kind of just the
very initial test that you run the one
that
just tests that you can do an election
you actually have to like
read to follow what the logic is going
on here
so the way i made this easier and kind
of like first
approach and this is what i did when i
took the class was just
convert all the topics into colors like
most
modern terminals supports like wide
array of
color support and again by doing this in
python you can use some fantastic
libraries
that do all the heavy lifting so you
don't have to get in the
in the width of doing this and here i
just have included different events with
different colors
and as you get more familiar with the
colors for example here all the timers
events are in gray so
maybe they are easier to ignore or we
are looking for
when someone is voting we can look at
like xi'an which is related to votes
and that like will just encode visually
things that are
much easier to pick up like for example
here jello is when we enact
elect a new leader we still have to
decide
who is saying what and in order to do
that
what i incorporated just having
different columns
and again what i'm doing is just running
here like what i'm doing
just running this standard test script
and then just piping that
into like the the script that i wrote in
this case i'm specifying that i have
three columns because of like three
peers in this test case
and i have now decided to ignore the
timer
like the events with the timer topic
because there are like too many of them
and if time in logic is working we
probably don't need them to debug what
is going on
and if you look at this law compared to
what we the plaintext log
is fairly easy to see that what's going
on is like
three servers are starting the last one
is becoming a candidate the other two
are voting for that
it's becoming a leader as soon as it
gets the first vote and then it just
heartbeats through the rest of the test
and there's nothing else to to look at
here but now again when compared to
this it's kind of like an order of
magnitude easier to pick up what is
going on
and as you tweak that to your liking it
becomes more and more efficient
and as you move to like harder tests
a lot of you have probably have had to
look at the logs of the
backup test in the 2b lab
there will be lots and lots of events
going on and even
kind of even if you love what you need
it might become like a daunting task
going through like thousands of lines of
vlogs just searching for the point
of failure and trying to reason of
what's going on
again if we look just like make this
a kind of like a simpler format to
visualize
we can quickly see what's going on we
just have like
five different servers that are starting
the first one is becoming a candidate
the other ones are voting for it
becoming a leader
and by looking at the different columns
we can see for example all
like purple encodes whenever something
is committed or applied so we can see
that
a new entry is received and
these these servers are receiving it and
because
backup 2 has like a very very bold log
i have and a lot of drop rpcs i'm also
ignoring
those topics here and as the test goes
on
we're gonna start reasoning about what's
going on it's also fairly helpful
to just have like some print statements
or like the bug statements in the test
code you
just can modify there to know what the
test is doing for example here the test
detects
that the first server seo is the leader
and then this connects s2 through s4
which are like this
3 on the right side and that's pretty
much what happens
we just get like a stream of entries
that won't be committed because there's
only two servers
that can talk to each other and then
after a while
we see that the first two are now
disconnected and the
the three on the right are reconnected
and now
they can form a majority and that's what
we will see like the
the last one becomes a candidate
achieves a majority
and kind of repeatedly we see this color
pattern of like green
and purple kind of like this staircase
signifying that oh yeah it's
receiving an entry and propagating it
through the other servers and the
disconnected servers here convert into a
candidate
and hopefully i've convinced you by now
by just
slightly changing the the presentation
of your logs kind of like the
mental effort to like go through them
can significantly decrease
and even though this is like really
fancy there's
not a lot of like fancy code going on i
just use
some of the self python libraries mainly
reads
and kind of all fits in about like a
hundred lines of
python script and if you're interested i
wrote like a blog post that will be
linking on the website on piazza about
kind of like the these steps to build a
tool like this and kind of how
it all fit together so like some like
design decisions
related to that and if anyone has like
any questions
specific to this happy to answer them
any questions for jose um yeah i have a
question more about like general
logging so i know that i had some bugs
that when i put in the logging they were
no longer there
um because of some timing issue
or perhaps a concurrency issue so what
what do we do then
uh okay so there's a couple things i do
uh first of all
one reason i log it's sort of a fine
grain always at the same level of
granularity
and the fine-grained levelity so that i
always have a trace with everything
and i generally don't have to go back
the other
thing to do is i do run the test many
many many times and
they save all logs and then once i hit
the wrong one
once i hit a bug then you know i study
that particular log
and so for example if i run something
overnight i just you know save all the
logs from all the runs overnight and
then
grab the one that narrow field
any further questions on the topic of
logging
okay good let me uh proceed uh
but before again you know looking at
code i want to talk a little bit about
the structure
uh that my particular solution has and
this is definitely not the only
structure
you can do it in many many different
ways and you're you're free to actually
do it in many different ways
and the fact that every year when i
teach class you know i actually
try to rewrite write implement the labs
again
and often experiment with you know
different types of ways of implementing
it
uh so the one i'll share you uh with you
today
is one that i wrote over iap you know
sort of getting ready
for a24 uh and then it has the following
structure
it's a pretty standard structure uh you
know like so let me just draw a box
you know signifying the raft library
uh you know there's two basically
api calls grade one start to sort of
initiate
um uh in append entries and
to initiate a logging operation in one
to actually
uh and output you know that those come
through the applied channel
um and then uh in you know the one
documentation i'll be showing you how
basically
one essentially one structure you know
the raft structure
that basically has all the state of the
uh
of the ref library you know the all the
sort of variables that are in the figure
two
and basically i have one lock on this
guy
and uh basically all my uh so i use
quite coarse grained locking you know my
rpc handlers all my
uh you know start uh take basically just
one lock
uh do whatever the stuff they need to be
do do and then
release the lock um so there's a couple
frets
that's sort of running around one of
course is the ticker threat you know
that we sort of
gave you uh and you know that just wait
as i'll show you in a second that will
wait for you know some number of
milliseconds
you know 50 milliseconds and then
run and then check you know periodically
if any uh timeout election time
has gone off and then does whatever
needs to be done
uh i have one fret dedicated to writing
on the apply channel
and so no other thread actually arrives
to the apply channel there's only a
single one
and it basically sleeps on a condition
variable
and so when for example a new account
entry comes in from the
leader and the commit uh
index goes up then you know the thread
that thread will
uh wake up on the signal on the
condition variable that will wake up the
thread that actually
looks at the applied that writes in the
applied channel it will grab whatever
you know entries out of the log and you
know stick them on the apply channel
um and uh so
that's one and the reason i have a
single thread is that of course you
can't hold locks
while riding across the applied channel
at least you know might
cause you some problems later um and so
i just have a single thread that
actually arrives on the
applied channel then uh
the there's of course you know number of
things coming in from the outside you
know require
messages coming in and of course each
message or each rpc you know starts its
own thread so like go
well the rpc library will basically
start a thread for every incoming
message
and basically the way i process every
incoming messages
the first thing it grabs the log on the
route structure it reads and writes you
know the graph structure and then when
it's done
it releases the the log and maybe uh
lock and maybe in between it will uh
update you know or
signal on the condition variable too
then you know of course like start
itself you know runs on the particular
fret
so it jumps into the raft library you
know does the same thing you know
acquire the lock
and then let me uh
you know appended to the the log in the
log structure
and then sends off you know the center
piece the append rpcs
and uh since i want to do the append
rpcs in parallel
um basically what the way it works is
that you know for every
rpc i start a separate thread
and that art and that thread actually is
responsible for you know
sending it reserving the response and
in the response you know doing any
updating that is necessary to the wrath
structure so
the response handler or when the
response comes in uh you know we'll grab
the
raft lock and then do whatever update
netflix here to the raft state and then
release the lock
so uh so there's a bunch of threads
quite a number of threads that can be
running around correct because our
messaging may be late you know and so
there may be many many many
uh threads here and there might be you
know multiple starts
there might be start out standing
instead of maybe multiple threads there
and of course the ticker you know also
will start
may send heartbeats and those art beats
you know again you know turn into
a separate thread but all those threads
are basically
serialized by the raft lock or my raft
lock serializers
and so when i create print log messages
you know of course that is inside you
know
done while holding the raft lock and
since you know sort of every fret runs
one by one
uh you know all the log messages over
make a lot of sense you know they
they're all serialized too uh
similarly i make our c handlers
atomic or serialized
uh so no fine grain locking uh and that
helps and i'll talk about it in a in a
second
and then the only sort of thing that you
know you that you have to be a little
bit careful with if you do sort of this
coarse grained walking
is that you can get into deadlocks and
particularly you can have a deadlock if
you hold blocks across rpc's and so
i never hold no locks across rpcs
and that is partially achieved you're as
it is as
achieved as a side effect of really
starting a new thread for every rpc
so that's sort of the overall structure
uh
of you know by this particular solution
that i'll share in a second with you
again other structures are possible but
hopefully this gives you some some ideas
any questions about this
what were the threads on the right on
the right these guys
yeah uh those are the incoming messages
so like a paint rpc a penta rpc
a request or a vote request like i think
the only two
so i also have a question
what's the is there a benefit of having
a single thread
uh sleeping on the condition variable
and then
having only that thread uh a thread
sending to apply channel
compared to having each rpc thread
uh sent to the applied channel uh well
everything has to go in order from the
apply channel correct
so the whole log that you made but since
in the wrath structure has to be
sent on the applied channel exactly in
order as the entries are in the log
and so that's just more easier to do i
find it easier to do with a single
thread because that thread basically
goes through the wrath log and just
sticks from there one by one the entries
on to the
apply channel and there's no further
coordination necessary
that makes sense okay yeah so like
we all you know this goes like
up into the surface that actually uses
the raft library
okay so one more word about uh
just a fine grained uh versus coarse
grained
uh some of you uh like a common mistake
uh early on you know when you haven't
done that much you know
apparel programming uh you might like
you know
if you have your ipc struct
you know maybe you have like the log and
some other fields
and you know some people or sometimes
you know there's a temptation
or not unreasonable you also have
multiple locks
so instead of having a single
lock or even half a single one
but not hold it for a long time
and um and i think in general
that minds reasoning about the code a
little bit hard uh so
uh so example a common thing that you
know that you might do
then it's like if you have an rpc
handler like like this some request
handler
you know whatever args reply
i'm just sketching this out you know and
you might you know something you might
do like you know whatever you walk
um do something you know with arguments
maybe you know update some state
you know in the graph structure then do
a new unlock
then maybe do some other stuff that is
not maybe directly related to the
wrath structure and then basically maybe
grab the log again
and then you know whatever update and
read maybe the wrath structure again and
then the
unlock and all you're sort of in a
single
rpc handler and
just as a thought exercise you know what
is risky about this
sort of style of fine grade walking no
i know this is a little bit artificial
but you know there's a reasonable common
uh uh sort of early mistake that you
know you might make
you have to like recheck your
assumptions before
locking again every time right yeah you
know basically
this executes atomically this executes
atomically
but lots of things can happen in between
right so for example new rpcs might have
been coming in
and they might be running two and they
might actually have been updating the
graphs struct or draft state between you
know these two critical sections
between one and two uh and so by the
time you know to
the you start running critical section
two the wrath structure might be
completely different
and make completely different content
and uh so to avoid you know those kind
of situations
uh you know my general approach is to
basically you know basically have this
to be
one critical one critical section so i
don't have to recheck
in any i don't have to reset the state
at the new when the second uh
critical section starts does that make
sense
and this problem shows up in different
you know
or this problem can show up in sort of
different uh fashion in different ways
uh but any sort of underlying problem is
always the same you know if you do a lot
of fine-grained blocking you're going to
have
additional interleavings that you have
to consider
and make sure that you don't have uh
incorrect
uh interleavings that result in
incorrect uh
behavior
i want to ask is it but it's not
possible to
avoid rechecking conditions after you
send an rpc
right inside the rpc thread
uh yeah you you cannot hold the lock
while sending correct so like you should
not
you know here you should not call
whatever you know
send our pc uh because you can't do that
while holding a lock because they can
easily result in deadlock correct you
holding the lock you send it to a peer
and rpc
while still holding the lock the peer
actually sends an rpc to you
uh but you're holding you know the the
your the leader already holds the lock
on the rx structure so the response
cannot be
uh processed and maybe you know the two
are interdependent
and then you have a deadlock
one thing that's worth noting is um
something i saw some people doing
is that they spin off a thread they have
to send an rpc
in that thread they take the lock to
prepare the arguments for the rbc
and then they send the rpc without block
and you can do that but it's often
um there's often fewer interleavings if
you generate the arguments for the rpc
before you split off the thread that
actually uh sends it
good point we'll see we'll show this
will show up in a second actually and
but doesn't that cause so sometimes it's
actually depending on the implementation
i think it's beneficial for
other rpcs to see the changes like um
for example if other rpcs made progress
you want to start off from the most
recent last log index
uh perhaps you know
it depends on exactly you know what you
do uh
like how your implementation works uh
i i don't do that at least i don't think
i do what you're
suggesting when i send an rpc to all the
peers all the peers are going to get
exactly the same arguments
and no changes in between
okay good uh so okay let me then uh
talk a little bit about the uh
implementation uh can people read
uh can people read the screen sorry i
will follow
yeah uh so i think you mentioned that we
shouldn't lock around sending
things over the ply channel uh
yes uh although i'm let me
you know it's risky uh because like
while you're holding the lock
correct and you send on the apply
channel you might also block i'm sending
on the apply channel because
the service you know must the other site
must be reading correct before you're in
block
of course if you have buffered and
unbuffered you know that changes a
little bit but let's say we have
not a buffer channel but just a an
unbuffered channel
and so the reader
if there's no reader then this writer
will block
and maybe holding the lock and that
might be
you know may lead to problems later and
lead to deadlocks
um on that
um isn't this all right like like the
applied channel will never
like the client who's calling raft
won't ever hold the lock right they're
like ah
you don't not not true actually here's
our sort of
service quick sitting on top calling
start
and reading from the apply channel
uh but it's called start and start is
because you know depending on how you do
it you know start as a thread you know
jumps into with that thread into the
raft library and
at least in my implementation the first
thing that the start function does is
actually wrap the raft lock
and it can't grab the lock raft lock if
it actually
the the apply thread is already hauling
it's trying to get something on the
applied channel
but the service now won't read from the
applied channel depending on how you set
it up
but i mean as you're saying there is a
risk here you just got to be a little
bit careful
so would the solution be just to like
create a new thread
i yes there's all kinds of possible
solutions here i'm just like
warning you that you know they're
alerting you that you have to think a
little bit about how you arrange
this
okay what isn't is that
me using a single thread not sufficient
because the thread that
puts it onto the ply channel will still
be looking at date
right so won't it still need to acquire
the lock
okay so okay let me back off in here but
it's easier to see that there are
deadlocks here correct
like if you're in the apply channel
you're not reading from the apply
channel because you're
causing you're calling start like maybe
again because and start can run
because the guy actually don't hold the
lock but he can't actually unlock
because he can't write to the fly
channel because there's no reader
you know there's easy to construct
scenarios where you can get into
deadlocks of course you can avoid all
these deadlocks
that's the whole goal and one way to
avoiding these deadlocks is actually not
to hold the lock while rewriting on the
channel
there are other ways of doing it too
i just i'm telling you in my
implementation you know i find it
convenient not to have
uh the whole box while riding on a
channel i think in general it's bad
practice
okay back to code
okay good so uh i'm going to show you
one particular implementation and again
uh you know this is an invitation that i
wrote over
january to get ready for the class so
there's nothing particularly special
about it
uh purely for myself and i'm sure
you know there are things about uh you
know that you were to violently object
to
uh but you know it gives you a sense you
know what i did so here i go
uh so in terms of the rash structure i i
basically you know
copy figure two uh as you will see in
the code there's going to be a lot of
figure two in the code
uh and you know the here is the the main
thing that probably the main thing to
point out is like here's the big mutex
and this is the wrath lock that
my code will acquire or release all over
the place but in a very course great
and the rest is just you know exactly as
you expect you know the persistence day
the volatile state the leader stage and
some snapshot state i won't talk much
about snapchat at all since you know
that's what we do for
friday um and that's
basically it uh then uh the interesting
i'm just going to go bottom off sort of
like in the beginning
you know what happens so at some point
the tester uh
uh the tester will uh
call make right and uh here's my uh
basically the the make uh call
it constructs you know the raf state uh
you know apply channel the condition
variable that i mentioned
uh it sets itself to a follower it's an
election timeout
and i'll talk about that in a second you
know initially some other parts
you know make an empty log and uh then
basically forks have two
uh go routines one is the applier that's
the
the fret that actually arrives on the
applied channel and then i got my the
ticker that we basically gave you
uh to uh that basically runs the ticker
code
um so nothing particularly exciting
going on here
so let's look at the ticker code
some people ask you know should you
structure everything in a single file
multiple files of course it's all up to
you what actually is most convenient for
you to actually you know find your code
in this case
i structured in multiple files and a
half basically vodogo
deals with all the election part
so let's look at the ticker uh
so the ticker basically runs every 50
milliseconds
and uh it calls this function tick and
the function tick is
like right up here uh it grips you know
you'll see that
all over the place it grabs the raft
lock
calls the user's defer to make sure that
like no matter where
i leave the function the lock actually
will be released
um and then you know checks what it is
the leader
uh and if it's a leader does one thing
it's not a leader that means that's a
follower
and it just checks whether actually the
election time
has passed and so basically the way i
compute that is like i get the current
time
uh and see if the current time is
actually past the
uh if now is now past the uh election
time
and if that is the case i'll start the
election and
uh or well first i'll set the election
time out again
uh as required by figure two and then
they'll start the election
in terms of setting the election
timeouts like the the first thing you
know the way
uh i do it you know i the election
timeout is set to one second which is
sort of i got from
uh i can hold on a second on the l
there's a
good reason uh from the chat the
the uh the selection diameter is one
second
and then of course you know you need to
randomize you know the
appears across the interval and i use an
interval from 0 to 300 milliseconds
and i add that to the election timeout
and so basically every peer
likely has to have has a slightly
different election time out
and so uh they will call uh take at
different spec
stages and you know with a bit of luck
uh only one or a few
actually will start the election i i
have a question
so you're only like
checking every like 50 milliseconds
right doesn't that lead to like
contested like elections
like because you're essentially like it
doesn't this like limit
like you know you technically can
like get for anywhere from three to like
zero to three hundred right like no i
could get from one second
to 300 from one second to any value
between
1000 milliseconds and 1300 milliseconds
right so
um but at the end of the day like
because you're like
only checking every 50 milliseconds
doesn't that just give it like
right it gives us more coarse grain but
it's good enough okay
uh i mean basically two constraints here
correct you know
you don't want to be too slow and uh
because that
means that you're takes a long time
before you start a new election and you
don't want to be too
fast because you know then you start too
many elections and you need to allow for
some time for an election
to lose some you know some votes may get
delayed
and you don't want to restart it before
you know you have
before the candidate has a chance to
sort of do a couple rounds of
communication with the followers
okay so somebody here people are
speculating about my capital l
uh this was just an experiment you know
for uh
this implementation i followed the
convention and i probably broke it in
some places but i followed the
conception that
if uh the caller the kali assumes that
the lock
is held then i put a capital l behind
the function
so start election assumes that the
caller actually has required the lock
and basically any function that starts
with an l has that particular you know
assumes that convention and so this is
purely
a coding prevention for myself and i
thought it was sort of interesting to
try that out for this implementation
and not always do that but i just did it
in this one
any questions or should we look at the
election part
okay well then let's look at the
election part and
you'll see uh here start election so you
know it doesn't require a lock right
because i assume a lot of the
uh caller holds it and basically just
follows figure two
you know so first you know the rule is
you have to increment the current term
by one so i do that i set the state to
candidate
and also uh dictated by figure two
basically
uh i record uh that i voted for myself
this is also part of figure two
uh and then you know this is for lab c
you know to see you already know
that like whenever you change basically
state that should be persisted
you have to persist as right afters and
so
so that's it and basically here you see
my debugging messages
uh like you know what jose says you know
i always have to source at the beginning
and this you know simplifies my life and
i have a bunch of other sort of
uh i don't have a perl script or a
python script as nicely as jose but i
have a bunch of sort of
unique scripts that i use to parse the
log and
print and process it um and then you
know we
call request votes and request closes
right up here
uh and we'll see in a second you know
how this is all gonna work out but
basically
it has a cell set you know we construct
the arguments once
you know up front and
let me so let's look at the recursive
arguments
uh and basically your your data here and
you know basically it contains exactly
uh you know what you know basically
figure two says that you contain the
term the candidate id
the last log index and the last log term
uh
and sustain struck in i one thing maybe
worth pointing out is i do
try to write these string functions that
you know allow
uh go you know when you're typing
percent v you know we'll call that
string function on destruct
and so that allows you to format you
know the
uh the structure the request in a sort
of a nice way
and again that helps with me that helps
me processing my log
and so basically every request argument
that i have i
print in one standard way and again to
simplify log processing
okay back to starting elections so
multiple
uh followers who start at the same time
you know they become uh one of them is
hopefully starts first it becomes
candidate and it does request votes
and here i construct you know the
arguments i put the current term in here
it was going to be one if this is the
first time for the election you know who
i am
what my last log index is you know which
presumably is
zero uh or one whatever the uh
yeah it's going to be zero i guess and
then uh
the uh term in that entry which is the
term zero uh because you know what we're
doing correct is we're running an
election for one
and we need to show what the previous
ones were
okay so then here this is sort of my
standard way of you know sending our pcs
i just go for all the peers skipping
myself
uh of course i have to count that i
voted for myself so i said the number of
votes to one
and then i basically fork off an art and
fred that basically is going to do
actually the sending the rpc to each
individual peer
the first argument is the peer to which
the rpc is sent they all get the same
arguments
and also pass in the address of the
votes so they can
have a shared vote count
any questions about this so
for request votes the the lock is being
held
and then you're sending the yeah so rpc
yeah so in uh request code here is the
lock actually held
inside of this function no right because
it's a new thread
yeah it's a difference it doesn't hold
the lock and you see my naming
convention hints at that because it
doesn't have an l there
okay so reuse request votes and the
request folds when it actually
starts running it has no locks because
only the
you know the parent held the lock and
this guy this thread actually hasn't
acquired the lock yet
right so it does not have lock
oh so yeah so so basically one fret runs
for
each of these request codes for each
peer it allocates a reply structure and
then basically it sends off you know the
rpc right and this is all done without
holding the lock
and then at some point we get a response
back
and then at that point in the response
handler i grab the log right at the
beginning
and do whatever response handling that
is necessary
and as you can see yeah all right i you
said
earlier that you shouldn't hold the lock
when you're doing like uh um
when you're doing a rpc call you mean
like basically it's okay to
it's okay for the rpc call itself in the
rpc call to do to hold a lock but not
like while you're calling
yeah no not across this like why you're
sitting
sending it over to network but it's okay
if you're doing it within the rpc
well even the reply handler like think
about this is like basically the reply
handler running
like so the response came back and now
there's a reply and now you have to
process the reply
no i'm talking about like say in the
request vote like the capital r
requests capital v votes that's okay to
hold locks
in there at least right where you want
to hold watch i
am actually like so like capsule request
votes here yeah that's what i'm talking
about
this one no like the function here
so it's request vote but it's uh i think
it's
capsule r yeah
so like you probably have a method right
it's the rpc call i think it means the
rpc on the receiver side
okay yeah seriously yeah yeah we'll look
at it in a second of course that will
you know it runs on the completely you
know way to think about it
it runs on a totally different machine
there we go there you go yeah yeah
absolutely so so basically it's two
places where i hold the lock like in the
handler
in the request handler and in the reply
okay thank you sorry sorry for being
confused
i'm glad we clarified that um okay so
uh grab block then put a print statement
in the log so that i can know what later
on i can study it
and then you know of course you know the
basic checks you know that you know
you're uh actually figure 2 doesn't
really say much about it
but you know this is the rule that
applies to all
servers correct if the term is bigger
then the reply term is better than the
current term
then uh you gotta switch to the follower
state
and uh to the term of the uh
the person that responded to you so
we'll look at that in a second
uh so that basically you know if this
was the candidate
and it was talking to a peer that
actually was in a higher term and
basically backs off
and becomes a follower
um okay so uh if
you know the follower responded saying
that i'm granting you my vote
then i increment you know numerous votes
the shared vote guide by one
it's just totally safe to do correct
because you know i'm holding the raft
lock
and so this is a serialized so multiple
the
thing that will happen correct is
multiple responses will come back
they may run in parallel but they will
be serialized because of the raft lock
so add up the votes if the vote is
longer than the
you know if i have a majority of the
votes then
and if i'm still in the same term as the
start when i started out actually uh
running the election
then i'm going to become a leader and
i'll send out you know the first round
of heartbeats which i'll look in in a
second
so i want to look at two things let's
see what become leader is
become leader you know it's right up
here uh you know has capital l
because it's you know already holds a
lock it basically sets the state
to the leader state um and it
initializes the next index
and the next index as i said in the last
lecture is basically a guess and it's an
optimistic guess
and uh you know i just set it to
whatever my last index is plus one
so basically i'm assuming that all the
followers are up to date
and if they're not you know we'll see
later they will back off
okay i'll back off uh
on the append entry sorry i reply
okay good all right so that's become
leader uh
let me look at new term
uh it's a new term is nothing really you
know too exciting it basically says i
can go go to the next
uh term that is supplied by the
uh caller uh i said voted for to minus
one because you know i haven't voted yet
in this term and i change to
my state to follower because this is you
know state that needs to be persistent i
call persist
okay so this is sort of the candidate
site and now we want to look at the
follower site or perhaps another
candidate that's also running an
election in uh in parallel
so uh so here's the request vote handler
and this is sort of running so this is
the piece of code that runs on the other
machine
if you will correct where uh what i just
was confused about a little bit
uh in answering that question and you
know you just
see the first thing it does uh this is a
revoked by the rpc library system
correct and
with its own thread and the first thing
it does it actually grabs the lock on
the
raft structure and then basically you
know this follows
literally the rules uh figure two you
know this is the rule for all servers
correct if the uh term the argument
determine the argument is higher than my
current term
then i should switch you know to this
new term uh
and uh that's it uh
then here's sort of the you know the
interesting piece correct this is all
related to figure 8c
what it means to be or not hc figure
seven
uh what it means to be up to date right
you can only become a leader
if you're up to date uh so i compute you
know the
up to date function uh and uh
and that's basically based on the last
index or in the term in the last index
and so it says up to date is uh if my
of our the term in the arguments is
equal to my term
in the uh
the call the caller the candidate has a
last login that is equal or higher to my
index
so basically to turn to equal the longer
the log should win
um and or uh if
you know the candidate x is in higher
term period then he always wins
the candidate wins so that means to be
up to date so compute up to date
and then basically go through the
different cases if the term is smaller
than the current term
that means that the caller is behind
and so i vote granted to false and then
in the other case if i haven't voted
uh or i voted you know already voted for
this candidate
and you know uh the candidate is up to
date
then i get my vote and
and reset the election timeout
so why why is this this second case here
the or the r voted for is rx candidate
id
because um the the candidate may resend
uh maybe their pc was delayed yeah we're
delayed or actually never made it right
and so
uh you know this is basically checking
uh so this allows me to vote twice for
the same candidate
but i can't vote for any other candidate
okay
so just to double check the logic uh
here so
if we have the candidate has a term that
is bigger than the current term
uh we obviously have to convert the
follower and update the term to the term
of the candidate
but we don't automatically grant them
vote
unless uh their log is at least is up to
date
i'm also wondering is voted for ever
reset to minus one
yep when they go to new term ever always
i knew said it always whenever you go to
the new term
oh okay i said to the only one it's one
place where this happens
any questions
so this gives you probably a reasonable
good sense about the overall structure
and basically
everything else follows sort of roughly
the same structure
and so let's go back and uh go here so
let's see
you know let's assume this guy actually
the leader or the candidate wins the
election
uh so it started the election let me go
trades back so we started the election
uh we requested the votes uh
and we won the election and we became
the leader
and then the first thing that the figure
2 tells you to do is like send a
heartbeat to every
uh peer
and so basically this is you know going
to be the standard code for sending a
pants
in fact you know the heartbeat code is
identical to this
append entry code except you know the
heartbeats often will may have a null
entry or no entries in the log that is
being sent to the
followers
okay so send the pens follows the same
structure as in votes
you know go cycle over all the peers and
if appears not equal to me
then basically send it to the pen
uh yeah and so here is the centipede
um and uh you know basically
we're keeping track correct of who what
the the next
uh log entry that the peer uh should
have
you know we initialize it to an
optimistic guest in equal drawers
so basically in this case there's gonna
be no log entries that are going to be
sent
so i can sort of skip all this stuff for
now and we'll come back to it when we're
looking actually
at start i fill in the append entries
arguments
and we could look at the structure if
you'd like to but you know it is exactly
as in figure two
uh maybe the only thing that is a little
bit
careful you've got to be a little bit
careful about is um
i allocate a slice you know to hold the
entries
that need to be sent in this particular
case the number of entries is zero
right uh because we're assuming that
everybody is up to date
and then i copy you know the uh part
from the
slices from the log in the raw structure
to the
uh to the entries in the arguments
uh and so i have really my own copy at
this point
of the log uh there's a here a little
bit of a danger correct that like slices
share memory
so this is why the copy needs to happen
so i copy the entries out of the wrath
structure that i hold the logon into my
private argument
structure and
once that is done basically i send you
know i started over function
i'll go and go routine for every peer
and in that you know go function
in that function uh i send the rpc
and then in the reply handler you know i
grab the log there's the reply handler
of the rpc i grab the log and then
process the reply
the append reply
does this all make sense
uh yeah does just yeah go ahead or maybe
one by one
one little question yeah so in center
pins l
we have uh we have the loop in which we
call rf.sendapendo
and we assume that lock is held through
that call but we do the you know any
thread
at which point uh the thread let's go
for the lock right
okay so like there's an outer loop
correct where somebody in the caller
holds the lock and basically it calls
you send a pin
l you know n times correct where n is
the number appears minus one
and for every one of them uh for every
iteration of that loop
you know we're going to create a new go
function that go function runs without
holding the locks right so it will send
its rpc without holding the locks and at
the same time a new go function might be
started by the caller
that actually also is going to send rpc
although send rpc is going parallel to
the followers
the followers respond and so all the
responses come back in
uh that will so that will return you
know when a follower response comes in
that returns from send rpc and then that
point i'll grab block you know the
process to reply
now if if the caller was still busy
sending uh our rpc's to the followers
then basically you know the reply
handler will block correct
until the uh caller is done sending all
the rpcs
yeah so my question was uh i i
assumed why that happens is because you
had a we had a differ
rf.lock like unlock that's why it
doesn't hold the lock when it
starts a new thread right or is that
just
when you start fret you don't hold any
locks
yeah yeah like whatever it is even if we
don't have like
uh that like even if we tried to hold
the lock right before the goku
it wouldn't hold it that's right yeah
yeah correct okay
i was sort of follow so in the uh
if okay block uh where's the defer being
like called from
from the return statement of that method
and when this block exits
when this block exits then the the new
unlock will be called
so the deferred the defer is called and
when the surrounding
basic block exits oh not just return
statements
not just return statements that's
correct okay
cool yeah it's cool it's very handy can
you repeat that so when does the
difference
like defer is called like so when this
defer or this unlock
runs when this basic block exits
or returns or goes out whatever terminal
you want to run so if you return from
this basic block
this unlock will happen
um sorry why um you need to check if the
current term is still
the term that you thought you were in
because some requests
can be slow and you might receive a
response
yeah after a long time yep yeah okay
so here there's all let's look at
process append reply i think this is
what you're asking like what does it do
uh and we haven't looked at it yet so we
can look at it
uh and actually it is more complicated
uh
it follows you know the general rule for
all service if the reply term is bigger
than my current term then you know you i
can switch to becoming a follower
and you know go into a new term if it is
actually equal to my term correct this
is what you were asking
uh like the if i if the reply comes in
in the same term that i send it in
you know my arcs term then i gonna do uh
i have a different function that
actually does all the processing
assuming that at least the terms are
matching
oh sorry sorry i meant in the leader
when it receives a response you have
you had like a check for the timers yeah
i'm basically having here too it's like
the same check here
i see i see okay
uh okay so you know basically this is
then the
uh append entries
reply code like so what the handler that
runs in response to a reply
we know that the term matches and
we check reply success uh if reply
success you know we
update our match indexes and
uh and next index
following exactly the rules of figure
two
uh if there's a conflict valid you know
then you know i process the conflict and
so this is the piece of code that's
going to deal with like backing off fast
um and uh
and in the if there's no conflict
information available then i just back
off by one
okay is it a quick question about how we
back off by one
um is it not problem that
i was i was thinking about this and i i
think it wasn't true but i
hadn't fully convinced myself um but
isn't it possible that rf dot next index
peer
changed between when we sent it and when
we're
processing this response yeah you've got
problematic
to decrement kind of using a potential a
value that's potentially changed
uh probably not great because i think
your risk
your concern is valid uh because
certainly you know the rap structure
might have completely changed
by the time this response comes in uh
and in fact you know
uh although unlikely of course because
this is the response to the same peer
correct
um
so there's a you know but i might have
multiple rpcs outstanding to that
particular peer
and so those reply handlers you know
might run in some order
um so i have a question so why do we
decrement the next index by one if
there's no conflict
um i think this
has to do that maybe at some point i
hadn't implemented conflict uh
the conflict term stuff yet
i i don't remember whether this actually
is essential or not
okay uh you know of course like you i've
changed my code multiple times and
you know as i go along implementing the
in response to the test
i don't think there's harm in it you
know the only downside could be that i
may send too many uh
entries on the rpc or send more entries
in the rpc that i really have to
on the next depend okay
okay any questions
okay good let me talk a little bit about
the
commit so we might have learned correct
that the follower actually has uh
has committed some entries that we
didn't know before and the match index
is updated
and so so basically i always check
after you know processing reply whether
i should
advance you know the commit point
uh and this is basically the you know
the
this code corresponds to the last bullet
of the leaders in figure two
uh and literally implements what
actually is supposed to be happening
there
um and probably the only thing that is
sort of interesting in here
is this particular point
and this has to do with figure eight
regular the scenario is that you're a
leader is not allowed to commit
a previous term unless at least has
committed one
entry in its current term and so this is
this is exactly that one check that is
described as section 5.4 uh
it checks whether the current log entry
uh
that i want about to be in the entry
that i'm about to commit
whether that actually has a term that's
different than the current term and if
that's the case i just skip it
now happens if there's another log entry
following that term
in my term for which i have a majority
of the votes
then i'll basically commit that newer
one
and then automatically it will also
commit the previous one
so that's that figure eight problem
and then i signaled the applier
and the applier you know may run
if there's actually you know let's look
at the
applier threat uh here's the applier for
that
i signally apply for it to wake it up
when uh
maybe advance the commit point uh
it has a last applied first graph's log
has last applied
and then you know basically go through
here and
uh dusty check you know that is the rule
for all servers
you know when you commit something and
it just you know follows that rule and
then basically writes something to the
applied channel and as you can see here
i
unlock before writing to the applied
channel and
uh then if there's nothing anymore to
uh nothing more to
supply in the earth on the applied
channel i just do a weight on the
condition variable
and again different ways of writing this
but this is the way i happen to do it so
why are you using uh
broadcast uh why instead of signal yeah
no
no good reason okay because there's only
one
there's only one listener yeah there's
no harm you know broadcast signal will
in this case do exactly the same thing
um for the applier yeah
um so i using a condition variable and
it seems like
like probably natural to do that is
there any disadvantage to doing it
um on it like on sleeping like sleeping
for a time interval then
like you know matching everything
together
um i i i
i dislike code with random sleeps in
them
i think it was generally a bad style of
writing code
um and so i don't do that
yeah the only place where i do sleep is
in the ticker
that's it and that's the way place where
you have to so otherwise
i should never do that actually that's
is there any disadvantage to doing it
with the ticker
sorry is there any any disadvantage of
like checking and like
like updating like alongside with the
ticker right like you have yeah
there's you could do that uh i find that
harder to reason about
i i'd like to you know so like if one
thread which charges this one thing and
then the ticker fred in one thing
uh you know i think there are people
that basically do everything in the
ticker
thread and you know one
for me is hard to reason about but
that's
more a question of you know personal
taste than anything
thanks
okay
any further questions
okay i want to quickly look then at uh
start because basically there's nothing
really left to discuss anymore you know
we talked basically about voting we
talked about appending
uh i haven't really discussed exactly
what happens on the follower site when
it gets in a
pen request but
basically follows figure two and if we
have time left we can look at that too
uh here's the start command
uh so this is like the service calls
this to append or an entry to
the log and uh you know immediately
grabs the log
checks whether we're still deleted if
not we'll return false
otherwise we create an entry and we
append it to the log
and lock has to be persistent so we're
persisted and then we send the applies
and this is exactly the same or we sent
the appends and this is exactly the same
code as the heartbeats
except in unlike in the heartbeats you
know most likely now it's going to
actually send the entry
uh that is uh that just has been
appended to the log
okay um
you noticed you know that probably many
places have this log
dot last index or log that something and
that's because like sort of extracted
the log away
into its own structure
um and here's the log actually it has
just a log of entries a slice of entries
and
the index zero and this is really for
part two d
uh where basically you're going to cut
up the beginning of the log
the sort of global log and you need to
keep track but the
index you need to keep track of what the
index is of the first entry that
actually you have recorded in your log
and you know to hide most of those
details away you know basically have uh
uh abstracted that way in this uh file
log.go
and there are basically functions for
appending you know to get the start of
the log you know to cut the end to cut
the cut to start
you know to get the slice out of it get
the last index get the particular entry
or get the last entry
uh and that might be convenient for 2d
although there's many other ways of
doing it
okay let me go back for a second to sort
of some of the questions that people
asked
and uh i think hopefully i have answered
many of them by now
uh but if not um
uh let me just review and quickly go
through them
uh so i think we talked quite
extensively about the election timeout
you know how to compute it how to check
where the timeline is passed
um uh the
uh there was a question about always
when receiving a message from leader
you know i only reset it when i receive
a message from the leader that actually
is in my current term
or in my new term if i become a follower
but not you know for somebody that's
behind in terms of terms
uh when to send the append entries and
under different ways of doing it
you can do it only in the heartbeats you
know some people have done that
uh you can do so never send anything in
start that's like i showed me
as i showed in the code uh or sometimes
you people do also do it in the response
if for example the follower is behind
you know send immediately the
remaining entries uh i don't do that
uh i never send anything in response
although i had an implementation that
does that
uh the risk is that i think you swamped
the follower in later
laps or in uh you know tests for 2c and
2d
um you in only
some people i think just send rp entries
only in the heartbeat so that means like
every
uh you know if you you're not allowed to
send a heartbeat more than ten times a
second
uh in the our rules of the game for the
laughs
so that means that you were gonna send
uh our pen entries once every
you know 100 milliseconds or maybe a
little bit faster
that may run into problems in lab
3 where we actually see if you make
fast enough progress
so basically i do it in the heartbeats
and i do it in start
i think we talked quite extensively
about debugging i've talked a bunch
about code organization
i think we talked quite a bit about
concurrency um
there's no more questions about like why
three five seven servers and never more
i think this is a the reason that is the
case because that i think reflects how
uh raft is actually used in practice and
really that three five seven is a
is based on the computation of knowing
what the mean time between failures are
right then in the raft paper it's
assumed that the meantime between
failures are rough you know a couple
couple months so if you run with three
servers and one goes down
uh you know you have plenty of time to
actually uh
uh rebuild you know a third server and
get it back online and so get back to
three before hopefully the next failure
happens
so that's why you know there's a small
number of servers
um
we talked a little bit about when to
persist um
there's a number of good questions about
like you know what happens if you uh
crash while writing to stable storage uh
so you may write partial state and that
would be a disaster
and so typically what people do is
actually they make sure that when they
write to stable storage that is an
atomic operation
uh you know this does not show up in the
tester because the tester basically sort
of simulates
uh persistent storage and basically
updates
the precision storage atomically but in
a real system that actually has a disk
uh you might like play a trick like the
mapreduce library did where you
automatically rename you first write it
in temporary file until everything is
written and then you atomic
rename or use a lot right ahead logging
system
uh but yeah you have to uh that'd be a
disaster if the
uh the crash or the precision state the
stable storage becomes inconsistent
okay let me stop here so that like
there's maybe a little bit more time to
ask questions and of course i'll stay
around
and as always and i can answer more
questions
i see there's also a ton of uh
discussion in the chat
i'm not i'm unfortunately not able
probably i didn't keep
up with all of it uh
okay good
okay so yeah any more questions
um i have a question about the log
your in your code for the log
the index zero it is
um i guess in the underlying
array what the start of the log
is is that right so this is basically
for
lab2d not for uh no
in lapse a b and c index zero would be
altered always zero here
and in lab 2d where you take snapshots
you know the index 0 would know the
index number of the snapshot
because you're going to cut the
beginning of the log
okay so if you take a snapshot at the
index 10 you know you're going to cut
from zero through nine
and index zero will be ten then oh see
this is
this is the end of the snapshot i see
okay
okay so basically everything through
uh to until index zero is actually
included in the snapshot so there's no
reason to
maintain that in that state anymore in
the log
any other questions
i hope this was useful uh particularly
still in time for you know
2c and 2d and maybe
there's some ideas here that might be
useful for you in implementing those
labs
i have a question about like
what kind of ranges for election
timeouts people used
um i think i use like
you know the the lower the like the
limit of like 100 milliseconds for the
heartbeats and then timeout anywhere
between like 300 and 700 milliseconds
yep i don't know if that's like totally
reasonable i use a little bigger number
correct like the
stranger we gave you is that you know
you should be able to
elect a leader in five seconds and
that means you should count on and you
know may have to run the election a
couple times
uh and so you know the numbers you pick
seems reasonable
any people that want to share a
particular annoying bug that they have
actually there were a number of
questions where people are asking what
is the most nasty bug that people have
seen
i had a pretty annoying bug in my
implantation
um i didn't take my own advice
and sort of did a like weird
implantation of a timer where i like
spawn off
a new thread to sleep or something and
then send a message back at the end
it was not particularly great design and
i had two different timers one for
uh heartbeats and one for election
timers and i was forgetting to
stop the one of those timers when the
server shut down
one of them was fine and one of them
wasn't and that meant i would slowly
gain
like a number of go routines over the
course of a long-running test
until it ran out and the race detector
crashed everything
and it was incredibly embarrassing
because it was literally just that i
forgot to
stop a timer so
but it took a very long time to debug
because i couldn't figure out
i think i thought there was a bug in the
lab rpc code and
no there wasn't no there's probably no
bugs in the lab rpc code it was just me
misinterpreting data
i'm talking about election timeouts i
have a
issue on uh where the
one call is called from config.go uh
that where it occasionally fails to
reach agreement
um i realized that if i increase my
election timeouts to
uh have like the random interval go up
to like 1500 milliseconds it
like greatly decreases the frequency at
which this happens but
i'm wondering if i should go even higher
than that for the random interval that
this is indicative of another bug i have
i think it's indicative of another bug
you have
my first guess my gut you know of course
i don't know for sure at all
uh but like you don't have to be able to
run with that kind of long timers
to pass yeah
most of the time when people are
tweaking their timeouts it's not
actually fixing their bugs it's just
changing how often they show up
okay thanks
uh here's a bug in the channel on the
chat channel this is a bug i had was
that i forgot to initialize the channel
how did how did that manifest itself as
a bug
oh like uh basically when i was sending
something it wouldn't
be able to receive it and i wondered
what was going on it turns out it was
just that it didn't ever
initialize it so it's like a nil channel
because i don't really know what the
semantics are of writing to a new
channel
i can't recall the top my head i know
the rules for that but i don't remember
what the rule is
do you have a comment on the previous
point
uh regard regarding the election
timeouts and setting them high
should we try and aim thus to set them
a little bit low so that if there are
any bugs we can expose them
oh yeah i'm not not a bad i plan i think
it's always good to like you know
push the boundaries and see if you have
any other box without working
so the boundaries should be something
akin to what the paper suggests
a little bit higher uh because the the
way we set up the tests are slightly
different
uh you know the in section of each uh
has a discussion on this correct
and actually the the rough paper kind of
has like guidelines and even if they
have like a specific value they
set the value based on their guidelines
and the guidelines said that you should
have kind of
elected a leader with like an order of
magnitude more time than what the hybrid
interval is yeah
exactly right like 100 like for example
like if you go to like 800 to a second
like
things will work out like it's fine even
if those are high because
that's kind of the guidelines it all
changes because we just made you change
the
kind of like the innermost heartbeat
frequency because of the rpc laptop
uh sorry can i actually see the
heartbeat timer
in the code yeah sure
basically you know every 50 milliseconds
uh the ticker goes off
the ticker calls tick and if i leader
i'll basically send an rpc
this comes down to basically a heartbeat
so near my implementation every 50
milliseconds i'm sending a heartbeat
um i had a question i
so i you were saying like um
like it should be like timeout should be
like an order of magnitude
like greater than heartbeat right
um but i started like playing to see how
low it could get
and you know i could like with a 100
millisecond timeout
you know it could go down to like three
to 500
milliseconds and still work like you
know
without without a hitch and i was
wondering like
is that like why
like how how low you know how low can
they get
and why are we making them so much
greater than the
on the election timeout or then the
heartbeat time
because we need to we need to give the
candidate a a shot
actually becoming the leader and some of
the messages might be delayed for a long
time
order dropped
yeah i have a question i think i missed
this part
which is how your like which
uh append entries you're sending from
start and which one's from the heartbeat
basically the same it's the same code
okay there's no nothing different i only
have one because if you look here at
this you know here scent depends correct
this is from the ticker yeah and
if you look at the api code the start
function
calls the same function
but in this case what which ones are
like if you're sending all of them from
start which ones are going to be sent
from the
ticker the ticker probably says mostly
empty
uh appends
okay so the bulk are coming from start
no warning is coming from the ticker
or like the actual log entries oh the
the the actual log rangers are are all
sitting in the struct
raft right so they're coming out they're
abstract
and if you look at start the only thing
start does
hold on let me go pull up start again
because it's a good question
like you pull startup basically it
appends it to the log here
right and that's all it does and like
the only difference basically between
ticker and start is that start actually
appends something to the log and the
ticker doesn't do that
and send the pens basically grabs you
know whatever
so this is the loop for all of them so
here's to an individual uh oops
here's the individual one that is sent
to one pier and it basically grabs the
right
log entries out of the uh
log right here you're copying it out of
the log
into the rx entries and so if it's a
heartbeat most likely this always be
zero not always correct because you
might the leader might
the follower might have missed some but
in the case when uh start calls this you
know you will always be sending the
thing that actually just has been
appended
okay because i i did it such that i'm
sending everything
in the heartbeats like all the entries
and uh
for some of the two css sometimes it'll
like fail to reach agreement and i'm
wondering if that's
why because here you're it seems like
the bulk of the entries are being sent
in start no okay that might not be the
reason why
you uh i don't think it will affect
reaching agreement it's probably not uh
dependent on the number of entries you
send in the uh
the number of log entries you're sending
in the append rpc
no no yeah i was able to make it all the
way
through lab two with only ever sending
um append entries from the heartbeat
timer yeah
but you will write problems and slow
things down though
yeah it can swing slows down to be clear
i don't recommend doing this but like
you can get through lab two with just
sending from the heartbeats so yeah if
you're running out through live streams
that's nice um all right
how do the timeouts work then or how do
the limits on heartbeats work
like are the limiter on heartbeats like
the same as the limit on
append entries rpc or are they counted
differently
the heartbeats are they're different you
know you can send you know you have to
send it you know
principal assume that every start can
result in an append entry
call right um and but you're
you're not allowed to send more than 10
heartbeats how
how do you like differentiate that on
the test
our beats have no entries most typically
okay so you literally go in and check
like oh we don't really literally check
but we basically see
if you make more progress than 10 times
a second
it's like one of the tests in lab 3
checks if you go quick enough
thanks
exactly for this reason maybe a little
bit annoying basically in the real
application correct if you delete you
know your
pence you know by 10 mil by 50
milliseconds before you do anything
so if a client you know imagine a client
submitting to your service you know
basically it's going to get
one uh append operation through every 50
milliseconds
that would be not a very desirable
service to use
um i had a question about accessing
parts of the rf struct
without luck so and send up center pen
entries
you are you're reading the peer um
peers
i guess slice but i know that it is
it is static but there
it could be that multiple threads
read the same thing twice right
so is is there a danger of the race
detector complaining about this
some echo sorry i'm sorry
um
so let me see uh so i guess i
don't hold the lock on rf rf gears it's
not the
yeah yeah maybe the race protector is
not complaining
uh because i always run this with the
race detector
sorry was that question about whether
iterating over peers could
cause races yeah yeah right because yeah
accesses it without holding the lock and
right yeah
rf.kill uh
oh i guess it was just an obscure
scenario if you kill it
at the same time as doing something else
i'm not sure
well yeah modify
it killed still doesn't modify peers
yeah okay thank you could i see how you
do the apply channel thing
again you talked about it earlier how
you needed to have a walk with the apply
channel
not a lock the opposite or sorry
what is it uh a condition variable yeah
not the condition variable yeah
oh uh huh so yeah oh what do you do with
the condition variable
though i brought a signal on it so like
when
when the match index is updated and
a new entry needs to be committed that
thread will
call signal and
that will wake up the applier thread and
apply a thread we'll see if there's
anything that needs to be pushed on the
apply channel which is the checks here
and if so it will push it on the apply
channel
oh okay and if there's nothing to be
pushed on your ply channel anymore it
goes back to sleep
okay
okay maybe this is it
for today