okay thank you okay so good afternoon
good evening good morning
good night wherever you are uh we're
gonna talk today uh about transactions
and as you probably noticed the reading
material for today is a little bit more
tutorial in nature
we're not studying a particular system
and see how
a set of ids are implemented in that set
of
in that system instead what we're going
to be doing is talking about
just the concept of transactions because
it is
it shows up in the next two papers that
we'll be studying
and those two papers have quite
a lot of material in them and assume
that you're familiar with transactions
in particular that you're familiar with
the two core ideas that we'll see in
today's lecture namely two-phase locking
and two-phase commit
and sometimes they are abbreviated as
you know to pc for two-phase commit
and 2pl for to face locking
uh one point of confusion uh that the
two terms really don't have to do much
don't have to don't do it i'm really not
not much related um you know they happen
to have both
the uh worked you know two words two
phase in it uh but you know they solve
completely different problems
um they happen to also show up typically
in the context of transactions
uh but they're even outside of
transactions they are
good ideas or warfare ideas and so
don't let your self confused by the fact
that they both have two phases in it
they're pretty pretty unrelated
okay so i'm just gonna dive in a little
bit and start talking about transactions
in general
um and the reason that we're
going to care about transactions a lot
is
that we want to be able to do
cross-machine operations
and so the problem that we're going to
try to tackle
in this lecture as well as in the two
upcoming papers
is cross machine
atomic ops
uh and so for example just to make it a
little bit concrete uh let's say we have
a client
we have two uh
we have a shardish key value server so
some of the
keys are on key value server one
some are on key value server two and so
the keys are split
across them so for example maybe keep a1
has
x you know our key aj2 has y and we want
to basically want to do atomic operation
across those two
keys and the easy way or the classic
example
in the context of transactions is always
doing a transfer
so let's say the client wants to do a
transfer
from x to y so here's our client
and you know it's going to do basically
a put
to x to maybe uh add
uh or subtract you know from the account
so let's do x minus one
and then you know the client is going to
do a put of
you know y you know plus one
transferring basically one dollar from
you know the account x to the
account y and our goal is basically
going to be
you know we want automaticity
with respect to failures
and concurrency
um so even if uh you know a variable
okay
the first key value server fails after
the
put uh then we would like to arrange it
that basically the transfer didn't
happen at all so generally the semantics
that we're looking for
is that both operations happen or
neither one of them happens
and so similarly from a concurrency
perspective if another client is running
and also tries to
inspect these accounts then what we
would like to be the case is that
both puts show up atomically and so an
other
transactions cannot observe an
intermediate results where an
intermediate result is for example
the money is deducted from x but hasn't
been added to y yet
uh so these are the type of things we
want to do and it's comprised common in
distributed systems you know that you
would like to
do operation across charge
so that's sort of the context
of what we like to do and the general
plan for
doing this it comes actually from the
database community
this general plan is transactions
and what we like to do is uh basically
group these operations for example in
the case of to transfer the two boot
operations
into a single transaction and we'd like
them the property that this transaction
executes
atomically and so you know typically you
know this requires some programmer
annotations
so begin transaction uh to indicate that
the the
client wants to do a startup transaction
then maybe then
you know the operations like at x i
guess i did x minus one
and then at y you know plus one
and then you have to indicate like when
the transaction action is completed
uh and so typically uh we've come to
make it a commit and uh and so the
semantics that we're looking for
is that these operations are executed
atomically with respect to concurrency
and with respect to
failure and just to make it a little bit
more exciting let's look at the second
transaction so that we can look at some
case studies about how transactions
actually interact
you know we might have a second
transaction begin
x which reads
actually these accounts so t1 gets
x and then t2
gets y
and then print t1
comma t2 and then end
or commit
so we have a second transaction that
basically reads the accounts x and y and
then prints the values
and one reason that we uh have two
transactions is so that we can look from
the concurrency perspective
how these transaction is actually
ordered and what our legal outcome and
what are
illegal outcomes now transactions turned
out to be
a general almost like a piece of magic
you know basically programmers
uh can annotate these begin and end
operations
and it takes a whole group of operations
together make them atomic
and use the system will take care of
everything it will take care of the
locking
it will take care of the recovery it's
all like the program doesn't have to
worry about it
the transactions are very very powerful
uh
construct and they're useful
in non-distributed systems you know you
have a single database machine
or multi-core database machine and
clients are submitting transactions to
it
then the transaction systems you know
will execute these transactions in as
much as concurrently as possible
but also even if the machine fails and
comes back up now you can actually
expect the the results to be there
and our focus of course is going to be
on distributed transactions
of the you know the ones that i had on
the previous slide
namely
one for example across yards which is
sort of a common case
in in data centers
the typical api of a transaction also
has one more operation
that i didn't list here and that is a
board
so the two transactions are shown here
are both committing but you could easily
have a transaction that
decides to board you know for example uh
you might discover that
example transaction t1 might check that
x has sufficient money in it in the
account and if the
account doesn't have sufficient money uh
instead of calling commit it would call
a board
and at that point the transaction would
be cancelled and even if a transaction
aborts you know sort of halfway through
and maybe has done some put operations
uh distilled the semantics should be
that none of those put operations
actually happened
um so in all cases when it's a border
commit either all of them hampered or
none of them happen
never a partial result a board also
might be called
by the transaction system itself for
example as we'll see later if
there's a there's a deadlock between two
transactions
then the transaction system actually can
abort one of the transactions
uh in the so that the other transaction
can continue and maybe a retry later
uh the transaction that was supported
uh okay so this is sort of the
primitives either begin transaction
commit
and abort three key interface
operations and then the semantics of
transactions are typically summarized by
a single word namely acid
and uh and that stands for like four key
properties of transactions
one it's atomic
and here really atomic refers to the
case where we have two transactions
running
um and if one transaction does multiple
uh put operations or multiple ad
operations
all those results will be all visible to
the other transaction or none of them
will be visible
so that's one aspect sorry
i said i said this is wrong so atomic
actually means to the crash recovery
case
so if a transaction actually to execute
multiple put operations
the transaction crashes halfway
the rule is that all the rights are
visible
all rights around stable storage or none
of them this is the
atomics with respect to crash recovery
uh
the c stands for consistent
which is something we're emotionally not
going to talk about
it's more related to databases it's
often the case that database have
internal invariance
like referential integrity uh is one of
them
and uh the transaction uh is supposed to
maintain that consistency and so no
internal consistencies
this is gonna be less of a topic for us
you know today and three
is isolated the i stands for isolated
and isolated was the what i just said
earlier
incorrectly isolate actually refers to
the case we are running two transactions
and uh they don't see they shouldn't
observe intermediate results from each
other so again
all the rights are applied uh
all or nothing with respect to the
disability to another transaction
and then finally the d stands for
durable
meaning that if the transaction commits
then the
results are written to a stable storage
so that if the system crashes comes back
up later
the latest rights or the latest
transactions
the latest committed transactions are
actually recorded on stable storage
any questions about sort of a quick
introduction to transactions
okay so i'm going to talk basically
about two topics
uh quite a bit namely the
a part of the transactions and the i
part of
transactions i'm going to start with the
i
part and talk a little bit about what
actually
correct isolation means
so basically what we're looking for is a
definition
for a correct execution of multiple
transactions for current transactions
and the typical definition or the gold
standard in the database literature
is called serializable
or serializability
and what that means is that if you have
two transactions or many transactions
and they execute concurrently
then the outcome has to be some serial
order
so either t1 executes before t2
or t2 executes you know before t1 but
there's some
silly or sierra order
and the serial order has to produce the
same outcome
that's the concurrent execution so if
you run two
transactions concurrently they produce
some outcome that outcome is only
valid or legal or correct if it could
have been
the result of a serial execution
so just to make a concrete with our
example
let's say in the account case x is
starts out as being
10 y starts out as being 10.
uh we run these two transactions that we
had earlier
on the board just quickly remind you
what the two transactions are
and one basically moves one between two
accounts and the other one prints the
results of the two
so if we think a little bit about it you
know if t1 goes first
then the outcome is going to be 9 10
and the print statement is going to be
uh
uh yeah and the the print state actually
there i say 9 10 i'm sorry
9 11 that's why i got confused
and the print statement is also going to
say you know
x was the one that was subtracted so 9
11.
so we're going to string 911 out and the
two values of the accounts are nine and
uh nine and eleven uh if two
t2 goes first then the outcome is you
know 10 10
because nothing no money has moved yet
and then
t1 goes and so that's a possible outcome
and so that's the two legal outcomes of
the two transactions that we're actually
uh if we executed the two transactions
concurrently and
uh the system guarantees serializability
now you notice that serializability has
probably a lot of
uh flavor of like the terminology that
we used before namely linearizability
the key difference between
serializability and linearizability
is that in linearizability there's a
real-time
real-time component that if the
transaction t2
starts after a t1 ends then
t2 has to show up later in the total
order in the serial order
in serializability that is not required
so even if the transaction started
you know wall clock time a little bit
later then another transaction
stopped or finished you know the system
is still allowed
to reward it so serializability in some
ways a little bit weaker
than linearizability
nevertheless serializability is a very
convenient
programming area right because from a
programming perspective
you can always think about transactions
executed in some serial order
and you don't have to consider all kinds
of interleavings
okay so even though uh you know
serializability is slightly weaker than
linearizability it actually
disallows a whole bunch of problematic
cases
so let me talk a little bit about that
just to make clear
you know what actually serializability
means
uh and what sort of executions the
uh transactions the transaction system
actually has to forbid
um so uh let's you know two cases
like here we have uh the first
transaction
we have the second transaction running
so t1 runs t2 and
you know one outcome that we could have
is like one
possible execution uh that might happen
is we
if we don't do something special you
know t1
uh gets x
uh you know here the transfer happens so
the updates to x and y happen
and then you know t2 doesn't get a y
and uh you know is this a legal or is
this a c reliable
is this a serializable execution that's
the sort of question we have to ask
and what is the answer to that one
um this is not serializable yeah
and because you know the outcome you
know if we write down what the outcome
is correct then the outcome is going to
be 9
11 here and this is going to write down
uh 10 11 right
i think so and if we go back you know to
our previous slide that is not one of
the two legal outcomes
right so this is not good so when we
think about the implementation of a
transaction system you know it has to be
the case that it forbids this particular
execution uh schedule and you know
there's a similar version
our transactions are these two examples
are not so complicated so they're not
that many in the leavings you have to
that you can consider and that could go
wrong but there's at least one other one
that can result in the not an incorrect
outcome
which is uh we do the put
x first uh so here we go
uh then you know we actually print the
two we do the two gets
so get x get y
and we do the foot of y
and is this a serializable execution
this is an execution that should be
forbidden by the serializable
transaction system or is it an okay
execution
it should be forbidden yeah it should be
forbidden correct because it has an
outcome that could not have happened if
we executed t1
first followed by t2 or t2 first
followed by t1
right okay so
you know what we clearly see is that you
know serializability you know excludes
you know executions just do
uh in order to actually make it easier
for programmers to think about actually
what a database does and there are two
broad approaches
to forbidding executions
and uh and these approaches
the the approach to sort of forgetting
is called concurrency control
um in the first approach or the first
category of solutions is what's called
pessimistic solutions
and the pessimist solutions basically
evolve locks
so the idea is that like when the
transaction runs
or starts uh it requires the net
necessary necessary locks
to maintain uh serializability and only
releases the locks
so when it's guaranteed that the
executions will result in a serializable
execution
so that's the one approach and we're
going to talk a little bit more about it
in a second
the second approach is is optimistic
and in the optimistic approach there's
basically no locks
and optimistic approach you just assume
things are going to work out
and basically when you get to the commit
point
uh you know the disaster system sort of
asks yourself the question
well you know all the given the
operation i've done in the past is that
actually
could that be uh the result of a
linearizable execution
or could that be the result of a
serializable execution
um and if so things are fine and no
problem at all
then you know we're good if it is uh the
result is
doesn't correspond to a sale of
execution then we basically just abort
and maybe and uh and it will retry
uh probably so we'll see
uh i'm not gonna talk much about
optimistic concurrency control right now
but next week or two weeks from now
actually we're reading the farm paper
uh and we'll see an optimistic uh a
transaction system distributed
transaction system of the type that
we're
considering that uses an optimistic
optimistic concurrency of
the currency control approach but the
focus for today
is going to be on pessimism
and one you know sort of the the
the flip way uh that these two
approaches are described
uh in the literature often is that sort
of pessimistic is
you know you ask for permission first
and then you do your operations
and the optimistics or the other way
around you just go ahead and do your
operations
and if it turns out to be wrong you just
apologize later
um and so there's a sort of
analogy if you will uh sort of between
the two different approaches
and now within each approach you know
whether it's pessimistic and optimistic
there are many different concurrency
control plans
uh you know to either increase
concurrency or provide weaker
consistency
and with more concurrency and so there's
like a there's a huge huge literature
and i'm just going to talk about one uh
particular approach which is very
popular
particularly if you want to achieve uh
serializability it turns out that
not although i said like serializability
is a gold standard for databases
it's often the case that um databases
offer multiple degrees of isolation so
you know as a programmer you can sort of
pick you know the degree of isolation
that you like
and the reason you may want to pick a
weaker degree of isolation so that you
can get more concurrency
now we're going to stick to sort of the
gold standard of concurrency
which is namely serializability and if
you do serializability
then a common approach is two-face
locking
an interface locking you know basically
sort of a walk per record
that's the starting point for database
record
and you know in our little example uh
that would be a sort of a
a lock per uh variable and i
prefer x and log for y and there's
basically two rules
uh one a transaction
acquires a lock before using
and so the idea is before you know you
can read or
write you know to x or y you first have
to obtain
the lock and the transaction system will
do this for you
and two the t holds
a lock and once you're acquired
you're not allowed to release it until
commit
or abort whatever whatever is the end of
the transaction
correct and so in our particular case if
we are like t1
running and we have t2 running and
t1 walks x first and then you know
lock y and it has to maintain
those locks until it actually reaches
commit points
so if t2 runs at the same time or
roughly at the same time
if two t2 starts a little bit later and
tries to grab the lock and x
uh t1 will have it if t2 started a
little bit later
and at that point you know basically t2
has to wait
a sort of standard locking protocol and
the basic idea of two-phase locking
is that um it's sort of a refinement or
an improvement over this
simple locking scheme that is described
uh in the documentary and
which sometimes it's called simple
disable locking or strict locking
where basically at the beginning of the
transaction you grab all the locks you
need
for the whole transaction you hold them
into the end and then you release them
and two-phase locking is a little bit
more fine-grained
in that um even if the transactions
might
uh um and they're not required to watch
immediately all at the same time at the
beginning
and instead you know they acquire the
locks incrementally as the transaction
runs you know which allows you know
certain concurrency patterns that you
know are disallowed by
uh strict lock-in
now the first rule seems you know pretty
clear you know why you need it
the second rule might be or maybe less
obvious and so it's
probably a good idea to actually sort of
see what goes wrong if you did not
maintain the second rule
and so let's say talk a little bit about
intel commit
and so here we have our two transactions
t1 and two two yeah the
transfer and the print statement and so
let's say
you know here we do our putif x and so
that means before the put of x the
transaction system walks x
and let's say that we're not following
the two-phase locking rule
and we actually release the lock x right
after
uh the put because we're done with it
actually it doesn't show up in
transaction
t1 anymore you know there will be a
later put with us to put to y
and let's assume that before actually we
get to the walking and y
you know t2 runs and actually t2
uh basically the whole you know
the two gets you know the get of x and
they get a y
run and so since you know t1 released to
walk on x you know it can get
locked at x since te1 hasn't
gone to the put yet you know it can also
get the lock on y
and so you know print x and y and
reset and then release the locks
so is this would this be a
uh a serializable uh
execution
oh it's the same as before yeah it's
exactly the same as before correct
because basically the
uh the print statements like here they
sort of slipped
in between the two to put in again and
the y between the two puts of the x and
the y
and we already concluded earlier that is
not a serializable conclusion that's a
serializable execution
so this is wrong and so this is an
example of demonstrating that if you
release the lock too early
in this case t1 release the x too early
you're not going to get a serializable
execution
and one way to think about it basically
is that whenever there's sort of an
intersection
between you know two lock sets so t1 has
a lock set of x and y
t2 has a lock set of x and y2
uh it is important that you know uh
during the these two transactions get
ordered in a particular way and that
means that
uh if the boxes intersect you know we
have to make ensure some total ordering
and that means that we actually have to
hold the locks you know to the end until
the
bit point so that no intermediate
results of the transaction are actually
visible to other transactions
and we release the locks before the
commit point you know we might actually
make
a result visible even though you know
maybe later it's actually even aborted
right and then the whole change will go
away
so this is reason why walks must be held
to the ants
now an obvious problem that many of you
asked about
and uh two-phase walking is no no
there's a
isn't there a chance of deadlock
if you're requiring the walks uh as or
the transactions execute
and so let's and this is absolutely the
case uh
and so for example let's modify t2
slightly
so t2 used to be you know t1 you know
gets x
instead we're going to do it in the
opposite order we're first going to get
y
and t2 gets
x and we remain we keep t1 the same
right so t1 actually still does first to
put to x and then to put the y
so now we can easily get into trouble
so this is t2 prime uh and this is just
the
ordinary tu1 that we already had it does
a put of x
you know before doing the put of x it
needs to get the
lock on x so l locks x
uh now let's say that the uh ordering
works out as follows you know the
same time q one t2 prime runs it doesn't
get
y so that means it got the lock on y
and now you can easily see if it goes
wrong here now
t1 is going to do a put of y or wants to
do a put of y
so it needs to get the lock on y
but i can't get it because you know t2
prime
uh actually has to lock so it has to
wait here that's the block
you know the same thing is going to
happen of course on the other side
before doing the get off x
t2 needs to get the lock uh off x
and you know it can't get the lock of x
because t1 has it
and so uh this has to wait two
and now we have you know t one waiting
on t
two prime and we have t t prime waiting
on t one we basically have a deadlock
um now what is the cool part
about transaction systems is that we
have to support operation
and so if the transaction system could
detect
a deadlock you could just abort one of
the two transactions
uh let the other one proceed and
hopefully that will actually get to the
end and commit
and abort the other one and then
the client or the application can decide
what to do with your board of
transaction it can actually retry it you
know maybe
wait a little bit and then retry it uh
and in the hope that at that point
you're not going to run into a deadlock
and so one way to think a little bit
about two-phase locking
is that it has a little bit of a sort of
an optimistic you know
flavor to it in the sense that it's not
guaranteed that it won't run into
problems
but even if it runs into problems you
know you can always abort
and then recover from that problem
any questions about this
so how do you how do you find the
deadlock
ah that's exactly i was hoping that
somebody was asking that question
so uh the way there's sort of two broad
approaches that people use
uh one is um
one isn't not as solid as you will
uh one is basically on a timeout basis
like if the transactions are running for
a long time and you know
they don't seem to make forward progress
uh you just aboard one of them
and so this is timeout based the more
systematic uh sort of way of thinking
about it
is to construct and wait for graph
as the transaction systems you know are
moving so
for example if you know t1 runs so
in the wait for graph the transactions
are the nodes so we can have a node c1
and we make a node t2 when they start or
t2 prime if you will
and when t1 runs you know it gets x
nothing together
then you know it gets to the lock of y i
can't do it so
we'll make an arrow from you know t1 to
t2 prime to indicate that t1 is waiting
for t2 prime
then at some point like you know t2 is
running you know t2
hits this 2t prime hits this point where
they want to lock
x it can't do it um so it will look at
like where it's waiting for who's
holding the lock well it's t1
and so we'll put an edge you know in the
weight four graph from t2
to t uh from t2 prime to t1
and now we see that there's a cycle and
whenever there's a cycle that means
there's a deadlock right because one is
waiting in the other
and the other is waiting on the first
and so
the transaction system can sort of
construct these graphs on the fly
uh detect when there is a cycle in the
graph
and then for example either abort t1 or
abort t2 prime
so this is called the weight
what happens after the abort
uh well uh so let's say we abort t2
just for as an experiment so
we're going to kill this guy so t2
basically
this transaction system is going to
range as we'll see in a second it's
going to arrange that basically
none results of t2 are t2 prime
invisible
uh at that point you know the lock is
released right
the board will force the lock release of
the y because t2 prime is backing out
that means that you know t1 can get the
lock on y and proceed to finish
uh the client that called t2 prime is
going to learn that the transaction
aborted
and for example it can just choose to
rerun it again
does it all make sense
okay so this is sort of the first part
uh you know actually all of what i
wanted to say about two-phase locking
uh except i wanted to address the sort
of homework assignment again
which is like in what situations does
two-phase locking allow for more
concurrency
than strict locking right where strict
locking was the protocol where
a transaction acquires all the locks in
advance
and this requires that the programmer or
like the beginning of the transaction
basis declares which locks the
transaction actually needs
sort of slightly undesirable like less
programmer friendly
but it has the advantage that you know
you don't actually
you can't run into these uh
you don't have to abort a transaction at
the end in the case you run into the
deadlock
uh so two-phase locking you know allows
for more concurrency
in principle or shoot live for more
concurrency um
and then the straight locking or the
simple locking scheme and
so i would like to do is a quick
breakout room uh
for a couple minutes like five minutes
again and uh
you know convince yourself or
constructing a case
where simple walking would disallow some
concurrency
that two-phase locking is actually able
to exploit
cool all right let's do breakout runs
okay uh see you in five minutes
we can't hear you
i think you're muted
um i have a question about one of the
previous slides
that you're talking about almost like
let me double check if everybody can
hear me now
yes oh okay good uh
go ahead uh on one of your previous
or i guess this is just the general
question but is the lock point always
the same as the commit point
or is it possible to start relinquishing
locks before your commit point
okay uh this is a very good question uh
so it depends
um so if you only do exclusive locking
uh as we've done so far at least in my
examples then the commit point is
similar to the
the lock point is similar to the commit
point in the board point
if you have read write locking some
locks that allow
both read locks and red locks then it's
possible to release
read locks earlier with some
restrictions
okay um so uh
can somebody give me one example of
where a two-phase locking is
uh allows for more concurrency than
simple locking
just to make sure that we're all on the
same page
the audit function example like you can
release the lock as soon as
you read this person's amount
like you don't have to wait until you
read every once
all right this is an example of
explaining the read uh read blocks if
you have lead logs
any other examples
if you have a transaction where there's
like a condition that only rarely like
um is true and you read a piece of data
when it's true
so at the beginning you don't need to
acquire the lock for that
only when you actually need to read it
yup that's a great example i
personally like that example a lot
that's a great one
good okay good so let's uh move on
basically then to the second topic
uh of this lecture which is uh two phase
commit
and this is really dealing with crashes
switch back to blue
we can't see the slides either yet oh
let me uh fix that
and hold on
our screen stop to
share that's the thing how about now
all good good thank you
all right so two phase commit
or to pc this is popular called
again this is a very uh well-known
popular uh protocol uh i'm going to talk
about the base sort of simple
straightforward
or the most common version of the
protocol
there are all kinds of variations of it
but you know in
they all sort of have the same
underlying idea and so again
typically in two-phase protocol and i'm
going to do it in the context of the
transfer transaction so a client that
actually
wants to do a transfer you know
basically submits the
uh the transfer transaction to the
transaction system
and uh and the machine that sort of
receives that transaction is called the
coordinator
and that machine is in charge
of running the transaction through the
transaction system
and so the coordinator will talk in our
case to two different machines
a and b where a holds you know
x and b holds y
and um uh
and basically the you know one way that
this typically goes is that the
coordinator first sort of
does the whole transaction but in a
tentative uh way uh so
uh the put x you know results in a
message to a
you know locking a uh modifying a
you know put put x except you know the
put is not actually
visible yet in the database uh what what
is done it is
put in a log um very much like in sort
of uh in the franzipani style where we
have a right ahead log
all the operations that we at some point
want to materialize in the database
itself
we first put in the log until later in
this particular case until we hit commit
and then we actually will install
everything in the database
so we'll do the put we do the second put
see here to y
uh and another same thing happens there
you know the
we got a lock on y okay so this should
have been lock and x
and we'll do a put on y
and again and we're gonna not actually
you know really put the
the value in the database we're usually
gonna log things so we log n
y and here we log x
okay uh and now the coordinate has done
two
you know the transactions the two of the
main operations and now so ready to
commit and here's where the two-phase
part comes in
and so the coordinator will send a
prepare message
and i'm first going to describe this
protocol in the case there's no failures
and everything works out just to start
sort of the
the the easy case as you will since a
prepare message
uh sends a prepare message to
prepare a you know prepare b
and the prepare message of course it
includes the transaction id
that is actually used for you know
distance action so every transaction has
a transaction id
and all the messages are tagged now with
the transaction id so we always know
about which transaction we're talking
about
uh when a and b you know receive these
preparer messages
uh you know they look at their state and
uh
you know see if they indeed can actually
execute the transaction you know they're
holding the lock on
x in this case the x is actually in the
log
and so they send back you know saying
yep i'm ready
to commit so yes
yes and at this particular point
uh user the crucial shorter step is the
coordinator now knows that basically
both a and b
are are prepared to commit
and so and i have basically promised to
commit by actually uh
responding very wide and at this point
the coordinator commits and then you
know sends messages you know again to
the a saying commit
and the transaction tid
similar message to b you know commit tid
and at this particular point uh a and b
actually perform the operation so
they basically install you know at this
point you know they install
now the log version of y here against
this transaction this participants
installs the
x and they release the locks so release
of y and here the release of x
and they respond back you know to the
coordinator saying like yep all done
and at that point the dejection is
completely
done in fact you know the coordinator
doesn't really have to remember anything
anymore about this particular
transaction
and uh also see later you know a and b
you know need to remember that state a
little bit longer
until they hear about the next
transaction all right so this is the
core
basic case when there's absolutely no
failure and
we see what we actually get the desired
outcome correct
you know when does the coordinator
commit the coordinator commits only
if a and b are
agreed
okay it could be the case that you know
example when
uh the coordinator sends a message to b
that b
decides well i can't really commit uh
maybe so there could be multiple reasons
for it uh maybe the
b actually is in a situation where
there's a deadlock uh
with y or uh you know
there's no space in the log anymore or
there's not enough money in the
account of y um and so you know
b could respond uh with a no let's say
uh in this so the other possible outcome
is you know the prepare message can
actually be consented
a no back and in that case the
coordinator gets one yes you know from a
a no from b
and so both do not agree and in that
case you know the coordinator cannot
commit the transaction and then it would
actually abort the transaction
and then say the board massachusetts you
know to a and b basically you know
uh discontinuing uh the transaction so
those are the two possible outcomes one
in the commit case one in the board case
uh and but it is always the case that
the transaction only commits
the top level transaction only commits
if both of the participants that are
involved in the transaction
agree to do so
um now that's sort of the outline
of the protocol so i want to now go
through a couple of cases you know sort
of to understand
uh you know what can go wrong and you
know how we do
how we deal how two-phase commit uh
arranges that actually
still the right thing happens actually i
have a question here
um so we said that like b might decide
that
it needs to board um and sends back a no
message what if it decides it needs to
abort after it replied yes
would that ever be possible i no we'll
talk about it in a second but that's
absolutely not possible
if you promise to commit you have to
commit
or you have to be ready to commit now
you have to be ready to commit
you don't commit right away you have to
wait until the commit message of course
but you cannot bail out anymore
so until the prepare the be can
unilaterally abort a transaction
once a promise yes it cannot
unilaterally board a transaction anymore
so is it possible where you're in
deadlock but you can't get out of the
deadlock
because everyone in that cycle has
agreed
to prepare a commit
if everybody agrees to prepare and they
can definitely commit then they will
commit
you're still holding blocks right but
what if you're in deadlock because we
mentioned before how one of the reasons
why you might want to order this
you would find it out before to prepare
okay if you get the locks and why
if you did not succeed in getting the
necessary watch for the transaction
then you know at that point
right thank you okay so this is exactly
the kind of discussion that's going to
come up so i'm going to go i'm going to
take the same board
and replicate it and consider a bunch of
different cases
so here's the same board again
nothing has changed so far uh it's
identical
and so what's the first you know to sort
of follow up on this question that we're
just asked
let's first consider the case where
b uh you know is in the prepared state
and then crashes like right after so
it is prepared
it pointed back sent back to
the coordinator that it actually is
agreeing to go along and right after it
sends actually the
prepare message okay message that it
actually crashes
what does that mean
what needs to happen how we're going to
resolve this
or what is the risk so basically
b crashes um if b crashes we need to
abort the whole thing right
no we cannot abort anymore right because
you know b already promised
and we're going to use the log
yeah well okay so b is going to crash
and then at some point it's going to
come back up
right it's going to recover hopefully
and what state doesn't need to remember
across crashes
um it needs to remember that i prepared
yeah i need to remember correct that it
prepared for transaction id whatever the
t
id was and that is holding the lock
on why and so when it comes back up
uh the first thing it has to do is sort
of look saying like how was i in the
middle of a
you know a participant in a distributed
transaction
and if you look at the state and you'll
see that it was actually prepared
for transaction id uh tid and it was and
it must hold the lock for l y or the log
for y before just anything else you know
before
talking to anything once it is in that
state
you know then it is if it didn't crash
right and
things are sort of back to normal and
hopefully at some point the coordinator
will retry
the commit message the b will get that
commits message for this transaction id
sees that oh yeah i'm indeed prepared
and i hold the lock and y
and so it just goes along and installs y
and etc finishes the transaction does
that make sense
so basically you know there's a little
bit of a refinement here
that we actually have to write some
stable you know some
data to stable storage you know as part
of the transaction
and which was part of two-phase commit
this is one of the reasons that
two-phase commit is a little bit
expensive
right because not only we have to send
sort of multiple round messages
uh but also uh a participant actually
has to write
uh things to stable storage and as we
talked about before
writing to stable storage is uh is quite
expensive right like
it could be easily a couple milliseconds
you know it's let's say
uh one millisecond you know
optimistically you know that means
basically that we're immediately limited
to sort of a thousand transactions per
second right no more
okay let's consider another case
uh and so let me duplicate this slide
again
and consider yet another case
let's say
we coordinate the crashes
and so uh here's red again
and you know we got like one uh
we got the prepared messages and the
coordinator you know maybe you sent out
one commit message
and then crashes like right here
uh you know what
what do we need to arrange you know to
make sure that the whole plan works out
and so the coordinator needs to uh store
into persistent state what
uh what are the commands that were
promised to be committed but were not
committed yet
yeah so the converter is almost the same
as sort of the it's in
anabolic and negligence to be case
correct now if we commit a transaction
we need to write to stable storage that
we're actually committing the
transaction so we need to write to
stable storage you know commit tid
uh so that when the coordinator comes
back up
then it can actually finish the
transaction until actually the
uh a and b that indeed the transaction
is committed because a and b are waiting
correct a and b
said like yeah we're happy to go along
and they're just
waiting and waiting until actually they
uh hear from the coordinator to decide
what's done because
uh once they decided once they went
along or once they agreed to go along
you know they cannot unilaterally
anymore bail out correct because
uh let's say they actually both said
that they agreed or wrong
then it means that the coordinator they
know they don't know
they may the court they may have uh send
a commit message to for example a
and actually has committed transaction
you know b hasn't heard yet maybe the
message got delayed then the the
coordinator the crash
and you know at that point it would be
totally wrong for b
to abort the transaction and really have
to wait until the
coordinator comes back to tell what
actually the outcome is of the
transaction
okay
so the only uh sorry the only message
that the coordinator is not going to
resend is prepare that one if it gets
like
doesn't get a yes it'll just abort yeah
exactly there's the next example
so let's do that uh let me duplicate
this board again
and talk about that case uh so
just for fun let's move it down so we're
gonna lose track
uh so let's say you know the following
thing happens
um the this period message never makes
it right
uh and then you know the coordinator can
unilaterally decide you know to
abort right and in fact you can tell b
you know to the board and you know he
doesn't really need to know
anything about it in english uh
the uh some would later you know will
come up and can ask the coordinator if
the coordinator doesn't know anything
anymore about this transaction you can
just tell ia oh yeah that doesn't
transaction we aborted because i don't
have a
commit record anymore and i was not
waiting to inform anybody
so in that case we can do an abort and
that means the b can release the locks
correct and
b can just proceed you know happily
trying to
do other transactions that might involve
uh y
okay um sorry so what will happen
if the message 2a gets lost the
coordinator aborts
and then b crashes but then when it
comes up
is going to wait for a commit message
from
the coordinator but the transaction has
avoided already
yeah or yeah so either there's two cases
uh you know presumably you know in the
most protocols actually b will ping
the coordinator because it knows who's
the coordinator
and ask if hey what's the outcome of
that transaction
okay so one more case i want to return
to one case that is actually sort of the
the most interesting case uh one of the
more tricky cases
so i just have a brief question uh yeah
hold on hold on one sec
sorry yeah yeah so the first question is
that uh
so let's so b let's say holds the lock
on y
all the way through between uh putting y
into the log
until installing y uh to the actual
state so that's
okay and then the second question so the
logs here are
uh distributed because we're dealing
with across servers or
uh i mean if y only exists on the server
b then maybe we
don't need distributed blocking so i'm
just curious of what the setup yeah the
setup is here is basically the a
maintains the locks for
all the shards that it has for all the
variables or all the records that it has
and b
maintains all the logs for all the
records it has
okay but if we for example have y being
on multiple servers then we need some
sort of distributed login
yeah yeah yeah like so this is we're
talking about the sharded case right
where the accounts are shared across
multiple servers
and only one server has a particular
account
awesome thank you i'll come back to this
later actually one more time
so the first thing i wanted to point out
uh is let's go back to
sort of the um the
uh the case where um
b or a you know said yes and then
crashes
correct um or actually
let me see is this the case uh no i want
the case to fall okay sorry
fix this line so a and b promised their
thing
uh but i want to go back to the case
where
that we already discussed which is right
after the commit point
um the coordinator crashes
right and in we know correctly this
is this interval of time from here to
there
basically uh b cannot unilaterally abort
anymore right because it
promised you know to go along and it
might
have been the case that actually a did
actually already
did the commit and so it cannot
unilaterally
abort anymore and so there's only one
option in this case and what is that one
option
you just wait yeah this is unfortunate
uh but true the only thing that b can do
is wait
and and it's still holding the lock on y
correct so that means that any other
transaction that involves y
you know it cannot proceed um
one has to wait you know until the
coordinator comes back
and announces or re-announces whatever
the decision was that actually was the
outcome for that particular transaction
and this is one of the sort of you know
sort of the two aspects
you know this is one of the sort of
aspects of two-phase commit
that are a bit undesirable right
where um the uh
the protocol might just block until a
machine comes back
does that make sense
so how do people do they'll deal with
this in practice well
it's a little bit unfortunate uh but
here's where
some of our techniques from the past can
come to rescue what could we do
with the coordinator to make this
scenario unlikely
so we can make it fall tolerant like
yeah yeah make it fall tolerant how
could we do it
well there are multiple approaches but
uh
we can do it maybe through uh rap
yeah you know run draft who basically
basically
run the coordinator not on a single
machine but basically have a replicated
state machine
that implements the coordinator and you
know we use raft to sort of
uh keep the replicated state machine and
implement the coordinator uh in sync
and then if one of the machines that
forms the coordinator fails uh hopefully
the two others are still there
and so we can still proceed right
and so it's potentially possible you
know to basically
you know replicate the coordinator or
actually any of the participants do
no using raft so let me actually
put this up a little bit so talk a
little bit more
a couple discussion points which is you
know we could use raft
to make the coordinator
for tolerant or available if you will
that's really the property we care about
does that make sense
in fact if you will see uh if you do
lab4 instead of a project
uh this is exactly actually what lab4
does lab4 actually uh
has a similar scheme where you know
there's a form of two-face
uh commit that you must implement and uh
move the
uh the master charter or the master
coordinator
that rebalances charge across uh
shard servers uh uses raf to replicate
itself and actually the shark servers
itself also replicate itself using raft
and so we're
many many dirac groups running in
parallel
and another the essence of lab four and
so this is like the typical
way you know if you're uh concerned
about like having the
system being blocked for a long period
of time you know one way to do it is
basically
make the uh coordinated fault tolerant
um so in amazing brings me to something
else which
a lot of people asked about you know is
raft
a raft and two-phase commit sort of
similar things
or could you do two phase commit with
raft or
i mean they have a little bit of a
parallel correct there's like a one
thing is called the
coordinator well raf is called the
leader we got uh
you know participants you know maybe you
know we can think about this as
followers
uh yeah so you know seems to have some
similarities like how do we think about
it like what's the relationship between
raft and to pc
the difference is that um in raft the
coordinator can change essentially
um otherwise it's like the single point
of failure
yep good point any
um so another difference is that uh raf
basically depends on the concept of a
majority whereas in two-phase commit the
coordinator
needs to get a response from every
single uh other server that is involved
in the
uh in the committee yeah that was a good
point so these are almost
like protocol differences right yeah and
you know we're wondering if
can we get to a point where like is
there a conceptual difference like
do they solve the same problem um
raft is for replicating the same thing
and two place committees when you do the
opposite when you
instead of having one thing you spread
across different servers
and then you have to deal with the
problem exactly exactly
in graph all servers do the same thing
they're implementing a replicated state
machine right
and in two pc actually servers
all servers operate on different data
the first participant was actually
operating on x and second participate it
was an operator y
so into pc really you know solves a
completely different problem than
wrapped you know raft is really all
about
high availability
and two pc is really about
atomic operations across servers
or across data that's living on
different servers
does that make sense so even though like
maybe they have some
internal techniques that look like very
similar the two
protocols you know are designed for
completely different problems
and not directly related now it's
interesting to see correct that we could
make a raft
we can use raft to make the coordinator
more fault tolerant or the petitions
made
more highly available but they basically
essentially
solve different problems
with that i actually wanted to end this
lecture
i'm happy to entertain more questions
hopefully this will very helpful in the
next two papers so the
next two papers are both through
transaction systems
one uh one from google
you want from microsoft research uh and
the second one uses optimistic
transactions
and you will see when you read these
papers there's a lot of machinery there
are pretty complex systems
but hopefully at least you know some of
the parts uh that will be described
you'll sort of now understand because
you know what two-phase commit is and
you know what two-phase locking is
okay with that i'll i'll end uh and
everybody who needs to go can go and
anybody wants to ask questions you know
please feel free
to do so
i'm sorry this might be a little
a strange question but for two phase
locking
it is also about atomic operations but
there it is about one
um not a cross service but a cross one
server and two faces across multiple
servers
yeah two-based walking is irrelevant to
if you have a single machine like a
multi-core machine
and you're implementing a transaction
system on a multi-core machine
uh you will have to lock you know the
records that are involved in the
transaction
uh and two-phase locking is a perfectly
good protocol for doing so
where two-phase commit is really about
distributed systems
i guess my question was is two-face
locking can it be part of to face commit
i'm not sure i know what that means uh
the way i think about it is that you
solve two different problems
okay it is the case that you know if you
if you maybe this is what you mean
um it is the case great that you know
there's uh the coordinator
uh or as part of like the initial setup
like when the initial puts are done by
the transaction
uh then that transaction will follow
two-phase locking
you know here the lock on a x is
required lock on b
is required uh so
we're locked on y is acquired and so the
the transaction does that in a two-phase
locking style
it could have done it using strict
locking too but you know
uh from the two-phase commit point of
view
it doesn't really matter like at some
point you know the sort of transaction
is tentatively executed
and the two-phase commit is really about
reaching agreement
that all parties agreed to go along
that makes sense thank you you're
welcome does two-face commit exclusively
for
like charted data no uh actually
it came out uh although
yes or no um the original sort of
two-phase commit came out of the
case where uh like you have different
organizations and they need to agree to
do something like you know you book a
uh on some uh a travel website you know
you book a trip
and another thing you book a hotel and
you want to sort of commit you know to
the whole trip if you know both the
hotel
website and the um uh
the you know travel website uh agree to
go along or sort of
commit to the transaction um and that's
sort of the setting where
you know so the setting that where it
came up is really you know you have
different organizations
that need to commit to a particular uh
uh operation uh and
uh for the reasons that uh in that
setting actually
basically people don't really want to
use two-face commit because that would
mean that
the travel agency website is dependent
on the
hotel reservation websites and these are
from different
organizations and you know people you
know the organization don't really trust
each other
and if one goes down then there's
actually can't proceed
and so that seems all bad so in fact
two-phase committee had
sort of a bit of a negative reputation
uh
because it's really you know really one
of the
original goals of to facebook is to
solve that problem with that problem
where people don't really want to solve
with two-phase connect
however in the context where like you
have a data center it's a single
organization and the database is charted
two-phase grid is widely popular and
a typical use
awesome thank you you're welcome
could you go back to the first failure
case that we talked about with
toothpaste a bit
where um it fails b fails after
responding prepared okay yeah this one
uh yeah i guess
i think i talked twice about this case
but like yeah
yeah i guess uh i was wondering
why b needs to persist or like
why it needs to remember that it
received preparer
um i guess my thinking was when it comes
back
up if it receives a commit message from
the coordinator couldn't it just
assume that it was prepared i guess
where does it use that information
well we could have aborted right before
the crash
and b needs to remember what it did okay
so there's another slight variation of
this protocol where
where you assume that you always commit
a commit so presume commit
uh where the message is slightly
different uh and you know there's an
optimization that you could consider
um and then would make sense in some
settings
uh i i didn't really talk about that
particular protocol but just a slight
different you know sort of variation
there's quite a number of variations
with two-phase commit
changing the minor ways
make sense yep
is that it for today
sorry you said that it can it could have
aborted
the transaction but if it did then it
will
never receive the commit
you mean uh in response to the last
question yeah yeah
yeah uh you know the the question was
like why does he have to record on
stable storage what it decided to do
and the injury is that
when b comes up it knows it needs to
know whether to actually commit it agree
to commit
or we agree to abort
and if it doesn't write anything it
doesn't know to what a degree
because it could have aborted after yeah
yeah okay i need to know that to
know what to do in the recovery stage i
see yes exactly
it also needs to record what it does
because if
it like aborts but the message never
gets to the coordinator
needs to resend the same message
right yeah well it needs to record that
it actually aborted that introduction id
so when the
coordinator asks you know what did you
do that actually responds with a no
got it thank you
thank you you're welcome
thank you okay see you all
next week
you