so i want to talk today about uh
memcache
this is a paper from uh facebook from
2013.
uh memcache is still widely used and
many websites or big internet websites
you use
have ids or architectures very similar
to it
the paper is an experience paper
so the goal of the paper is not so much
to introduce new ideas or new concepts
uh or new in innovative ways of building
uh
systems but you know that's more to
report on actually practical experience
in trying to build systems that in this
particular case can
support a billion requests per second or
multiple billion requests per second
um and so there sort of three lessons
you know that you can take away from
this particular paper
uh one is they got very impressive
performance
out of building out a building system uh
with an off the shelf component
so the systems consist of standard open
software packages like
mysql memcached and they combine that
together
to actually build a system or scale that
out to a system that can actually
support in a billion
requests for seconds um as you can see
as we see in this lecture you know
they're sort of continuously in tension
between performance
and consistency
and as you will see in this paper here
the design is mostly driven
by performance uh you know but you know
they want to you know provide some
you know the grief consistency and the
sort of that
uh is sort of added to uh you know
make the system at least be usable for
the applications that actually facebook
has
in fact you know the consistency model
is quite different from
the consistency mods that we've seen
before most of the systems
we talked about so far actually provide
either external consistency or
linearizability
uh they're very strong for its
consistency
and then in the case of facebook their
applications don't really need
linearizability uh if the user
is reading news articles and the news
feed is a couple seconds behind
it doesn't really matter and so they're
they have absolutely not
the goal of providing uh sort of
linearizability or you know strict
consistency
so that's an important thing to keep in
mind um
despite that they're not shooting for a
strong you know consistency
there are some sort of cautionary tales
in the paper that you know adding uh
consistency measure um is not easy and
you sort of not have
you know prepared for him at a from the
start um
uh but nevertheless you know the you
really can't argue
uh with the success of this system uh
it's
really very successful and allows
facebook
and uh websites that you know follow our
inaudible strategies
to actually scale to a large large
number of users
um so my plan for this lecture basically
is first to talk about performance
because
really the performance is the driving
force behind this design
and then at the end you know talk more
about consistency
before jumping in though let me know if
there's any questions
okay so let me uh start with sort of a
little bit of a broader introduction
to uh performance and basically so talk
about like website
evolution
i'm sure many of you actually have built
uh websites
and you know if you're sure to start out
and you don't have any users you know
that's pretty straightforward you know
you can buy a machine or random machine
on amazon or anywhere else
uh and you just have to basically need
three components you know you need a
web server so let's say apache
uh you need a you sort of an application
framework to build your website in
uh maybe it's php maybe it's python you
know in
case of uh facebook they i think they
use php
uh and you need a database to actually
store the data
off your website and so for example you
might use you know whatever mysql
as you know facebook is doing
and so you know clients you know connect
to your website
um run you know the whatever application
code
uh whatever application service the the
website provides
and store and retrieve data using
the database the database provides
transactions
uh it has sql so it's easy to query
uh over the data in different ways uh
and all the persistent state is short in
the database so you know you just have
to back up the database
and you basically have a good sort of
fault tolerance plan
and that's sort of the uh and for any
website that has a small number of users
this is completely sufficient
and the way many websites are built
however you know when the number of
users increases
you probably need to go to a much a
little bit more sophisticated design
so this is sort of step one in the
evolution and then step two
sort of try to address you know the
first bottleneck that we'll run into
uh when you have a larger number of
users and typically the bottom line that
you will run into
is basically the computation of cycles
being used you know by the application
so if you have thousands of users
running at the website at
the same time or ten thousand or
whatever number of users it is
uh and you know just the running you
know the application code
on a single cpu or a single computer uh
gets to uh you know is the drives
basically the cpu load up to 100
and then you know you can't support more
and so fortunately this is actually
straightforwardly solved because you
know the database actually has all the
persistent state
so the typical way you solve this is you
know you keep the
the one machine with the database or
keep the machine on the database
then i just buy a bunch of different
machines for the front ends and i'm just
going to talk about the front end
there's one thing
uh which is you know typically the the
website
apache plus you know some application
codes and you know
if you get more users you buy more
machines
you know they all of connect to the
database you know to get their data
um and uh and actually this design works
out
extremely well because basically the
front ends
are stateless you know all this data
again is in the database uh and so
adding a new server you know is pretty
trivial
uh all the front ends will see the
latest rights because all the data is
actually stored in the database
so there's no consistency issues in
terms of fault tolerance is easy if one
of these machines fails you know no
problem at all
uh maybe the other missions have to take
over the load
or you know you have to bring on a new
machine of mine but you don't actually
have to anything in terms of complicated
uh
data restoration or restoration because
all the data is actually in the database
and so this is a good just typically
those are the first thing that happens
as a website to your scales
now of course you have you give your web
skills set scales further
uh and you know you need to support you
know more than say you know for example
a simple
mysql setup can probably support a
hundred thousand
you know simple read transactions uh or
simple read queries you know per second
uh probably you know thousands you know
of right transactions
and so if the total number request you
know from your users actually goes over
uh that hundred thousand then uh
you need a different plan so then the
next plan
is typically is sharding
and you know so far this is all pretty
standard and so what you do is actually
you take the storage machine and you
split it in multiple machines
so the front ends basically stay the
same we still have our
any front-end machines
and you know here we have our sharded
database
and basically you know uh some range of
the keys lives on you know whatever
maybe
one two forty live on you know uh
chart one uh 42 whatever 70 you live
on chart chart2 and 70 to 100 you know
just to make stuff up
uh there's a chart free so basically you
take the tables and the database or the
rows in the database
and sharpen by key and so when a
front end needs to know of course which
databases there are and
even though it needs to get you know t32
you know we'll go to shard one if it
needs to get you know to
push a50 it'll go to shar2
um and so this gives us database
parallelism
so like if every uh most
requests actually are on two different
charts
you know basically instead of actually
limited by the one
machine we're actually getting the
throughput of one machine say a hundred
thousand
times in the number of machines that we
have
um and so that is
typically the next step and of course
this actually has
this step is a little bit more painful
than the first step
uh because now you might actually have
cross our
transactions if you need them or if you
want to avoid them you got to
group the keys you know that go to go
together
uh on the same machine uh otherwise uh
you know you need some two-phase commit
type protocol
uh if you do uh transactions for
cross-sharks so uh
this is the step from the first you know
design two to design three
is sort of a significant significant
step
now um if you grow further further
you might think well you know you could
just shard the database further and
further
watch your fewer queues of keys per
server but that actually increases
uh you know the the sort of the risk
that you actually have to do
uh crush uh short transactions um
so there's another way of going uh which
is to observe that like well
maybe it's not really important that the
database actually
supports the reads uh you know we can re
offload the reach
you know from the database and basically
the database only does the rights
uh then maybe you know we can get a big
you know performance gain
and so that's basically the the next you
know common step
that websites take if they scale up is
you know add caching
and you know it could be in the form of
memcached or redis
you know sort of popular you know open
source uh
packages for caching um and then the
basic plan is you know
roughly as follows you have a lot of
front ends as before
and we have a set of caches on the site
all right we'll talk a little bit about
that in a second a little bit more in
the case bouquet
the case you know we gotta hear our
caches
cache layer cache one cache two
cache three and then in case of facebook
these are called
each individual server is called a
memcache d daemon
and you know the whole cluster or the
collection of caches is called memcache
and you know there's still our database
i'm going to shard it
across maybe multiple machines
this is sort of the storage layer
and then sort of the idea is you know
pretty
straightforward if your front end needs
to
want to read the particular key it first
tries to cache
and hopefully you know we'll hit in the
cache and so basically get a quick
response back you know from the
uh cache if it's not in the cache and it
can retrieve it you know from the
storage system and then install you know
the
data in the cache and writes you know
basically go straight
you know to the storage server
um and this you know this sort of kind
of design
you know we'll talk about it much more
in the details in a second but this sort
of kind of design where you add a
caching layer
works extremely well for read heavy
workloads you know so if you think about
facebook
uh it is going to be you know there's a
whole lot of users
and what they're doing is reading other
people's posts
you know looking at the timelines you
know maybe watching
looking at pictures reading the news
articles etc etc so there's a very
heavily
uh oriented uh
workload you know workload oriented to
reach
um and you know in this case you know
the reasons are going to be all surfed
from these caches and these caches can
be
like dirt simple uh
and think about like the uh
caching the key value server that you
built in lab3 you know the key value
server itself is actually
nothing more than a hash table maybe you
know you want to be a little bit smart
about
uh having locks per bucket and so that
you have a bunch of concurrency within
the
the cash server itself or the key value
surf itself
but it is basically pretty
straightforward um
the two challenges that come along uh
with this where the main challenge
basically is um
how to keep the database
and the cash consistent
so that's sort of challenge one and you
know a lot of the paper
is devoted to not talking about that um
and the second challenge
which is also the main theme for the
paper is how to make sure that the
database doesn't get overloaded
and the the issue here is that
once you know you scale up say to a
billion requests per second you know by
using caching
uh if any of the caches fail that load
will shift
you know from the front ends you know
perhaps to the database
uh and of course you know the database
uh is completely not designed you know
to support that kind of workload
and basically will fall over and so a
key
challenge in uh the whole
set of lessons that you learned from
this particular paper is the
techniques to basically avoid you know
going to the database so that there's no
risk
that actually you overload the database
okay any sort of question so far
let me say a little bit uh about
consistency because that will be
although i'm going to talk mostly about
performance you know it's going to be
important to keep in mind even in this
sort of section about consistency about
the performance um i had a quick
question sorry
um it goes back to like having the state
like the
um clients be stateless
um so what yeah there we go on the
second part of website evolution
why is it important for the clients to
be stateless
that makes the replication easy right
the clients don't actually
you don't replicate the data so you
don't have to keep the data consistent
you know all the data lives in one place
maybe
the database server okay yeah so the
idea is like any
any client can like fail and it doesn't
matter yeah it doesn't matter
and you know you're going to come
computing uh and usually you don't have
to worry about actually keeping data
consistent because data is only in one
place
like a lot of the things that we've been
talking about this semester you know
doesn't show up in this particular
design
okay okay so
getting back to sort of uh once you do
actually
cache data you do have this consistency
issue correct
and uh and so you know the instant
question is like
what is database what is their facebook
shooting for and
something typically it's called almost
like it's called eventual consistency
which is a pretty vague
term um but basically you know
maybe to contrast it is to say it
actually does not
shoot for linearizability uh and
in fact you know what they're sort of
shooting for is you know they do want
you know right ordering
so arrays are all applied in some
consistent you know total order so that
you don't get weird
you know going back in time problems and
that is all done basically by the
database
so not really a big concern you know for
uh the memcache layer itself
uh in terms of reads uh it's okay if
reads are behind
and that is really the property of the
applications that you know facebook
wants to support
again you know the uh the the data
that's in these caches is you know the
data that their users actually consume
you know web pages uh posts
uh timelines print lists and all that
kind of stuff
and or status and none of that
actually it's really that important for
users to see a very
uh um you know up-to-date you know
picture you know
it is lights behind a little bit you
know one to two seconds no problem at
all
uh certainly left behind for you know
hundreds of milliseconds you know the
user won't even notice you know
it's not perceptible uh so it's okay to
if you're behind
you know of course you don't want to be
behind for hours you know the users
might actually notice
um but you know for a little while
behind it's actually not a particular
big deal so they don't really
shoot you know for strict
linearizability where reid observes the
last right
you know if it's some reason right you
know that's fine
uh there's one exception to that and
which is that they do want to arrange
that you know
clients read their own rights
and uh and meaning that you know if
uh one client you know updates uh a key
k and then immediately reads later that
key k
it's very desirable that that client
actually does observe its own
uh right because it actually makes it
more complicated
to otherwise branding complications
would be even more complicated
so this is roughly what they're shooting
for
and you know this is quite a bit weaker
than some of the models that we have
seen before and reminding me a little
bit you know from
about the zookeeper sort of style of
contract that you know it can provide
okay so one other thing that i want to
say go back a little bit
uh so we need to keep the databases and
the caches
and the cache consistent in some manner
and so
the basic plan that facebook
follows
is an invalidation plan
or a cash invalidation plan
and we'll see later in the lecture you
know why that is the case
but basically what happens if the front
end does right
uh you know it goes actually to the
database
here's mysql
but they run next to the database you
know another program
you know whatever called squeal
and basically you know it looks at the
transaction log
so mysql you know maintains the
transaction lock you know to implement
transactions
and you know sql looks like this
transaction log sees you know what
things get modified
and basically if there's a
you know a key that gets modified so it
sees like kk gets modified
it will send an invalidation message to
the cache
basically deleting
definitely it just issues a delete of
that pk you know to the appropriate
cache
and that way you know the data will be
removed and then at some point later
when a client comes along
doesn't read it will get a miss
in the the in the cache read and
retrieves the data
from uh
reads it from there so here does it get
let me call this a get
is a read gets the data from the read
and then actually installs it in the
cache
and so one thing you might wonder like
why actually
does the application itself install the
data into the cache so it doesn't put
and then this has to do with actually
that these caches you know what they're
called are look aside caches
and the reason they sort of look aside
is that because typically what the
application will do with the data that
it actually reads from the database
is maybe massage it a little bit there's
some computation on it maybe it'll take
the text of the
page and actually turn it into an html
page or html5
and then store the result of that the
html version of the page actually into
the cache
or maybe you know reach a bunch of
different records aggregates you know
some data
and you know puts the aggregated result
in the cache
so the application is sort of in control
uh in this design of what to put in the
cache and it puts a little bit more
burden
uh on the on the front end or in the
application or the client
in this case um but it has an advantage
you know that you can sort of do some
pre-processing before actually sticking
something in the cache
and this sort of in contrast where the
cache would be transparent where the
cache would you be sitting between the
front ends
and the storage server and if you're
missing the cache then the cache will
choose the data
but of course the cache and the database
don't really know what the application
exactly wants to store
in the cache and so in the look of site
the design
this uh the application is sort of in
control of the cache
so in a little bit more detail we can
look at this uh
picture that of like how actually
read the writer implemented so here's
the
reads oops sorry
so this is a figure two uh
from the paper
and so here is our web server that is
our client
and the client you know uh retrieves
decay from the memcache
as we'll see in a second you know
typically it actually will
ask for a whole bunch of keys you know
there's nothing common that you know the
web server will ask for 20 to 100 off
keys you know presumably it's trying to
compute some webpage the web page
contains
aggregates data from lots of different
places and for every features data that
needs to be put
into that webpage uh the client
issues uh uh a get request we have made
perhaps with many many many keys
um that goes to memcache
uh it gets results back and you know
when sending that gap to demand cash you
know you might contact many
uh memcached servers the results come
back to the web server
if uh anything is missing you know it
can process the ones that actually
return the pro positive result but you
know we get nil back
then the
client you know goes and does a select
from the database who runs a sql query
that returns some data and the results
you know
of that and the client might do some
computation
and then actually install you know the
processed values
that came back from the select into
memcache
that's sort of the read site and again
again here you can sort of see the lucas
the look of site you know property or
aspect of this design
where memcache is not really sitting
straight between the web server and the
database
but sits on the site and is managed by
the client
so here's the right uh site
uh so for example uh if the web server
or the application needs to
whatever add a post or you know
put a picture in the post or whatever
the server uh doesn't update you know
sends basically the update
uh to the database uh this is just
performed like a
normal transaction and then of course on
the database on the site
you know as we saw before you know we'll
do invalidations
uh uh using you know this uh the squeal
demon um
and but that squeal beam in your
operates asynchronously
oops sorry
and so the client the the right doesn't
really wait until that invalidation is
happened again once the update in the
transaction
once the update is done in the database
the transaction is completely completed
it will turn to the client and then in
parallel the
school do actually as well builds the
invalidations
uh and because you know the
school does the invalidations uh
asynchronously
uh the web server just to uh as a
precaution
does the delete of the key in the
memcache immediately
and so when and the reason for that
delete is
only because you know we want to read
our own rights
so when the web server for example looks
for that key k
uh right after it did the update then it
will miss
in metacash d and it will go and
actually retrieve
the new value and then install it uh and
but that's just the case where uh
whatsoever immediately it reads its own
uh
reaches reach the key okay that it just
actually
uh updated a little while ago
okay when you're in principle it's not
necessary you know to do this
delete uh the invalidation at some point
will happen
and we'll kick out you know that kk out
of the cache
and that's fine you know for basically
other clients but just with this client
you know we want to make sure that
actually it reaches on
its own rights i have a question
yeah so why doesn't it
set after the delete yeah
that's a very good question like why
doesn't do you update immediately
correct
and i i think that so
that's called like an update scheme uh
and that's in principle possible here
too
uh but i think it's a little bit tricky
for them to make work because i think it
was going to require some cooperation
between the database
uh the cache and the client and i think
the
issue is as follows um let's say we have
a client c1
we have a client c2 uh
and we'll see similar sort of type races
showing up when let's say
client x1 sets x21 and sends that to the
database
um and then uh
so like now let's so this is a
hypothetical update scheme
uh and the main point of this you know
slide will be or
this board will be sort of talk about
like doing action update is not
completely trivial
uh let's say client two at the same time
or roughly after it you know says x22
sends that to the database
uh and let's say decline one has got a
little bit delayed
and so we're implement your scheme
correct and you know we immediately do a
set
of k to two and let me
say k zero at the end in the beginning
so this will update
map cache d correct so the cache is now
going to have a value of you know
whatever
ka now 2 2 then
you know point 1 actually comes around
to do actually it set
so it will do a set here or put and set
you know put
whoops says k
to one and so this will overwrite the
two
and now we have a stale value
in the cash
and worse you know this value sort of
this uh
is there um sort of persistently still
yeah any you know get later on you know
we'll see actually the the state value
and so this is not so desirable and so
you want to avoid that
and of course you can make maybe the
update scheme work
uh by for example you know ordering or
time stamping or assigning a sequence
numbers to the updates
and then by the database and then uh
the key value server or the memcached
you could basically
not perform updates that are out of
order
but a scheme like that was going to
require some participation of the
database
uh i mean and required modifications to
mysqval and one of their goals was to
actually build everything from
off-the-shelf components
and so you know they prefer to go this
is invalidation scheme
which i think is just simpler to
implement uh
because basically you know your the
database the only thing it has to do
uh is this like additional process that
sits on the site
and you know reduces the standards you
know delete operation
uh that you know memcache d already
supports
thank you does that make sense
and we'll see a similar issue like this
one show up later again correct then
because there's a uh you remember in the
paper
there's some discussion about these
tokens or leases
to deal with state of values but that's
going to be as we'll see
stale values on the reach site uh where
inter still values that sort of have an
internet interesting
interaction between readers and writers
but can be solved uh
totally in the context of memcache d
without actually making any database
modifications
um so why do we have a separate process
to basically
issue the invalidation so this says
siegel i think it was called
so white so like why do we have this
process uh if
the front end itself will issue a delete
k
anyway um we'll see you later on
why this is going to be very useful uh
and particularly you know what we're
going to do is we'll see is that the
cache is going to be replicated
and we need to set a new validation to
every replica okay
thank you it's not going to send a
delete
to every memcache replica
the squeal yeah we'll see in a second
hold on and we'll see that in a second
in fact i was going to go and talk about
it right now
uh so so so far
actually most of this story uh is pretty
standard
uh you know small changes here
uh and what you know what we talked
about so far is
nothing really uh too exceptional things
get more interesting uh
right after this and um and so
we get more into sort of facebook
specific uh optimizations or performance
tricks and uh and the one first
uh thing that we're gonna see so let me
get this
in order to go back
um the first thing that actually uh that
sort of becomes unusual
is that actually facebook basically
replicates a complete data center
at the time of the writing of this paper
there were basically two data centers
one on the west coast let's switch back
to blue
so data center one they're called
regions
here's data center two
and uh they basically have you know
they're
all have a client it's going to
so a lot of front ends
maybe this is the one on the west coast
and then you know this is the main cache
or the memcache layer
and both have their own memcache layer
so here these are front ends again a lot
of front ends
so these are a lot of memcached these
a lot of memcached ease a lot of
memcached easier
and then you know there's the storage
layer and which is our you know
sort of sharded you know databases
so a lot of machines here too
and basically you know the data center
two the one on nexus and these goes
uh is a direct replica of the one on the
west coast
and uh and the scheme that they
use kind of for right because you know
we have two replicas really of the data
correct the data
of the database is stored in two places
so we need to keep
in some way you know these two copies up
to date and the basic plan at least on
the right side
is to all the rights are going through
the primary
and one of the regions is the primary
the other is the backup region
so this is region two and in fact
i think in the paper the west coast is
the primary
and uh the east coast is the backup
and so all rights uh actually go you
know through
the storage layer on the primary so even
rights now issued by the front
ends on the east coast you know go
to the database here so the database
there
on the primary just runs the transaction
and you know we know and then basically
propagates
you know these invalidation messages
first of all it
takes the log that actually sits on this
side and
basically copies it or transmits it over
to the other side
and so this is the squeal process that
basically does that
and you know that that uh process
basically applies you know the log to
the storage in the database on the other
side
so keeping the two databases in sync and
as a side effect you know it might
actually incent invalidation messages
or delete messages to delete keys
and so you might wonder like you know
why do it in this way you know why not
for example everything on the west coast
and you know basically double the number
of you know
memcaches and all that kind of stuff but
you know the one prime reason to do this
is this gives good read performance
for user good response for users are
actually sitting on the east coast
so you know they will connect you know
to one of these guys
uh they will look up the data in the uh
cache their memcache on the east coast
and they will return the data straight
out of the net cache
so we're basically going to get really
good you know one we still get our good
read performance
in fact you know we can also get low
latency because we're basically you know
reading from a replica
now that's close by of course you know
the
these caches you know might get a little
bit more out of sync than example there
in the single data center because like
this whole updates
and invalidation it all happens
asynchronously
but that's more or less getting a little
bit okay correct because
uh we've already said that we're
actually not looking for you know strict
uh consistency or reliable or
generalizability
um i have a question so
um if so if
someone in the east coast of a client of
the east coast writes
it writes directly to um uh to the
storage on west right
um which um
it doesn't invalidate uh
this guy also goes and invalidates to
its cash
oh but we said right right but we said
um
like the client itself to read its own
right
yeah so where does the that where does
this go that of course goes through here
correct
yeah yeah yeah that makes sense okay um
okay okay um i've
got a question to you um
do clients always talk
so will given client always talk to the
same memcache server
no uh because i'll
go back a little bit earlier and we'll
talk about this in a second because this
actually is a
a problem as we'll see uh so the front
end basically talks
uh the the keys are sharded across the
memcache
servers right uh and so like whatever
key k1 k1 lives in c1 k2 lives in c2 et
cetera et cetera
and typically at front end when they
need to construct a webpage it needs to
get a whole bunch of keys
and so it sends actually these requests
basically parallel to the different
uh memcacheds and gets all the responses
back
uh and the uh and so in fact you know
the front ends are very likely to talk
to every
uh memcached in the system
i see but for but for a given key it
would always talk to the same server
yes yeah uh they actually happen to use
consistent hashing
so if like if we'll talk a little bit
about a second a little bit more but
like one of the one memcache d serves
goes down correct
you know can't talk to that one anymore
and so it might be over time that the
assignment from
sharks to uh servers will change a
little bit
sorry actually just to follow up on that
so the requirement for
clients to read their own rights is
is kind of like a week guarantee right
because if the server that it deletes
from
goes down and then it has to read from a
different replica it might end up not
reading it's right
if in the presence of a failure hold on
hold on hold that fight for a little
while okay
then we'll see there's a number of
countries or races if you will and they
have different techniques for solving
those races
oh sorry final question yeah uh final
all right
um so we're uh we're doing
um we like for read for read our own
rights
we make sure that we go directly to the
storage servers
right after a write correct yes i'm not
in the cache
um but you also said the
no no hold on hold on when you do write
you do the update in the database
right then you delete the k from your uh
system so for example in this particular
case uh
you know you would you know you will do
it right you know to the primary
delete the kek from your local cache
so when the next time you do get uh
you're gonna
uh read from the storage server again
right
exactly yeah um but um
i was i was curious so you also said
the right to storage happened
asynchronously right
the the this in this replication happens
asynchronously and the invalidations
happen
asynchronously not the rights okay the
rights are synchronous
so you do the delete after you finish
the right okay great
thanks
so if you do all right and you're from
the
[Music]
so you're not you're not from the
primary region
you do a right to the primary storage
and then you invalidate your memcache
and then do a read
but you will read from your storage and
maybe
uh your story isn't up to date yet yes
so you gotta read and so we'll see how
they solve that
that's correct but first let's talk more
about performance because they're this
is not good enough with them yet they
want more performance
um and so i you know if you're sort of
broadly speaking
um there's sort of two strategies for
getting performance
uh i'm just tapping bay back a little
bit
and we already seen them a little bit uh
in a very high level so they're two
business
plans one is to partition or shard
and that's very cool because in fact we
see this being used basically both on
the storage layer
and the memcache layer and so if you're
you know you need more capacity
uh you know you should buy another
server uh
change the hashing function and suddenly
you got more capacity in your memcache d
and you can hold more data right and
that data can be accessed in parallel
so you know you get a lot of capacity
flossing the capacity plus on the
parallelism side
uh but you know if you have a particular
key that is extremely hot
uh like a lot of clients actually need
to
get that key you know whatever a
particular person and facebook who has a
timeline that you know everybody's you
know following
then you know that that key is going to
hit a lot
and you know it's being served you know
luckily in this case is being served
maybe by two different servers one in
the west coast and one on the east coast
uh but you know presumably a lot of
clients on the east coast and in the
west coast we're gonna hit the same
or the two the memcache d server on the
west coast and the memcache reserve and
east coast that hold that key
um and so that's not going to be that
good right because like
that single server might actually get uh
overloaded and it turns out
the key distribution uh varies widely
and so that's not so good and so to
solve problems like that you know the
second sort of approach
is to replicate
replicate data so here's partition data
and i'll know is replicate data
that's great you know for hotkeys
if you can take the same key replicate
it on a bunch of different memcached
servers
then the clients that all meet that key
can be spread across you know those
memcached servers and get the keys
basically in parallel
uh and so that works actually good for
hotkeys
it doesn't really increase your capacity
right so you just
just takes more
and in some ways we can see that in the
previous picture you know we have
replication in action here correct we
have replicated
one data center you know from the west
coast completely to the east coast
that hasn't introduced you know
increased the total capacity
uh for demand capacities because both
memcached the main cast layers you know
store
you know stored the same amount of uh
data you didn't increase the capacity of
the the memcache layer
um but you know you're allowed to now
read from these two different and
memcached layers on the east and west
coast in parallel
okay so we see a little bit of form of
replication going on
and you might wonder like you know what
else is left to be done
and this comes to uh this question was
asked a little bit earlier
let's say you need more capacity now
right so well
one solution to you know more capacity
even in a single data center so i forget
that there's two data centers just look
for
think from the perspective of a single
data center we want more capacity
well one option correct would be to
whatever just buy more memcached servers
and just keep buying more of them and
that turns out to be slightly
problematic
and one reason that that is problematic
is because
these front ends talk to basically
every memcache server
and so they you know almost at least for
writes
you know we know that they have tcp
connections open and so there's a large
number of tcp connections um
and furthermore and as we uh said before
if it actually is a particular key
heart a hit heart then the
uh that doesn't really be solved by
sharding so you can you know buy more
machines but there's not one key is hot
that lives in one machine that actually
is not going to really improve your
performance
so their next step in terms of you know
improvement is to actually replicate
with inside
a single data center so
more performance and this is this idea
of clusters
and this is really a story about
replication
and so what they actually do is like if
we look in the single data center
we got we got our storage layer
and then within the storage layer
basically we're going to
replicate a set of front ends
so here's a front-end layer and here's
our
memcache layer
i'm going to take that and just
replicate it
multiple times
and i'm going to call this a cluster
and uh and the reason this is good you
know is this actually deals deal well
with
you know it's good for popular keys
if your public key will now be
replicated you know potentially multiple
clusters
and so that is nice
second it reduces the number of
connections
and this is actually particularly
there's multiple reasons why this is
important
uh it avoids what they call the
before it's the in-cast problem in cast
congestion
and so as i said before like one of
these front ends uh
may have to retrieve you know 500 you
know whatever
under you know tens to hundreds of keys
um and so it will send them in parallel
to all the
particular uh then cache that are
important they will all respond
uh and of course you know you have many
many more
uh memcaches we're gonna have much more
parallelism a lot of packets will come
back exactly at the same time
they can easily lead into uh queue
cures being overloaded or includes being
full and therefore pack is getting
dropped
and so by reducing the number of
connections not actually every friend
they talks to
you know reduces where responses are
going to come back and we avoid this
in case congestion problem and in
general it sort of reduces the pressure
on the network
it's actually hard to build networks
that have bisection bandwidth that can
sustain
a huge load and here by sort of making
using replication basically every
network for one cluster really has to
support that one cluster
well
now uh so this is all good of course you
know this is
the downside of the design like this is
that if you have unpopular keys
uh there's in public keys gonna get
stored in
uh multiple regions and basically you
know do nothing
or then really contribute to uh
improvement in performance
and so in fact you know what they do is
they have one additional sort of pool
that they have
and they call this the regional pool
and applications can decide
to store not so uh popular keys
into the regional pool and to just stick
it at the side
and uh so that these uh uh
so that they uh they don't uh are
replicated in times across all clusters
so you can think about a regional pool
being shared among
multiple clusters and used for the less
popular keys or less
infrequently used keys okay
so this is going to help with popular
keys because um
each cluster is going to have its own
memcache
yep yeah every culture has its own
has his own front ends it has his own
memcache
and basically users you know the the
users are basically
uh uh load balance across all these
clusters
but this still does not increase
capacity right
not increase uh capacity uh if you want
to
the uh increased capacity
you you well increase capacity a little
bit correct because like all the
unpopular stuff is not being extra cash
and you're stuck in the regional pool
okay and so that space is now free to
actually store other keys
so to avoid in-cast congestion they
would also reduce the number of shards
per cluster right yeah or you know don't
include
don't grow it the alternative plan
correct was not to introduce clusters
but basically keep growing the memcaches
charts the numerous shards in a single
memcache
and you know that has its own
limitations
makes sense thank you
okay well uh
so this sort of the the base design
except there's sort of all kinds of
perform challenges that they had to
resolve most of these performing
challenges
really have to do with i think the way
to think about is protecting the
database
so
go back to this picture correctly we
have now designed
apparently to support you know billions
requests per second
and but the storage layer itself uh you
know you started
because certainly not you know sustain
billions requests per second
and it would be a disaster uh if for
example
let's say all the memcaches failed or
some way another or a whole cluster
failed
and all the front-ends you know would
hit the storage servers
uh then you know the storage servers
would fail over you know they couldn't
handle that kind of load
and so they got to be very very careful
with actually
putting doing anything that requires
more load than the storage servers so
so one for example challenge i'm going
to talk about the number of them
is to bring up a new cluster
you know the easy way to bring up a new
cluster would be just to
you know build the cluster you know turn
the machines on
install the software and then be done
uh and basically rely on the fact that
you know
if the data is not in the cache you know
you'll have a miss
and then we'll miss we'll go to the
database and actually you know collect
the necessary data
um and you know what is the problem
about the kind of design
it's going to have a lot of cache misses
because there's nothing in the camera
yeah
for example let's say you have you had
one cluster
and you entered the second cluster right
and you moved half of your users to the
second cluster
right then 50 of sort of your uh
requests are going to miss in the cache
and they're going to hit the database
and the database will fall over
correct so how do they deal with this
no not the gutter this is the
i think they were making the new cluster
read some entries from the cache of an
old cluster
yeah okay so it gets in the new cluster
uh if they miss in the new cluster they
go to the old cluster
from an existing one
and then they set in the
new cluster so basically one way to
think about is
they fill up a new cluster or warm up a
new cluster
by uh reading from an existing cluster
and so that maybe increase the load on
an existing cluster a little bit
but at least the bond actually put a lot
of pressure on the database
and as we'll see in a second uh you know
that also introduces again some
uh consistency issues uh and you know
we'll see that a little bit later okay
so that's one
you know example of the performance
challenge the the address
the other performance is a popular term
used in many contexts that are called
the thundering herds problem
what's the funding hurt problem
i guess when there are a lot of um
writes and reads
approximately at the same time and
because there are a lot of
rights the data will be invalidated um
many times and the database will be uh
assaulted with requests yeah and you can
make it even simpler like a single right
uh cause an invalidation of a key
correct
um and you know anybody any client that
reads the key right after it so like you
could have the following situation
you have a very very popular key the uh
you invalidate the key so you delete the
key from the cache
all the uh machines or all the front
ends uh that need that popular key
you know we'll do a get on that key all
get back nil
and then they all want to like read
select from the database correct
and that you know might cause you know
the puts a lot of pressure on the
database
so they want to avoid that problem and
so how do they do
that how do they avoid that problem
they use the leases
go ahead say more oh yeah yeah i think
like they gave like
a like a time like for key specific uh
for for the user and then like some like
some time
what i understood it was like kind of a
lock and then uh
like if another user tries to to like
use it
they would like wait and then hopefully
it would be updated fast enough so that
in the next retry they will get it
yeah so basically okay so the get if you
do uh
get and you get nil back you get two
situations
either you got a lease
right the first client basically that
doesn't get and misses you know gets
released from them cash d
and that memcache d that at least
basically gives you the right to do an
update
or tells the client like you know you're
responsible for doing the update
and um if you don't you know the first
one
then uh you get a basically a retry
message
or result and that basically tells the
client like oh you should retry it soon
and
not immediately and maybe spread around
a little bit uh they probably do some
you know binary backup type style thing
and retry
to get and you know most cases the
client that you know the first client
that missed uh will have updated
uh the key k you know reasonably soon
like
in the order of milliseconds and then uh
these retries actually will succeed
right and and there's no really there's
no explosion
on the number of requests to the
database with this scheme
of course it introduces uh as we'll see
in a second more you know race
conditions
um uh but you know first let's
keep focusing on performance
um there was another thing about leases
right
uh where they uh fit like
address um stealth sets yeah so that so
these
form two roles uh as we'll see in a
second one for consistency and one for
performance
this one is for performance
and so we'll talk about consistency in a
second and then we'll see the second
reviews that's one way to solve one of
these race conditions
okay one more uh there are many more in
the paper uh but just one more that's
sort of interesting at least
i find it interesting um you know what
happens if they have a
memcache do you remember failure
it depends if it's the whole data center
that
oh the whole collection of cash servers
that failed
just consider a handful i want to do
they used gutter that someone mentioned
before yeah
that they mad they failed memcache
but they don't um delete them
yeah so the so the the scenario correct
the problematic scenario is like
a memcached sure fails uh that will
result in a bunch of misses those misses
will hit the database and they want to
avoid hitting the database right
any client that actually has a couple
keys in those servers is going to try to
retrieve the key will fail and then you
know have to do something
so when the get fails
you know the easy solution is to go to
the database
about that you know we want to protect
the database and so that doesn't seem to
a great idea
and so what they do is actually they
have a small other cluster or another
pool like the regional pool you know
they're called the gutter pool
and the gutter pool is basically a sort
of a handful of manchester machines
that is just available uh and and
they're available for the
short period of time the the system sort
of reconfigures and repairs itself and
adds new memcached servers you know to
uh to replace the ones that failed
but in that period of time you know
that's when you order minutes
or maybe a little bit more uh they don't
want you know
the get requests or the selects to go to
the database instead what they do when
they get fails
you go try first the gutter pool and
you know the gutter pool will uh you
know the first one that hits the gutter
pool you know will fail
or it will miss uh do select in the
database get the results stick it into
the gutter pool
and then subsequent uh requests our
guests will actually then be answered
from the gutter pool
and at some point you know the man cache
d uh machine that was failed you know
has either been replaced or replaced
with another machine or recovered
and then you know the load just shifts
back to this memcached server and the
gutter bull sort of sits again in the
site
to sort of carry over between these sort
of transition periods
okay so this sort of gets us to the
i guess the reading question for today
as you just mentioned
the gutter poles you don't do a delete
from the gutter pool
and invalidations are actually also not
sent to the gutter pool
uh and the question is like you know why
or you know can we speculate on why so
maybe this is a good time for a quick
breakout room
a couple minutes you know to either
discuss other aspects from the
memcached design and you want to discuss
we're trying to figure out what the
answer to that question is
so maybe we can do a breakout yes thank
you
next
this
okay is everybody back
it looks like it yep okay good
okay so uh anybody you know the paper
doesn't answer this question
very precisely but anybody don't want to
dare to speculate what the answer is
on the deletes no deletes or no
invalidations to the
gutter cluster we said that uh okay
oh what we said was something like if
you do then it would
have a lot of pressure on the gutter
pool because there are so few machines
and for every cache miss there are two
requests and for
a cache header just one so if you do
that
after every write you would have an
extra request
on the gutter pool and it's so small so
you don't want to do that and also you
would
protect the database as well because you
constantly query it after a write
request yeah exactly i think and
in general the delete messages also will
have to go to two polls correct the
original memcached people
all the memcached depots i need to
invalidate it and two together
and so you know also double the delete
traffic so i think that's a perfectly
i think that's the the reason it's a
small set of machines it's just there to
sort of
over uh basically get you through that
transformation from
uh a deleted memcached server failed
netcast
server to a new memcached server
good okay so um is all i want to say
about performance
uh even though there's more in the paper
instead i want to talk a little bit
about sort of these races
on the sort of come about because of
this uh trying to
achieve uh the high performance though
we've been talking about
uh they're gonna be three races i want
to talk about and in fact i think all
three you already identified
and so amazingly motion discussion is
presumably going to be about
um you know how they uh avoid them
and so race one is what they call scale
sets
and you know scenarios uh swallows
we have a client one and just one region
nothing uh
one cluster nothing a particular actual
uh setup
so incline one uh there's a get buffer k
you know that turns out to get a nil uh
in the scenario
uh it will read you know the value from
the database
and maybe this is the client that
actually got the token correct
uh and it's the one that actually is
allowed you know to uh
set it uh but then before it actually
gets to set you know another client you
know comes in
and writes you know k is two
to the database and then there's a put
of k on two
uh and then you know the uh other client
you know actually finally gets around to
do doing actually it's put so that's a
person of
k comma and this is like maybe v1
so okay comma v1 and now
we have a stale value in
the cache and that you know state value
is sort of permanent there
until somebody else does an update okay
and that's sort of undesirable right
that really breaks their sort of
contract with the applications
and they don't want to go back in time
uh you know would be
anonymous that actually the user could
observe and so i want to
try to avoid that um
and so what do they how do they solve
this problem
would you choose yeah some say
the leases help out here they already
have the leaks right because this guy
got at least four
must have gotten released because
otherwise he's not reading from the
database
and so at the client one presents this
lease
at the put
or can put a presenter release at the
boot um
and in fact it will and what is the
additional step basically
to check that the this hasn't expired or
something because
if the other client was able to oh yeah
yeah sorry i i mean i just realized i
made a mistake
so this is why the question is also not
so good uh let me see
the client 2 doesn't do a put correct
that was invalidation consistency
i got myself confused here so what does
the client actually decline to do
after it sets the database
going back to the lead yeah it doesn't
delete
for the reason that we talked about
earlier correct so it doesn't delete of
k
and what's the side effect of what
happens with release of uh key that's
being deleted
but it doesn't like um verify or it
doesn't
yeah actually what happens with this as
a side effect of the delete the
the lease is uh uh
invalidated so it invalidates the lease
and so when the put comes along so my
timeline is a little bit you know
this this happens quite well before
right so the put happens after the
delete the put will present the lease
that it got at the get
but that lease has been invalidated by
the delete and so the
dispute gets rejected
so basically one way to think about this
is that they leverage
you know the lease mechanism to avoid
the funding hurt problem
they extend it to basically also
avoid this stale set problem
right does that make sense
even if we don't have this lease
invalidation mechanism
we would still obey the like the weak
consistency that uh
you would have ordered rights that
happened at some point in the past but i
believe that
the thing that this thing ensures is
that you observe your own rights right
because you're all right that also
ensures that you don't go back in time
right like if you read something uh and
uh and like everybody else that comes
now after this client two
uh will see you know the old v1 and so a
client might get well behind
and not see that new right for a long
long period of time in fact one might
seem not at all
yeah but uh i mean would this be
actually going back in time because
uh clients did not read anything after
maybe
maybe back in time is the wrong word but
it won't observe v2 for a long long time
i see right now there's not something
that we wanted to happen
it's okay behind a little bit but not
you know for a long long time
okay uh second race which you guys
already mentioned
uh already uh identified too
because advantage of many uh
i guess lab debugging you know know all
about races
uh race two and this is the cult cluster
race
and sort of in the similar style uh
we have two clients client one
with client two
uh and uh
let's say k is v one originally and so
we're in both coins are in the cold cusp
cluster
uh explain one sets the
key to a new value in the database
deletes the k
into called cluster correctly the
current cluster that's actually in
and then this client doesn't get
in the cold cluster
sees that it actually is
not there and i'm just gonna do uh
get from the warm cluster
get the value back
i mean that black you know get actually
gets there before actually the
uh the cold cluster or the worm cluster
actually has been updated
uh and so now it will do a set of
you know decay to v1 or put sorry let me
be consistent put off k to v1
in the uh called cluster
and now we have sort of the same
situation as before
where you know the we have sort of a
permanent scale
value in the cold cluster
and how do they solve that problem
anybody remember
so they have a small extension that
avoids this problem
and you guesses what it could be if you
which are c1 and the warm cluster called
clusters you know both in the cold
clusters
oh and they're different they're in
different called clusters right
um i'm not sure that matters
yeah actually it doesn't
anybody
i think they mentioned like the hold off
for two seconds though
i'm not entirely sure about all the
details of that
yeah the basically the
uh this actually causes they put a hole
they call this a hold off of two second
hold off
on any sets to that key so this
particular
after you do a delete in the cold
cluster
you can't do any sets to that key for
two seconds
and so this particular foot will be
rejected
and this is only during the warm up to
their face correct so when the cluster
comes up
it's cold you know for you know a couple
hours it runs you know to sort of start
warming up
and get its content in place and once
you know it's sort of
warmed up then you know they stopped
doing this trick
but basically sort of to you know you
know just paste this problem over
uh they uh you know think that two
seconds is sufficient
and that's the sufficient for basically
that right to
propagate to the cold database too
okay
good there's one more right problem as
i'll let me quickly mention that because
again you already mentioned it
so race number three that they talked
about in the paper and i'm sure they're
more but you know the one they say
the one that i talked in the paper about
and this is between
regions and it has to do with the
primary and the backup
problem framing backup and it's sort of
a similar problem
um and where uh
you know the client one does uh write to
the database
to the database and this is a client in
the backup so this is a backup client
sits in the backup region so it doesn't
write to the
database in the primary region so it
goes off
and then it does delete
of the k in of course the backup region
from its cache and um
then in principle if we do immediately
and this is like one of you mentioned
this like if you immediately do
get that particular k right then uh
it and uh and it won't see
the uh it will fetch from the
uh uh you know it
won't see actually the result of that
right uh so we won't see
its own uh rights uh because that right
is still
on the way to the backup or to the
primary the primary will
you know send through an uh uh the
sql thing uh squeal thing uh and
propagate
update to the database in the backup
area and so
only then you know again in the back of
they'll actually in the backup area in
the back of region we'll actually see
the k change
and so we're so we have a problem here
right where uh
if this k k would proceed without any
modifications
then uh we would see not our own rights
and anybody you remember how they solved
this problem
um was this the remote marker yeah
absolutely
it is so when the delete is k k key
and they they make they keep it in the
memcache d
of the backup uh and mark it as remote
and so when this the client one doesn't
get
they will see hey i'm gonna get a
basically gets remote back from its
local
memcache and then it goes basically to
fetch it from the primer
for private region
okay
but then the the remote marker
will be removed when it's safe to read
from
the back yes i think when the database
the
backup database gets the data from the
primary
it can remove the marker
because then it's safe to read it from
the primary database from the backup
database
does that make sense
okay so let me do a quick summary
and because i'm running a little bit
over time uh so quick summaries
you know uh caching is vital
we basically get you know this kind of
capacity that we're
talking about this paper like billions
of operations
per second there's sort of two
strategies to sort of get this high
capacity one is petitioning
uh which gives you sort of parallelism
or sharding
and the other strategy is you know
replication which is really good for
hotkeys
keys that are being requested by lots
and lots of clients
uh so that's the keys get replicated on
multiple machines
and um and you know we also see the you
know there's sort of a bunch of
almost ad hoc you know techniques to
sort of uh
get around some of the serious
consistency issues that
pop up even if the system is only
designed to give
weak consistency and so this whole sort
of consistency between the
database between
db and uh
cash or memcache is tricky maybe much
more tricky than you
uh might have fought uh because when
manchester's the cash
you know what could be the problem uh
but then as you can see you know it's
actually pretty tricky
uh and in fact you know there's quite a
bit of
research going on trying to figure out
like how could you do better
okay with that i want to conclude so
that people that need to run can run or
you go to their next zoom meeting and
but i'll see you around
and answer any questions if you have any
questions remaining
and otherwise i'll see you first thank
you
sorry i have a question about so
for example for the last thing we talked
about with the remote marker
how did they know that this is going to
be
a relevant data race or how did they
decide that
it is going to be more useful to
do this additional steps of remote
marker
versus just getting stable data well i
think there is because they have this
requirement right up front although
the people didn't really stipulate it
very uh clearly
uh they really want this
like for example you you do a user
add something to their timeline read it
again
and it's not there and so that is a
thing that could just be observed
directly by users
and uh a strange inconsistency and
they just they won't avoid that
okay that makes sense that makes sense
and my other question was
on the one of the first slides where you
had
invalidation of the memcache
let me find where i had that
uh i hear
well uh yeah this is the day it's like a
little bit wild now
but oh no it was one of the later
well ones also has some validation on it
oh no it doesn't uh
maybe the next one yes oh yeah
yeah yeah um so the client is going to
set the invalidation only for its local
region and the squeal is going to do it
for the transfer and for the non-local
okay that makes sense thank you so much
you're welcome um professor anne
um two why did you add your final
question
sorry sorry yeah yeah no go ahead please
these are after class they don't count
um so first so servers servers in um
um in a region are assigned when we have
clusters
each one are assigned to a cluster right
yeah
yeah yeah so every every class is really
a replica
okay nice yeah and like like
servers are assigned to one single
replica yeah
nice and then um the second one was like
straight from the paper and very precise
but it says
um like okay here um
in i think generic cache in page two
it says like um the use
memcache is more a general p-value store
and in particular they say it takes
little effort for new services to
leverage
the existing marcher infrastructure
without the burden of tuning optimizing
provisioning
and maintaining a large shuttle fleet so
i i wasn't sure and i looked up and i
couldn't find what up like
what's existing marching infrastructure
i don't actually know exactly what
they're referring to
so okay all right cool
thanks
see you uh i wanted to follow up on a
question that i think william asked
about
uh a certain failure mode if i'm in cash
d
server fails um
i think there's a die i'm trying to
think which slide would be helpful to
look at
uh um
this was earlier oh maybe that one the
one you were just
just anything that kind of shows them
them catch the the overall system
diagram i guess
okay well the remote multiple doors but
this is the
one basically if you think about it as a
single cluster if you will yeah okay
um yeah look at another one but i think
this is sort of
probably good enough then yeah i think
this is this is good
um yeah i think his question was
um so shoot
uh try to remember it um but it was
something about like
uh if a client if a front end writes
um yeah if a client
writes to its memcache d server and that
memcached server crashes
and then the client immediately tries
then it switches presumably switches to
another
memcached server and then reads it again
what mechanism make sure it doesn't see
that it seemed the result of its
previous rate
i think what happens is we probably go
to the gutter
okay when the memcache d fails correct
that client will get a no response back
and uh when that no response comes back
it actually goes through the gutter
which has
nothing in it uh probably in the first
try
and we'll read it from whatever database
okay okay that that makes sense
and it's a little bit unclear exactly
what happens when a new machine gets
added you know they don't really talk
much about it in the paper
but i presume this is actually the
consistent hashing part where
keys will sort of be automatically
shifted from one machine to another
um i guess would it if there were
multiple clusters
wouldn't it not maybe i just need to
reread it about the gutter but wouldn't
it
potentially shift to another memcache b
in the oh actually it wouldn't no no
no no i think and then always when a get
fails
the client goes through the gutter right
okay yeah these clusters are kind of
self-contained with the front end and
the memcache
okay okay that makes yeah that makes
perfect sense all right
thank you follow up on that
when it falls back to the gutter what if
like
two different clusters uh their memcache
server fails like at the same time and
so they both go to the gutter
and now we're doing like concurrent
rights to the gutter
um how do we ensure that those rights
don't go out of order
uh you know they do sets correct uh
and the the rights always go to the
the database to the primary the primary
order is all of them
so i think rights are always ordered
the only thing that you know the
clients might do is you know set the
value in or put a value into the kv
server
but then they have done that after
they've read from the database
right so what if someone's like doing a
they do
a read um and then they're setting it
into the database but
like uh let's say two different clusters
fail um
and then i'm not sure if this is
possible actually but let's say like
uh one cluster one first reads from a
key gets back to value
and then there's a write in between and
then the second cluster then reads
and then they both try to put into the
memcache servers
but but let's say those
servers fail yeah maybe you know maybe
it's a good question i think there's all
kinds of little corner cases that
actually not describe the case
i think maybe leases will help out
because that
server you're going to set to doesn't
have the lease
for uh the the first one who did the get
got the lease back
correct to do the set um and
uh the if in the meantime the service
gets replaced
the replacement server does not know
that actually the lease was granted
and so we'll reject the set
i'm just speculating correct okay yeah
so
for the gutter how does it control
lisa's there
i don't know oh okay i see
sorry i can speculate but you know
certainly i don't know uh what would you
say if you had to speculate
well i would first have to go sit down
and think a little bit about it
okay that makes sense yeah thank you
i have a bit of a tangential question
which is um
i thought it was really cool that they
were using udp for the get requests and
then tcp for the others
and i was wondering like how common that
is is that like a very
standard thing to do yes yes and no
um it is you know
i can people prefer in general to use
tcp because it provides reliability
ordering and all the good great stuff
but there's real overheads with it you
know like the uh you know the state that
needs to be maintained per
connections uh per connection and so
there's always a little bit of a
struggle like when machines have a lot
of
incoming tcp connection or a lot of
outgoing connections
that always causes problems and uh
in in the default you know if you run
into that problem is to basically do udp
type stuff
okay sometimes like novel from this
paper
no it's not enough from this paper uh
some people like to roll their own sort
of like reliability transport protocol
over udp
like quick yeah for example
yeah because they mentioned they also do
like uh sequence numbers
connections okay but presumably then
overtake congestion windows and all the
other scaling and all the other tcp
features that tcp has
thank you you're welcome
another oops sorry go ahead
uh okay i guess uh i just wanted to
quickly ask about
um kind of the replication between the
different clusters
but basically they don't do any formal
representation yeah they're correct
well yeah they're uh no
well yes and no right because you know
the uh databases need to be updated
oh hold on hold on let me actually go
back and make sure
you know what you're talking about let's
see clusters
yeah we've got multiple clusters yeah
there's no real replication going on
between the clusters right because
there's one single storage layer
right and so there are they're kind of
like depending on
these leases to keep the caches
up-to-date or
the the every cluster is completely
independent
right they have nothing to do with each
other and
user are divided over these clusters
and so one user talks through one
cluster and
uh and then you know within the cluster
you know they use
leases or
and this database invalidates leases and
keys
right god okay yeah so it's like the
squeal and the storage
yeah all the rights basically in the end
just go through the storage correct
all rights go through here
they get ordered and you know they pop
out
of the validation messages
thank you
um yeah go away yeah uh
so tangential question um
and i guess i'm not sure this is because
of the way we've kind of
presented papers in the class but it
kind of seems like
um the way these systems are developed
is like okay we have like
uh these these systems like our needs
are continuing to scale so let's
like maybe this is also not an accurate
representation but it sounds like let's
add another layer
to kind of handle this float or to kind
of you know cache something
or add another layer of complexity on
top of it
is it fair to say that like system
development
has generally been like let's just add
another layer
to kind of deal with yeah yes or no
i think the the design of this system
took a very pragmatic approach you know
to figure out like run into a real
problem and solve the real problem
uh and uh and then basically if you
think about it you know not a lot of
additional mechanism right
you could actually uh make it all work
uh so in terms
i mean i think it's pretty impressive
that you can get this kind of
performance and they have off-the-shelf
components
right
absolutely people also go back once in a
while say like okay how would i design a
system to
get better performance and don't for
example have this inconsistencies
between the database and the caches
and you know it actually turns out to be
a research problem
you know because people haven't really
figured out how to do that and so you'll
see recent research papers that
describe alternative solutions or
new components of a solution because
like you know any of the proposals i
know of
you know cannot support the building
operations per second yeah
right okay that's interesting
thank you yeah this is fascinating stuff
it's like a real world
system design uh i have one more
question if you don't mind
yeah go ahead no uh so in the design
here where they replicate across
different regions
so sorry just to clarify when they the
first clarification question i have is
when they replicate against different
regions each region has like a bunch of
internal clusters right yes yes
and then uh my follow-up question to
that is
it seems like everything is yeah
everything is hitting the primary
storage
if let's say we wanted to scale up so
that we didn't
have all the rights hitting the primary
storage
how would you like go about designing
yeah
yeah my suspicion is that there are
actually uh
the design that's correct okay so
there's a bunch of points of that
there's a whole other paper on this
topic about actually how to do the
replication
uh so this is not the only facebook
paper around scaling things up there's a
system
that was published in 2015 or wormhole
where you know they have a scalable
design to propagate these rights
my suspicion is also that they will or
have shard
the users to particular regions
and make some regions the primary for
those users
i see so they assign different regions
primaries for different shards
yeah i think so that's why i would do or
try to do
and i'm speculating here uh
would it be a wise decision to do like a
consensus protocol across the storage
layers or would that
just be like too high you could do that
like
we would spend or does not correct right
and how fast is spanner pretty fast
ah when you look back into the back end
of the table
how many transactions per second could
it do
um i do not remember the exact number
i think about a hundred oh oh
in fact effect four i think white area
right this is for right transactions
right yeah okay right right the right
transactions are very slow
yep
uh sorry i think i realized that i did
not understand
race one okay let me see if i can
replicate it
yeah let's see where we race one
i think i'm just confused what is v2
uh v2 is this right
hold it i'll mark it
okay
and the problem is that it is like
wedged
in between the first one
okay
okay so like
we wanted it to be deleted so that the
next person can
re refresh it from the database but
now it's there with the old value yeah
so basically we have a permanent stable
value
really the issue is this permanent
business
or you know permanent between clothes
correct because it's a cache
uh but like now this this put
uh that came after you know basically
the k
being k the k like k being updated you
know to v2 so we have k
2 here really correct that's what the
right value should be
and here and actually this is v1 so
let's say this is one
what we've done here is we basically put
the k one
in after the
and that's just not the right thing
everybody that comes after now and
doesn't get on k
correct is going to get one back instead
of two okay that makes sense
okay now including client two which is
going to be bizarre
right right okay that makes sense thank
you so much
you're welcome part in the beginning
about
the evolution was also pretty helpful i
think
okay good good thank you so much you're
welcome