okay uh good afternoon good morning
good evening good night wherever you are
uh let's get started again
uh so uh today we have a guest lecture
and probably speaker that needs a little
introduction
uh uh there's uh russ cox uh who's one
of the
co-leads on the go uh project and
you know we'll talk a lot more about it
uh let me say a couple words
uh and not try to embarrass russ too
much
russia has a long experience with
distributed systems uh
he was a developer and contributor to
plan nine uh when he was a high school
student and as an undergrad at harvard
he joined the phd program at mit uh
which is where we met up and probably if
you're taking any
sort of you know pdos class if you will
there's going to be a
you will see russ's touches on it
and certainly in 824 you know the
the go switch to go for us has been a
wonderful thing
and uh but if you differ in opinion
of course feel free to ask russ
questions and make suggestions um he's
always welcome to uh entertain any
ideas so with that russ it's yours great
thanks can you still see the slides
is that working okay great so um so we
built go to
support writing the sort of distributed
systems that we were building at google
and that made go a great fit for you
know what came next which is now called
cloud software
and also a great fit for a24 um so
in this lecture i'm going to try to
explain how i think about writing some
current programs in go
and i'm going to walk through the sort
of design and implementation of
programs for four different patterns
that i see come up often
and along the way i'm going to try to
highlight some hints or rules of thumb
that you can keep in mind when designing
your own go programs
and i know the syllabus links to an
older version of these slides so you
might have seen them already
i hope that the lecture form is a bit
more intelligible than just sort of
looking at the
slides um and i hope that in general
these patterns are like common enough
that you know maybe they'll be helpful
by themselves but also that you know
you'll
you'll the hints will help you prepare
for whatever it is you need to implement
so to start it's important to
distinguish between concurrency and
parallelism
and concurrency is about how you write
your programs about being able to
compose independently executing control
flows whether you want to call them
processes or threads or go routines
so that your program can be dealing with
lots of things at once
without turning into a giant mess on the
other hand
parallelism is about how the programs
get executed about allowing multiple
computations to run
simultaneously so that the program can
be doing lots of things at once not just
dealing with lots of things at once
and so concurrency lends itself
naturally to parallel execution
but but today the focus is on how to use
go's concurrency support to make your
programs clearer
not to make them faster if they do get
faster that's wonderful but but that's
not the point today
so i said i'd walk through the design
and implementation of some programs for
four
common concur excuse me concurrency
patterns that i see often
but before we get to those i want to
start with what seems like a really
trivial problem but that illustrates
one of the most important points about
what it means to use concurrency
to structure programs a decision that
comes up
over and over when you design concurrent
programs is whether to represent states
as code or as data and by as code i mean
the control flow in the program
so suppose we're reading characters from
a file and we need to scan over a c
style quoted string oh hello so the
slides aren't changing
yeah it will they well can you see
prologue gorgeous for state right now
no we see the title slide oh no yeah i
was wondering about that because um
there was like a border around this
thing when i started and then it went
away
so let me let me just unshare and
reshare
i have to figure out how to do that in
zoom
uh unfortunately the keynote menu wants
to be up and i don't know how to get to
the zoom
menu um
ah my screen sharing is paused why is my
screen sharing paused
can i resume there we go yeah
all right i don't know the zoom box says
your screen sharing is paused so if that
now now the border's back so i'll watch
that
all right so um see
i was back here so so you know we're
reading a string
it's not a parallel program it's reading
one character at a time so there's no
opportunity for parallelism but there is
a good opportunity for concurrency
so if we don't actually care about the
exact escape sequences in the string
what we need to do is match this regular
expression and we don't have to worry
about understanding it exactly
we'll come back to what it means but but
that's basically all you have to do is
implement this regular expression
and so you know you probably all know
you can turn a regular expression into a
state machine
and so we might use a tool that
generates this code
and in this code there's a single
variable state that's the state of the
machine
and the loop goes over the state one
character at a time reads a character
depending on the state and the character
changes to a different state until it
gets to the end
and so like this is a completely
unreadable program but it's the kind of
thing that you know an auto-generated
program might look like
and and the important point is that the
program state is stored
in data in this variable that's called
state and if you can change it to store
the state
in code that's often clearer
so here's what i mean um suppose we
duplicate the read care calls
into each case of the switch so we
haven't made any semantic changes here
we just took the read care that was at
the top and we moved it into the middle
now instead of setting state and then
immediately doing the switch again
we can change those into go to's
and then we can simplify a little bit
further there's a go to state one that's
right before the state one label we can
get rid of that
then there's a um i guess yeah so then
there's
uh you know there's only one way to get
to state two so we might as well pull
the state two code up and put it inside
the if where the go to appears
and then you know both sides of that if
now end in go to state one
so we can hoist that out and now what's
left is actually a pretty simple program
you know state zero is never jumped to
so it just begins there
and then state one is just a regular
loop so we might as well make that
look like a regular loop um
and now like this is you know looking
like a program
and then finally we can you know get rid
of some variables and simplify a little
bit further
and um and we can rotate the loop so
that you know we don't do a return true
in the middle of the loop we do the
return true at the end
and so now we've got this program that
is actually
you know reasonably nice and it's worth
mentioning that
it's possible to clean up you know much
less egregious examples you know if you
had tried to write this by hand
your first attempt might have been the
thing on the left where you've got this
extra piece of state
and then you can apply the same kinds of
transformations to
move that state into the actual control
flow and end up at the same program that
we have on the right that's cleaner
so this is you know a useful
transformation to keep in mind
anytime you have state that kind of
looks like
it might be just reiterating what's
what's happening in the program counter
um and so you know you can see this
if the the origin in the original state
like if state equals zero the program
counter is at the beginning of the
function
and if state equals one or if an escape
equals false and the other version the
per encounter is just inside the for
loop and state equals two is you know
further down in the for loop
and the benefit of writing it this way
instead of with the states
is that it's much easier to understand
like i can actually
just walk through the code and explain
it to you you know if you just read
through the code you read an opening
quote
and then you start looping and then
until you find the closing quote you
read a character and if it's a backslash
you skip the next character and that's
it right you can just read that off the
page which you couldn't do
in the original this version also
happens to run
faster although that doesn't really
matter for us
um but as i mentioned i'm going to
highlight what i think are kind of
important lessons as hints for designing
your own go programs and this is the
first one
to convert data state into code state
when it makes your programs clearer
and again like these are all hints you
should you shouldn't
you know for all of these you should
consider it as you know only if it helps
you can decide
so one problem with this hint is that
not all programs have the luxury of
having complete control over their
control flow so
you know here's a different example
instead of having a read care function
that can be called
this code is written to have a process
care method that you have to hand the
character to
one at a time and then process care has
no choice really
but to you know encode its state in an
explicit state variable because
after every character it has to return
back out and so
it can't save the state in the program
counter in the stack it has to have the
state
in an actual variable but
in go we have another choice right
because we can't save the state on that
stack
and in that program counter but you know
we can make another go routine
to hold that state for us so supposing
we already have this
debugged read string function that we
really don't want to
rewrite in this other way we just want
to reuse it it works
maybe it's really big and hairy it's
much more complicated than the thing we
saw
we just want to reuse it and so the way
we can do that and go is we can start a
new go routine
that does the read string part and it's
the same read string code as before we
pass in the character reader
and now here the um you know the init
method
makes this this go routine to do the
character reading and then every time
the process care
method is called um we send a message to
the go routine on the car channel that
says
here's the next character and then we
receive a message back that says like
tell me the current status and the
current status is always either
i need more input or you know it
basically you know was it okay or not
and so um
you know this lets us move the this the
program counter that we
we couldn't do on the first stack into
the other stack of the go routine
and so using additional go teams is a
great way to hold
additional code state and give you the
ability to do these kinds of cleanups
even if the original structure the
product the problem makes it look like
you can't
but go ahead i i assume you're fine with
uh people asking questions
yeah absolutely i just wanted to make
sure that yeah yeah definitely please
interrupt um and so so the hint here is
to use additional go routines
to hold additional code state and
there's there's one
caveat to this and then it's not free to
to just make go routines right you have
to actually make sure that they exit
because otherwise you'll just accumulate
them and so you do have to think about
uh you know why does the go routine exit
like you know is it going to get cleaned
up
and in this case we know that you know q
dot parse
is going to return where you know parse
go
sorry that's not right um
oh sorry the read string here read
string is going to return any time it
sends a
a message that says need more input
where'd it go
there's something missing from this
slide
sorry i went through this last night um
so so as we go in we go into init we
kick off this go routine it's going to
call read care a bunch of times
and then we read the status once and
that that first status is going to
happen
because the the first call to read care
from read string is going to send i need
more input and then we're going to send
a character back
um we're going to send the character
back in process care
and then every time process care gets
called it returns a status
and so up until you get um you know need
more input you're going to get the
um uh sorry
this is not working um you're going to
get any more input for every time you
want to read a character
and then when it's done reading
characters what i haven't shown you here
what seems to be missing
somehow is when things exit and when
things exit
let's see if it's on this slide yeah so
there's a return success and a return
bad input that i'd forgotten about
and so uh you know these return a
different status and then they're done
so when process care uh you know
in in the read stream version when it
returns you know bad input or success
we we say that you know it's done and so
as long as the caller
is going through and um
you know calling until it gets something
that's not need more input
then the go routine will finish but you
know maybe if we stop early if the
caller like hits an eof and stops on its
own without telling us that it's done
there's a go routine left over and so
that could be a problem
and so you just you need to make sure
that you know when and why
each go routine will exit and the nice
thing is that if you do make a mistake
and you leave guardians stuck they just
sit there it's like the best possible
bug in the world because they just sit
around waiting for you to look at them
and all you have to do is remember to
look for them
and so you know here's a very simple
program at least go routines and it runs
an http server
and so you know if we run this it kicks
off a whole bunch of effort routines
and they all uh block trying to send to
a channel and then it makes the http
server
and so if i run this program it just
sits there and if i type control
backslash on a unix system i get a sig
quit
which makes it crash and dump all the
stacks of the go routines
and you can see on the slide that you
know it's going to print over and over
again here's the go routine in h
called from g called from f and and in a
channel send
and if you look at the line numbers you
can see exactly where they are
another option is that since we're in an
http server
and the hp server imports the net http
prof package
you can actually just visit the http
server's debug pprofgoreteen url
which gives you the stacks of all the
running go routines and unlike the crash
dump
it takes a little more effort and it
deduplicates the go routines based on
their stacks
and so and then it sorts them by how
many there are of each stack and so if
you have a go routine leak
the leak shows up at the very top so in
this case you've got 100 go routines
stuck in h called from g
call from f and then we can see there's
like one of a couple other go routines
and we don't really care about them
and so you know this is a new hint that
it just it's really really useful to
look for stucco routines by just
going to this end point all right
so that was kind of the warm-up now i
want to look at the first
real concurrency pattern which is a
publish subscribe server
so publish subscribe is a way of
structuring a program that you decouple
the parts that are publishing
interesting events
from the things that are subscribing to
them and there's a published subscriber
pub sub server in the middle that
connects those
so the individual publishers and the
individual subscribers don't have to be
aware
of exactly who the other ones are so you
know on your android phone
um an app might publish a make a phone
call event and then the the dialer might
subscribe to that and actually start and
you know help dial
and and so in a real pub sub server
there are ways to filter events based on
like what kind they are
so that when you publish and make a
phone call event like it doesn't go to
your email program
but you know for now we're just going to
assume that the filtering is taken care
of separately
and we're just worried about the actual
publish and subscribe
and the concurrency of that so here's an
api
we want to implement with any number of
clients that can call subscribe
with a channel and afterwards events
that are published will be sent on that
channel
and then when a client is no longer
interested it can call cancel and pass
in the same channel
to say stop sending me events on that
channel and the way that cancel will
signal that it really is done
sending events on that channel is it
will close the channel so that the the
receive the caller can can keep
receiving events until it sees the
channel get closed and then it knows
that the cancel has taken effect
um so notice that the information is
only flowing
one way on the channel right you can
send to the channel
and then it the receiver can receive
from it and the information flows from
the sender to the receiver and it never
goes the other way
so closing is also a signal from the
sender
to the receiver but all the sending is
over the receiver cannot close the
channel to tell the sender like i don't
want you to send anymore
because that's information going the
opposite direction and it's just a lot
easier to reason about
if the information only goes one way and
of course
if you need communication in both
directions you can use a pair of
channels
and it often turns out to be the case
that those uh
different directions may have different
types of data flowing like before we saw
that there were runes going in one
direction and status updates going in
the other direction
so how do we implement this api
here's a pretty basic implementation
that you know could be good enough
we have a server and the server state is
a map of registered subscriber channels
protected by a lock
we initialize the server by just
allocating the map
and then to publish the event we just
send it to every registered channel
to subscribe a new channel we just add
it to the map and to cancel we take it
out of the map
and then because these are all um these
are all methods that might be called
from multiple go routines
um we need to call lock and unlock
around these
to um you know protect the map and
notice that i wrote defer unlock
right after the lock so i don't have to
remember to unlock it later
uh you've probably all seen this you
know it's sort of a nice idiom to just
do the lock unlock and then you know
have a blank line and have that be its
own kind of paragraph in the code
one thing i want to point out is that
using defer makes sure that the mutex
gets unlocked
even if you have multiple returns from
the function so you can't forget
but it also makes sure that it gets
unlocked if you have a panic
like in subscribe and cancel where
there's you know panics for misuse
and there is a subtlety here about if
you might not want to unlock the mutex
if
the panic happened while the thing that
was locked is in some inconsistent state
but i'm going to ignore that for now in
general
you try to avoid having the the things
that might panic
happen while you're you know potentially
an inconsistent state
and i should also point out that the use
of panic at all in subscribe
and cancel implies that you really trust
your clients not to misuse the interface
that
it is a program error worth you know
tearing down the entire program
potentially
for that to happen and in a bigger
program where other clients were using
this api
you'd probably want to return an error
instead and not have the possibility of
taking down the whole program
but panicking simplifies things for now
and you know error handling in general
is kind of
not the topic today
a more important concern with this code
than panics is what happens
if a go routine is slow to receive
events
so all the operations here are done
holding the mutex which means all the
clients kind of have to proceed in
lockstep
so during publish there's a loop that's
sending
on the channels sending the event to
every channel and if one subscriber
falls behind
the next subscriber doesn't get the
event until that slow subscriber you
know wakes up and actually gets the
the event off off that channel and so
one slow subscriber
can slow down everyone else and you know
forcing them to proceed in lockstep this
way
is not always a problem if you've you
know documented the restriction
and for whatever reason you know how the
clients are are written
and you know that they won't ever fall
too far behind this could be totally
fine it's a really simple implementation
and um and it has nice properties like
on return from publish you know that the
event has
actually been handed off to each of the
other grow routines you don't know that
they've started processing it but you
know it's been handed off
and so you know maybe that's good enough
and you could stop here
a second option is that if you need to
tolerate just a little bit of slowness
on the the subscribers then you could
say that they need to give you a
buffered channel with room for a couple
events in the buffer
so that you know when you're publishing
you know as long as they're not too far
behind there'll always be room
for the new event to go into the channel
buffer
and then the actual publish won't block
for too long
and again maybe that's good enough if
you're sure that they won't ever fall
too far behind
you get to stop there but in a really
big program
you do want to cope more gracefully with
arbitrarily arbitrarily slow subscribers
and so then the question is what do you
do
and so you know in general you have
three options you can slow down the
event generator
which is what the previous solutions
implicitly do
because publish stops until the
subscribers catch up
or you can drop events or you can queue
an arbitrary number of past events
those are pretty much your only options
so we talked about
you know publish and slowing down the
event generator
there's a middle ground where you
coalesce the events or you drop them
um so that you know the subscriber might
find out that
you know hey you missed some events and
i can't tell you what they were because
i didn't save them but but i'm at least
going to tell you
you missed five events and then maybe it
can do something else to try to catch up
and this is the kind of approach that um
that we take in the profiler so in the
profiler if you've used it
if uh there's a go routine that uh fills
the profile on on a signal handler
actually
with profiling events and then there's a
separate go routine whose job is to read
the data back out and like write it to
disk or send it to a http request or
whatever it is you're doing with profile
data
and there's a buffer in the middle and
if the
receiver from the profile data falls
behind when the buffer fills up we start
adding entries to
a final profile entry that just has a
single entry that's that's
a function called runtime.lost profile
data and so
if you go look at the profile you see
like hey the program spent five percent
of its time in lost profile data
that just means you know the the profile
reader
was too slow and it didn't catch up and
and we lost some of the profile but
we're clear about exactly
you know what the error rate is in the
profile and you pretty much never see
that because all the readers actually do
keep up
but just in case they didn't you have a
pretty clear signal um
an example of purely dropping the events
is the os signal package
where um
you have to pass in a channel that will
be ready to receive the signal
a signal like sig hop or sig quit and
when the signal comes in
the run time tries to send to each of
the channels that subscribe to that
signal
and if it can't send to it it just
doesn't it's just gone
um because you know we're in a signal
handler we can't wait and so
what the callers have to do is they have
to pass in a buffered channel and if
they pass in a buffered channel
that has you know length at least one
buffer length at least one
and they only register that channel to a
single signal
then you know that if a signal comes in
you're definitely going to get told
about it
if it comes in twice you might only get
told about it once
but that's actually the same semantics
that unix gives to processes for signals
anyway
so that's fine so those are both
examples of dropping or coalescing
events
and then the third choice is that you
might actually just
really not want to lose any events it
might just be really important that you
never lose anything
in which case you know you can queue an
arbitrary number of events you can
somehow arrange for
the program to just save all the events
that the
you know slow subscriber hasn't seen yet
somewhere and and give them to the
subscriber later
and it's really important to think
carefully before you do that because in
a distributed system
you know there's always slow computers
always computers that
have fallen offline or whatever and they
might be gone for a while
and so you don't want to introduce
unbounded queuing in general you want to
think very carefully before you do that
and think well you know
how unbounded is it really and can i
tolerate that
and so like that's a reason why channels
don't have just an unbounded buffering
it's really almost never the right
choice and if it is the right choice
you probably want to build it very
carefully
um and so but we're going to build one
just to see what it would look like
and before we do that i just want to
adjust the program a little bit
so we have this mutex in the code
and the mutex is an example of of
keeping the
the state whether you're locked or not
in a state variable
but we can also move that into a program
counter variable
by putting it in a different go routine
and so
in this case we can start a new go
routine that runs a program a function
called s dot loop
and it handles requests sent on three
new channels publish subscribe and
cancel
and so in init we make the channels and
then we we kick off
s dot loop and s dot loop is sort of
the amalgamation of the previous method
bodies and it just
receives from any of the three channels
a request
a publish a subscriber a cancel request
and it does whatever was asked
and now that map the subscriber map
can be just a local variable in s dot
loop
and and so um you know it's the same
code
but now that data is clearly owned by
s.loop nothing else could even get to it
because it's a local variable
and then we just need to change the
original methods to send the work over
to the loop go routine and so uppercase
publish
now sends on lowercase publish the
channel
the event that it wants to publish and
similarly subscribe and cancel
they create a request that has a channel
uh
that we want to subscribe and also a
channel to get the answer back
and they send that into the loop and
then the loop sends back the answer
and so i referred to transforming the
program this way as like converting the
mutex
into a go routine because we took the
data state of the mutex there's like a
lock bit inside it and now that lock bit
is
implicit in the program counter of the
loop um
it's very clear that you can't ever have
you know a publish and subscribe
happening at the same time
because it's just single threaded code
and just you know executes in sequence
on the other hand the the original
version had a kind of like clarity of
state where you could sort of inspect it
and and reason about well this is the
important state and and it's harder in
the
go routine version to see like what's
important state and what's kind of
incidental state from just having a go
routine
and in a given situation you know one
might be more important than the other
so a couple years ago i did all the labs
for the class when it first switched to
go
and and raft is a good example of where
you probably prefer the state with the
mutex is because
raft is is so different from most
concurrent programs and that like
each replica is just kind of profoundly
uncertain of its state right like the
state transitions
you know one moment you think you're the
leader and the next moment you've been
deposed
like one moment your log has ten entries
the next moment you find actually no it
only has two entries
and so being able to manipulate that
state directly
rather than having to you know somehow
get it in and out of the program counter
makes a lot more sense for raft but
that's pretty unique in most situations
it cleans things up to put the state in
the program counter
all right so in order to deal with the
slow subscribers
now we're going to add some helper go
routines and their job
is to manage a particular subscriber's
backlog and keep the overall program
from blocking
and so this is the helper go team and
the the
the main loop go routine will send the
events to the helper
which we then trust because we wrote it
not to fall arbitrarily behind
and then the helpers job is to cue
events if needed and send them off to
the subscriber
all right so this actually has um two
problems
the first is that if there's nothing in
the queue
then the select is actually wrong to try
to offer q of zero and in fact just
evaluating q of zero at the start of the
select will panic
because the queue is empty and so we can
fix these
by setting up the arguments separately
from the select and in particular
we need to make a channel send out
that's going to be nil
which is never able to proceed in a
select
um as we know when we don't want to send
and it's going to be the actual
out channel when we do want to send and
then we have to have a separate variable
that holds the event that we're going to
send it will only you know
actually read from q of 0 if there's
something in the queue
the second thing that's wrong is that we
need to handle closing of the channel of
the input channel
because when the input channel closes we
need to flush the rest of the queue and
then we need to close the output channel
so to check for that we change the
select from just
doing e equals receive from n to e comma
okay equals receive from n and the comma
okay we'll be told
whether or not the channel is actually
sending real data or else it's closed
and so when okay is false we can set
into nil
to say let's stop trying to receive from
in there's nothing there we're just
going to keep getting told that it's
closed
and then when the loop is fine when the
queue is finally empty we can exit the
loop
and so we change the for condition to
say we want to keep exiting the loop as
long as
there actually still is an input channel
and there's something
to write back to the output channel and
then once both of those are not true
anymore
it's time to close it's time to exit the
loop and we close the output channel
and we're done and so now we've
correctly propagated the closing
of the input channel to the output
channel
so that was the helper and the server
loop used to look like this
and to update it we just changed the
subscription map
before it was a map from subscribe
channels to bools it was just basically
a set
and now it's a map from subscribe
channel to helper channel
and every time we get a new subscription
we make a helper channel
we kick off a helper go routine and we
record the helper channel in the
subscription map
instead of the the actual channel and
then the rest of
uh the rest of the the loop actually
barely changes at all
so i do want to point out that like if
you wanted to have a different strategy
for you know what you do with uh clients
that fall too far behind
that can all go in the helper go routine
the code on the screen right now
is completely unchanged so we've we've
completely separated the
publish subscribe maintaining the the
actual list of subscribers map
from the what do you do when things get
too slow map
or problem and so it's really nice that
you've got this clean separation of
concerns into completely different go
routines and that can help you you know
keep your program simpler
and so that's the general hint is that
you can use go routines a lot of the
time to separate independent concerns
all right so um
the second pattern for today is a work
scheduler
and you did one of these in lab one for
mapreduce and i'm just gonna
you know build up to that and and this
doesn't do all the rpc stuff it just
kind of assumes that there's kind of
channel
channel based interfaces to all the the
servers
so you know we have this function
scheduled it takes a
fixed list of servers has a number of
tasks to run
and it has just this abstracted function
call that you you call
to run the task on a specific server you
can imagine it was you know doing the
rpcs underneath
so we're going to need some way to keep
track of which servers are available
to execute new tasks and so one option
is to use our own stack or queue
implementation
but another option is to use a channel
because it's a good
synchronized queue and so we can send
into the channel
to add to the queue and receive from it
to pop something off
and in this case we'll make the queue be
a queue of servers
and we'll start off it's a queue of idle
servers servers that aren't doing any
work for us right now
and we'll start off by just initializing
it by sending all the known servers into
the idle list
and then we can loop over the tasks and
for every task we kick off a go routine
and its job is to pull a server off the
idle list
run the task and then put the server
back on
and this loop body is another example of
the earlier hint to use guaranteeing
select independent things run
independently
because each task is running as a
separate concern they're all running in
parallel
unfortunately there are two problems
with this program
the first one is that the closure that's
running as a new go routine refers to
the loop iteration variable which is
task
and so by the time the go routine starts
exiting you know the loop has probably
continued and done at task plus plus and
so it's actually getting the wrong value
of task
you've probably seen this by now um and
of course the best way to to
catch this is to run the race detector
and at google we even encourage teams to
set up canary servers that
run the race detector and split off
something like you know 0.1 percent of
their traffic to it
just to catch um you know races that
might be in the production system
and you know finding a bug with a race
detector is is way better than having to
debug some you know corruption later
so there are two ways to fix this race
the first way
is to give the closure an explicit
parameter and pass it in
and the go statement requires a function
call specifically for this reason
so that you can set specific arguments
that get evaluated
in the context of the original go
routine and then get copied to the new
go routine
and so in this case we can declare a new
argument task two we can pass
task to it and then inside the go
routine task 2
is a completely different copy of of
task
and i only named it task 2 to make it
easier to talk about
but of course there's a bug here and the
bug is that
i forgot to update task inside the
function to refer to task two instead of
task
and so we basically never do that um
what we do instead
is we just give it the same name so that
it's impossible now
for the code inside the go regime to
refer to the wrong copy of task
um that was the first way to fix the
race there's a second way which is you
know sort of cryptic the first time you
see it but it amounts to the same thing
and that is that you just make a copy of
the the variable
inside the loop body so every time
a colon equals happens that creates a
new variable so in the for loop in the
outer for loop there's a colon equals at
the beginning
and there's not one the rest of the loop
so that's all just one variable for the
entire loop
whereas if we put a colon equals inside
the body every time we run an iteration
of the loop that's a different variable
so if the guard if the go function
closure captures that variable
those will all be distinct so we can do
the same thing we do task two and this
time i remember to update the body
but you know just like before it's too
easy to forget to update the body
and so typically you write task colon
equals task which looks kind of magical
the first time you see it but but that's
what it's for
all right so i said there were two bugs
in the program the first one was this
race on task
and the second one is that uh we didn't
actually
do anything after we kicked off all the
tasks we're not waiting for them to be
done
um and and in particular uh we're
kicking them off way too fast
because you know if there's like a
million tasks you're going to kick off a
million guard teams and they're all just
going to sit waiting for one of the five
servers
which is kind of inefficient and so what
we can do
is we can pull the fetching of the the
next idle server up
out of the go routine and we pull it up
out of the go routine
now we'll only kick off a go routine
when there is a next server to use
and then we can kick it off and and you
know use that server and put it back
and the using the server and put it back
runs concurrently but
doing the the fetch of the idle server
inside the loop slows things down so
that
there's only ever now number of servers
go routines running instead of number of
tasks
and that receive is essentially creating
some back pressure to slow down the loop
so it doesn't get too far ahead and then
i mentioned we have to wait for the task
to finish
and so we can do that by just at the end
of the loop uh going over the the list
again and pulling all the servers out
and we've pulled you know the right
number of servers out of the idle list
that means they're all done and so
that's that's the
full program now to me the most
important part of this
is that you still get to write a for
loop to iterate over the tasks
there's lots of other languages where
you have to do this with state machines
or some sort of callbacks
and you don't get the luxury of encoding
this in the control flow
um and so this is a you know much
cleaner way where you can just you know
use a regular loop
but there are some some changes we could
make some improvements
and so one improvement is to notice that
there's only one go routine that makes
requests of a server at a particular
time
so instead of having one go routine per
task maybe we should have one go routine
per server
because there are probably going to be
fewer servers than tasks
and to do that we have to change from
having a channel of idle servers to a
channel of
you know yet to be done tasks and so
we've renamed the idle channel to work
and then we also need a done channel to
count um
you know how many uh tasks are done so
that we know when we're completely
finished
and so here there's a new function run
tasks and that's going to be the per
server function and we kick off one of
them for each server
and run tasks his job is just to loop
over the work channel
run the tasks and when the server is
done we send true to done
and the you know the server tells us
that you know it's done
and the server exits when the work
channel gets closed that's what makes
that for loop
actually stop so then
you know having kicked off the servers
we can then just sit there in a loop
and send each task to the work channel
close the work channel and say hey
there's no more work coming all the
servers you should finish and then and
then exit
and then wait for all the servers to
tell us that they're done
so in the lab there were a couple
complications one was that
you know you might get new servers at
any given time um and so we could change
that by saying the servers come in on a
channel of strings
and and that actually fits pretty well
into the current structure where
you know when you get a new server you
just um kick off a new uh
run tasks go routine and so the only
thing we have to change here is to put
that loop
into its own go routine so that while
we're sending tasks to servers we can
still accept new servers and kick off
the helper go routines
but now we have this problem that we
don't really have a good way to tell
when all the servers are done because we
don't know how many servers there
are and so we could try to like
maintain that number as servers come in
but it's a little tricky
and instead we can count the number of
tasks that have finished
so we just move the done sending true to
done up a line
so that instead of doing it per server
we now do it per task
and then at the end of the loop or at
the end of the function we just have to
wait for the right number of tasks to be
done
and so so now again we sort of know uh
why these are gonna the finish um
there's actually a deadlock still
and that is that if the the number of
tasks is um
is too big actually i think always you
you'll get a deadlock
and if you run this you know you get
this nice thing where the dirt it tells
you like hey your routines are stuck and
the problem is
that you know we have this run task uh
server loop
and the server loop is trying to say hey
i'm done and you're trying to say hey
like here's some more work so if you
have more than one task you'll run into
this deadlock
where you know you're trying to send the
next task to a server
i guess that is more task than servers
you're trying to send the next task to a
server and all the servers are trying to
say hey i'm done with the previous task
but you're not there to receive from the
done channel
and so again you know it's really nice
that the
the guardians just hang around and wait
for you to look at them and we can fix
this
one way to fix this would be to add a
separate loop that actually does a
select
that either sends some work or accounts
for some of the work being done
that's fine but a cleaner way to do this
is to take the the work sending loop the
task sending loop and put it in its own
go routine
so now it's running independently of the
counting loop and the counting loop
can can run and you know unblock servers
that are done with certain tasks while
other tasks are still being sent
but the simplest possible fix for this
is to just make the work channel big
enough
that you're never gonna run out of space
because we might decide that you know
having a go routine per task is you know
a couple kilobytes per task
but you know an extra inch in the
channel is eight bytes
so probably you can spend eight bytes
per task
and so if you can you just make the work
channel big enough that you know that
all the sends on work
are going to never block and you'll
always get down to the the counting loop
at the end pretty quickly and so
doing that actually sets us up pretty
well for the other wrinkle in the lab
which is that
sometimes calls can time out and here
i've modeled it by
the call returning a false so just say
hey it didn't work
um and so you know in run task it's
really easy to say like if
it's really easy to say like if the call
uh fails
then or sorry if the call succeeds then
you're done but if it fails just put the
task back on the work list
and because it's a queue not a stack
putting it back on the work list is very
likely to hand it to some other server
um and so that will you know probably
succeed
because it's some other server i mean
this is all kind of hypothetical but
um uh it's a really you know it fits
really well into the structure that
we've created
all right and the final change is that
because the server guarantees are
sending on work
we do have to uh wait to close it until
we know that they're done sending
and uh because again you can't close you
know before they finish sending
and so we just have to move the close
until after we've counted that all the
tasks are done
um and you know sometimes we get to this
point and people ask like why can't you
just
kill go routines like why not just be
able to say look hey kill all the server
guardians at this point we know that
they're not needed anymore
and the answer is that you know the go
routine has state and it's interacting
with the rest of the program and if it
all of a sudden just stops
it's sort of like it hung right and
maybe it was holding a lock
maybe it was in the middle of some sort
of communication with some other guru
team that was kind of expecting an
answer so we need to find some way to
tear them down more gracefully and
that's by telling them explicitly hey
you know
you're done you can you can go away and
then they can clean up however
they need to clean up
um you know speaking of cleaning up
there's there's actually one more thing
we have to do which is to shut down the
loop that's that's watching for new
servers
and so we do have to put a select in
here where
uh you know the the thing that's waiting
for new servers on the server channel we
have to
tell it okay we're done just like stop
watching for new servers because all the
servers are gone
um and we could make this the caller's
problem but but this is actually fairly
easy to do
all right so um pattern number three
which is a a client for a replicated
server
of service so here's the interface that
we want to implement we have some
service
that we want that is replicated for
reliability
and it's okay for a client to talk to
any one of these servers
and so the the replicated client is
given a list of servers the uh the
arguments to init is a list of servers
and a function that lets you call one of
the servers with a particular argument
set and get a reply
and then being given that during init
the replicated client then provides
a call method that doesn't tell you what
server it's going to use it just finds a
good server to use
and it keeps the same keeps using the
same server for as long as it can until
it finds out that that server is no good
so in this situation there's almost no
shared state that you need to isolate
and so like the only state that persists
from one call to the next is what server
did i use last time because i'm going to
try to use that again
so in this case that's totally fine for
a mutex i'm just going to leave it there
it's always okay to use mutex if that's
the cleanest way to write the code
you know some people get the wrong
impression from how much we talk about
channels but it's always okay to use a
mutex if that's all you need
so now we need to implement this
replicated call method whose job is to
try sending to lots of different servers
right but but first to try the
the original server so so what does it
mean if
you know the try fails well there's like
no
clear way for it to fail above it just
always returns a reply and so the only
way it can fail is if it's taking too
long
so we'll assume that if it takes too
long that means it failed
so in order to deal with timeouts we
have to run that
that code in the background in a
different go routine so we can do
something like this
um where we set a timeout we create a
timer
and then we use the go routine to send
in the background and then at the end we
wait and either we get the timeout
or we get the actual reply if we get the
actual reply
we return it if we get the timeout we
have to do something we'll have to
figure out what to do
um it's worth pointing out that you have
to
call tdot stop because otherwise the
timer sits in a timer queue that you
know it's going to go off in one second
and so you know if this call took a
millisecond and you have this timer
that's going to sit there for the next
second
and then you do this in a loop and you
get a thousand timers sitting in that
that um that queue before they start
actually you know um
disappearing and so this is kind of a
wart in the api
but it's been there forever and we've
never fixed it um
and and so you just have to remember to
call stop
uh and then you know now we have to
figure out what do we do in the case of
the timeout
and so in the case of the timeout we're
going to need to try a different server
so we'll write a loop and we'll start
at um the id that id0 it says
and you know if a reply comes in that's
great and otherwise we'll reset the
timeout and go around the loop again
and try sending to a different server
and notice
there's only one done channel in this
program and so
you know on the third iteration of the
loop we might be waiting
and then finally the first server gives
us a reply that's totally fine we'll
take that reply that's great
um and so then we'll stop and return it
and but if we get all the way through
the loop it means that we've sent the
request to every single server
in which case there's no more timeouts
we just have to wait for one of them to
come back
and so that's the the plain receive and
the return at the end
and then it's important to notice that
the done channel
is buffered now so that if you know
you've sent the result to three
different servers
you're going to take the first reply and
return but the others are going to want
to send responses too
and we don't want those go routines to
just sit around forever trying to send
to a channel that we're not reading from
so we make the buffer big enough that
they can send into the buffer and then
go away
and the channel just gets garbage
collected
that says like why can't the timer just
be garbage collected when nobody's
referencing it instead of having to to
wait when it goes off when you said that
you have multiple
waiting if it goes off in one
millisecond yeah the the problem is the
timer
is referenced by the the run time it's
in the list of active timers
and so calling stop takes it out of the
list of active timers
and and so like that's arguably kind of
a wart in that
like in the specific case of a timer
that's like
only going to ever get used in this
channel way like we could have special
case that by like
having the channel because inside the
timer is this t.c channel right
so we could have had like a different
kind of channel implementation
that inside had a bit that said hey i'm
a timer channel right
and and and then like the select on it
would like know to just wait
but if you just let go of it it would
just disappear we've kind of like
thought about doing that for a while but
we never did and
so this is like the state of the world
um but but you know the garbage
collector can't distinguish between
you know the reference inside the
runtime and the reference and the rest
of the program it's all just references
and so until we like special case that
channel in some way like we we can't
actually get rid of that
thank you sure so um so then the only
thing we have left is to
have this preference where we try to use
the same um id that we did the previous
time
and so to do that preference um
we you know had the server id coming
back in the reply anyway
in the result channel and so you know we
do the same sort of
loop but we loop over an offset from the
actual id we're going to use which is
the pre
the preferred one and then when we get
an answer
we uh set the preferred one to where we
got the answer from and then we reply
and you'll notice that i used a go to
statement that's okay if you need to go
to it's fine
um it's not sort of there's no zealotry
here
all right so uh the fourth one and then
we'll we'll do some questions
um is a protocol multiplexer and this is
kind of the logic of a core of any rpc
system
and and this comes up a lot i feel like
i wrote a lot of these in grad school
and sort of years after that
and so the basic api of a protocol
multiplexer
is that it sits in from some service
which we're going to pass to the init
method
and then having been initialized with a
service you can call
and you can call call and give it a
message a request message and then it'll
you know give you back the reply message
at some point
and the things it needs from the service
to do multiflexing
is that given a message it has to be
able to pull out the tag that uniquely
identifies the message
and and will identify the the reply
because it will come back in with a
matching tag and then it needs to be
able to send a message out
and to receive you know a message but
the send and receive
um are there arbitrary messages that are
not matched
it's the multiplexer's job to actually
match them
so um to start with we'll have a go
routine that's in charge of calling send
and another group team that's in charge
of calling receive both in just a simple
loop
and so to initialize the service we'll
set up the structure and then we'll kick
off the send loop and the receive loop
and then we also have a map of pending
requests and the map
it maps from the tag that we saw the id
number in the messages to
a channel where the reply is supposed to
go
the send loop is fairly simple you just
range over the things that need to be
sent and you send them
and this just has the effect of
serializing the calls to send because
we're not going to force
the service implementation to you know
deal with
us sending you know from multiple
routines at once we're serializing it so
that it can just be thinking of
you know sending one one packet at a
time
and then the receive loop uh is a little
bit more complicated it pulls a receive
it pulls a reply off the
the service and again they're serialized
so we're only reading one at a time
and then it pulls the tag out of the
reply and then it says ah i need to find
the channel to send this to
uh so it pulls the channel out of the
pending map it takes it out of the
pending map so that you know if we
accidentally get another one we won't
try to send it
and then it sends the reply and then to
do a call
you just have to set yourself up in the
map and then hand it to send and wait
for the reply
so we start off we get the tag out
we make our own done channel we insert
the tag
into the map after first checking for
bugs and then
we send the the argument message to send
and then we wait for the reply to come
in undone
it's very very simple i mean like i used
to write these sort of things in c and
it was it was much much worse
so that was all the patterns that i
wanted to show
and um you know i hope that those end up
being useful for you in whatever future
program you're writing
and and i hope that they're you know
just sort of good ideas even in non-go
programs but that you know thinking
about them and go can help you when you
go to do other things as well
so i'm gonna put them all back up and
then um i have some questions that fran
sent that were you know from all of you
and um we'll probably have some time for
uh you know questions from from the chat
as well
i have no idea in zoom where the chat
window is so
when we get to that people can just
speak up just
i don't use zoom on a daily basis
unfortunately um
so uh and and normally i know how to use
zoom like regularly but with with the
presentation it's like zoom is in this
minimize thing that doesn't have half
the things i'm used to
anyway um someone asked how long ago
took
and so far it's been about 13 and a half
years
we started discussions in late september
i joined full-time in august 2008 when i
finished at mit
we did the initial open source launch
november 2009
we released go one the sort of first
stable version in october 2011.
uh or sorry the plan was october 2011.
go one itself was march 2012.
and then we've just been on you know
it's a regular schedule since then
the next major change of course is is
going to be generics
and um and adding generics and that's
probably going to be go 118
which is going to be next in february
someone asked you know how big a team
does it take to build a language like go
and you know for those first two years
there were just five of us
and and that was enough to get us to uh
you know something that we released that
actually could run in production
but it was fairly primitive um you know
it was it was a good prototype it was a
solid working prototype but
but it wasn't like what it is today and
over time we've expanded a fair amount
now we're up to something like 50 people
employed directly or employed by google
to work directly on go
and then there's tons of open source
contributors i mean there's literal cast
of thousands that have helped us over
the last 13 years
and there's absolutely no way we could
have done it even with 50 people
without all the different contributions
from the outside
someone asked about design priorities um
and and motivations and you know we we
built it for us
right the priority was to build
something that was gonna help google and
it just turned out that google was like
a couple years ahead we were just in a
really lucky spot where google was a
couple years ahead of the rest of the
industry
on having to write distributed systems
right now everyone using
cloud software is is writing programs
that talk to other programs and sending
messages and you know there's
hardly any single machine programs
anymore
and so you know we sort of locked into
at some level
you know building the language that we
that the rest of the world needed a
couple years later
and and then the other thing that that
was really a priority was making it work
for
large numbers of programmers and because
you know google had a very large number
of programmers working in one code base
and and now we have open source where
you know even if you're a small team
you're depending on code that's written
by a ton of other people usually
and so a lot of the the issues that come
up with just having many programmers
still come up in that context
so those were really the things we were
trying to solve
and you know for all of these things we
we took a long time
before we were willing to actually
commit to putting something in the
language like everyone basically had to
agree
in the the core original group and and
so that meant that
it took us a while to sort of get the
pieces exactly the way we wanted them
but once we got them there they've
actually been very stable and solid and
really nice and they work together well
and and the same thing is kind of
happening with generics now
where we actually feel i feel personally
really good about generics i feel like
it feels like the rest of go and that
just wasn't the case for the proposals
that we had
you know even a couple years ago much
less the you know early ones
uh someone said they they really like
defer uh which is unique to language and
and i do too
thank you um but i wanted to point out
that you know we we did absolutely
you know create defer for go but um
swift has adopted it and i think there's
a proposal for sipos bus to adopt it as
well so you know hopefully it kind of
moves out a little bit
there was a question about um go and
using capitalization for exporting
and which i know is like something that
uh you know
sort of is jarring when you first see it
and and the story behind that is that
well
we needed something and we knew that we
would need something but like at the
beginning we just said look everything's
exported everything's publicly visible
we'll deal with it later and after about
a year it was like clear that we needed
some way to
you know let programmers hide things
from other programmers
and you know c plus plus has this public
colon and private colon
and in a large struct it's actually
really annoying that like
you're looking you're in the you're
looking at definitions and you have to
scroll backwards and try to find where
the like most recent public colon or
private colon was
and if it's really big it can be hard to
find one and so it's like hard to tell
whether a particular definition is
public or private and then in java of
course it's at the beginning of every
single field
and that seemed kind of excessive too
it's just too much typing
and so we looked around some more and
and someone pointed out to us that well
python has this convention where you put
an underscore in front to make something
hidden
and that seemed interesting but you
probably don't want the default to be
not hidden
you want the default to be hidden um and
then we thought about well we could put
like a plus in front of names
um and then someone suggested well like
what about
uppercase could be exported and it
seemed like a dumb terrible idea
it really did um but as you think about
it like
i really didn't like this idea um and i
have like very clear memory of sitting
of like the room and what i was staring
at as we discussed this
uh but i had no logical argument against
it and it turned out it was fantastic
it was like it seemed bad it just like
aesthetically
but it is one of my favorite things now
about go that when you look at a use of
something
you can see immediately you get that bit
of is this something that other people
can access or not
at every use because if you know you see
code calling a function to do
you know whatever it is that it does you
think oh wow like
can other people do that and and you
know your brain sort of takes care of
that but now i go to c
plus and i see calls like that and i get
really worried i'm like wait is that is
that something other classes can get at
um and having that bid actually turns
out to be really useful for for reading
code
a couple people asked about generics if
you don't know we have an active
proposal for generics we're actively
working on implementing it
we hope that the the release later in
the year
uh towards the end of the year will
actually have you know a full version of
generics that you can you can actually
use
the the um that'll be like a preview
release the real release that we hope it
will be in
is go 118 which is february of next year
so maybe next class
uh we'll actually get to use generics
we'll see
but i'm certainly looking forward to
having like a generic min and max the
reason we don't have those is that
you'd have to pick which type they were
for or have like a whole suite of them
and it just seemed silly it seemed like
we should wait for generics
um someone asked is there any area of
programming where go
may not be the best language but it's
still used
and and the answer is like absolutely
like that happens all the time with
every language
um i think go is actually really good
all around language
um but you know you might use it for
something that's not perfect for
just because the rest of your program is
written and go and you want to
interoperate with the rest of the
program
so you know there's this website called
the online encyclopedia of integer
sequences
it's a search engine you type in like
two three five seven eleven and it tells
you those are the primes
um and it turns out that the back end
for that is all written and go
and if you type in a sequence it doesn't
know it actually does some pretty
sophisticated math on the numbers
all with big numbers and things like
that and all of that is written in go to
because
it was too annoying to shell out to
maple and mathematica and
sort of do that cross-language thing
even though you'd much rather implement
it in those languages
so you know you run into those sorts of
compromises all the time and that's fine
um someone asked about uh
you know go is supposed to be simple so
that's why there's like no generics and
no sets
but isn't also for software developers
and don't software developers need all
this stuff and you know it's silly to
reconstruct it
and i think that's it's true that
there's someone in tension but but
simplicity in the sense of leaving
things out was not ever the goal
so like for sets you know it just seemed
like maps are so close to sets you just
have a
set a map where the value is empty or a
boolean
that's a set and for generics like you
have to remember that when we started go
in 2007 java was like just
finishing a true fiasco of a rollout of
generics
and so like we were really scared of
that we knew that if we just tried to do
it
um you know we would get it wrong and we
knew that we could write a lot of useful
programs without generics
and so that was what we did and um and
we came back to it when you know we felt
like
okay we've you know spent enough time
writing other programs we kind of know a
lot more about what we need from from
generics for go
and and we can take the time to talk to
real experts and i think that you know
it would have been nice to have them
five or ten years ago but we wouldn't
have had
the really nice ones that we're going to
have now so i think it was probably the
right decision
um so there was a question about go
routines and the relation to the plan
line thread library which which was all
cooperatively scheduled
and whether go routines were ever
properly scheduled and like if that
caused problems
and it is absolutely the case that like
go and and
the go routine runtime were sort of
inspired by previous experience on plan
nine
there was actually a different language
called aleph on an early version plan
nine
that was compiled it had channels it had
select
it had things we called tasks which were
a little bit like our teens but it
didn't have a garbage collector and that
made things really annoying in a lot of
cases
and also the way that tasks work they
were tied to a specific thread so you
might have
three tasks in one thread and two tasks
and another thread
and in the three tasks in the first
thread the only one ever ran at a time
and they could only reschedule during a
channel operation
and so you would write code where those
three tasks were all operating on the
same data structure
and you just knew because it was in your
head when you wrote it
that you know it was okay for these two
different tasks to be scribbling over
the same data structure because they
could never be running at the same time
and meanwhile you know in the other
thread you've got the same situation
going on with different data and
different tasks
and then you come back to the same
program like six months later and you
totally forget which tasks could
write to different pieces of data and
i'm sure that we had tons of races i
mean it was just
it was a nice model for small programs
and it was a terrible model for for
programming over a long period of time
or having a big program that other
people had to work on
so so that was never the model for go
the model for go was always
it's good to have these lightweight go
routines but they're gonna all be
running independently and if they're
going to share anything they need to use
locks and they need to use channels to
commute to communicate
and coordinate explicitly and and that
that has definitely scaled a lot better
than any of the planned line stuff ever
did
um you know sometimes people hear that
go routines are cooperatively scheduled
and they they think you know something
more like that
it's it's true that early on the go
routines were not as preemptively
scheduled as you would like
so in the very very early days the only
preemption points when you called into
the run time
shortly after that the preemption points
were any time you entered a function
but if you were in a tight loop for a
very long time that would never preempt
and that would cause like garbage
collector delays because the garbage
collector would need to
stop all the go routines and there'd be
some guaranteeing stuck in a tight loop
and it would take forever to finish the
loop
um and so actually in the last couple
releases we finally started we figured
out how to get
um unix signals to deliver to threads in
just the right way
so that and we can have the right
bookkeeping to actually be able to use
that as a preemption mechanism
and and so now things are i think i
think the preemption delays for garbage
collection are actually bounded finally
but but from the start the model has
been
that you know they're running
preemptively and and they don't get
control over when they get preempted
uh as a sort of follow-on question
someone else asked uh you know where
they can look to in the source tree to
learn more about guru teams
and and the go team scheduler and and
the answer is that you know this is
basically a little operating system like
it's a little operating system that sits
on top of
the other operating system instead of on
top of cpus
um and so the first thing too is like
take six eight two eight which is like
there i mean i i worked on 6828 and and
xv6
like literally like the year or two
before i went and did the go run time
and so like there's a huge amount of 688
in the go runtime
um and in the actual go runtime
directory there's a file called proc.go
which is you know proc stands for
process because like that's what it is
in
the operating systems um and i would
start there like that's the file to
start with and then sort of pull on
strings
someone asked about python sort of
negative indexing
where you can write x of minus one and
and that comes up a lot
especially from python programmers and
and it seems like a really great idea
you write these like really nice elegant
programs where like you want to get the
last element you just say x minus one
but the real problem is that like you
have x of i and you have a loop that's
like counting down from
from you know n to zero and you have an
off by one somewhere and like now x of
minus one instead of being
you know x of i when i is minus one
instead of being an error where you see
like immediately say hey there's a bug i
need to find that
it just like silently grabs the element
off the other end of the array
and and that's where you know the sort
of python
um you know simplicity you know makes
things worse
and so that was why we left it out
because it was it was gonna hide bugs
too much we thought
um you know you could imagine something
where you say like x of dollar minus one
or len minus one
not len of x but just len but you know
it seemed like too much of a special
case and it really
it doesn't come up enough
um someone asked about uh you know
what aspect of go was hardest to
implement
and honestly like a lot of this is not
very hard um
we've done most of this before we'd
written operating systems and threading
libraries and channel implementations
and so like doing all that again was
fairly straightforward
the hardest thing was probably the
garbage collector
go is unique among garbage collected
languages in that it gives programmers a
lot
more control over memory layout so if
you want to have a struct with two
different
other structs inside it that's just one
big chunk of memory
it's not a struct with pointers to two
other chunks of memory
and because of that and you can take the
address of like the second field in the
struct and pass that around
and that means the garbage collector has
to be able to deal with a pointer that
could point into the middle of an
allocated object and that's just
something that java and lisp and other
things just don't do
um and so that makes the garbage
collector a lot more complicated in how
it maintains its data structures
and we also knew from the start that you
really want low latency because if
you're handling
network requests uh you can't you know
just
pause for 200 milliseconds while and
block all of those
in progress requests to do a garbage
collection it really needs to be
in you know low latency and not stop
things and we thought that multicore
would be a good
a good opportunity there because we
could have the garbage collector sort of
doing one core
and the go program using the other cores
and and that might work really well and
that actually did
turn out to work really well but it
required hiring a real expert in garbage
collection
to uh like figure out how to do it um
and make it work
but but now it's it's really great um i
i have a quick question yeah you said um
like if it's struck like it's declared
inside another stroke
it actually is all a big chunk of memory
yeah
why do why did you implement it like
that what's the reasoning behind that
um i well so there's a couple reasons
one is for a garbage collector right
it's a service
and the load on the garbage collector is
proportional to the number of objects
you allocate
and so if you have you know a struct
with five things in it you can make that
one allocation that's like a fifth of
the the load on the garbage collector
and that turns out to be really
important
but the other thing that's really
important is cache locality
right like if you have the processor is
pulling in chunks of memory
in like you know 64 byte chunks or
whatever it is and it's much better at
reading memory that's all together
than reading memory that's scattered and
so
um you know we have a git server at
google called garrett
that is written in java and it was just
starting at the time that
go was you know just coming out and and
we we just missed like garrett being
written and go i think by like a year
um but we talked to the the guy who had
written garrett and he said that like
one of the
biggest problems in in garrett was like
you have all these shot one hashes
and just having the idea of 20 bytes is
like impossible to have in java you
can't just have 20 bytes in a struct
you have to have a pointer to an object
and the object
like you know you can't even have 20
bytes in the object right you have to
declare like five different ins or
something like that to get 20 bites
and there's just like no good way to do
it and and it's just the overhead of
just a simple thing like that
really adds up um and so you know
we thought giving programmers control
over memory was really important
um so another question was
was about automatic parallelization like
for loops and things like that
we don't do anything like that in the
standard go tool chain there are there
are go compilers for go front ends for
gcc and llvm
and so to the extent that those do those
kind of loop optimizations in c
i think you know we get the same from
the go friends for those
but it's it's not the kind of
parallelization that we typically need
at google
it's it's more um you know lots of
servers running different things
and and so you know that sort of you
know like the sort of big vector math
kind of stuff doesn't come up as much so
it just hasn't been
that important to us um
and then the last question i have
written now is that someone uh
asked about like how do you decide when
to acquire release locks and why don't
you have re-entry locks
and for that i want to go back a slide
let me see
yeah here so like you know during the
lecture i said things like the lock pro
like new protects the map or it protects
the data
but what we really mean at that point is
that we're saying that the lock protects
some collection of invariants that apply
to the data or that are true of the data
and the reason that we have the lock is
to to protect the operations that depend
on the invariants
and that sometimes temporarily
invalidate the invariants from each
other
and so when you call lock what you're
saying is
i need to make use of the invariance
that this lock protects
and when you call unlock what you're
saying is i don't need them anymore and
if i
temporarily invalid invalidated them
i've put them back
so that the next person who calls lock
will see you know correct invariants
so in the mux you know we want the
invariant that each registered pending
channel
gets at most one reply and so to do that
when we take don out of the map
we also delete it from the map before we
unlock it
and if there was some separate kind of
cancel operation that was directly
manipulating the map as well
it could lock the it could call lock it
could take the thing out
call unlock and then you know if it
actually found one it would know
no one is going to send to that anymore
because i took it out
whereas if you know we had written this
code to have
you know an extra unlock and re-lock
between the done
equals pending of tag and the delete
then you wouldn't have that you know
protection of the invariants anymore
because you would have
put things back you unlocked and
relocked while the invariants were
broken
and so it's really important to you know
correctness
to think about locks as protecting
invariants
and and so if you have re-entrant locks
uh
all that goes out the window without the
re-entrant lock when you call lock
on the next line you know okay the lock
just got acquired
all the invariants are true if you have
a re-entrant lock
all you know is well all the invariants
were true
for whoever locked this the first time
who like might be way up here on my call
stack
and and you really know nothing um and
so that makes it a lot harder to reason
about like what can you assume
and and so i think reentrant locks are
like a really unfortunate part of java's
legacy
another big problem with re-engine locks
is that if you have code
where you know you call something and it
is depending on the re-entrant lock
for you know something where you've
acquired the lock up above
and and then at some point you say you
know what actually i want to like have a
timeout on this or i want to do it uh
you know in some other go routine while
i wait for something else
when you move that code to a different
go routine re-entrant always means
locked on the same stack that's like the
only plausible thing it could possibly
mean
and so if you move the code that was
doing the re-entrant lock
onto a different stack then it's going
to deadlock because it's going to
that lock is now actually going to real
lock acquire and it's going to be
waiting for you to let go of the lock i
mean you're not going to let go of it
because you know you think
that code needs to finish running so
it's actually like completely
fundamentally incompatible with
restructurings where you take code and
run it in different threads or different
guarantees
and so so anyway like my advice there is
to just you know think about locks as
protecting invariants
and then you know just avoid depending
on reentrant locks it it really just
doesn't scale well to to real programs
so i'll put this list back up
actually you know we have that up long
enough i can try to figure out how to
stop presenting
um and then i can take a few more
questions
um i had i had a question yeah um and
i mean i i think coming from python like
it's very
useful right it's very common to use
like like standard functional operations
right like map
yeah um or filter stuff like that like
um like list comprehension
and when you know i switched over to go
and started programming
it's used i i looked it up and people
say like you shouldn't do this
do this with loop right i was wondering
why
um well i mean one is that like you
can't do it the other way so you might
just look through the way you can do it
um but uh you know a bigger a bigger
issue is that
well there's that was one answer the
other answer is that
uh you know if you do it that way you
actually end up creating a lot of
garbage
and if you care about like not putting
too much load on the garbage collector
that kind of is another way
to avoid that you know so if you've got
like
a map and then a filter and then another
map like you can make that one loop over
the data instead of three loops over the
data each of which generate a new piece
of garbage
but you know now that we have generics
coming um you'll actually be able to
write those functions like you couldn't
actually write what the type signature
of those functions were
before and so like you literally
couldn't write them and python gets away
with this because there's no no
you know static types but now we're
actually going to have a way to do that
and i totally expect that once generics
go in there will be a package slices and
if you import slices you can do
slices.map and slices.filter
and like slices.unique or something like
that and and i think
those will all happen um and you know if
if that's the right thing then that's
great
thanks sure um
one of the hints that you had it was
about
running go routines that are independent
like concurrently um and some of the
examples of the code i
i think i couldn't understand it seemed
to me like you can
just like call the function in the same
thread
rather than a different thread and i was
not sure why you would call it in a
different thread
so um usually it's because you want
them to proceed independently so um so
in one of the
one of the examples we had like the
there was a loop that was sending
um you know tasks to the work queue
but there was the servers were running
in different go routines and reading
from the work queue and doing work
but then when they were done they would
send uh you know hey i'm done now to the
done channel
but ascend in go doesn't complete until
the receive
actually matches with it and so if the
thing that's sending on the work queue
is not going to start receiving from the
done channel until it's done sending to
all the work queues
or sending all the work into all the
tasks into the work queue
then now you have a deadlock because the
the main thread
the main go routine is trying to send
new work to the servers
the servers are not taking new work
they're trying to tell the main thread
that they're done
but the main thread's not going to
actually start at like reading from the
done channel
until it finishes giving out all the
work and so there's just they're just
staring at each other waiting for
different things to happen
whereas if we take that loop that if we
just put the little girl routine around
the loop that's sending the work
then that can go somewhere else and then
it can proceed independently and while
it's stuck
waiting for the servers to send to um
take more work
the servers are stuck waiting for the
main go routine to you know
acknowledge that it finished some work
and now the main goal team actually gets
down to the loop
that you know pulls that finishes that
actually acknowledges that it finished
the work that reads from the done
channel
and so it's just a way to separate out
you know these are two different things
that logically
they didn't have to happen one after the
other and because they were happening
one after the other that caused a
deadlock and by taking one out and
moving it let it run independently
um that removes the deadlock
thank you so much sure could you talk a
little bit about how ghost race detector
is implemented
sure it is the llvm race detector um
and so that probably doesn't help but
but it is exactly the thing that
llvm calls thread sanitizer and um
and so we actually have a little binary
blob that uh you know we link against
because we don't want to depend on all
of lvm but it's the llvm race detector
and the way the llvm race sector works
is that it allocates a ton of
extra virtual memory and then based on
the address of
of the thing being read or written it
has this other
you know spot in virtual memory where it
records
information about like the last uh
thread you know it thinks of threads but
their go routines
um has with the last thread that did a
read or a write
and then also every time a synchronizing
event happens like you know a
communication from one go routine to
another
uh that counts as establishing a happens
before edge between two different go
routines
and if you ever get something where you
have a read and a write
and they're not properly sequenced right
like so if you have a read and then it
happens before something in another
chain which then you know later does the
right that's fine
but if you have a read and a write and
there's no happens before sequence that
connects them
then um then that's a race and it
actually you know
has some pretty clever ways to you know
dynamically figure out quickly you know
did this read happen is there a happens
before a path between this readings
right as they happen
and it slows down the program by like
maybe 10x
but you know if you just divert a small
amount of traffic there
that's probably fine if it's for testing
that's also probably fine
and it's way better than like not
finding out about the races so it's
totally worth it
and honestly 10 or 20 x is is fantastic
the original thread sanitizer was more
like
100 or a thousand x and that was not
good enough well what's the rate
detector called
lrvm uh it's called thread sanitizer but
it's part of llvm
which is um the clang c compiler the the
one that
um almost everyone uses now
is is part of the llvm project
can you talk about slices um and like
the design choices having them as
views on a raise which like confused me
at first
yeah yeah it is a little confusing at
first um
the the main thing is that you want it
to be efficient to kind of walk through
an array or to like
you know if you're in quicksort or merge
sword or something where you have an
array of things
and now you want to say well now sort
this half and sort the other half
you want to be able to efficiently say
like here this is half of the previous
one like
you know sort that and so in c the way
you do that is you just pass in
you know the pointer to the first
element and the number of elements
and that's basically all a slice is and
then the other pattern that comes up a
lot when you're
you know trying to be efficient with
arrays is you have to grow them
and and so you don't want to recall
realic on every single
new element you want to amortize that
and so the way you do that
in in c again is that you have a base
pointer you have the length that you're
using right now and you have the length
that you allocated
and then to you know add one you you
check and see if the length is is bigger
than the amount you allocated if so you
reallocate it and otherwise you just
keep bumping it forward
and and slices are really just an
encoding of those idioms
because those are kind of the most
efficient way to manage the memory
and so in in any kind of like c plus
vector or
um sort of thing like that that's what's
going on underneath
but it makes it a lot harder to um like
the c plus
vector because of ownership reasons you
know the vector is tied to the actual
underlying memory it's a lot harder to
get
like a sub vector that's just the view
onto like the second half for merge sort
so that's sort of the idea is that it
just like there are all these patterns
for
accessing memory efficiently that came
from c and we tried to make them fit and
to go in an idiomatic way
in a safe way
can you talk about how you decided to um
implement the go like remote module
system where you import directly from a
url
versus like yeah um i mean i just didn't
want to run a service and like like
you know a lot of the things like ruby
gems and those like were not as as
for the front of my mind at the time
just because they were newer
but like i had used pearl for a while
and like cpan and and i just thought it
was it was insane that like
everyone was fighting over these short
names like db you know
there probably shouldn't be an argument
over like who gets to make the db
package
um and so putting domain names in the
front seemed like a good way to
decentralize it
and and it was also a good way for us
not to run any server because you know
we could just say well
you know we'll recognize the host name
and then and then go grab it from source
control
um from someone else's server and that
turned out to be a really great idea i
think
um because we just we don't have that
kind of same infrastructure
that other things depend on like in the
java world it's actually
really problematic there are multiple
there's no sort of standard registry but
they all use these short names
and so uh like maven can be configured
to build from multiple different
registries
and you if you're an open source
software package provider you actually
have to go around and be sure that you
upload it to all the different
registries
because if you don't if you miss one and
it becomes popular someone else will
upload different code to that one
and um and then like maven actually just
takes whichever one comes back first it
just like sends a request to all of them
and whatever comes back first so like
you know if someone wants to make a
malicious copy of your package all you
do is find some registry other people
use that you forgot to upload it to
and like you know they get to win the
race sometimes
so it's like it's a real problem like i
think having domain name there really
helps split up the ownership in a really
important way
thank you sure
so the maybe we should take a quick uh
pause here
those people that have to go can go i'm
sure russ is willing to uh stick around
for a little bit longer
yeah and answer any questions uh but i
do want to thank
ross for giving this lecture uh you know
hopefully this will help you running
more
good go programs these patterns
and uh so thank you russ very welcome
it's nice to be here
and then more questions feel free to ask
questions yeah
oh just a little logistical thing uh the
slides that are on the 6824 website are
not
they exactly the same as russ's slides
people
check them out i'll get franz a new pdf
yeah
more general question about when is
writing a new language the
like the best solution to a problem
that's a great question
um it's almost never the best solution
but you know at the time we had just an
enormous number of programmers like
thousands of programmers working in one
code base
and the compilations were just taking
forever because
um seatbelts plus was just not not meant
for you know efficient incremental
compilation
and and so it and furthermore
at the time like threading libraries
were really awful like people just
didn't use threats i remember
like one of the first days i was at mit
and talking to robert and robert said to
me
um like in 2001 he said to me like well
we don't use threads here because
threads are slow
and and that was like totally normal
like that was just the way the world at
the time
um and and at google we were having a
lot of trouble
because it was all event-based like
little callbacks in c plus plus
and there were these multi-core machines
and we actually didn't know how to get
things to work on them because like
linux threads were not something you
could really rely on to work
and and so we ended up like if you had a
four core machine you just run four
different
process in completely independent
processes of the web server and just
treat it as like four machines
um and that was clearly like not very
efficient
so like there were a lot of good reasons
to like try something
um but you know it's a huge amount of
work to get to the point where go is
today and i think that
um so much is not the language right
like there were important things that we
made did in the language that enabled
other
um considerations but uh
so much of the successful languages the
ecosystem that got built up around it
and the tooling that we built and the go
command and like all these like not the
language things so
you know programming language uh people
who are like focus on the language
itself
i think sometimes get distracted by all
the stuff around like they miss all the
stuff around it
um can i ask a follow-up on that yeah i
was wondering how is
working on go different now since it's
more mature than
it was before oh
that's a great question um you know in
the early days it was so easy to make
changes
and now it's really hard to make changes
i think that's the number one thing
um you know in the early days like
everything was in one source code
repository literally all the go code in
the world was the one source code
repository and so like there were days
where we changed the syntax like you
used to have a star before chan
every time you set a channel because it
was then it was a pointer underneath and
it was all kind of exposed so you'd
always say star channel instead of jan
and
and and similarly for maps and at some
point we realized like
this is dumb like you have to say the
star let's just take it out
and um and so like we made the change to
the compiler and i opened up literally
like
the couple hundred go source files in
the world in my editor and like
the entire team stood behind me and like
i typed some regular expressions and we
looked at the effect on the files
yep that looks right save it you know
compile it we're done
and like today you know we can't make
backwards compatible changes at all
um and and even making you know new
changes like it
it affects a lot of people and so uh
you know you sort of propose something
and you know people point out well this
won't work for me and you try to like
adjust that maybe
um it's just it's a lot harder we
estimate there's at least a million
maybe two million go programmers in the
world and
it's very different from when they were
you know four or five
not sure if this is a valid question but
what what language is go written in is
it written in go also or no
now it is now it is the original um
compiler runtime were written in c
but a few years ago we went through a
big um we actually wrote a
a program to translate c to go and that
only worked for rc code but still it was
good enough
so that we wouldn't lose kind of all the
sort of encoded knowledge in that code
about why things were the way they were
and like how things work so we have to
start from scratch
but now it's all written and go and you
know a little bit of assembly
and that means that um people can uh you
know
people who know go can help on the the
go project whereas before like
if you wanted to work on the compiler or
the runtime you had to know c really
well and like
we weren't getting a lot of people knew
c really well like there's not actually
that many of them proportionately and
and furthermore like our entire user
base is go programmers not c programmers
so moving to go was was a really big
deal
i was wondering how did you prioritize
what features to add to the language at
like this point like in all generics
like a lot of people were like asking
for that like
did y'all know like how you choose what
to work on
i mean we've considered language mostly
frozen for a while
and um and so we haven't been adding
much uh there was a long period where we
said we weren't adding anything and then
we added a little bit of things
in the last couple years to lead up to
generics just kind of shake the rust off
on like all the like
what breaks when you change something in
the language so like you can put
underscores between digits and long
numbers now
things like that um but you know
generics has clearly been the next thing
that
needed to happen and we just had to
figure out how
in general we try to only add things
that don't have weird kind of
interference with other features
and we try to add things that are you
know really important that will help a
lot of people for the kinds of programs
that
we're trying to target with go which is
like distributed systems and
that sort of thing
cool thank you oh i had a question
actually yeah
uh so um for i noticed that like you
know
uh go doesn't have like basic functions
like min or max for like
yeah so is that like something that
you're considering like say adding with
like the generic stuff maybe is that why
you didn't decide yeah exactly right
because like you can't have a min
you'd have been event and you could have
minivan date but those had to have
different names and that was kind of
annoying
um so now we can write just a generic
name over any type that has a less than
operator
yeah that'll be good and you know
honestly like for the specific case of
min and max
so i know it's not that hard to code i
know i was gonna say i'm starting to
feel like we should just make some
built-ins like
like you know print and things like that
so that you know you can just always
have them
but even if we don't like you it'll be
math.min and that'll be there at least
um yeah we really didn't want to make
them built-ins until we could like
express their types and we couldn't do
that until generics happened
because there is actually a min for like
floating points actually
yeah i know it's kind of weird because
it's because the math library is
basically copied from the c math.h set
of things yes
so that's a good point like we can't
actually put them in math because
they're already there
okay but no yeah but we'll figure it out
like i think we should probably just put
them in the language but we have to get
generis through first
and another thing actually i noticed
that you did usako like competitive
programming yeah i did too
actually oh cool yeah so how did you so
actually i included this in one of the
questions that i
submitted let me pull it up um so my
question was like
um how did how was like how did you
go from doing competitive programming to
like doing what you
you're doing now at google working on
going how's the transition
between like competitive programming to
systems also
finally what made you decide to go into
systems and how did it relate to
programming i mean competitive
programming at the time that i did it
was not as all-consuming as i gather it
is now
like like you know you could just like
be able to
implement a simple dynamic programming
like little two for loops and that was
fine and now you have
all these like complex hall algorithms
and all that stuff that i can't do
so like you know at some point like at
some level like it was different
um but you know i was actually more
interested in the sort of
systems you kind of stopped from the
start and and the the program contests
were just like something fun to do on
the side
so there wasn't like a huge transition
there um i was never into like
implementing complex algorithms and and
that you know max flow and all those
sorts of things
on the other hand like when you start a
new language you actually do get to
write a lot of
core things right um like someone has to
write the sort function
and it has to be a good general sort
function and like i spent a while
last month like looking into dip
algorithms and and that's like you know
sort of matches that background pretty
well so like it does come up
um but you know it's just it's just a
different kind of programming
oh so you thought of it as more of a
side thing back then no like yeah
it wasn't it was definitely not the sort
of main thing i did when i was writing
programs
yeah because like today it's effectively
like the main thing i know i know it's
you
know if you don't do it full-time like
there's just no way you can
you know there just weren't that many
people who cared it you know in
uh 1995 yeah 20 years later
um can you ask a related question to
that so how did you decide to go
from i'm from like academic work
into i mean your work is still like a
little bit more different than
like the usual like software engineering
thing but
still yeah um
you know i got lucky uh i i grew up near
bell labs in new jersey and so like that
was how i ended up working on playing
the iron a little bit in high school and
college
um and so you know i sort of knew i was
going to go to grad school and
you know the plan was to go back to bell
labs but it kind of imploded while i was
in grad school with the dot com boom and
the dot com crash
and um and so like you know google was
was sort of a
just vacuuming up phds systems phds at
the time
and and and doing really interesting
things i mean you probably you know
there's a i don't know i haven't looked
at syllabus for this year but you know
there's things like spanner and
um big table and chubby and and things
like that and you know they they had a
whole host of good distributed systems
kind of stuff going on
and so you know it was sort of lucky to
be able to to go to that too
um and you know at the time i graduated
i was also looking at you know
industrial research labs like microsoft
research and
and places like that so you know there's
definitely an opportunity there for
you know researchy things but not in
academia if that's what you want
um it's a little harder to find now i
mean most of the places i know like
microsoft research imploded too
a couple years later but um you know
it's uh it's still an option and and you
know it's just a
slightly different path um you end up
the the differences i see from academia
is like you end up caring a ton
more about actually making things work
100 time and supporting them for like a
decade or more
whereas like you finish your paper and
you kind of like get to put it off to
the side and that's that's really nice
actually
at some level um it's uh
it's definitely strange to me to be you
know editing source files
that i wrote you know in in some cases
actually 20 years ago
um because i used a bunch of code that
i'd already written when we started go
and it's very weird to think that like
i've been keeping this program running
for 20 years