works again okay so the plan for today
is talking about gfs
i'm going to do it in sort of multiple
steps uh
one i'm going to talk a little bit about
storage in general
and why it's so important
and why we'll spend a lot of time in
this class talking about it
then um i'm going to talk a little bit
about
uh intro to gfs and that's main design
uh we'll focus on consistency which will
be sort of the main theme
through this lecture uh and as part of
the consistency
uh you know we probably uh do a
hopefully still time do a breakout room
and talk a little bit about
in the breakout rooms about the lecture
or the question that was posed for
lecture and then
we'll resume uh discussion of uh
of consistency okay
so um let me talk a little bit about the
storage systems in general
and why they so feature so prominently
uh
in 6824 and the main reason is
uh it is just a fantastic building block
for um
4000 systems
and so the basic idea is that you know
if you command the
you know if you can build an uh durable
storage
uh system then you can structure sort of
your application as
you know the app is basically um in your
stateless
and then you know the storage holds all
the persistent state
and that simplifies the design of the
apps tremendously
because the app basically you know
doesn't really have any stable storage
you know that it has to maintain itself
in fact you know sort of factored it all
out to the storage system and so you can
start up
in a new application very quickly you
know it crashed doesn't really matter
because it only has soft state no
not any hard state and you start it up
again and then what you start up again
you just reach the state from the
distributed storage system
and you can see this quick like when you
look at any website you know basically
they're structured in that way
like there's a storage back end you know
that little name
state and then you know there's the
application uh
middle tier that does the application
specific computation or whatever run
javascript go or whatever
um and you know it front ends that out
you know to
uh you know clients on the internet and
uh so storage is just there's like this
fantastic uh building block and i think
this is one reason that we're gonna
see this over and over in this class
that means that you know the storage
system itself of course has to be highly
fault tolerant
and as it turns out to be a very tricky
thing to do and so that is
the other side the flip side of it will
make life for the application easy but
you know the
designing and actually fault on the
system storage system is not easy
so why is it hard
and it basically comes down to uh
you know one reason that drives uh these
designs which is like we generally want
high performance
when you think about the storage system
for today you know gfs
you know its main goal is to basically
support mapreduce types applications and
so
it really needs a high performance well
what does that mean well it means that
you typically have to
short data
across servers
so you can't use one server you have to
use multiple servers and the
reason you want to read from you know
the disk and often a particular machine
has a limited
uh throughput if you want to read more
than actually a single disk and sustain
you have to use multiple disks and you
have to use multiple network cards and
so you can immediately get into this
sort of
large-scale systems as in the gfs papers
where you have thousands of machines
but if you have many servers
some are going to fail and you're going
to get failures
or maybe you're just going to say more
exclusively you have constant faults
uh and you know let's assume that the
computer crashes you know once a year
you know um now let's say you know you
have a thousand
machines like you know in the gfs paper
or actually many more than a thousand
changes but it'll minimal a thousand
machines
you know how many fails you're going to
see per day roughly
um around three yeah around three right
but that means that you know the
sort of uh a failure of a computer
unlike my laptop at the beginning of the
lecture
uh is usually a common scenario
and so if you're going to move up to
more than a thousand gene ten thousand
machines you know a hundred thousand
machines
and you're running the application you
use that kind of number of computers
you're gonna get faults
and so that means that you want a full
tolerance design
and you know the get fault hollows you
know at least in the case with your
storage system the typical approach the
way to go is going to go with
replication copy the data on multiple
disks
you know so that they want this fails
you know the other disc hopefully half
the
the data but if you go into replication
and so the data is in multiple places
that runs into
the challenge that you know the data may
be out of sync and so you can actually
get into inconsistent potential
inconsistencies
you know to avoid these inconsistencies
you know
if you desire a strong consistency
basically your replicated system behaves
as if it's uh
you know it has the same behavior as an
unreplicated system
then you know you will need some
consistency protocol
and that can require some maybe sending
messages and that may be lower
performance
and maybe the messages themselves is not
really huge you know performance
overhead but there are tick bill as
we'll see
you might actually have to read uh or
write to durable storage as part of that
protocol
and you know reading and writing to
storage internally tends to be you know
quite expensive
and so here so that we see this
conundrum like you know we want high
performance
uh we want fault tolerance because we
have many servers
we want high performance so we want many
servers we have many servers we mean
fault tolerance
uh that means replication that means you
know uh inconsistencies
because we have data in multiple other
places you know to fix the
inconsistencies we need our surface to
get a protocol that might lower
performance
and so here's sort of this fundamental
challenge you know in designing these
distributed storage systems that
there's a struggle between consistency
and basically performance
and we'll see that throughout the term
so let me talk a little bit about
consistency
it is at a very high level i know i
promise you for the rest of the semester
we're going to go in
more detail as we go so first let's talk
again about the ideal consistency
an ideal consistency the way the
simplest way to think about it is that
basically the machine behaves as if it's
a single
system
that's also the desired behavior and the
sort of two things
that make that desired behavior or two
um
hazards that make that desired behavior
uh hard to achieve uh or you know at
least you know
requires you know some thinking and one
is concurrency and second thing is
failures
so let me start with consumer
concurrency because even if you have a
single
machine with multiple clients so your
currency within the single machine
you actually have to think about
consistency and you know this course is
quite obvious you know let's say we have
you know one machine we have one disk
uh well multiple requests you know come
in from different clients
and if the machine is a multi-processing
machine they might actually run
uh these requests material in parallel
so
so let's think a little bit about it you
know what does it mean so
uh so let's say we have from client one
that does a write operation
to a key x and the right one
and it's the same time there's a request
coming in it writes to
x2 but actually writes the value too
right now you know if we want to specify
or state what consistency means we need
some rule
about like what will happen and the rule
is typically phrased from the
perspective of the reader so let's say
there's another reader coming in
or another request coming in from
another client and it actually reads x
and the question is like what is the
value that actually that reader or that
this client observes
like a little bit more complicated or
more interesting let's say we have a
fourth client which we're going to bring
out this
issue of consistency definitions and
more clearly and it also does a read of
x
well after you know the client three
actually read x
so now we have some state like what is
the desired outcomes and what are
incorrect outcomes and that's sort of
really what
defines consistency so um
so let's take the first case c3 you know
what be in a reasonable outcome for
uh the read of c the read what is the
reasonable outcome for the read of c
to return what values
you know what value would make you happy
will make an application programmer
happy
two to be very reasonable
any other reasonable values one
yeah one would be reasonable because the
operation happened concurrently so
maybe we don't really know which one we
don't really want to restrict in what
particular order they go
so we know they say like either one is
fine you know because they're running
concurrently
what are some values that we would like
not to see
for the c3 you read seven yeah seven any
other value right
because nobody wrote that so that would
be undesirable
okay so good so like we we agreed that
probably just
the original outcome for c3 would be
either one or two
okay how about c4
the same as c3 really exactly the same
so let's say c3 to return one what do we
expect c4 to return
whatever c3 saw yeah because it rained
well after c3 right so we
if one was returned we expect one here
too
right if two was returned we expect two
here
does that make sense
okay so you know there's like a super
brief
you know sort of introduction of saying
like how can we define
consistency and then the typical way we
do it is using sort of traces and we
argue about like what are correctness
you know for
particular traces and we'll see more of
that and of course you know the server
can enforce
you know this kind of uh consistency by
for example using locks as you
have done in as you're doing the
mapreduce or in you know any concurrent
goal program that you're right
so that's sort of the standard technique
you know to enforce uh
consistency in terms of in the presence
of concurrency
is to use locks now
in the exhibit system uh you know the
ideal consistency either sort of as i
said there are two hazards and the
second hazard
is basically failure so it's just
replication in general like we have two
servers now assembly
so here's s1 here's s2
and you both have a disk
and here we have our same clients as
before you know c1 and c2
and they write you know 2x
uh and you know let's say you know
just to illustrate like what kind of
complications what kind of you know
just to illustrate that we actually have
to do something let's start with like
the most
you know dumb uh a replication plan so
like
very bad replication
so in this particular bad replication
kit and plan what we're going to do is
like uh we're going to allow a client
you know when a client actually wants to
update or write
uh we're going to tell it to basically
the protocol that we're going to follow
is the client writes it to
vote search in you know whatever don't
really coordinate that you just write it
to both
um and so for example if we have client
one and client two running
uh you know then you know maybe client
two does the same thing
and and then we're going to ask
ourselves the same question like
what does c3 see when it actually
reads and let's assume that for reading
we're going to say like ah we're either
way
uh we're gonna read from eight year
replica as as i said this is a very bad
replication plan basically there's no
restrictions
so what are the possible outcomes so
this guy writes one
this guy writes two and you know now we
see
three what are the possible outcomes for
each reach
one and two again yeah one or two no
nothing really that bad happening rick
how about c4 and we do a read of x
well after c3 x like this in the
previous
board also on m2
yeah uh one and two again but what
happens
c3 reads one
but the c3 c4 may return
one or two one or two and it's not what
we want or not
no no i mean you know again correct be
difficult for an application writer to
actually reason about this
um you know particularly even if c3 and
c4 were the same thing you first read to
a teacher one
no modification mate the next second
read returns another value how's that
possible
and it makes application programmers
difficult to write
so you know and the reason of course
that this inconsistency shows up here
is because we basically have no protocol
you know to coordinate you know the
clients
the readers and the writers so we need
some form and distribute system
typically we need some form of a
protocol to fix these
and get the desire to enforce that we
get the desired consistency
okay and so what we're going to see in
this rest of the semester is a whole
bunch of different types of protocols
that have different tradeoffs in terms
of
fault tolerance and the consistency okay
and the fact you know to get her into
get our head in that kind of thinking
uh we're going to use a whole bunch of
different case studies
and you know the case study for today is
gfs
and this is an instant case study you
know we wouldn't have signed
it uh and one reason it's an instant
case study because it brings out sort of
all these
you know sort of this core issue correct
gfas you know design
designed to get high performance
yeah that means it actually uses uh
replication
and fault tolerance
um and uh you know it struggles with
this consistency so it's like the field
fours or the themes that we're going to
be
consistently seeing throughout the
semester you know show up in this one
paper um the other
side of this why is an ancient case
study because it's a successful system
google doesn't actually use gfs at least
at this point in my understanding
there's a successor file system called
colossus you know but then it's inspired
by dfs
and uh but there are there are other
sort of uh sort of these cluster-based
file systems and therefore like map
type of usb apps like hdfs they're also
very much inspired by the design of gfs
um and you know one thing that is
actually interesting
at the point that this paper was written
uh in sort of late uh
early 2000's you know it was pretty you
know distributed file system were well
understood you know topics so people
knew about phil tolerance but they knew
about
their replication people knew about
their consistency all that kind of stuff
is
pretty well understood um however
nobody actually sort of built you know a
system you know at the scale of
thousands of computers
and and that sure brings out a number of
you know challenges
uh that previous system have to not
address and the in fact
the design is not completely standard
uh so the indesign that we were reading
about it's not uh was not sort of the
standard design that you would see in
academic papers at that time
and those are two aspects that make it
non-standard uh woeful which we'll get
more
uh we'll spend more time on one is you
know there's actually a single mass
structure the master
is not replicated you know there's a
single machine that is sort of in charge
of like almost all the coordination
uh in the system uh and so and that is
unusual uh you know you know why would
you build this
file you know fall tolerance system
which has a single point of failure
right that would be sort of not
something that
people in the academic literature were
doing at that time
and the second thing is that uh it
actually has
it's not consistent you know it can have
inconsistencies
and again again emotionally in the
literature in at that particular time
you know people were really sweating
actually you know to be able to you know
distribute systems that actually have
strong consistency
and you know don't have the anomalies
that you know we saw in the previous
walk
all right and so uh so even though
like a lot of the core techniques you
know were well known uh
you know the way that we're putting
together uh i was actually quite
different
and so that makes it interesting and
particularly you know the scale you know
which you know this system actually
operates is impressive
and pretty common even for today you
know so this issue
uh of struggle between fault tolerance
uh replication and performance and
consistency is
is a standard problem recurring problems
for almost any distributed storage
systems you know that people build today
and changes over time so like s3 for a
while you know didn't really have to
have that strong consistency you know
lately it's got much stronger
consistency
okay um so i want to since the paper is
really driven
uh and the design is driven by voltel
over
by performance i wanted to go back to
the mapreduce
paper for a second and this is a graph
you know of the mapreduce paper
and one way to think about gfs
is that it's the file system
for mapreduce
all right so the goal is to actually run
mini map reduce jobs and get high
performance
and we know that basically from we can
tell from the mapreduce paper already
that you know sort of g
vest is impressive in that matter in
terms of performance
uh so if you look at the you know this
side of this graph
and this is straight out of the
mapreduce paper uh this is the normal
execution of one of the
mapreduce jobs uh and again it has you
know three
sort of parts to it one is the first
part is input like reading
the input files the input to the map
from the file system and in case you
know the paper didn't say much about it
but
those are written right from gfs
there's the internal shuffle that we
really care about and then you know at
the end
you know the reduced jobs right back the
results into gfs
and uh and so uh the performance you
know part of the performance of this
mapreduce task is
determined by you know the rate at which
uh the mappers can actually read you
know data from
uh the dfs file system right so we're
running many many mappers at the same
time in fact some
mappers from different jobs now maybe
reading the same files
so we look at the input like this this
this
this top you know graph shows the
input in terms of megabytes per second
at the rate at which you know the
mappers actually
jointly collectively for one particular
job you know can reach from the file
system
as you can see you know it goes over
well over uh a thousand
or ten thousand megabytes per second
and you know the first question to ask
you is maybe like it's not an impressive
number
yeah should we be impressed with that
number or we're thinking well
you know give me one disc and i do
i think because it's older maybe yes
okay good ssd
how much what like what rates can you
write read
okay let me tell you this roughly the
throughput of a single disc
uh at the time that this uh for this
paper it was around like 30 megabytes
per second like somewhere in the tens of
megabytes per second
so here we're looking at you know well
over 10 000
megabytes per second correct and so that
is an impressive number
and you know you have to do work that's
you know that we'll see in the gfs
design that allows that kind of
throughput
and of course into this technology in
the case of the gfs of course if the
district
does faster you know it would be you
know what the real goal here correct is
like we have a thousand machines
maybe each one has a disc you know each
one can read at 30 megabytes per second
we just want a thousand times 30
megabytes per second to get out of it
okay and so uh that's
what you know drives a lot of this
design is to immediately allow these
mappers to
read in parallel from the file system
from this
joint file system okay
so let me say a little bit you know more
about this like what are the key
properties
that gfs has you know one big
large data set without any of that
and so i think the data set you should
think about is like the map produce data
sets you know so for example
the whole end of the complete crawl of
the world wide web
is stored in this you know the stupid
file system
uh has to be fast as we talked about and
you know the way they get like high
performance is to do automatic charting
shard the files across multiple disks
they allow multiple clients to read from
those disks comparable
all right another goal is global
and without meaning uh you know it's
shared where again all apps
see same file system
and that's convenient like if you have
multiple uh mapreduce jobs you know
that operate on the same set of files uh
you know they can first of all read all
the same set of files but they can
produce new files and then other map
producers can use those you know files
again and so this is a very convenient
you know live sharing between
applications so it's very convenient to
have
and of course you know dfs has to be
fall tolerant
i mean it's likely they're going to be
failures and so we want like automatic
you know close to automatic full
tolerance as possible and you'll see gfs
doesn't provide complete automatic but
there's a pretty good job effects for
getting high
with full followers
okay any questions about the this part
so far
like a broad intro to this topic and
uh sort of a few intro awards about gfs
okay let's then talk about the design
so
so here's the uh the design is seen in
uh
you know from the figure one i think in
the paper
and there's a couple things i wanted to
point out on top a little bit more in
detail about
so first of all you know we have an
application and that you know the
application again you know might be
mapped reduced jaw
you know considering multiple reduced
tasks multiple map tasks
and they link with the gfs library and
so
uh it's not a linux file system you know
this is not the file system you use to
you know whatever edit your files on or
compile uh
it is really intended you know as a
special
reverse file system for these uh large
computations
and as i said before again our real goal
correct is that it
achieves that impressive number like you
know we want the number of megabytes you
know from a single disk times the number
of machines and a single application
should be able to exploit that
and so the way they arrange that is to
have a master
that is basically in charge of actually
knowing where things are
and the client just periodically you
know talks to the master
uh to uh you know to retrieve
information so for example
it opens a file and the open call will
result in
a message you know to the master and
uh that has to respond back and say like
all the for this particular file name
the chunks that you need are uh are here
or these are the chunks that you need
and there's chunk handles there's
identifiers for the particular chunks
that
constitute a file and here are the
servers
that sure that chunk so you get back you
know a chunk handle
as well as you know a bunch of jump
locations
and one file might you know basically
file consists you know if you think
about a big file
and it consists of many many chunks
jump zero chunk one jump two
etcetera jump three blah blah blah
that's it's that's
there any check chunk is pretty big 64
megabytes
right so even the application one should
be you know the second second is uh
second 64 megabyte
goes to the gps and says like hey i want
to
read you know the second chunk you know
of this particular file
uh and then the give answer will answers
back with the handle for you know
chunk one as well as the servers that
actually holds junk one
all right and so uh
multiple applications might ask you know
for chunks from the same file
and they will get you know uh for
example the one application might be
reading chunk zero another application
might be already a chunk two
they will get different lists back for
each of these charts
so then the gfx client you know once it
knows the chunks and chunk locations
and basically straight talks to the
child servers
uh and it basically uh reads you know
the data you know at the
speed of the network and you know maybe
whatever disk you know that sits behind
this particular
trunk server uh directly to the
application
and here you can see where we're going
to get the big wing right because we're
going to be able to read you know for
multiple
you know the multiple clients can be
reading from multiple disks at the same
time and we're going to get like
tremendous amount of performance
right so for example it's like here's a
map task running
there's another map test running and
also as a client
you know they you know they're all going
to be talking to the set of servers you
know that whole
you know the challenge of all the
collection the data set and those are
going to read
in parallel from all the different chunk
servers
and that's going to give us like the
high throughput uh
number does that make sense
is that sort of the overall plan clear
here
just to sort of complete it like a chunk
server is nothing really uh uh
sort of a linux box and linux computer
with you know disk to it
in fact the 64 megabyte chunk is just
stored as a linux file
in the linux file system okay
okay so i want to zoom in on the
different pieces and i'll start with the
master because masters are really
the control center here
so talk a little bit about the state
that actually the master maintains
okay um so first of all you know it has
the mapping from file name
to an array
of chunk handles
and as you saw in the paper one of the
goals of actually uh
is to maintain all this memory of most
of the information actually directly
available
in memory so that nasa can respond to
clients very quickly and the reason why
reason to do that is because
you know there's one master many clients
you want to execute every client
operation as
efficient as possible so that you can
scale the master to at least a
reasonable number of clients
and then for every chunk handle
the master maintains some additional
number information particularly
it maintains a version number
in a list
of chunk servers that hold
a copy of that chunk
and as we'll see in a second you know
one of them is
named one of those servers is a primary
and the other ones are the
secondaries
and the typical number that you know a
chunky stored ad is a three servers
and we can maybe talk a little bit later
about like y3
and then you know there is a lease
associated
with each parameter so there's at least
time maintained as well
then there's a two sort of other big you
know sort of storage components and
these are sort of the applica you know
the file system level things and then in
terms of implementation
there are there's a log and there are
checkpoints
and since the masters are the crucial
you know the the
control center whenever uh there's a
change
to the namespace for example you create
a new file in
gfs or you know the mapping for
filemaking to junk blocks
changes uh all those operations are
written to this log
and the log sits on you know unstable
storage
and the basic idea is that like the
before responding to the client that the
change actually has been named
the master writes it to stable storage
first and then responds to the client
and so this means that
if the master fails or crashes then
later comes back up you know it can
replace log to reconstruct you know the
state of its internal state
and by writing it first to uh storage
before responding to the client
client will never observe strange
results you know
you could do it the other way around
correct and that result in a problem
because you know the client will think
that the file has been created server
crashes back up and then the file
doesn't exist
uh so there's sort of another
consistency point
now replaying always back all the
operations from the beginning of time to
log is
of course undesirable that means that
they have to master crashes and we have
only one of them you know we'll be down
for a long time
and so in addition to that you know it
actually keeps checkpoints in stable
storage
so periodically the master makes a
checkpoint of its own
external state and the mapping profile
into array uh junk handles
and stores that on on stable storage
and so then they'll only have to replay
the last part of you know basically all
the operations in the log after the last
checkpoint
so the recovery is actually quickly
so there's another couple interesting
questions that we can ask ourselves like
what
state does need to end up in stable
storage you know for the mass detection
function correctly
so the first question that asks is how
about this array of
uh chunk handles the mapping from file
name to chunk handles
does that need to be stably stored
we're going to be only memory
um but if the master crashes
i think you can like get that
information from the servers
chunk servers um so maybe only
uh main memory yeah uh well let's answer
the question what other people think
so it can be reconstructed from the log
so when the server crashes
only the log needs to be in the hard
storage
and then it can reload it from the log
to main memory yeah so it definitely has
to be in the law correct so we
agree that this array of check handles
basically has to be installed in stable
storage
right because otherwise we lose like
when we create a file and we didn't
write this table stored we just lose the
file right and so this mapping for file
names
chunk handles need to be in stable
storage how about this uh
chunk handle to chunk handle to list of
junk for our servers
does that actually need to be long
i think in the paper they say that when
the
master reboots it asks the servers
to tell to tell the master what the
chunks
that they have are yeah correct so this
is not actually this is basically just
volatile state
not not stable storage so and same
should
be true of the primaries and the
secondaries
and true of the least time how about the
version number
does the master need to remember on
stable storage the version number or not
yes because it needs to know if um the
chunks in the
other servers are still or not yeah
exactly
that's exactly right correct so the
maximum must remember the version number
because
uh if it it doesn't and like the whole
system went down
and the turning servers came back up and
maybe the chunk server actually with the
most recent data does not come up like
an older guy comes up with like version
number 14
uh then the master has to be able to
tell that you know that junk server
reverse number 14 was not the most
recent
uh chunk server and so it needs to
maintain
you know the version number on disk so
that actually can tell which chunk
server actually have
the most up-to-date information and
which ones don't
okay i have a question here yeah
if well i mean if if the monster
fails and then it has to come up it's
anyway going to connect to all of the
chunk servers
and it will find out what the largest
version is
okay except right does the billet find
out what the last
[Music]
first of all it will try to talk to all
chunk servers right and some chunk
servers might be down
okay yeah and that's that may be just
the charger that actually has the most
recent version
right yeah okay so you can't take the
max of the
live trump servers uh that we incorrect
any other questions about this
okay let's look at the two sort of basic
operations
uh to really get down to consistency and
of course
that's going to be reading and writing
so reading a file
and then we'll talk about writing a file
so
reading file in some sense is
straightforward you know we talked about
it basically a client
sends a message you know to uh with the
file name
plus offset to the master
and basically ask you know please give
me you know the
chunk servers uh and the chunk handle
that
um that hold that uh
and hold the data at that offset and so
an end times the
chunk handle so if you like read byte
you know whatever
uh zero you know it's pretty clear
correct that has to be the
first entry in the
list you know from file name to uh
trunk handle so i am in the master
function junk handle
it basically replies you know with the
master replies to the client with you
know the junk handle
and list of chunk servers
for that uh for that handle
and the version numbers
so basically the the client gets back
and that's it's saying you know that's
junk you know 221
yeah and uh here are the three machines
with the ip address with the few
machines that actually have it
uh and the version number is like
version number 10.
um then the client caches this list
and then it basically sends a message to
the closest
so reads from closest
sure
uh and so why does the client actually
read the cache
this information
yes you see later correct that actually
causes some problems
so it doesn't have to contact the master
for some time if it wants to
to read again or write to that to that
yeah and why is that important
to like reduce the i guess the traffic
um in general it takes less time if you
have less communication with the master
yeah and then you know the the same with
aspect correct this design is that the
mass
actually is a single machine and you
know a single machine can just have
a limited amount of memory and a limited
network interface and so
if you have too many clients talking to
it you know wouldn't be able to serve
right and so client caching is important
to reduce the load on this single
machine
okay why read from the closest server
minimize network traffic yeah minimize
network traffic yeah so the whole goal
correct is to
pump as much data you know through the
clients as possible the highest fruit
booth
uh and you know we have to there's two
problems that we have to cross with the
data center network one you know there's
probably you know some topology and we
maybe swamped like the top links of the
topology
uh and they actually increase latency
you know to actually get to
the other side all right so it's
important to be able to be to the
closest site again to basically maximize
you know the
throughput you know that the joint setup
and clients you can sort of experience
when they're reading in parallel from
many many chunk servers okay
so the chunk server you know s you know
better checks the version number
and if the version number is okay you
know then send data
okay why is the check of the version
number there
to check if it's to stale yeah yeah
we'll usually
do our edmond's best to avoid reading
stale data um
and you know as we'll see in a second we
don't do it you know if it doesn't do a
perfect job at me and but tried hard
to minimize you know the occurrences of
the
clients reading stale data okay
that's reading reasonably
straightforward
so let's look at the writing
so this is the picture from the paper
and so let's say a client wants the you
know let's focus on a pen
uh and so they argued that the very
common operation for them is to append a
record to the file
and can we see why you know
given what you guys know from you know
sort of mapreduce and you know
google does that make sense that why
append is so important
um because largely in doing mapreduce
you need to uh or as the the map
function spits out uh information it's
largely just
adding on information rather than
changing previously spit out
enumerations
yeah you know maybe the map is not the
best example because it to the local
file system not to gfs but the reducer
does
uh the same argument and also the
magician
yeah so you know the workloads they're
writing is basically
consume a lot of information and you
know append records you know to file
with the resulting computation with the
result of the computation
okay good so you know step one you know
we have a client
uh it will talk to the master to figure
out like where to write to
and so the master looks in its you know
table right the file name
to chunk handles
and finds you know the junk handles and
then you know
looks at this table of you know chunk
handles
to servers to find the list of servers
that it has
that have a particular thing that have
that particular chunk
okay so what happens next so there's two
cases right like one there
there's already a primary and the second
k uh the first k one but two cases
having a primary or not a prime so let's
say this is the very first time that
this particular client
contacts the master for this particular
uh chunk nobody else has done
it so far so there's no primary so in
that case you know we need to
the master needs to pick a primary right
how does it do that
um i think the master just picks any of
the available chunk servers right
yep yeah picks one uh so it's one of
those
primary and the other ones are the
secondary what other steps are involved
in this sort of
um yeah and then subsequently the master
grants elise
um to that primary and that lease
has a certain like uh date of expiry
yeah what else does it have there's one
more other crucial information
um even
it increments the version number yeah
increments oh oops
yeah step one is increment this version
number correct
uh because you're going to make a new uh
priority and whatever time you make a
new primary you know
you go sort of like you want to make
think about is like a new epoch in the
design of the file system or for this
particular file and so you create the
version number
because you're going to have a new
mutator uh so basically the master
increases the version number
uh it uh sends to the primary uh
the new version number and the
secondaries and saying like hey guys
we're gonna
start a new uh we're gonna start a new
mutation
uh you've got for our forming a replica
group and your replica group with this
particular version of
whatever like version number 12. right
and the primers in the secondary store
that version number what to do is they
store that version number
do they store down disk on their desks
or
in memory or
i don't know anyone
what do we what do we think okay let's
first do memory let's say it's distorted
in memory would that be a good design
no sorry you can go
um i guess it wouldn't because if the
chunk server goes down
and then it comes back up it it should
know what version it has
yeah because otherwise you couldn't
convince the primary that it has the
most recent one right otherwise the
primary decision the master couldn't
pick
you know the chunks of this motivation
data so it has to be on disk so
basically this version number lives on
this
both at the chunk servers and actually
at the master
right so when the chunk when the master
gets back you know the
acknowledgements from the primary in the
secondary that they uh
written the version number two disk and
at the primary actually has received the
release
then you know the master also writes
its version number to disk and then
responds to the client
okay so two back to the client
that responds with the list of servers
primary plus the
secondaries plus the version number
okay then you know the next step and
again here we see the whole goal is to
type a lot of data through the network
is the client actually uh
just sends the data that wants to write
to the
to the primary and the secondaries the
way it actually does it is sort of an
interesting way
it basically contacts the closure
secondary it knows off
you know out of this list and sends the
data there
and that secondary you know move the
data over to the next
person in the list and then to the next
server in the list
um and so that's the way you know the
data is sort of pumped you know from the
client
you know to the in the pipeline to all
the uh replicas
and you know you know when the secondary
receives the first second they receive
some of the data immediately starts
actually pushing the data to the uh
further down the pipeline
okay the reason that this design is this
way is sort of basically this network
interface that the client has that goes
through the outside world
these are like used as a full network
interface to push the data down the
pipeline
and so that gives us high throughput
okay
okay so then you know if it's all
successful and the data has been pushed
you know
to all the servers those servers don't
store that information on this yet you
know it just sits there
sort of on the site you know to be used
in the next step
so the next step is then basically for
the client to send a message like an
append message
to the primary and at that point
you know the primary will check you know
the version number right
whether it actually verse number
corresponds to this version number and
if it doesn't you know correspond to
each uh
they don't match and then the primary
won't allow it
uh the primary checks is lease which the
lease is valid
because the lease is not valid anymore
it cannot accept uh
any mutation operations because if this
lease is not valid there might be
another primary now outside
in the world so it checks the release
and then if you know basically the
version numbers match the lease is still
valid
and basically picks an offset to the
right head
and then the next step is you know
basically the right you know the data
that just came in
you know this record uh to uh stable
storage
so the primary action at this point
writes it to stable storage
the data and then sends messages you
know to the secondaries you know saying
please write the data to
and since the primary picks the offsets
you know the
it tells the secondary where to write
you know that particular record into the
file
so maybe like whatever it takes to
offset it you know 125
and then it will tell the secondaries
you know all to write you know the data
that came in
earlier at offset 125.
and then you know if everything works
out you know everyone uh everybody
all the secondaries in the primary
successfully write their data back you
know to disk
then it actually responds back to the
client saying like okay
success your append actually has
happened
there's a way the the the right actually
might be not successful or depend might
not be successful and namely for example
the primary is written through its own
disk
uh but it fails to write it you know it
fails to connect to one of the
secondaries maybe the secondary
actually crashed or maybe the secondary
just has a network connection that
doesn't work
and in that case the primary actually
returns an error
to the client so uh
error if
one secondary didn't respond
and in that case the client library what
it will do is usually try and retry
uh it will uh reissue the same event
and we'll try again uh in the hope that
the second time around
you know that data actually that will
actually get through
uh and so this is what they recall like
you do it at least once
if you retry will the primary pick the
same offset
i don't think so no i don't need it
takes a new offset
uh and writes the and writes it at this
new particular offset
and so that means correct if you look at
sort of the the disks of the
you know the you know view of the file
on the three replicas
you know the primary s1 and s2 you know
it might be the case of the new wrote
like
you know at 125 the data
uh we succeeded maybe in s212 but s
s2 actually doesn't have there's no data
right and then we retry again then we
might directly read the same data
x and maybe we'll succeed in all three
as you can see here that basically
replicates records can be duplicated
is this something that can happen in a
standard file system like your linux
file system or your laptop or your
computer
no no would you be surprised if
your computer did this
i mean yeah this is not how standard
file rates work yeah
and it would be inconvenient to have
this property or just like doesn't
matter
pretty bizarre like you know presumably
like you know you compiler you know
produces output
in a file and then maybe you know
certain blocks are written twice
and then you can't run the program
anymore like you know
the whole thing is just garbage at that
point so
it would just be weird but like you
write an email message and then
basically the body of the email message
shows you twice
uh so this is not what your typical file
system
would do and so this is like a slightly
bizarre and you know what is the
justification
why why do you think this is a good idea
i'm not sure what this is a good idea
but i'm confused how that works for
mapreduce specifically so if you
run word count and you do that and like
some files
and you count and they're like word a it
shows up
once but you do it twice because
something failed
and now you have a1 a1 so your account
is going to be wrong
how how yeah i'm confused yes
how do that work it seems like you know
if you don't do anything then this is
really highly inconvenient
where it actually returns to the
application will compute the wrong
result
they said uh they used checksums and
unique ids to check you know that every
um yeah every record was like
once um additionally uh when you do
record append
the um response which is returned from
the primary to the client
gives you the offset um into the file
where your data was actually written and
the rest of it is assumed to be
like undefined um
yeah i think the key point here correct
is like basically the application
doesn't interact with the file system
directly it interacts with through some
library in the library basically
if you write the pen records the library
sticks an id in it
and so and also you use the library to
read you know these records
and so if you see a record with the same
id you know you skip the second one
because you know that's clearly the same
one
and you know they have a double you know
an extra finger there for checksums to
make sure that the record didn't get
garbled
uh and we uh basically to detect the
changes in the bytes but you know the
the id basically helps them to
cite allows the library to decide oh
well this is the same record i'm just
not going to give it to the application
or the application doesn't need to
process it okay
my question is instead of rewriting to
every replica wouldn't it be better to
remember which
replica is failing and to stop until it
can be written to that one
yeah so there's a bunch of different
designs possible let's return to that
later um
you know i think one reason that they do
this this way is like if there's a
prayer you know
temporary failure like a network
disconnection or whatever you know the
least the right will succeed and they
will continue
and there doesn't have to be any
reconfiguration there has to be nothing
you know
out to the right can just keep going
right
and so the right doesn't have to fail
okay uh just a quick question in general
the um all of these servers are trusted
right yes absolutely
this is actually an important point this
is not like you know your linux file
system where there's permissions and
access control rights and all that kind
of stuff uh
these servers are completely trusted the
clients are trusted the master's trusted
the software written by google is
trusted the whole thing is trusted
right this is a completely internal file
system the fact that they're sort of
cool that it's
like a little bit maybe surprising they
don't even know about this file system
in such amount of detail right because
it's only used inside of
google and one of the cool things is
that you know in that
period of time and still they do uh they
wrote up the papers and
describing actually how these systems
work and there's one reason we can
we know about it and it has been
extremely cool
uh that they did that
okay um so okay so we don't understand
how read works you never understand that
right works you know there are some sort
of
interesting uh behaviors and i want to
talk a little bit more about
the consistency correct and that really
comes down to uh
you know what does it read observe after
you know you did an event and you know
the homework question
uh really got after this and so what i
would like to do now is i'll take a
quick break out like five minutes and so
you can discuss
you know the the answer to this question
and then come back
and talk a little bit more in detail
about consistency
okay so i'm gonna
make lily okay
everybody back everybody can hear me
just
double checking yeah uh hey professor
question can you go back to
this slide with the um
when we talked about the right here so
you mentioned
the master response to the client with
the version number yeah
and if that is the case then isn't it
possible
is it even possible would it even have
to read like a steel data because uh the
client has a version number and
the chunk servers would have the version
number so they can just compare those
if they don't match the the clock that
checks chunk service can just say
i have a still laid out so uh you should
not read this
okay let's go yeah let's go for the
scenario a little bit more detail let me
actually get rid of this window
okay let's talk about uh so i think the
scenario that we're talking about
that leads into a problematic situation
which follows
we have a primary we have a secondary
with two secondaries
segmented one secondary two uh
we have a client on this site uh we have
a primary
with the the client reach you know it's
back like a version number is a 10
uh the later on
you know the other primary will
uh
okay so s2 it has get some servers uh
then at some point the um and so this
information is cached
on the side you know maybe you know the
uh
one of the secondaries like s2 crashes
or at least appears to be disconnected
from the network
so what the master will do is increment
the version numbers you know go to 11
let's say messages 11 11. uh
then you know another client may come
around and start writing
so we'll write in a new value to s1 and
s2
for the file so the chunk has now been
updated so let's say the chunk was
original 10.
same as the version number and now it's
11. there's 11 here
uh but you know that's the case that you
know even though the master
and the prime and the secondary couldn't
talk to secondary two but the second
client
the first client can still talk to the
secondary
and it will read their version numbers
match right they're both 10
and it will read it will send 10 back
so here we have the case where the right
has completed
as acknowledged has to be okay and
nevertheless there's a client that
actually will read a stale value back
so why doesn't that 11 go back to the
client
uh the first client the reason is
because the first client caches it for a
longer period of time
they don't actually have anything in the
protocol that actually does that so does
the version
increments when the um when the system
tries to push
and update to s2 and it's not able to or
version numbers only increment the
version numbers maintained by the master
uh may only increment when you
select a new primary
not when you do it there's there's also
a serial number that they talk about
but that's different from the version
number that's just the order you know
the rights
okay how does the primary know which
secondaries it has to check with
uh before making before completing a
write successfully
the primary the master tells us the
master tells the primary you're the
secondaries you need to update
um so when the master basically issues
the lease to the primary
and uh if one of the secondaries is down
at that
moment does the master consider this a
failure or
does it just update the version number
for the servers that are alive and
it just forgets about the other one
because it's going to have an outdated
version number anyway yeah you know the
the the paper is a little bit vague on
exactly how the recovery part or
the reconfiguration stuff works
uh but i imagine that you know basically
the primary actually does
heartbeats with p1 s1 and s2 uh at some
point that decides you know s2 is dead
and uh at that point uh it will point
and the lease of the primary maybe
runs out uh and then it will create a
new primary and a new s1
and an another s you know to actual
holes you know or maybe just s1 because
there's no uh
you know no additional chunk server and
that forms the new
you know replica group for that chunk
oh so the lease doesn't run out yet
basically
well the primary can't uh a point okay
so here's like some interesting cases
let's see
so you guys are doing exactly the thing
i want uh
based on this paper which is you really
start thinking about all the problematic
cases
and this is exactly how you think about
persistence you know when you start
thinking about consistency you need to
sort of consider
all possible failures and argue whether
you know those failures lead to
inconsistencies
um so the one thing you know let's talk
about this one case
where we've got a master we got a
primary
and let's say the uh the primary and the
master are get disconnected
actually let me draw the picture
slightly differently
master in the middle we got a
you know server we got a server here you
know s1
s2 and let's say s2 is the primary
um and so you know whatever it may talk
to
some other servers out there
and perhaps again even as one is the uh
is one of the secondary for this primary
so
let's say it's a network petition so the
master sends messages you know heartbeat
messages
doesn't get a response um
when can the master point a new primary
when the lease is over for us too
yeah right let because uh the the
the primary has to wait but the master
has to wait until the lease has expired
uh because if the lease uh was not
expired
then maybe we have two primaries at the
same time right
p1 and p2 uh are staying at the same
time and
would that be bad
uh yeah then i think
wait would would clients clients
wouldn't know where to send
to and the master wouldn't know which
one was primary right well presumably
some clients might be still talking to
this primary correct
yeah some other clients might be talking
to this primary in their primary for the
same chunk
so i think you get very bizarre
orderings correct where like some brands
will get lost
you know you know like it would be a
mess it would be not a principled
you know argument where like one you
know we're all right to happen in order
and one at a time
so this is a bad situation so and this
the situation is voided like this split
brain
syndrome this is sometimes called the
split brain syndrome where you end up
with a system where you have two masters
and this is a problem here is avoided
because of like the leads
and the mass will not appoint any other
primary until the
least of the first frame absolutely has
expired and it knows even if the primary
is up but not reachable
to it but may be reachable to other
clients that primary won't accept any
right messages anymore because at least
has expired
does that make sense
okay let me say one more thing before uh
wrapping up and i apologize was partly
because
you know uh my i had some technical uh
problems but i wanted to make one more
uh point and it came up in the
the discussion too in the breakup room
which is
you know how can you do better you know
how to get strong consistency
or maybe just stronger they got pretty
strong consistency but not you know
with some little you know issues
and so there's a bunch of different ways
you can do it and
in fact you know the uh what we're going
to be seeing
uh you know one i think one issue that
shows up here all the time is like you
could instead of like updating
the primary and then reporting or making
rights visible incrementally it's
probably not a good idea
right so probably what you want to do is
like update all
secondary primaries or none
but not as in this you know particular
design where like somebody get updated
and some may not get updated and that's
actually visible to the client
so there's a bunch of like you know
techniques or the protocol
changes that you could do uh that will
make this better and the fact you know
we'll see
in labs two and three you know you will
build systems that actually have these
stronger properties
uh and the deal with these scenarios uh
that you know the currently
here lead to inconsistency in fact if
you look at google itself
you know and we'll read some of these
tables later google built additional
storage systems
other storage systems that have stronger
consistency
and basically tailor those over to a
different application domain
so for example like in uh like halfway
to ten remember we just paid a paper
called spanner
you know that actually has a much
stronger you know story for consistency
and and even has support from
transactions
uh whether it's like the application
domain is quite different you know like
you can sort of see here that gfs is
really tailored you know to sort of the
redu uh running mapreduce jobs
okay so i hope this is a you know useful
introduction sort of consistency
and you're starting thinking about these
kinds of problems because they will be
recurring a set of problems that will
show up in the rest of the term and i
apologize for running over a little bit
late
thank you hanging around if people want
to ask additional questions you know
feel free to uh
ask them and if you have to run to
another class you know please run to
another class