good afternoon good evening good night
good morning wherever you are
or whenever you're watching this um so
today
uh i want to talk about um
spanner this is a paper from 2012
but that the spanner uh system is in
active use and
uh also still continuously under
development
so it's a it's a real system um the main
topic
and the mighty spanner is really
interesting is it supports wide area
transactions
and this is a really powerful
programming model so even though the
data or like maybe the data sharded
across
multiple uh servers and the servers
being in different data centers in the
different
uh pieces on on the planet you can just
run
transactions and they have
uh semantics they're atomic you know
respect to failure all the rights happen
or none of them
and they provide serializability and so
that's an incredibly powerful uh
programming abstraction
and of course you know the challenge is
to implement it
efficiently uh and one big challenge is
just like a law of physics you know the
speed of light you know
sending a packet from one end in one
part of the us to the other part of the
us or to another continent
that takes a lot of time uh you know
we're talking about tens of milliseconds
and so uh what we're gonna see in this
paper is that
uh read write transactions are actually
are indeed quite expensive
uh but they work uh very hard to make
read-only transactions
very inexpensive and so the
read-write transactions
are implemented using two-phase commit
as we talked about last
week and two-phase locking and
one of the things that is interesting
about it is that
the participants in this protocol are
just basically taxes groups
uh the re-only transactions
can execute at any data center
and they ever can run very fast in fact
you know if you look at the tables
the six in the back the paper you'll see
that read-only uh transactions somewhere
at like ten times as fast as rewrite
transactions
and there are two key ideas there uh
that we'll talk about
this lecture one is snapshot isolation
which actually is a standard uh database
idea uh but i use it here
to make the reach fast um and in
particular you know to make it actually
work well in a distributed wide area
setting uh they rely on synchronized
clocks
or days
now those clocks are not perfectly
synchronized uh
and so their transaction scheme must
deal with a little bit of
swap or drift or error margin
you didn't exactly know what the true
time is
as i said is widely used
both internally in google but also
as a google customer you can use it uh
spanner is basically a cloud service
that you can use as a google customer
uh if you use gmail uh probably your
email
or parts of the email system actually go
through spana
maybe before diving into uh in more
detail
i want to make one logistic comment
related to spanner
as you may already have seen we made
some adjustments
for the long weekend along upcoming
weekend
and first of all lot 4a is
not as heavy duty as in the other labs
so hopefully to take them less time
we also canceled next week's lecture so
that you can actually use that as
uh time to work on uh 4a and we made the
deadline for
4a more flexible so next friday is not
convenient for you
you can actually choose to you have
another extra late hour
to uh submit it later uh and hopefully
that will
allow you to enjoy the long weekends and
you know perhaps get her some sleep and
maybe do something else than
debugging and your labs um
the second point i want to make is
direct related to spanner
uh some of you noticed this and came
through in the
questions this paper is quite
complicated
and there's many reasons why it's
complicated but one reason is that
actually uh there's a lot of things
going on
uh it's a powerful system it has a lot
of different components to it
uh and you know the interaction between
the different components
is important and so this is a lot a lot
of material in
this paper and so what i will try to do
in this lecture is try to make that more
clear
by focusing on a couple aspects of the
paper and i'm
not going to do a full treatment of the
paper uh
uh but you know focus i think what are
the most important ideas and why we're
reading it in
eight to four uh that took me actually
you know a little bit of time for
uh you know a few years to figure out
actually how to
present this paper or explain it in a
way that i think is
maybe easier to understand you know if
you're for
in the context of 6824 okay but ask
questions
as always
okay um so let's just dive in and
talk a little bit of the high level
organization uh
and more from the point of view from the
way i want to
talk about this about spanner in this
lecture
and so there's multiple data centers and
you know there's for convenience
or simplicity you know just think about
their free data centers
a b and c
and it can be anywhere in the world
um and the goal is that basically you
know data will be
like we haven't made a data like a chart
you know that you know
contains you know some database rows or
you know some key value pairs
uh so we're looking at the chart maybe
it has the keys a2
you know m and the basically idea is
actually you know we're going to
replicate that chart across data centers
and with the goal that like even if a
complete data center goes down
then you know we can do a proceed uh and
the way we're going to arrange that we
can be able to proceed is that
basically these charts they're going to
form
these replicas that are sitting in
different data center we're going to
form one
taxes group
so if you're sort of thinking about this
we're trying to think about those in
terms of lab
uh three then you can think about that
you know we have a key value store
where the key value servers are uh
spread around different data centers
and the uh keys are updated you know the
vaccinating uh raft you know writes you
know through the wrath
log and then you know the individual key
kvs
you know update their state and so you
can think about like you know
lab free being here instead of running
you know free kv servers on your machine
uh you're going to run one cave user in
different
data centers
okay um so you know
then like there's there's going to be a
package group per shark so
uh there um
you know there might be other shards
that have old other parts of the
p-value space or database rows
so let's say you know we have only two
shards you know for this particular
database
uh you know charts containing a to the m
and then the shard containing end to z
and they are going to form their own
access group
and the reason we want to get a multiple
chart is to get
parallelism
so that we can you know if the uh
transactions involve different charts
you know the disjunct
this uh disjointed set of shards you
know they can do these injection can
actually proceed completely in parallel
so as i mentioned earlier we have a
apache group per shard
you know for replication but you know
patches actually provides us
uh you know an additional sort of
benefit uh
you know the communication cost right
from a to b or from a to c might be uh
very expensive
uh and since you know access allows to
proceed or raft allows us to proceed
with just the majority
uh you know the slowest machine might
actually have not that much performance
impact
and so we can sort of easily tolerate
either slow machines
or actually one you know data center uh
being down
so the majority rule helps us
in two ways you know we get data center
fault tolerance and
some sort of slowness
uh now a final goal as we'll see in a
little bit more detail
is that uh a client of a
spanner so let's say you're some server
that uses spanner i would like it to be
the case that you know the server can
actually use a closed replica
and so the replicas you know typically
are placed
closed close to the clients that
actually use them
in fact we'll see that read-only
transactions
can be executed basically by the local
replica and without any communication
to the other data centers now when i
talk about client
uh here this is typically sort of the
back end service of some
google service so for example this might
be the gmail server that's sitting
uh you know also in some data center and
maybe in the same data center and talks
to the replicas in that particular data
centers
and of course outside our real clients
like users
that you know you know read or write
email
okay any sort of questions about this
high level
organization
okay so let me sort of uh
uh lay out the challenges that i want to
focus on in this lecture
um and so we're going to sort of three
main challenges
one is uh the way i said like
i said we want to actually read only
transactions without actually having to
communicate
with any other server but we've got to
make sure that the read sees the latest
right
this sort of classic uh challenge that
we've seen before you know zookeeper
uh zookeeper sort of avoids it doesn't
really address the challenge direct
head-on
and just like weakens the consistency
but here in this uh design
we'd like to arrange it in a way that
actually we still uh keep
linearizability in fact you know we're
the spanish shoot for a strikingly a
stronger property than linearizability
second thing is when you want to support
spender wants to support transactions or
cross charge
so even this is actually like we do a
bank transfer and
one account is in one chart the other
account the destination count there's
another chart
we want to arrange that you know the uh
it still you know can be executed like a
transaction and have
asset semantics and finally you know the
transactions both
read only once and the read right ones
uh must be serializable
the type of stronger than serializable
and you know we'll see that uh uh
you know for this you know for the
basically for the read write
transactions you know we're going to use
two phase locking two-phase commit
and uh the basically the two particles
that we talked about
uh in the last lecture and so
what i'd like to do first is talk about
these right transactions
and then uh talk in more detail how
uh read only transactions are executed
so that they can run
uh very efficiently
okay so read write transactions are
basically two-phase locking and
two-phase
commit hopefully this is going to be
easily easy to understand
and they are going to involve these sort
of complex timing diagrams that we
looked at last last week and so
you know the way it's set up and i'm
going to simplify a bit but you know the
way it's sort of simple
setup in spanner is we have the client
and the client is sort of in charge of
really running the transaction
it uses a transaction manager or
transaction library
uh that actually runs on the client
machine
and is in charge of basically you
orchestrate the
the transaction and again the client
here is not you know the user web
browser
or for gmail but basically the servers
uh or the server on the
gmail server in the data center that is
the client of spanner
and so let's make the picture reasonably
simple uh so we're gonna have two shards
instead of three
four five and so we have chart a and we
have shard b
and let's assume we're going to just
execute the
transfer uh transaction the same one as
before where we're going to deduct some
money from one account and add it to
another account
and initially i'm going to talk about
this without the timestamps
and in some ways you know the one reason
to do so is that
actually for the read write transaction
timestamps are not very important
the timestamps actually are mostly there
for read-only transactions
and they need a little bit tweaking to
the rewrite transactions uh to support
the read-only transactions and therefore
the time stamps sort of
um drifting to read writer's actions too
but in essence you know the read-write
transactions are just basically straight
uh two-phase locking and two-phase
commit
so the client is going to reach these
accounts so for example let's assume
that
you know read x uh so it reaches that's
going to do the transfer transaction
from
moving money from adding uh 1 to x and
you know subtracting uh
or subtracting one dollar from x and
adding a dollar to y
so it's going to read x and let's assume
that actually sits in one chart
so this is going to be a cross chart
transaction uh
and here's to read off why
um and uh
there's gonna be uh when the client
executes this uh
where issues these read operations they
go to the charts and the charts actually
keep
walk table and so they record
basically this transaction you know so
they said let's say this is transaction
whatever tid
and they're going to record that you
know the x is owned
you know it's the log table x is owned
by the client
you know and here in this case y is
owned by the client
and that's sort of the very standard as
you know we've seen before
now the thing that is slightly different
here and
i'm not fully drawing it out here is
that when we're talking to one chart a
chart a is really one of these axis
groups
and so it has you know free uh
yes in this case you know a group of
free peers
and uh so sa is really a replicated uh
uh service you know consisting of
multiple peers
in when executing a read-only
transaction we're going to be talking to
the leader
of that peer so if you think in terms of
rap style you can just think about it
the read request goes to the leader of
the
uh access group and
uh another yes so that is so every time
i sort of draw this one single arrow
here for s a or for sb
uh you know it's a much more complicated
uh story particularly when the rights
get involved because rights actually are
going to go through
you know the pact social raft group
um the read-only
uh or the log table is actually not
replicated
it is just stored at the leader of the
taxes
group and if the leader goes down during
the transaction
then basically the transaction has to be
restarted or
the transactions will be aborted because
the lock information is lost
the reason that the lock table is not uh
um
it's not the replica this is an agreed
operation fast
okay so once you know the
client actually has gotten the uh the
value of an action y
and that's taking out the walks you know
in sort of two-phase locking style
the uh you know it's gonna
subtract one from x you know add one you
know
to y and then this is gonna submit a
transaction
so basically all the writes are done
locally at the client
again sort of this is the gmail server
um
and one everything is when the client is
done with the transaction it submits
transaction to
to spanner and uh
it submits it to a transaction
coordinator
and so so some you know a set of servers
uh
or some machine is being picked as the
transaction coordinator
and again the transaction coordinator is
a taxis group
and so it's multiple peers in
different data centers and one reason
that we want this to be a taxis group is
so that
as we've seen before in two-phase
protocol over the two-phase commit
that if the coordinator fails it might
actually block
uh the participants right like if the
participants have pre-prepared and
agreed to go along with the transaction
but then the coordinator fails you know
there's petition to
have to hold on to their locks and have
to wait until the
uh coordinator comes back by replicating
the coordinator we're using taxes
and we make the coordinator highly
available and so
basically sort of avoid that particular
sort of disaster scenario
okay so the transaction coordinator is
then basically in charge of running the
two-phase commit protocol
and so it will send you know the updates
for x and y
to the leader of chart a
uh x y to the leader of you know sharp b
um the they you know grab the logs you
know in this case
uh you know they already hold the locks
uh or promote the locks to right
read right locks and uh basically
prepare
unit transactions so they don't really
execute it yet but just make the
you know typically using right ahead
logging you know
prepare the changes and if everything is
okay
then they uh you know basically commit
to the transaction by entering sort of
this prepared state
and this is sort of a big moment because
at this point
the transaction is where the peers or
the participants are committing to this
transactions and we know from last
lecture you know the participants do
actually have to record some state
so that if they fail and they come back
up they can recover and pick up
from where they left off so at the
prepared
state basically this results into a
pax's right
you know recording the state of the
transaction uh
and the two pc state
uh the logs that the
you know participants holding et cetera
et cetera and so
um this patch is right so the leader of
this particular chart is there's a push
uh
axis right across the different peers in
the group
to ensure that that uh state is
replicated in fault tolerance
um and so once you know the
the participants have you know prepared
and agreed to prepare
then you know they sent back okay you
know okay
so this is very similar to our two cases
protocol that we talked before
and at this point you know the
coordinator can commit
and of course in the point of the commit
the coordination record that actually
made the commit decision
uh because our participants may come
back later and want to know and find out
about it and you know we might have
failures
so again the paxo state or the pc
the two-phase commit state uh is written
uh
two using paxos and replicated
uh using paxos and for
this you know whole presentation you can
just think about actors as being
complete
substitute or equivalent to raft you
know
spanner predates raft but like you know
for conceptually and
you know through first order uh you know
for this paper they're
basically the same
so at this point the transaction commits
and this you know is really the commit
point
which once the the transaction
coordinator has written down
the the transaction is committed uh that
is the
actual commit point and then it informs
you know the participants you know that
this has happened
and you know they're going to respond
back if okay great transaction is
committed and the transaction
coordinated we clean up its state
and at some point later the sharks can
also clean up their
state and at the point of commit the
participants release release their locks
okay so that is sort of the basic story
for read write transactions and so any
questions about this
and then i think the simple way to think
about it is this is two-phase
commit two-phase locking uh with the
main difference between
what we talked about last week and uh
this week is that
the participant the the transaction
coordinator
the participants are all apache groups
or they're replicated they're highly
available
and some of the problems that you know
we talked about the two-phase commit
last time
are less relevant here because the
participants are
much more highly available
so the um each shard is replicating the
log table or no
yeah well it's not electric in the lock
table it's replicating the lock that's
holding when it does the prepare
so only the lock when it's that that
it's holding during the breakdown yeah
the state that it needs to do the
two-phase commit
so then they like the current locks for
some transactions it hasn't reached the
prepared stage
it will they just be lost then we lost
and then the transaction will abort
the participant would just not
participate
and tell the coordinator hey i lost my
locks to that can't do it
thank you
okay so now the rest days like this
lecture is about the read-only
transactions
in
so these two interactions are only two
reads
no rights and they are
uh common and so one of the goals is to
actually make them very fast
and the way you're uh they're gonna the
way they achieve
you know the high performance is the
range that the reads
spanner makes in high performance
because reeds are only from local sharks
and they have no locks
and no locks is good because it means
that read write transactions can't
block on the read transactions or
another way of saying is that read only
transaction can't block redirect
transactions
and no no two-phase commit
and so that means also no wide area
communication necessary and so
that the reads can definitely execute
from a local replica
and you know also see of course you know
that this is the read from our local
charts because the
the the real challenge here is like how
to still get consistency
or you know serializability uh but it's
important to point out like you know
but for no moment you know assume that
we know how to do this but you know if
we could
then reading from only like a local
chart
uh how holding no locks not doing 2ks
commit it means that like all the
communication is local within that
within that particular data center and
it can be very fast and you know if you
look at the end in
tables three and six in the paper
you basically see that uh they're
basically you know read-only
transactions
are you know ten times faster than reef
ran transactions
these right transactions are in the
order of hundreds of milliseconds
which sort of makes sense because they
have to uh communicate
long distance uh and but the read-only
transactions are in the order of you
know
uh five to ten milliseconds
okay so the key challenge of course is
always going to be uh we've executed for
global replica
how to get correctness
so let me talk a little bit about it
because it's slightly different
than what we see before uh so practice
means two things here
one you know the transactions are
serializable
so they must execute in some serial
order so we think about
like we have a read write transaction uh
we have
and we have another read write
transaction then we have a read-only
transaction
you know the read-only transaction has
to sort of fit between the two
read write transactions and read-only
transactions should not observe
some part of the read-write transaction
so the read-write transaction does
multiple writes like the first one
then the read-only transaction you know
sees all those rights or none of them
and similarly for the one that actually
is past them okay
so the second so this is the standard
thing that we talked about
uh last week serializability and then uh
when they go for something stronger
and what they call external consistency
and external consistency means that if a
transaction
two starts after transaction one
has committed uh then
you know t2 must see
t1s right
so like we'll go back into this previous
picture like so if this read-only
transaction
this one started after uh
the first transaction committed then
this read-only transaction must see
uh the reach and the rights of that
uh transaction t1 and
um and so the idea if you think about
this
basically this sort of sort of external
consistency means like serializability
plus this real-time requirement and in
fact you know it is very similar
to linearizability
um and uh except you know the uh
you know one way to contrast external
consistency
uh for transactions with linearizability
is that
uh external consistency is really a
transaction level property and the way
we've been talking about
mineralizability so far
it always has been sort of on individual
reach and rights
uh and uh but to the first order you
know i think you can sort of think about
them exactly in the same way
and like linearizability you know
external consistency is pleasant for
programmers
uh and uh is very strong
consistently require a property
all right any questions about the
correctness definition there or the
correctness
goal that the spanner has
okay okay let's talk about how we
actually achieve this correctness for
read-only transactions
and let me start out by explaining a bad
plan that actually doesn't work
and then we're going to talk about a
better plan
so the back line is we're going to read
the range that we read always the latest
committed value
that seems about right right
because we have to arrange that if t2
starts after
g1 committed we'll see we have to see if
it's right so you know why not read the
lead is committed value and then we
should be
maybe we're good so here
is the the problem case of course you
know it doesn't actually work
so t1 naming t1 does the
right of x there's a rate of
y as the transfer commits
then you know we have another t
transaction we have transaction
t3 where t3 is the read-only action it
actually does a read of x
and so this is sort of real time and
then after
the t2 then after t1 or t3 starts
t2 runs uh just runs quickly and
addresses the right of x
the right of y it commits and then you
know t3 you've got a little bit delayed
and then actually does the secondary
read reader y and
that's a sort of time you know as usual
going that way
um and you know if you're following the
uh
release the latest committed value then
you know what is this read going to
return
it's going to return the value from this
transaction t1
and this grid is going to return the
value from y and that objection because
you know that's the last committed value
and that would be wrong right
because now we're actually in a
situation where basically you know t3s
observes and writes you know from
different transactions and not get a
consistent picture
so uh so this rule is not good enough
uh and uh to avoid
this problem and not you know use this
bad plan spanner uses a different plan
and that's plan is called snapshot
isolation
this is actually your standard database
idea
and mostly sort of in the local
databases
and not actually across the white area
and so we'll talk about that in the the
sort of the
white area aspect in a second but just
let me first explain what snapshot
isolation is
and so what snapshot isolation does is
we're going to assign a timestamp
to a transaction
and you know there's two different
points where we're going to assign these
timestamps for rewrite transactions
it's going to be you know the commit
started to commit
and for read-only transactions it is
going to be the
start of the transaction
and then we're going to execute
all operations drop the transaction
in timestamp order
i'll explain in a second but whatever i
mean that
and be able to execute all the
operations in timestamp order you know
each replica
doesn't store one value for a particular
key
the replica actually stores multiple
values
for a key namely with their timestamp
so for example at a particular replica
we can ask please give me
the value of x at time 10 or give me the
value of
time stamp x at 20. and so
sometimes this is called uh databases or
multi-version storage
you know what basically you keep before
for every update you basically keep a
version
of the data items so that you can go
back in time
and so this fixes you know the problem
that i
sort of showed in the first case because
basically what's going to happen let's
look at the free transaction again
so we got t1 we've got t2 we got
t3 uh t1 just write a one
you know there's a right of uh right of
x write a y
let's commit and let's say the commit
actually happens
at you know you know 10.
so this transaction basically runs at
time step 10.
then you know at some point we're going
to get our read of x
i'll talk about that in a second uh and
then here we have this other transaction
we get the variety y the right f
certain right of that y x right or y the
commit
let's say distant action commits at time
step 20. so
just run basically
uh at that time stem and then we have
the read of x and we have the reader y
now when the read of x happens uh it's
going to be assigned a time step you
know the starting type inside of the
transaction so
the starting times let's say that the
starting time of this
transaction is 15. so t2
runs at 15.
and so when the read of x is executed uh
you know it needs basically to read the
latest value
uh of x after uh
after uh you know before 15 uh
and you know the we do that you know the
latest committed value for
uh time step 15 uh before times of 15 is
going to be the times
the the values from this transaction
so x now reads the the value of
transaction one
uh but of course read y also will
execute at the timestamp
of the start of the transaction so it's
going to also read y
at the time at 15 and you know there's
going to be only one value
for that by y15 namely that is the one
produced by the transaction t1
and so read one uh the read y will also
read from td1 and so we avoid you know
this problem that we had before
where we would be reading from different
transactions
and so this gives us the linearizability
or the serializability that we'll be
looking for
because all the transactions are
executed in a global timestamp order
does that make sense and so what you can
think about is that every replica
basically keeps a table
right of uh values and timestamps
and so we're gonna have like x at you
know value 9
add to 10 and x at you know value
8 at 20.
and so when the read comes in you know
at a particular replica you know when
the reach for 15 comes in i could just
you know pick out you know the
latest uh write you know preceding its
type stamp
um so i have a question so uh when we do
the read x
let's say so let's just focus on read x
uh so x itself
it exists on some shard which is
replicated on a taxes
group which let's say you know like
there are like three servers
that replicate x and when you read from
x because we want the read-only
transactions to be very fast we
just read from the local replica which
might not necessarily be the leader
uh so like how do we guarantee that we
don't read the scale
that's how do we that that we don't make
a statement you know
brilliant question and uh that's exactly
the topic i wanted to talk about next
uh because the problem is you know as
you point out you know
there's a challenge that maybe the
replica hasn't seen
seen the right to x right at
time stand for whatever can right
and so the way uh you know this problem
is solved
in the spanner and the solution they
called something what's called
save time
and so the way this is resolved is that
basically taxes
or raft you know sends all rights
also in timestamp order
so there's not a you know you can think
about like the total order is not a
counter as usual for example i've done
maybe in uh
lap uh uh lab three
but it actually is literally a time step
and since the time stems also form
global order you know the
that global order of timestamps you know
sufficient you have to order all the
writes
um and then there's a rule there's an
additional rule for a reit
before you can do a read so before read
of x
uh that you know timestamp 15
the replica has to wait
for a right that is
with timestamp bigger than 15.
right because there's a c is a right
with a timestamp bigger than 15
it knows that there's certainly no
writes anymore before 15.
and so therefore it's safe to execute
the read
at time step 15. and know what value
actually needs to be returned
and so for services that are so this
means that the reaction may you have to
get it delayed a little bit
until the next right now of course for
busy services you know these rights will
come along
all the time and so the weight is
probably non-existent or almost
non-existent
okay but this is the rule that needs to
be followed to make sure that indeed
this problem
uh of replica actually have not seen the
right yet
uh returning the wrong value
the rule is slightly more complicated
you also have to wait
also wait for transactions that have
prepared but not committed
for example transaction might have been
prepared basically at you know
say a timestamp 14 uh but it hasn't
maybe committed it's right yet you know
to
the uh key value store and so we got to
make sure that you know
uh any transaction that was you know
prepared before
our read timestamp that actually commits
before we actually turn the value of the
read okay
does this make sense um with this
also be the case for different charts or
do we consider different charts just
separately uh
did the reach just hit a local chart
right the local replica and
so i'm not 100 sure what the question is
i think that i think the question i'm
asking
is the correctness guarantees
do they apply across charts
yes you know they apply to the level of
transactions right so
uh so if a read only reach a local
replica we still have to make sure that
the transactions are
externally consistent and by following
these rules now we achieved that goal
okay that makes sense thank you
okay um now
you know we're sort of getting to sort
of the
core part of the spanner paper which is
really
you know to be we want a reason about
time like timestamps
uh in this case and you know the clocks
you know of the
different servers uh must be
uh the clocks must be good it must be
perfect people must can a different
participants
must agree on the timestamp order and
uh if the transaction takes a particular
timestamp you know that timestamp must
be the sort of same timestamp everywhere
in the system
uh so and so the way i've described it
in this previous
slide is that you know whatever
competition that there picks
the retransaction assigns a timestamp to
it like 15
which maybe go back a little bit you
know here you know we're just assigning
uh
timestamps to these transactions and it
better be the case that
actually t1 and t2 and t3 agree on these
timestamps
uh and that they're comparable and so
as we'll see in in
a second this only matters really for
read-only transactions
um and we can you know consider sort of
the two cases like so what what happens
here so the question that we want to ask
is
what happens is like one replica or like
one server this has
the wrong time right and so it doesn't
agree
with the time at the other servers and
uh
what kind of problems could it introduce
so let's first think about the case
what the time stamp is too large
uh so for example you know let's go back
to our
uh version here with this case so let's
say
the read-only interest actually starts
reading
and it reads actually instead of
you know 15 maybe whatever the value of
returns actually
is uh 25.
and what would i do
or let make it a little simpler you know
18.
to get less confusion you know what what
is the outcome of actually having a time
stamp that
is off but off in the direction of being
too large
it's still less than 25 doesn't it still
read
than 20. doesn't it still read from the
first one but if it's greater it'll read
from the the second one
yeah which either one is fine correct
the real key
issue here is that uh you know before
reading remember
you have to wait until you see your
right right so if you're
so what happens if your time stamp is
too large
or off on the too large side you have to
wait for
in this yeah exactly you have to wait
right a little bit longer maybe
but nothing goes wrong
um so now the other question is
what if the timestamp is too small
so for example the read when the t3
the machine that executes t3 you know
asks for the time
instead of time 10 it actually gets back
you know say nine
and this is sort of variation of the
lecture
question so basically like t3 runs at
nine and maybe this is a good time for
actually so if you take a breakout room
and you can think and argue what you
know what is the outcome
what does the potential outcomes you
know or what could go wrong
if actually the time stamp that got
assigned
at t3 is 9 instead of 10.
so maybe we can do a breakout in here
really would have been possible
okay i think lately he's back
hold on a second here
okay anybody else getting that voice
okay
uh
um
foreign
first
okay everybody are you back and
everybody can hear me again
yep
we're all good
assume yeah we're all good yes yes we're
good
we're all good okay
um okay so back you know sort of this uh
question here
uh usually we're investigating
we're relying on scheme where the clocks
or different machines are perfectly
synchronized as i mentioned
matters only for read-only transactions
because read write transactions you know
grab
logs and use two-phase locking to get a
total order
so they will execute in some
serializable
external consistent order but we see
that for
read-only transactions the timestamp's
crucial
at least we think it's crucial for if
they're too large you know not maybe
just affect performance negatively but
the question is what happens if the
time stamps is too small right and so uh
the
particular question we're asking is like
what would happen
if uh in uh
the scenario that we looked at here at a
second uh where we have transactions you
know t1
uh actually i wrote this wrong you know
two two and three
with t3 is doing the read and uh
this read instead of actually happening
uh maybe
at 15 uh it actually happens
you know because the clock is you know
freeze wrong it actually happens at 9.
you know how about would that be
uh break our serializability
anybody okay looks like hi
okay sorry i didn't hear you because i
actually had uh some problem on my side
tonight uh
uh i can hear you i think can you repeat
the answer sorry i said it would break
serializability
yeah why uh because then your uh
your read would happen um which you
assumed to be happening after your
latest write
would then happen before it which would
wouldn't yield the the right
yeah yeah so just make this the story
complete you know t3
really is executing at time 15
right which is after you know tu
t1 committed so p3 must see
t1's right but if the clock is wrong and
times m9 got assigned to uh to t3
then t3 will actually read the value of
x
uh before uh transaction t1
executed and i'll be wrong that will
break external
consistency
okay everybody clear on that
okay so clearly we'd like to avoid this
and uh and so the central problem that
uh that analysis is how do we get clocks
how do we keep clock synchronized
oh wait i just have one more question
about
so this scenario basically can happen
because
um it's always the coordinator for a
read write transaction that assigns the
timestamp so
even if the read is local and it happens
on so it's possible for the machine that
was
running behind to have a version that's
in the future of its local clock
yeah or in the past in the future yeah
okay and that can happen because it's
not that machine who decided the time
stem
no okay so forget about which machine it
is like t3
uh is going to decide on the time stamp
for its transaction correct
uh we go back here to this picture so
here's we got t3
uh so t3 starts uh
and t3 starts uh in principle you know
in
absolute time in true time after ten
right because t3 starts after
t1 as we can see from this picture like
so this particular read x you know so we
assign a time step to uh read only
transaction we start uh
we assign the timestamp for the read
only transactions at the point of to
start a transaction
so the read of the x is the start of the
transaction for t3
t3 basically needs to get the timestamp
so it asks you know please give me the
current value of its clock
and uh you know if you know the clock is
reliable
and correct you know it will give back
sometime after 10 for sure
right because t3 started after 10.
but let's you know we were hypothesizing
that the clock of t3 is not
you know completely personally
synchronized and the clock actually
returned nine
and so now uh transaction uh three will
execute at time step nine
and that will cause us to read the value
from before
t1 and that will break uh
external consistency
okay but um if if the
if the replica on which we execute d3
had the
it may have the version
10 of variable x right
it might it might but you know it's
executing atoms
at time 9 and so we'll get the value
from before 10. right this is version
memory
yeah yep yep
yeah just making sure this is a very
good question so i think these are very
important points or to get
crystal clear what's going on here
okay so so i think we're now hopefully
all on the same page
you know the it's very important that
these clocks and these different
machines are pretty perfectly
synchronized
and of course you know it's not possible
to get uh perfect uh single clock
synchronization and there's a couple
difficulties
um it's difficult to get clock
stabilization
uh because clocks naturally drift
uh and so you know when you think it's
you know whatever 10 p.m
and plus one microsecond you know my
machine might think it's you know
10 p.m and two plus two microseconds
uh and that just basically because you
know they're sort of you know they're in
your machine or in the servers that are
oscillators you know that's to keep
track of time
they are supposed to uh you know
run at a particular frequency but the
frequency you know is not you know
perfect
uh you know and better clocks you know
like you know atom clocks have
better oscillators that are much more uh
precise
uh and that's sort of the kind of clocks
that uh uh
spanish is sort of relying on that you
know pretty high precision
but you know they're still they need to
sort of synchronize once in a while with
common
you know global time and
so to avoid you know the problem with
drift you know they have
pretty precise clocks you know they use
atomic blocks
which are more precise than like the
clocks in your computer
uh and then they synchronize with global
time
so to make sure that like all uh clocks
are agree
uh on the global time and then they sort
of keep taking taking picking
and then resynchronize periodically
synchronized clocks and with global time
and they
use gps the global position systems that
broadcast
time as the way to
synchronize these different atomic
clocks and then keep them
running in sync and so it looks like
the paper doesn't really say too much
about actually how the
true time system works uh but it looks
like you know they have maybe
a few or one atomic clock you know per
data center
the servers synchronize you know without
time server to
regularly uh synchronize their local
clocks with that uh
time master and the different time
masters in the different data centers
you know synchronous
synchronize themselves uh through
the gps system uh but
and so as a result the clocks are
actually on the different servers are
pretty close
uh in terms of you know they talk about
the epsilon you know what the error rate
is and so it seems like the epsilon
uh for their clocks if you look at one
of the sort of tables in the end of the
paper
is in the order of a few microseconds to
you know a few milliseconds
and so when a machine beats you know ask
you know the
operating system please give me what the
current time is uh the current time
that it gets returned maybe a few
microseconds off
from true time or even a few
milliseconds off from two times
okay so this is a little bit of a yeah
go ahead
uh before i yeah so uh so like the paper
uh i mean as you mentioned we did not
really go in that into that but
just like the process of synchronizing
the clocks or even
measuring how different they are yeah i
mean shouldn't we also account for the
time
of the message travel i mean yeah yeah
yeah
i think that's what they mean sorry i
didn't say much about this but this is
what they mean so they
sort of keep a running estimate about
what they think you know the
for example to synchronize with the time
master the
presumably the time library on the local
machine in our keeps uh
track of the you start to make an
estimate of like what is the average
delay or
the normal delay for sending or
receiving a message to the time master
and basically use that to correct for
any
uh small mistakes
then they also the protocol clearly has
support for outliers and so
more outliers you know maybe something
bad happened in the network and
therefore
your timestamp got delayed a lot and so
you should not include those
uh and i guess there's a third problem
which is that you know sometimes these
oscillators
go uh kaput you know you know they just
are not correct anymore
and so they may return incorrect values
and so the
you know again they don't talk about a
great amount of detail but
it seems so it's just that you use
similar techniques like ntp
to deal with those kinds of problems
thank you thank you
so if you're interested in this kind of
stuff uh there's this protocol called
ntp that actually you know when your
computer undoubtedly uses to actually
synchronize its clock where it's with
you know global time
uh and ntp has all these kind of
mechanisms uh
in built into it but ndp is not the
doesn't have the same position
or the same small margins uh that
actually true time has
and so i think in ndp you know you
should be thinking that these error
rates are in the order of uh
you know milliseconds to 10 milliseconds
and basically that has to do mostly with
the round trip time
any further questions about this
okay so um clocks are not perfectly
synchronized
we know that basically there's a margin
of error and what basically the
true time does is actually uh giving
you know when true time gives an answer
you know it gives you a certain best
estimate to guess what the current
uh absolute time or true time is plus
you know what the
machine thinks is the margin of error
and so
uh and uh and so the solution
or this uh to solve you know to deal
with
this clock drift uh is to
not use timestamps you know true time or
just just pure timestamps
uh but basically timestamps are
intervals
and so every value returned from
uh now like from the current time uh
basically has uh earliest
and the latest
and so for example we asked for the
current time
uh and it is true time is you know 10
a.m or 2 p.m
uh it might return an interval saying
well the earliest days could be
is you know uh 1 p.m 1 59
in you know 59 seconds and you know
whatever
uh 20 microseconds you know
and latest you know it might be you know
uh 2 p.m
and plus you know two microseconds
you know some machines might be uh more
than a couple microseconds or some
machine
like even a millisecond uh in that case
in some things case in the paper you
know the margin sometimes
uh in the order of 10 milliseconds or
you know multiple milliseconds
but it gives them an interval and it's
sort of guaranteed that the true time
is within that interval so
is the interval epsilon or two epsilon
uh the paper doesn't really talk about
it
in that sense uh it is just an estimate
about what the margin of error is
and i think if you look at the details
of the protocol often that marginal area
boils down to two epsilon
okay now to deal
so now we need to adjust uh our
protocols right because our protocols
have some rules about
uh setting the start time a foreign
timestamp
or setting the start time for a
transaction using a time stamp
and uh and a rule for
uh you know reach uh much into weight
until the c to the next right
and we'll see though basically there's a
couple rules that need to be changed
to deal with uh intervals as opposed to
with a true time so
first of all the start rule is different
uh so the start rule uh
uh is the current time
you know we asked the computer please
tell me what the current time is get
some interval back
and then the start time that we pick is
the latest
and so that just means correct that the
whatever time stamp the start rule
actually is science
is guaranteed to be after through time
so we know that two times in the past
and
for read-only transactions you know this
is assigned to this the start of the
transaction
and for you know read writings access
before it actually is at the point that
the commit starts
so that part doesn't change the only
part that really changes is that
you get the end point of the interval
and the reading at the endpoint of the
interval is so that at least through
time has passed
the has passed
okay and then there's there's a second
rule
that we didn't have before which is to
commit wage rule
and uh we're going to delay a
transaction
so if there's actually got some
timestamp at the commit time
uh with the start of the commit and then
we end we get to the end of the commit
then we're going to delay that commit
delay commit until the
timestamp that was assigned at the
starting of the commit
is
is a past oh i mean my notes are wrong
here more than one second
all right we're going to delay until uh
the timestamp is before
uh now earliest
so we know that it actually is
definitely before true time
okay uh so so that's sort of the
modifications
to the protocol and let's see sort of
how that works with a simple example
to get a little more feel for it
so the example i'm going to use is a
slightly simpler than the previous one
i'm just going to focus on the
transactions that just write some x
and we can still have you know free
transactions
so here's uh t1 and t1 does
right to x and then commits
and you just you know let's you know we
don't really care too much about this
transaction so let's
see that it commits it one so two time
at one
so now we're going to run transaction
two two
and you know it's going to write yeah so
the traction two three of course
runs after t1 and
it writes gonna say x2 so he writes x1
it writes two through x uh it starts to
prepare which was the beginning of the
commit
and so uh at the beginning of the commit
it was going to ask for a time
and so it's going to get an interval
back and
you know we know that uh the true time
that's going to get back is some
whole line that interval but somewhere
in that interval and so the interval in
fact you know might you know start
well before you know through time uh
let's say you know the interface starts
even at
you know one you know which overlaps
with the mission section t1
and you know maybe the latest value of
true time
is of the intervals 10. so that's what
it gets back
and what the we're going to pick as the
timestamp
is we're going to pick you know this
value 10.
and we want to pick the latest you know
value because we want to make absolutely
sure
that you know if there's a transaction
uh that started before
uh you know the true time uh that you
know we pick a time that is definitely
after that inject
that the true time so we're going to
pick 10 which is definitely beyond one
and so we'll never get confused about
this previous transaction
then at some point you know so this
transaction you know
uh picks timestamp 10 and that 10 you
know
might be a little bit further in the
future of true time right
so uh the transaction does the prepare
all the
whatever necessary work you know the two
phase commit and it actually hits the
real commit point
uh and there i may have to wait
right because as the commit rule uh we
have to wait a little while
until we're absolutely sure that 10 uh
is actually in the past and so
uh this basically at the commit time uh
what
you know the uh transaction coordinator
will do is like at the commit time and
just keep reading his local clock
and we'll keep reading his local clock
until it gets an interval back
where the earliest time is past 10.
so maybe at some point you know of
reading boom boom reading rereading it
gets an accent interval back and that
interval
and if the interval starts to say at
nine or seven it keeps reading
until it actually gets a value that's
bigger than
uh ten and then you know we know for
sure
that uh the true time has passed
and so it's safe actually to uh commit
the trajection
and so any transaction that now runs
after t3
half must have run after uh two times
10.
so let's say you know transaction three
starts
at some point and uh transaction three
starts after t
two so we have to now make absolutely
sure that now we read
you know x is two if it reads so this is
going to read
x um and
um uh and so you know we'll
it will ask for the current time uh it's
going to get maybe an interval back
uh you know the interval uh might
overlap a little bit with the t2
uh but you know the true time uh
you know maybe the for this clock is
pretty precise and the true time the
interval gets back is from 10 to 12.
so two times is somewhere between 10 and
12.
uh we know it basically has to be past
you know 10 because
you know we're gonna t3 reads by
definition
path you know after t2
and and that's going to work out because
basically t
t3 is going to pick us its timestamp
the end of the interval you know by the
latest rule so
t3 is actually going to run the
timestamp you know through time 12
if you will uh and that will guarantee
you correct that
you know this interval we know is for
sure
past the true time 10 and so when t3
reads you know it's going to read x is 2
because it will observe you know the
value of transaction 2 because you know
the
uh it's reading well beyond uh true time
and this must cause a little bit of a
delay uh but hopefully if the clocks are
pretty precise
uh as you know we talked a little bit
earlier the delay is actually going to
be small
does this make sense
i'm sorry i had a question so if
um t2 is saying that it's going to
start a transaction at time 10 um then
when we read something do like in the
same transaction do we also need to make
sure that 10 is
outside like before the
now interval the question is like
let's say p2 does more than rights and
does some reason rights
you know uh t2 should observe its own
rights correct
is that the question you're asking um
t2 like when when we when we
for example was we're also going to read
why
so let's make this add this to it
yeah or yeah i thought after that but
that's fine okay
either way i don't really care before to
prepare i actually reach wide
okay let me
yep
and then
[Music]
oh
okay maybe maybe this maybe maybe the
reason to read writings actually don't
really matter that much
okay because if you go back at the very
beginning
uh at this picture you know the
uh if a read write transaction does
reach correct uh
the reads will go to the uh
the shark masters or the shark leaders
that will technically take the read
blocks out
uh and uh the reason
basically the client executes all the
operations locally
right and so it gets read values and it
will read the most recent
read the value that it got after it
locked you know the
um the locked variable so
basically in rewrite transactions the
locks really do
all the global ordering there's the
two-phase locking and serious global
ordering
and so really the interaction that is
interesting is the interaction between
you know the read-only interaction which
is t3
in the read write transactions so when
is t2
actually commit and we're reading it
before it commits
yeah so the protocol in the read writing
section is we're reading
right early on we first do all the work
and then we go to the commit phase
so here's like here's the commit point
or here's where the
client says like please commit this
transaction and sends it to the
transaction coordinator and then the
transaction
coordinator runs the two-phase commit
protocol
but you know the all the shards you know
and these have locks
on the values that actually that
transaction is actually
using
okay
okay all right so let's try to summarize
a little bit
so uh redrag transactions
you know are basically
globally ordered or serializable
external consistent or serializability
plus
external consistency due to the fact
that they basically do two-phase
commit plus two-phase locking
the read-only transactions are the ones
that actually are special
because they are only contact a local
replica
and the reason they actually see you
know the correct value
is because of snapshot isolation
each data item is
actually versioned and stamped with the
time stamp on which it actually was
modified and so
uh you know you can read in the past uh
using snap circulation and then you know
to ensure that you know so this the
snapshot isolation really gives us
extra serializability
but you know spanner actually shoots for
something stronger namely it actually
shoots for this external consistency
property which is like linearizability
you have sort of this real time
component to it
and to actually ensure you know that we
get actually external consistency
we execute the read-only operations in
timestamp order
and because you know timestamp order
requires on
perfectly synchronized clocks the
spanner relaxes the rules a little bit
by actually using
time intervals
and the whole goal correct and the whole
you know by using these set of
techniques
you know it turns out that read-only
transactions you know are very fast
so rewrite the transactions are
basically you know not actually
particularly fast you know if you look
at the
table six it's you know 100 milliseconds
for a read write transaction that means
basically you can only do 10
transactions per second right
which is really not much but the
read-only transactions
are fast now this is the case though
like you know
uh you know although the read writing
sections are
maybe not that fast they are very
powerful
you know you're basically doing uh
transactional operations across multiple
sharks that are sitting in different
data centers and centers in different
parts of the world
and that just for programmers an
incredibly convenient
uh and powerful tool uh that you get
asset semantics
across shards in that are replicated
in all over the world
so uh this is all i wanted to say
actually about spanner uh
i hope this actually was helpful and
that you're not
uh he may be less confused and not more
confused because
because of this lecture but if you have
still questions then feel free to hang
around and
i'll be happy to discuss this or any
other aspect of spanner
and good luck finishing 3b and i hope
you get time to enjoy the
long weekend
thank you
um so i have a question maybe early in
the slides so when you have the diagram
for uh for the two-phase commit for the
read write
transaction so before we communicate
with the
uh with the um with dtc
that dc stands for the coordinator yeah
uh
coordinator yeah okay uh so before we
communicate with the transaction
coordinator when we read
x and read y initially uh we don't do
any uh
communication with the tc so my question
is what is the nature of
these reads do we treat them as
read-only so we read from the replica
that is closest to us or do we actually
do like a majority uh type of
communication
uh you know it we go actually to the uh
let's go to the participant leader
sorry it goes to the taxes leader
i see so it goes to the oh okay so it
goes like in lab three
sure so it's basically so the read x
here
basically goes the same thing as in lab
three so it goes through the leader and
it gets
replicated through the whole no it
actually doesn't uh the
there's no uh i believe there's no
actually uh read going inside uh
running through taxes but you know it
goes through the transaction leader
uh alter the the taxes leader and the
taxes leader you know of course knows
what the last right was
but what if the for example we have some
failure and the leader
thinks that it's the leader but it's in
some partition and it actually has
outdated information
um i don't know exactly you know how
they deal with this case
uh i think i think their leases make
that impossible yeah
so they have uh the so
every leader is leader for a period of
time
and you become and during that uh period
of time no other leader can be leader
okay that's it awesome thank you
thank you very much hey um
i had a question with the last diagram
with the time interval
yeah uh yeah i was wondering if like
if the read for t3 or like let's say
like the right
and t2 that time interferes from like 1
to 12
also such that the right happens at 12
for t2
and t3 reads also happens at 12 what
happens in that scenario
uh okay you gotta i'm gonna walk you
through one more you decide
okay yeah um so for t in t2 the right
right now it's from one to ten right
maybe what happens if that's like 12 so
that it's like the same as
the transition three okay twelve not two
i twelve sorry i was meaning both just
yeah um so if uh
the uh so it the the the
p correct section 2 would pick 12 as the
uh start time of the uh
of this of that of the the read write
transaction
it would wait correct until
12 shows up in the interval before it
commits
so true time is somewhere between 1 and
12. it will wait until
at least he's 13 right and so true time
is now
beyond 12 for sure yeah
and now we know that t3 starts
after t2 right right so it could never
got this interval back because the true
time is already
definitely past 13 or you know
you know past 12. so when
this guy now reached its clock we know
that there's going to be some interval
you know maybe it still includes 10 uh
but you know it will include
14 or 13.
and we'll pick the latest value correct
and so let's say it picks 14
and so it will do a time stamp actually
at 14.
i try so basically like that scenario
wouldn't have happened because
the time interval thing would have
guaranteed the earliest and latest
yes and it is the case the t3 definitely
started after t2
you know by definition right that's the
way we set up the example
and then also then like if if instead
like the read
was happening around the same time as
command like not necessarily strictly
after as
in this case like would is there any
guaranteed on that
like this
great question so remember what the
definition of linearizability is correct
if
t2 and t3 basically run roughly
concurrent or like real run
truly concurrent then it doesn't matter
you know t3 can go 4 2 t2
or after okay
but then what about serializability
aspect because they if they
execute again like it might not
necessarily be in the same order right
the warrior actually could do some total
order and t3 either goes before t2
or after teeth uh two but
either order is fine which is both are
allowed by serializability or
linearizability
because the execution is truly
concurrent
you know starts before t2 committed
gotcha and then for the t3 like the if
the commit and read happens at the same
time
the t what t3 is actually going to read
is just going to depend on
if the replica it's reading from has
that commit
all right okay gotcha thank you so much
hey welcome
good questions um i had a
question about so like
if if it's what it is in this picture
and
they when it tries to commit 12 is not
there it's just gonna
retry and wait again okay
it's just keep reading the clock until
it gets an interval back where the
earliest is passed and it's uh
timestamp okay um
and i also have just a clear just to
make sure
the guarantee that it provides is that
if
if it designs then timestamp x
and by the time where x is like before
the now interval um this
machine or this backs of the group will
have seen everything
or yeah i guess this machine will have
seen everything that has happened
at like before x is that right
yeah i think more or less yes i'm not
good up since you're what you're asking
but you know what we we get an interval
back what we know is that the true time
is somewhere in this interval
so here's true time
and so when we start this prepare uh you
know we know that you know true time is
not past 12.
uh but it's somewhere between 1 and 12.
and so when we do commit
you know we got to make sure that the
commit actually happens really after you
know through time
and so we're going to wait a little bit
you know so we know we got big 12
and we're going to wait until actually
our clock gives us an interfall
where true time is definitely past 12.
uh i think i think what i was asking
more was more like
if you pick 12 and then you your
interval is returned to be
13 to 20 do you know that
anything that um like with timestamp
less than or equal to 12 the other
changes for
those transactions that you're going to
be able to see them
yes okay
okay that makes sense thank you yeah
so i don't totally understand what the
point of commit weight actually is
uh because it seems like uh commit
weight will happen after you've already
selected the time stamp for the
transaction that
you're interested in and you'll simply
delay the actual like
absolute time at which the thing will
actually get committed just to make sure
that
i know extra mode no but at the commit
time you really start
updating the database
and so and at the commit time you have
to commit your return
like in t3 didn't run until after the c
right because that was our definition
like t3 started after
t2 committed right right right but like
what would happen if you didn't do like
what do you lose if you don't then t3
would run concurrently with t2
all right okay all nice i know not sure
which scenario you want to explore but
uh if you know we allow t3 to start
before c
then you know we have a completely
different story correct because then
there's nothing to discuss
uh because d3 runs concurrently with t2
and it could observe two t or not and
both are
okay i see
and so the time stamp for c you know we
ought to wait until
you know we pass true time uh
off you know uh this time the prepared
number that we get back
so we know that the true time really has
passed
t3 could you never pick a time at a true
time that actually would
be it would be before t2 uh committed on
i see i see
okay um i i guess it seemed like since
everything was already
versioned that if you sort of modified
the data if you
physically modified the data this early
like that would be okay because
everything has
a time step attached to it so no one
would you know from far away it seemed
like no one would do the wrong
thing and it's like looking more at what
they actually define as
their external consistency i don't
really understand similar to
linearizability because it just says
that
if a transaction actually commits before
another one starts
then they'll have then the first one
will have a smaller timestamp and the
latter one
is it also sort of like implicit in that
that transactions
execute in the order of their timestamps
for future yeah yeah yeah
maybe my shorthand notation was not so
brilliant
but yeah absolutely uh the real
requirement is that
if a transaction uh starts after
if t2 starts after t1 committed
you must observe all the rights from t1
right right right
i see i guess the i guess the type
knowing that the timestamp of t2 is
larger than t1
will tell you that you're going to have
observed everything of t1 because
you're okay that makes sense
thanks
any other questions if there's still
anybody there
i had a question about um a uh
4.2.3 the section the schema change
transactions ah yeah
yeah okay good yeah i didn't talk about
it at all i was just curious about
like because essentially they talk about
like predicting the time of the commit
uh well here maybe let me
just tell you what the way i think about
it and then you can see me
you can tell me where you could where
you know where the confusion is
so uh so schema change correct that
means basically adding column to a table
or the leader column of a table uh
something along those lines so it
really changes you know the layout of
the
database and uh and so
schema changes are generally expensive
and the way they make sure that they're
atomic they run them in far in the
future
uh so they're running with a timestamp
you know well beyond the current time
and so that gives that transaction can
just like do its stuff right because
every other transaction is reading and
writing using reversion memory
and you know they're creating them
version members way farther in the
future
so it can't affect any of the current
transactions running
now it could be the case that you know
the uh you know this takes so long
uh the the by the time they actually
want to
you know commit the
schema migration part uh the there is
actually transactions that are starting
to
uh encroach on the time that that
uh migration transaction started okay so
those you know those are transactions
you know time just marches on you know
we're they're doing transactions
and then the rule is that basically any
rewrite transaction or in any read-only
any transaction basically have to stop
until basically the transfer of the
the migration transaction has completed
because the migration transaction is
time stamping you know the
new values you know with its timestamp
so when there's a request essentially
for this migration
um it chooses a commit time far into the
future
and then you know we hope that basically
you hope that basically the that
transaction also commits you know
yeah by then yeah so
and any reads that come at a time up
until then
are served from the current yeah local
replica no problem at all correct
because
they couldn't have even seen that right
okay and i guess it's a cool trick it's
a pretty cool trick
if you have version memory you can
schedule things in the future
yeah it's a cool trick i was just
wondering how they actually like
figure out that point in the future
yeah that's probably some
some heuristic or something okay so but
but essentially so if
if you if you don't choose the time
that's far
enough in the future then you run the
risk of
okay so then you have like incorrect
results okay
so to avoid that risk of incorrect
results which is actually block
yeah i see
okay awesome thanks so much you're
welcome
all right bye