all right
well it's five after so i'll just go
ahead and get started so today's
lecture is a q a on the first lab the
mapreduce lab
and also some just general coding q as
for go programming that might help in
future labs so feel free to stop at any
time or
put questions in the chat and i'll be
checking it um occasionally
and i'm sure like the other case can
also um help as well
uh if you are unmuted and typing it
would be helpful if you meet yourself
but yeah all right so the agenda for
today the first thing we're i'm going to
do is actually walk through a solution
of lab one
and this is my personal solution um it's
probably not perfect but it's an example
of what you could have done
um second we're going to discuss some
alternative solution designs
uh
um third we're going to discuss some of
the common design mistakes and
some of the bugs that you guys had in
your solutions
um four just go over some general tips
and then finally
we're going to if there's time go
through some q and a's both
questions you might have right now and
also
questions that you submitted um before
lecture
so first for the lab solution
walkthrough
um let me know if the font's too small
um if now i'll just stick with this all
right so
i basically uh went step by step
and i'll show how i developed my
solution so the first thing i did
was this is rpc.go and the first thing i
did was
figure out the api in which i wanted my
worker and coordinator to communicate
and so the first thing i did was define
what types of tasks there are and so
there are map and reduce tests and
in order to signal that the coordinator
has
things the job is done there's a done
test
and so these are the types of tap so
you zoom in a bit can you zoom in a bit
oh yeah the fine
yeah uh is that that good
all right yeah thanks cool
yeah it's hard for me to tell how it
looks
hopefully this is good um
and so the there are two rpcs i decided
to implement
the first is a worker asking the
coordinator to give it a task
so one of math reduce or done and please
exit
and basically there's like the arguments
you don't really have to put any
arguments or you're just asking for a
task
and the coordinator replies with what
task is this
which task of that type should you do
and also some extra data that's needed
for the map or reduced tests such as the
number of map tests in the system
or the number of reduced tasks and the
second rpc
is a finished task rpc that the worker
uses to notify the coordinator
that it has finished the task and it
passes in as arguments which task it has
finished
and they don't actually really need to
get reply for this so that's the first
step
um of the implementation
so hi all right so as a second step
what i did is implement the handlers for
all these rpcs
and so that's in coordinator
so first i had to actually populate the
coordinator with the coordinator state
and so there's the mutex which protects
the state from concurrent access
because the coordinator will have
multiple threads running um
concurrently then the second uh
part is to keep track of just like the
files that we need for map tests
and the number of map and reduced tests
and
this metadata is used to track which
tasks have we issued
and which tasks have finished um
the ones that we've issued we keep track
of a timestamp so that we know
if these tasks haven't completed within
a certain amount of time to reissue them
and finally we have um the like has all
has the coordinator finished um boolean
so to handle the get task rpc we have a
handler
that um essentially what it does
is it will set the reply fields
right now i haven't yet implemented the
part that actually issues the tests
and if all the math and reduce tests are
done
it will send a done task to the worker
and exit
um and then we have the the
handler for the finish finished rpc
and what this does is it basically
depending on what task it was
sets that uh flag to true that it has
that
task has finished so that's the second
step
which is implementing the handlers with
our pcs
so the third step i have is um
actually sending the rpcs and
so that happened isn't the work
so
top of this is what we provided what it
does is it starts up this loop
that basically for every loop it calls
the handler forget task in the
coordinator
and depending on what task it gets it
will either perform the map task
with the relevant data or metadata that
it needs
perform the reduced task or in the case
of done it will exit
and so that's very simple and once it's
finished that task it will send
a finished task rpc to the coordinator
so this is just the skeleton code for
the worker sending rpcs
all right so we have rpcs we have the
handlers we have the senders
and so now let's actually like implement
some stuff
so
in step four it's i just added
a ton of handlers to manage this
intermediate file
stuff which a lot of you also did
and basically it uses like os rename it
gets like a temporary file
um so it's not super interesting and
then the next step
let's actually implement some of the
worker functionality
so we're back in the worker
and now let's implement the perform map
function
and what this does is as many of you
have to do
it reads the file maps them to keys
and then creates temporary files writes
them to
the intermediate files and then we use
an atomic rename
to ensure that maps aren't conflicting
as they process the keys and write them
so this is pretty much taken from
the sequential implementation and how
you would apply the map function
and then similarly we
implement the reduce function so
here's the format and then we have
perform reduce
and so what that does is it gets all the
intermediate files um
with the appropriate uh from all the map
tests
uh for this reduced task and sorts them
so the sorting happens in the
in the worker because the worker needs
the reducer needs access to all keys of
that type
and then to sort them i
it wouldn't make sense for the mapper to
sort them before because the mapper only
has access to a subset of the keys
and then we apply the reduce function to
all values of the same key
and then we atomically rename the
temporary reduced file to the
final reduce file so now
this loop we've implemented basically
the actual performance of the task and
we're basically done with the worker
implementation
so one last step remains um and that's
actually implementing
how this coordinator tells the worker
which task to do
and this is probably where um
you ran into the most uh complexity with
synchronization
in the coordinator so let's go back to
the coordinator
so nothing has changed in the state
so but now what we've done is we've
added a loop in the coordinator
that handles sending the test to the
worker
and um when we're
issuing the map tests so first we want
to issue all the math tasks
and so essentially what this loop does
here
is until there's a task to issue
the coordinator will just
iterate through this loop and if we're
done with all the map tests then we'll
break out the loop
and then if all the map tests are done
then we issue a reduced test
which is what's done here
so oh yeah i have
i guess i have one last step which is
actually what we do when the maps or the
reduces
um when there's no task to issue and so
what we want to do then
is the coordinator should just wait for
a task to issue
and once it there's a test issue it'll
do another iteration through the loop
and then actually issue the task
and i'll continue until all the map or
all the reduced tests are done
and if they're done it'll return again
so
all right so in order to support
that weighting what my solution
does is it uses a condition variable
um and
essentially what that does is if there
are no
map tests to issue but the mappers
um but they're uh because we've assigned
all them
for example and we're waiting for them
and they haven't timed out yet
then what we want to do is wait um
because we cannot issue a reduced task
if all the mappers have not finished
so we're just going to wait here and
then once we get
some type of signal we're just going to
go back to the top of this loop
and check whether we can issue a task
again
similarly if all the reducers aren't
done but we can't actually issue the
worker task we're going to wait for
there to be some type of signal so when
does the signal actually happen
well we want to signal any time
either a task has gone on for too long
and we haven't heard back so there might
have been a failure
or if the if a worker has actually
completed a test
because for example that might mean all
the math tests have finished and we can
move on to a reduced task
so in order to um
do that what we have are
we have a guru team here that's
uh kind of spun off immediately as the
coordinator starts
and what this does is every once in a
while
um after some you know maybe every
second or so
when a task might not have finished or
maybe this is
10 seconds i can't remember actually it
doesn't really matter it just wants to
wake up the coordinator every so often
so the coordinator
will do another check to see whether
there is a task to issue
and so this just loops around and every
second it will broadcast
to wake up the coordinator um
and the other time we want to signal is
when a task is finished
so that's actually going to happen in
this handle finish task
which is called when a a worker
like senza i finished a task our pc
and so here we have a broadcast right
after
we set the fields to done
or to completed to done and
when the coordinator goes back to go
check one of these loops and see whether
there's a task to
finish it will see that updated done
status
so that's essentially my solution
um it uses convars and mutexes to
protect shared state of the coordinator
so this is only one possible solution
and
i'll get back to here
and so this is the the kind of layout of
the steps i took
are there any questions on that
particular solution before i move on
can you please elaborate a little more
on the conditional variable
sure um
so uh what exactly so i guess like
you a conditional variable is very
useful
for when you want to wait for a
particular predicate
or particular condition to become true
so in this case a condition variable
is a natural let me just
go to wherever i use this um is a
natural
way to implement waiting for there to be
a task available
because you know it's a particular
condition
and it occurs
asynchronously so for example a task is
available
when a worker has finished a task
um or a task might be available
when the um
when a failure occurs and we need to
reissue the task
so you can think of any case in which
a you need to wait for a particular
condition
that's where condition variables become
very helpful
um does that help a little bit
yeah thank you
you can also uh like all of these
higher level like channels condition
variables um
all these higher level synchronization
perimeters are actually they're
built on top of blocks so they're all
implemented using locks
it's just their uh kind of like a higher
level way of thinking about
synchronization that allows you to
reason
for example about conditions
um would that have the same effect as
for example sleeping
in that loop that you have in the
um in the get task function instead of
like having
a condition variable that
makes the loop run every second
i guess yeah so it it is
like it's essentially the same as
sleeping um
the so
the uh loop here the timeout loop here
the difference is that
for example the condition variable or
you could be woken up
by a test that has completed where in a
loop in which you
sleep for example a second every single
loop
you have to wait a second whereas
with a conditioned variable you could be
woken up after you know like
10 milliseconds because the worker has
completed a test
so it potentially has better liveness
properties
but in this case we do like say if every
task
always takes over like five seconds or
something
then yes this is essentially
very similar to sleeping for one second
every loop
thanks i have a question i think i
missed the part where you um
how you handle uh when uh like a request
comes for a task
but you're like there's no tasks to give
out currently like do you
how do you tell the worker to like sort
of either come back or do you
keep them waiting and sort of
tangentially to that
um i'm curious why you chose this like
sleep
uh way of doing it instead of just like
checking the time when you get
a request for tasks and seeing like when
you get a request
what has timed out and reissuing it then
instead of like constantly checking
yeah okay so yeah so um i'll just your
first question first um so basically
how i handle the i've completed the task
um
is uh
once all map tests have finished once
all reduced half
tests have finished then the test that
we
returned to the worker because the
worker has called us
um to ask for a task is this
extra task type that i called done
um and then i also set the coordinator
is done to true
and so in the worker so i'll go to the
worker now
in the worker we have um
this loop that basically as the worker
is asking for
tests if it gets returned a task
is a done test then it exits um
so that's how i handle conveying to the
worker that it should exit
i guess i was asking like sorry if you
know let's say
uh you're still finishing up all your
map tasks and
you get requests for a task and you
still can't give out your reduced tasks
how do you tell the worker oh so that's
um a lot of you are
um an alternative design is to basically
if the worker if there's no task to give
the worker
then the coordinator returns or reply to
the worker immediately
and the worker sleeps in its loop but
you can see here right the worker loop
there is no sleep
and the reason for this is because this
call
will block until the coordinator replies
and in my solution uh going back to the
coordinator
for example like if we look at not done
in this solution the coordinator handler
will not return that reply
to that call unless it has a test
to return so it's we're waiting in the
coordinator
rather than in the worker um so the
coordinator is the one
that is constantly checking to see
whether there's a task
and sleeping where whereas the worker
just
simply blocks on this call until the
coordinator returns to it
is it is there any advantage to doing it
um
in the coordinator um
so i think one advantage is that
all the workers aren't constantly
sending rpcs you send an rbc it's one
rpc
per task right right um whereas if the
worker is constantly looping and
sleeping
and constantly replying you have a lot
more network traffic
yeah um i think that's but definitely
both solutions
are feasible and they both work
right um i had one other question which
is i i see you use uh
defer for the uh for unlocking quite a
bit
and yeah while i was doing my
implementation i
i realized i mean in a straightforward
function
it it's clear when it gives up control
of the lock
when but for example if you
like have a go routine created
from within the function
it's not very clear when it gives up
control
so a go routine runs on a separate
thread so the goverting never
starts with the lock acquired even if
you spin off the routine
while you hold the lock okay yeah
if we if we issue like a go if we create
a go routine
it'll just spin up a thread and from the
beginning it will not have a lock
right yeah yeah it's essentially just
like
you know you can think about another
thread just starting to run that go
like go funk that function okay
yeah and then um yeah okay and then
defer
unlocks at any return like
any return statement or yep yeah it's
pushed onto
a like basically like the functions to
run
when the there's a stack of functions
that the
returning from like handle get task will
run
so um i also have this in the slide so
you'll be able to refer to this later
but defer just ensures that when this
function exits
you over you'll run on lock and then i
could also do something like
um like like unlocking
and like i could just do something like
uh before the last print
or print one so these are all pushed
onto a stack
and then they're popped off in um fifo
order
no phone uh
yeah first in first out
no they're run in
lasting out yeah so it's a stack right
so
um this will run before unlock
locking which won't actually run before
the the lock
so if you're going to use multiple
difference just be careful in the order
that you use them but deferring the
unlock at least
is a very useful strategy um
that will come in handy okay i'm
um so the last thing is uh if we if we
call up function within
um within our
our function where we acquire the lock
it doesn't return the lock
right uh when it goes to the other
function
the other function returns to this
function and then until we
like the thread keeps a lock like
through
like jumping around yeah
yeah so like a function that's just like
a normal function call within one thread
will be called with the law count yes
thanks
all right so you guys have already kind
of discussed some of the alternate
synchronization designs
like waiting in the worker rather than
the coordinator and we've talked about
some of the pros and cons of that
um using time actually i think you
covered all these except for channels
maybe
so just one thing i wanted to note
because there are a couple questions
about this
so waiting for mac has to be done or
like any synchronization
that we've shown is on a single server
so cross-server communication between
the worker and the coordinator
are they're only it's only done ever by
rpcs
so for example like locking in the
coordinator has nothing to do with
locking on the worker
or on your raft implementation locking
on different servers
like don't interfere with each other so
i just want to be clear about that
um so one thing i thought would be
interesting is for you to see
a kind of an example using channels
because there are also some questions
using channels about using channels
so this is kind of it's a
not complete implementation of using
channels
but it's a potential way to that you
could think about having used channels
in
mapreduce and so in this example
the input to the coordinator actually
includes a channel
in which the coordinator is told of
what workers exist and this is
to handle the
possibility that workers are failing and
then some client
is telling the coordinator hey this
other worker joined our cluster
here's a new worker that you can give
tasks to so that's slightly different
than what we
had in the lab
so the coordinator has two channels
one in which it will send
tasks to workers or it won't send tests
to workers it'll send tasks to a
thread that will issue tasks to workers
and then it has a done channel so
again just like i i know i
said something a little strange which i
was like oh you can send
tests to workers over the channel but
you actually can't the channel
is only on the coordinating your server
and we'll see how that works in a second
so the first thread of the coordinated
that we create
is a go routine that basically will for
every worker um start the issue
worker task thread so
what this does is as workers are you
know
coming and going because they're failing
and then restarting
this channel basically says okay we want
to for every of these workers
start a thread that will issue this
worker tests
um so this is one go routine here
then the coordinator what it does is it
for all the tasks that we're given it'll
just
push those tasks onto this channel and
this task channel we actually made it a
buffered channel
so we know it will hold exactly num
tasks tasks which
are the that's the limit of the number
of tasks
that will exist on the system so what
this also means is that we can push
the number of tasks uh tasks
onto this channel without blocking so
the coordinator will not block
on pushing tests to the task channel
and then the coordinator will read from
this done channel until it has
done so number of test times in which
case it knows it's done um in this case
we're
i'm not separating macro reduce test
let's just imagine that there are
some number of tasks that the
coordinator needs to run
and once it's knows the tasks all the
tasks have finished
it closes the task channel and then
um basically we'll exit
and so the where some of the
interesting part comes in is these
worker task threads which i've separated
out into
a function here so these all run
on separate go routines and what it does
is for as long as there are tasks in the
test queue
it will pull a task out and then
oops i didn't mean to that and then uh
call basically an
rpc that will send the task to the
worker
so note that this channel actually is
talking to another thread of the
coordinator and that thread
is actually the one that's in charge of
calling
um the the worker
and then once it's done with the task it
says it's done
if it's not able to if the call fails
for some reason
for example it times out then what this
loop does is it'll push that task
back onto the task channel so another
worker or potentially this threat again
could pick up that task
so just to clarify how the channel
communication works so the worker
sends tasks on the attach channel which
is read through these loops
and this loop will exit when the
coordinator closes the channel um
done it's sent on these worker issue
worker threads
um and it's read by the coordinator the
original coordinator thread
and this exit equals true will basically
tell
the coordinator like oh i don't need to
listen for any more workers coming
or workers starting up so it'll cause
this other girl routine to exit
so i know that this is a pretty complex
example it's also not quite what we
um specified in the lab but it's an
example of how channels could be used
to implement something like mapreduce or
something similar to mapreduce
there is a question in the chat about
where is exit divide
in this code
that is a good question and it's not
so it it'll it they'll be exactly the
same thing as done
um it'll just be another channel
that's uh a bullion yeah
that's a that's a good uh good cash
oh can i i can't i've seen how do you
add things to the workers channel or
when do you add things to the workers
channel like how would you handle done
this gif
so in this case um worker the workers
channel
is provided to the coordinator so
imagine that
for example in you know how your
coordinator
was actually called or created by
the mr coordinator in maine
in the that folder so we would
imagine that in an mr coordinator we
would create
a workers channel and mr coordinator
would basically
be in charge of tracking when workers
crash
and when workers join so this is for
example
in a case where you know maybe new
servers are added to our cluster at some
later point
or some worker crashed and then came
back and and our coordinator would be
constantly
sending like these worker ids to
our coordinator in order to tell it hey
like this new worker you should
start issuing it tasks um so that part
is not shown
got it yeah i just i just uh was
wondering like
so this is really cool i was just
wondering like inside like
the lab one like how i think it's like
call worker and you've defended an rpc
to the worker uh
is that something we could have done in
black one
uh it's possible but
it definitely was not what we pushed you
toward um
because you would basically insist
setting up the coordinator as being the
rpc server you would have to set up
like rpc servers on the workers
um you could also think of in this
implementation
call worker could have handlers actually
for each worker
and each worker could be sending the
coordinator
like get task rpc's that's a little
that's a little funky um so in this
example it's actually more natural to
imagine
that call worker um that the coordinator
is the client and the
workers are the ones that are handling
got the yeah okay thanks really cool
i have two questions um first is just a
general lego question so in that
second for loop on on the left at the
bottom
if you don't use i will go complain or
in a for loop uh so
i run like all the go linter and all
that stuff
and it's fine i think
like in this case you
do need to have eye because you're
incrementing it and keeping the state of
eye around
through the can you do the same thing
with like uh
like just a norm like a while loop like
a just for empty for loop
with a select um where it's like
popping off of done um
so you
can't actually well you still need to
keep track of
how many times you've read from done
right because you can't just
read once you have to read number of
test
times
i see okay yeah so you do need
some type of state that will track that
um
and then there's the for the one on the
right like the where you're like
reading from ask and repopulating it um
is there like any
downside to that or if you're like just
constantly reading and adding
back and forth to the same channel uh
i don't i can't think of it off the top
of my head so in
in this case at least you won't block
because every time you read it you're
popping something off the channel every
time you
um add it you're pushing something so
because we have that the task is a
buffer channel
like you'll never block on that
so in terms of like performance
i think i mean channels are built using
locks
so locks are usually more lightweight um
but i don't think i don't think you'll
see like a huge
performance impact um doing something
like this
okay i guess i have like a sorry just
like a general
question of like what's your like
calculus for choosing between
mutexes and channels or like a hybrid or
like at the very beginning yeah
so mutexes are very natural for just
protecting a piece of state
so like your coordinator or like your
raf servers have a log
i want to protect every time i append to
the log um
that seems very difficult or it seems
very unnatural to try and do using
channels because
essentially you'd be using the channel
as a lock you'd want to
ensure that no one else is modifying the
state while you're modifying it
and then you would have to essentially
before you modify it
try to read on the channel to ensure
that no one else or
like someone would have to send
something on the channel to show that
they've done
they've been finished modifying it and
so on and so forth
so in that case it's actually very hard
to imagine how you would do it with
channels whereas
mutexes would make that completely
straightforward
um where channels come in very handy
is like i think our implementation
already has this like apply
channel is where you have to wait for
uh in some ways it's like almost like a
specific instance of a condition
variable in which you want to wait for
something
to be ready um or a
um like a very specific type of
command to be finished um so
for something like issuing tasks it's
actually not a bad example
um or something like blocking until
you have something on a queue it like
it's you can almost think of it as like
a queueing system
or at least that's how i like to think
about it but
for almost all modifications to shared
state or like the race conditions you'll
encounter locks are
much simpler and in some ways a lot
easier to reason about but
yeah thank you sorry i have a follow-up
question to
this slide um what happens if
the so you call the go issue worker task
thread which spins up another
go routine i mean it goes through all
the tasks in the channel what if it
fails when it's what if the go routine
fails when it's
sitting on the if call worker
so
if it fails then i guess
you've taken a task out
and not put it back
um i'm actually not sure that seems like
uh
like you're not you're saying like the
entire thread crashes
rather than as coworker not like
returning falls or something
yeah like the the go routine crashes
or is that possible for a single go
routine
to fail or would like the entire thing
just blow up
france you know i think the model you
should have is that if a
go routine crashes the process crashes
yeah that would solve it
oh sorry so if just the worker crashes
then you pick a different task
but should you i guess you would still
have
the same worker like
worker number um
would you still connect to the same
worker even though they
have failed yeah so in this case
basically
call worker would just continue
returning false
and you know this their routine that's
uh
specific for this worker would just
continue to loop
um and eventually when
the ma when the coordinator has
determined that all the tasks have
finished
it'll close the channel and then the
discover team will exit
so there could potentially like if all
your workers
continue crashing and you have like
hundreds of new workers joining
like you could potentially have a lot of
go routines just that are just like i
can't contact my worker i can't contact
my worker
but once the task is finished this all
of them will exit
properly
cool all right so that's an example with
channels
and now let's move on to some of the
more like your questions and bugs and
things like that so some common but
passing design mistakes that we saw was
pushing
too much work to the coordinator so
essentially making the coordinator
bottleneck
um and this included both like the
coordinator and
sorting the results or the coordinator
like reading file contents
whereas a lot of the kind of beauty of
mapreduce
is that all the state all the
computation happens on the workers
um and another common um
it's not really a mistake but
potentially something you can think
about is
how many rpcs are you sending and like
do you really need to send that many
rpcs so for example
sending an rpc to check whether there's
a map task available
and then sending another rpc to ask like
give me a task
is a little redundant and you want to
try and like reduce
the number and types of like reduce the
api between the
master or the coordinator and the worker
um but these were like they would pass
the test and
it's just things we wanted to point out
so now okay cool we're about like
halfway through lecture
so for the next say like five six
minutes
why not we're going to do breakout rooms
um let me stop sharing actually
all right so we'll do breakout rooms and
oh shoot let's see
uh
i think zoom just crashed on me
we could still hear you don't see you
all right i'm back
yeah i upgraded zoom right before this
lecture that was a bad idea
but all right for the next five or six
minutes uh you should
talk about just like you know any
interesting bugs or observations you had
about the lab
um or you could you know complain about
how long it took you to find a certain
bug
or ask questions to each other and then
we'll come back
and go over some of your questions all
right
um
okay all right see you in a bit
oh so i thought you were with franz do
you want me to move you somewhere else
probably best but let me see if i can do
it myself
okay i'm going to be right back
all right are we mostly back
i think all right cool
all right so i hope that was pretty fun
or at least
you got to talk about some of your
frustrations during the live
um yeah so for the rest of the lecture
we're going to go through
oh right first before questions here
some general tips that you'll want to
look out for for
future labs um so first of all
the one thing you'll find very handy
for debugging is just you know classic
printfs
and so you can have conditional
printouts which only print
when you want to debug so for example
you don't have to go through your code
and comment
them all out before you submit or
something like that and so
in the wrath lab we provide this dprintf
in the utils.gov file um and you can
modify that
to for example also print out like the
server id
every single time you call dprintf or
something like that
so yeah like customize it to you know
print out in different colors for
different rpcs things like that
um and also like redirecting your output
to files
just so that you can like search the
files will come in handy
um another trick that you probably want
to
keep in mind is you can look at all the
go routines to see
where in their like execution they're
running and so just type control um
backlash in order to do that
and the final thing which we've already
sort of talked about are these differs
and these slides will be uploaded also
so you can refer back to them
but essentially you can push multiple
functions to run right before the
function returns
and they just be careful of the ordering
all right so now let's get to some of
your questions
um a lot of you submitted also questions
about raft so
those we'll get to for like the rough q
a or like
maybe office hours or you can put that
on piazza but i'm going to focus mostly
on the ones from mapreduce
or maybe we have time then we can also
get to the rough questions
right so the first category of questions
kind of falls under
um questions specifically about
mapreduce
um so some more complex tasks that you
might want to use
mapreduce for um it's actually used a
lot in ml or like data mining
statistical
applications um i linked here to
uh hadoop which is uh it implements
mapreduce and a lot of people use it to
run
these type of tasks and for example
here's a simple or
maybe not so simple but basically matrix
multiplication example of how you would
run that using macroduce
um second like you for a full tolerance
of the coordinator the paper food
is a very simple um checkpointing
mechanism in which you'll just start up
the a new coordinator using the last
checkpointed state
and in some ways this is a very natural
design for macro dues
because everything is deterministic so
there's no
um the coordinator really doesn't have
that much state to hold all it needs to
know is like which tasks have finished
and which tests haven't
um so you could use raft of course to
like enable fault tolerance and have a
set of coordinators that all agree on
like the commands that's issued so far
and the current state but
in some ways it seems a little overkill
for
um the coordinator for something that's
more stateful
it's uh like a key value store or
something it
it's much more natural to use slanted
craft
um so some other questions about
reproduce the shuffle or combiner step
when does it happen and what does it do
so combining occurs
um like right after the map functions
applied for example in combining the
word counts
of a particular word because having a
lot of entries that
you know like the one you could you know
combine them and then write only that to
the immediate file
our intermediate file um sorting occurs
at the reduce
after all the outputs of the map are
read by the reducer
um let's see a successor to mac produced
yeah so actually
i'm not super familiar with it but you
can look at stuff like
google cloud data flow um and other
sort of directed graph computations
where
inputs flow into a node so you can think
of it as a graph and then they
might flow out to other nodes and that
node in the middle
that performs for example a map
computation and produces intermediate
data
that is then sent to other like reducer
nodes in the graph
so it's a um interesting way
it's like a data data flow way to think
about mapreduce
um and i'm sure that there's others that
i'm not necessarily like that aware of
i don't know one one maybe one of them
spark which we'll read later about oh
yeah
yeah so but the i i like the graph way
of thinking about that reduce
because right now we're only really
thinking about like a two-step operation
where it could actually be like you know
many many steps
um oh yeah and then how are inputs
partitioned in practice so
usually because the input space
is very application specific and the
output space is also application
specific
um it's really up to the programmer to
specify
um there sometimes are
natural for example like maybe a local
matrix computations and you want to
combine them or
so on so forth um or you could if it's
just like an
enormous document or like enormous text
text
files you can just split it up into
reasonable sizes of work so that you
know like
applying the map function isn't going to
take forever um and also it depends on
the size of your cluster so how many
workers you have
so some further mapreduce questions why
do macrosphere files locally so in the
paper
this is because at that time the network
band bandwidth was
their bottleneck um that's why they
don't
use gfs and they only use gfs to write
the
um
yeah to write the output files um are
leaders necessary for distributed
systems
not necessarily um they're
like think of bitcoin like other
decentralized systems in which
all the nodes sort of perform
computation and some random node or like
some node in the network is responsible
for
committing that so there are definitely
more like egalitarian designs
um oh yeah and then our challenge was
actually to run map reduce onto
on like actual different servers rather
than um
what we kind of had you do in the lab
and so in order to do this like you
would just
instead of using sockets to communicate
um over for like the rpcs
you would use like tcp id basically like
normal
um like over the network communication
and you would use a shared file system
like gms so
the equivalent i think all of you have
access to athena
if at least if you're at mit and you
could you know
ssh to multiple athena machines and use
afs which is
the file the shared file system that i
think that uses
to basically you can access your files
on athena from any machine
um similarly you could do the same thing
by renting aws instances and using s3
but uh we didn't expect you to spend any
money to
to run our lab
right so some questions that came up
about just like general code design so
we've
some of these we've discussed as well so
lab one was pretty small lab two is
going to be
much larger um especially as you get to
the later stages
and as lab 3 and lab 4 come along as
well
and one thing that i personally find
very handy
is to separate different chunks of code
by their purpose
so and also in how i
implement each step of my code
so separating them out by for example
rpcs
and the settlers and handlers and feel
free to
actually separate these out like
physically in different files
um that won't like that's fine for our
tests and
it will probably help you um like not
have thousands of lines of code in one
gigantic file um i
i personally like to put all definitions
of state together
and then functions are
like sort of separate but that's my
personal preference um factoring out
common pieces of code into functions
will also be very helpful
for example every single rpc you will
get in raft you need to check for a sale
term
so putting all that logic so that resets
all the state properly and everything
into one function that you can just call
will help
because you know you don't want to
actually forget to like reset your
election timer like reset voted for or
something
um although you should have reset the
election timer so don't do that
that was an example i pulled off the top
of my head um
and also finally having a good
environment with like autocomplete or
like being able to search
for certain keywords in your code and so
forth can help a lot
um so if you need any help setting this
up like come to office hours or there's
tons of tutorials online you can look up
you know a good editor
but it's not necessary it's definitely
not necessary but it could
it does help um and then oh yeah so
someone else has using go
decrease the amount of time students
spend debugging so i've never actually
implemented the labs in c
plus plus but according to franz like
well
the one huge advantage of go is its
memory management
so it uses garbage collection and you
don't have to deal with like
you know there are pointers but you
don't have to deal with them in the same
way that you would in c or c
plus plus um so like i don't know how
many of you run into psych faults
so far but i'm guessing very few of you
or they were very easy to fix
and this definitely makes it easier to
debug
um or there are just certain types of
bugs that you don't need to worry about
sorry i have a question yeah and this is
like a more
ghost specific question um but uh when
you have a function
that can take in uh let's say you have
like a
you have like the pen entries arc and
you also have like the uh
request vote arg both of them have a
term variable inside
but when you pass it to a function how
do you
tell the function that's like hey i
expect a struct
that has a term field
is that possible so you you define
the types right so it's like any other
when you pass it into the function the
function expects an argument of a
particular type
and those types yeah yeah let's say i
want to share one function across
both types i believe you can use an
interface
um but i'm not sure oh yeah so i tried
but when i do dot term it says i don't
know this
field or like it doesn't exist i think
you need to convert it
or you need to still have casting i
can't remember but there's a way to
coerce you have to type casted back you
know to whatever
structure want to access
like you basically need to tell go
that by the time i actually use this
variable
it is of a particular type got it
thank you so one thing if you want to
reuse the function for multiple
different types
you can pass in an interface but you
might also need to pass in for example
a like uh enum or a bull or something
that tells it
like hey this is going to be of this
type and then you need to cast that
interface
into the right type before you use it i
think
i think the way people usually handle
this is by um putting setters and
getters in the interface
so you don't actually need to know which
type it is
in actuality you can just access the
variable using interface
yeah but
yeah i don't think it you should need
to use interfaces that much in raft
like i don't think i used it all other
than the command which is provided
um
yeah like i guess factoring out common
pieces of code is good unless it adds
additional complexity um
or like i wouldn't try and force your
types to all
be able to run on the same function like
it might just be simpler
to have two slightly different functions
or if the only like shared piece you're
using is the term you can have
like the same function take in just the
term and in both cases pass in the dot
term of the
structure we're using yeah
cool all right some other code design
questions this is your extreme museum
once when separating the code into
multiple files is their naming
convention
like required because when we make the
lab it seems like it's copying the
source file so is there any naming
conversion
um i mean i would put them in raft the
raft folder
but there's no naming convention like
you can name your files whatever you
want
um okay our grading scripts will replace
anything that's necessary for or like
anything that
belongs to the testing framework so
the config file or like the test file
anything that you change in there will
be wiped out
um yeah there was
like also be slightly careful about
using external dependencies
um i ran into a couple issues with
grading
some scripts i had external dependencies
like
using some github package go package
but those were i was able to like fix it
just be a little careful
if you do that but yeah create as many
dot go files and raft as you want
um yeah so a pointer versus
a value well passing by reference can be
cheaper
because go won't just like copy the
struct um this was
this question was asked in particular
for
why call takes the arguments and the
reply as
um pointers and so you know those could
be
potentially extremely large and so good
doesn't have to copy them
when you call the function that's the
main reason um using bud locks and
channels are possible
yes um you'll use them both in math so
you will definitely see how it's
possible
oh yeah and then we're getting a lot of
questions about timeouts um
so in math in the mapreduce lab the
timeout was sort of
well we gave you a set 10 seconds for
the worker test when they failed
but in terms of like how long do you
sleep and stuff you were pretty much
able to choose anything under that for
raft you have to choose timeouts a
little more carefully
and our tests are like kind of sensitive
but not super sensitive
like you'll be able to for example
probably be within a range of like one
to
100 to 200 milliseconds and be fine
um yeah uh
in terms of choosing them it
probably helps to first think about why
you're
waiting at all and for example in the
for raft your leader is sending
heartbeats
and your timeout is to detect when the
leader is dead
so you kind of want to give the leader a
couple chances to tell you that it's
alive
otherwise you know you'll just
continuously think it's dead
so depending on what you set your
heartbeat time out to be
or your heartbeat interval to be which i
think we give you some guidelines
if it can't be 10 more than 10 times per
second or something like that
um depending on what you set your
heartbeat to be
you'll want your timeout to be something
like pretty reasonable like maybe
allow for the chance to get two to three
heartbeats
and then you'll have to randomize some
like
range because you don't want all your
servers to start elections at the same
time
and to do that you can you know like a
range of
maybe like two to five heartbeats
sometime out between there is reasonable
but in terms of the test you'll
see whether you're sending too many rpcs
or too many bytes are going over the
network as
the tests go um in later labs
and you can tweak your timeouts very
easily it's
slightly implementation dependent
so i can't tell you like what's the
perfect number for you
but thinking of it in terms of like why
am i timing out
in the first place and how many rpcs do
i want to get from like
other servers before i time out is a
good metric to keep in mind
um so hopefully that helps a little bit
timeouts
uh okay yeah so some implementation
questions that
um came up about the mapreduce lab and
also the labs in general
so some people actually did implement
backup tests which is pretty cool and we
definitely did not require that
for this lab um and
i think something that was important to
keep in mind is that the paper
has makes a distinction between start
restarting a task because a worker has
failed
and issuing the task again
to speed up a lagging task that you know
the worker hasn't failed
but you want the task to complete faster
and so backup tasks are used for the
latter when tasks are haven't failed yet
but they're
they're just slow and timeouts
start tasks when workers are actually
detected to fail
so in the paper the coordinator actually
gets heartbeats from the workers
whereas in the design that we proposed
for your lab
we use timeouts both to detect that
worker has
probably failed and also to detect slow
tests
so some in some ways we make that just
we don't have that distinction
we just assume that like if this task
hasn't completed in this set of time
that you know like probably the worker
has failed or maybe it's just insanely
slow and let's reissue it
so that's why um our labs
don't really mention backup tests
um so and then yeah so there
this is again going back to the
confusion the next question um
about like synchronization if the
servers are on different machines so the
servers
are on different machines and they only
communicate using rpcs
all synchronization is just protecting
or like synchronizing the threads on one
server
um i just wanted to emphasize that one
more time
um common sources of race conditions
just you know
blocking um i
in some ways i think uh someone's
talking about like
you know how do you know when to log and
how do you know when to
you know use synchronization so anytime
you're modifying the state of the
you know like your raf server or the
coordinator anytime you modify this date
you want to unlock and what you'll
notice
is that for almost every function
in your raft implementation for example
you will have
a lock and then a defer unlock like
right after that
the only times you need to make sure
that you're not locked
is when you make a call that might block
so
sending an rpc um
you know sending something over a
channel those type of operations you
shouldn't lock around because then
you're
you're that thread will just be blocked
on that and hold the lock
and stop the server any thread on the
server from making progress
um yeah and then there are also some
questions about like
there are some data races that are
benign like for example you could set is
done
um to be true and you know like you
don't really need to walk around that
but the razor detector is complaining
um you could use an atomic bowl which
has the same behavior as like walking
before and
unlocking after but
even though you might think this data
race is benign it's
undefined behavior so it just so happens
that you know eventually
the next read like your read might miss
the fact that it's done but the next
time you call is done it'll say
true and then you're fine but undefined
behavior
could technically be implemented as
anything
like it just so happens that your
compiler and your processor does
something reasonable
when there's a database so you should
handle them especially when they're this
simple
um and they don't really affect
performance that much
another thing is well
in in theory you could have
this like is done data race could
potentially mean that your
process would never exit because you
know the right
to is done setting it to true might
never actually propagate to the thread
that's reading
what whether it's true or not because it
could be stored in
some like buffer and never flushed what
locks ensure
is that you're right um the next thread
that reads
is done will see the last
um right is done and i'll actually flush
it from
for example a potential buffer that the
right could be stored in
so yeah that's just emphasizing like
you don't want data races even if you
think that they're really friendly um
clean way to exit so
sending a exit rpc from the coordination
worker
works also like the
quote-unquote like messy exits where the
worker like
tries to send an rpc and sees the socket
is closed like those are also fine
um we like both
solutions are equally acceptable um
and then unexpected end of file errors
so
you can look i have a link here that
basically shows when it's invoked in the
client but it's a little
um confusing as to when that actually
happens so i would
not worry about it too much if anyone
has insights into
uh if they got this error at a very like
strange moment then we could look into
it but i think it's very specific on
your implementation so i would have to
look at that
in particular but we got a bunch of
questions about that
um yeah i think so that's basically
most of the questions that came up and i
think now if you have any questions
about you know
go mapreduce or if you want to
ask some stuff about the the labs i had
a question about
um the clean way to exit
um so you're saying like send an xcr pc
i was just wondering if there were like
if there was like a case
where like a worker for some reason just
takes a very like
a very long time to reach the server
right like
like how does the server know like when
to
like shut down because because uh
because the the coordinator shuts down
at some point right like when
when when it says like done when done
returns through
um it shuts down and so it stops
replying
to the workers um how does it decide
when to do that if it's waiting for for
workers
to to shut down themselves
oh so in this case the coordinator
isn't oh i guess so sun is
probably the wrong word the coordinator
isn't waiting for the workers to respond
the coordinator is it's not sending it's
replying to the
request from workers with a like the
task is done please exit
so the worker isn't uh the coordinator
isn't actually
waiting for the workers at all and so in
this case the coordinator could actually
still exit before the workers and cause
the workers to
like you know have a disconnected socket
error and then exit
yeah i guess that was my question right
like like if
if it like the coordinators replying
to workers right that are like
potentially like
asking for um get tasks
but what happens if the worker shuts
down
or sorry the coordinator shuts down
before it gets a
like a re i get i get task rpc from
the worker oh then the next time that
the worker tries to contact the
coordinator the worker will see that the
connection is closed and then exit
okay yeah that just clean
uh i shut down that as well get
uh essentially i mean you could imagine
that
you know you could set up the workers to
be rbc servers and then you would
actually have the coordinator be sending
these like please exit and the
coordinator would have to wait for the
workers to exit
but it's not um
or it doesn't seem like you would get
any utility out of that um
thanks yeah uh cat i see you have your
hands uh yeah something that i was
wondering about
is for the future labs are we allowed to
have more files because i think
explicitly in the map produce lab we
were only supposed to have three
and it didn't read something where it
was like hey you should have all of your
stuff
contained in one oh yeah so
you can definitely have more files um
that's like i would almost encourage
that
um i did we say that about mapreduce
i i don't i can't remember whether we
did what were you saying you couldn't
edit any of the other
main files is it like yeah you can't
edit the files and
yeah okay i misread that thanks this
makes me
feel a lot better all right yeah yeah um
but definitely like bringing up your
code will be useful
um i have a
question about the benign data races um
i guess like because sometimes there's
for example in raft you just want to
like read the current state
of the uh of the raft server um
why would multiple write multiple
threads writing to it
and one reading so why would a read and
a write to the same variable
end up cause undefined behavior because
three either comes before or after the
write
so one thing that can happen
and most processors don't do this but
every time you have a
like so these any thread can run on like
a separate core
um and every core has a
buffer for the data that it's reading or
writing
um or writing i guess like a store
buffer so for example
thread one could write one value
to the state and thread two could
try to read it um or like multiple
threads could be writing
and thread one without a lock so locks
essentially flush the buffer um
without that lock this right might just
like stay in thread one's like store
buffer forever
and the read will never return
um the updated value so
this behavior doesn't quite happen in
practice but it's an
allowable behavior because you do not
have the law
sorry so what happens if the right has a
lock but the read doesn't
like doesn't read always need a lock
yes
because
i think i'll read i i googled it a
little bit and people are like yeah
don't
don't even try lot less share data but i
don't really understand
why that would be a problem
go ahead you could like be doing
something that assumes the thing was
true and then like when you read
it's not actually true yet like there
might be multiple things right
that's why you don't want to lock this
read so
the only time you might
be able to even get away with this is if
you
only read a single word and that's all
the thread does and it never
does multiple reads but i think you
still have some issues with
one of the other things is
if you're reading more than one piece of
data like if on one thread
you take a lock a sign a a sign b
another thread it doesn't take a lock
might see b the new value of b before it
sees the new value
of a the ordering that you messed up and
so if you read like
a term uh from one that
from one variable and like whether or
not it's the leader from another
variable
you might read a pair of values that
never actually existed
because there aren't the guarantees
like when you're working with concrete
systems you
need to build everything based off what
the guarantees are that the platform
provides to you
and if you don't there's all kinds of
weird edge cases that can
throw you off and yeah
yes because i think the only case in
which you can even
like try to reason about this is that as
if there's only ever
one like you know word in the system
that you're ever
trying to read and write to as soon as
you try to
write or read multiple uh pieces of data
then it's
like you won't be able to reason about
anything without loss
basically if you want to play games with
this you have to
really understand the compiler the
programming language and the memory
model
the processor you're using and yeah it's
like memory coherency system
um it gets slightly complicated
incredibly quickly
yeah it's also like i mean this is all
undefined behavior so even if it works
now
like you know i could someone could
write just like a new compiler and then
you're like that's where the whole thing
about like demons can fly up your nose
like it can literally do anything if you
have a database because it's like oh
this program
like doesn't have any semantics that we
can
like you know go crazy so i would i
would not risk it
okay it makes sense thank you yeah so so
even when we're accessing like
anything just reading like let's say a
rap server state we should still
wrap it in a lock yes right yeah it just
gets annoying sometimes because you have
to like
wrap the single read in a lock and
unlock but
i'm not sure if like anything
uh that shouldn't happen super often
um like i mean maybe if you want to for
example check that you're still a leader
if you're not exit or something like
that but
yeah i don't like i forget do we use
like atomic pools for
like killed state for example
that like you could use an atomic bowl
which essentially is like
locking and unlocking right before
accessing it
and right after but
yeah i
i i think you'll like having in some
ways very like coarse grain locks and
knowing that
you're the only one touching a piece of
state will become
very handy as you reason about your
implementations
thank you
uh i have a question about the channels
so
when you make a channel it's only
between two threads
right or it can be between multiple
threads but like
if you not if you don't have it um
buffered it can potentially just lock
and block forever right so
for example if you want to do something
raph and then you have like election
you have a channel that like does
something about election
timeouts you would need a buffer channel
that's like the size of the amount of
servers correct because like you could
like
send something and then like it blocks
because
you can be you can have multiple like
election uh
things election messages sent between
the channels
correct so if you want a on buffer
channel it should only be between
it should only be between two threads
only correct
um i mean not necessarily like if two
threads are consumers and one thread's a
producer
then okay but
multiple producers i guess you would
need that correct
well not necessarily i mean if the
consumer is
you know just doing a loop and
constantly reading then
all the producers would just
like i guess it depends on how they're
scheduled
uh but if you like you would eventually
have someone reading from the channel so
you can have multiple producers and one
consumer
actually does anyone know about the like
kronsalt um
do you know about the ordering
guarantees of channels like is there a
liveness guarantee or are you
i feel like there isn't a liveness
guarantee so i guess if you have
uh it's kind of like logs right like if
you're always trying to acquire the
locks and another spread is like
also spinning and like trying to acquire
the lock there's no
guarantee that you will ever require it
which is why like
randomization might be necessary in that
case
also i realized i think lecture is
technically over
um i am holding the office hours right
now so if you have questions online too
or i want to continue asking questions
i'll be there
um and i think like maybe franz if you
want to stick around or
other others but i will move to
to office hours now
so thank you all so much for coming
thank you thank you
um
oh can i just ask a quick question
yeah all right franz you're the host now
so i'm going to just hop off to my
office
oh what's the theme like my color scheme
yeah
that's a good question i'm not actually
sure
let me check