as you probably have noticed uh i put up
the
here on the on the my shared screen
the part of the web page uh the most of
the class is driven from the schedule
i'll talk a little bit later about it uh
but you know hopefully you find the
url and you found the schedule
and i'll return to that a little bit
later in more detail
okay so what's the plan for today
i'm going to talk a little bit about
what is a distributed system
so what is it and maybe give a little
bit of
historical context you know how uh
distributed systems have developed over
the
last couple decades
then hit a little bit on the core
structure
like what you should expect
then uh talk uh what are the main topics
or the main recurring topics that we'll
see throughout the term
and then we'll see actually first
illustration of those main topics by the
case study
uh that was assigned for today the paper
mapreduce
which is also the topic of the first lap
and
if you watch the piazza you know we just
uh
uh posted that to the lab on piazza
url so that you can get going and it's
due next uh
next friday all right so let's start
with the basics
and talk a little bit about you know
what is a distributed system
and sort of uh you know maybe easy to
start with a little picture
uh you know the internet cloud
we have computers connected to with
clients and it may be servers
maybe you have servers that actually are
complete data centers
clients and the data centers themselves
you know may
be internally distributed systems that
are connected by internal networks
the data centers themselves might be
have internal connections you know
outside of the internet
uh with sort of a large collection of
you know computers connected by networks
and
you know sort of informally you know the
way i think about it about the
distributor this system is that there's
a multiple
you know more than one computer uh
networked you know so they can interact
only through
you know sending and receiving packets
uh as opposed to say a multi-processor
where you can interact through shared
memory and they're cooperating
you know to deliver some service
uh those are the four
key words that define you know for me
distributed systems
uh often you know you might not be
you're aware that interacting in the
distance of the system you know you
might be
using some clients for example the zoom
client uh but at the back end on the
zoom client you know there are huge data
centers or multiple data center
supporting actually you know this
particular distributed application
uh and in some ways you know we wouldn't
be having these
zoom lectures if there are more in the
you know even there weren't
distributed systems and uh so they often
perform you know the backbone of the
infrastructure that supports
applications
okay
so why are distributed systems uh
interesting or you know what what what
are the main sort of use cases you know
for
distributed systems
and those are broadly speaking there are
basically
four main reasons one is to use connect
separated machines
you know you might have uh uh you know
we're in bo
all of us many of us as we uh just saw
in the introduction are
in different locations and we get you
know we're
connecting uh with our laptop
or our phone or our ipad you know to
some server that actually sits in a
completely different part of the world
um that's probably the most basic reason
why you care about uh distribute systems
because you know just one they have two
machines they're physically separated in
space and you want to connect to them
and once you can connect them you know
that has an additional benefit that
actually may allow sharing between
users so
you and i can actually connect to the
same computer then actually we can start
sharing data
and you know that enables all kinds of
you know collaborative
uh possibilities and you know whether it
is like file sharing
you know whether it is you know sharing
of screens you know what it's sharing uh
of a computing infrastructure you know
it's all enabled because we can connect
you know to physically separated
machines
so they're probably a very important
reason and there are a couple other
really
important reasons one is to another one
is to increase capacity
you know through parallelism
and you know the paper that we assigned
for today and what is the topic of the
first
lab the map produced paper there was a
good example of that
but the other example is you know for
example there are many many zoom
sessions going on at the same time
and you know zoom.com has to support it
all and that requires a lot of computers
to basically you know increase the
capacity so you can support all those
in parallel zoom sessions
another important reason is to tolerate
faults so for example
uh you know because you know the
computers might be physically uh
separated
you know one part can go down and that
hopefully won't affect another part of
the
uh another part of the surface so that
you know reserves can always be
delivered you know so you can get high
availability
and we'll see that as a major theme you
know for this class
and then the final one is going to sort
of be uh
you know also sort of takes advantage of
this in a physical separation
uh which is going to achieve security
for example if you have uh
if you have a very sensitive uh service
like whether
the service that manages your password
for your you know customers you know or
for login
uh to your service uh you know you would
like to uh
really uh guard that one you know
machine and not share it with anybody
else or not share any other application
run any applications on it
so you have a very narrow interface you
know to that machine
and it allows you hopefully you know to
get better security because you just
have to protect that one small interface
and so by putting things on separate
computers and
isolate them uh you know you might
actually be able to it's a good stepping
stone to get security
these are major reasons uh
the main four reasons i think why one
wants to uh
why distribute systems are popular um i
want to talk a little bit about you know
giving a little bit of a historical
context
you know for uh distributed systems and
so where they
came from and what sort of happened over
there
over the decades actually
and you know sort of basically sort of
the stupid systems as we sort of now
look at them or the way we recognize
them probably started around
the same time that local area networks
happened
from here you know i think early 80s
uh and so for example you would have a
campus network like at mit
uh and connecting for example the
workstations like in athena clusters you
know to the athena servers like afs
uh and so that was sort of the sort of
the typical distributed system at that
point and afs also dates you know from
that you know period of time
uh of course the internet was there too
uh but there was really not sort of
large-scale
internet applications the way we you
know are using them now it's the main
the main sort of internet skills i typed
to see the systems you know was dns the
domain name system so
we still use and basically email
and so when i early in the early days
when i like started systems and i was
over basically the main examples
uh that we had to discuss
now things have changed quite
dramatically since the 1980s and the
importance of decision systems has just
tremendously increased uh and one you
know
significant point uh is was data centers
you know the rise of data centers
right that went along with basically the
big websites
and here you know we're talking sort of
the
roughly speaking in the 1990s or early
1990s
and so what happened basically is that
uh you know somewhere in the late 80s or
early 80s the
government or congress allowed
traffic on the internet and that
basically resulted in
boom uh where you know you start getting
big websites that were supporting large
large number of users
and you know the applications from those
times are like for example
uh you know web search you know
being able to search all the different
you know web pages that actually were on
the
on the world wide web uh you know
shopping
and uh and so these you know
applications you know gave rise to
two sort of things one huge data sets
you know sort of indexing
to support web search you have to index
all the web pages on the internet
uh so that means like you have together
crawl all the web pages then
computer reverse index and then you know
you could use that for your search
engine
and that was just a tremendous amount of
data that didn't fit on one computer
and the amount of computation to
actually do the first indexing you know
it was also too
much for the same computer as a result
you know you know so the data centers
came about
you know companies started to put lots
of lots of computers and data centers so
that it can support those kinds of
applications
so that's one a lot of data and the
second one is there's a lot a lot of
users
not uncommon for you know big upside
websites that have hundreds of millions
of users and that just requires a lot of
machines to actually
support all those users and so we see
a tremendous amount of innovation in uh
this period of time where
it's still continuing uh and some of the
papers that we read like the map
produced paper actually sort of
started from you know that period of
time
that whole thing sort of sort of
excelled that whole development
accelerated with
the emergence of cloud computing
another early you know whatever mid late
2000s uh and so here where we see a move
where
uh users our customers uh basically move
their computation and the data
to data centers you know run by other
people like amazon
you know google uh microsoft you know
you name it
and so a lot of the computation daily
computation that people
just used to run on their you know their
desktop or on the laptop just moves
inside of the cloud computing and like
an application change you know all that
instead of like running an application
on your local computer you run actually
the application inside of the cloud
and that means you know that these data
centers can have to grow further
and support uh this new set of
applications
and not only that you know the so the
customers that were outsourcing their
computing
to cloud computing also started to run
large websites themselves
and you know do gigantic computations
on the cells you know whether it's no
machine learning or large data sets
or any other kind of type of computation
and so
you see is that you know the users
themselves wanted to build large-scale
distributed systems and that means like
the cloud providers and they're starting
building a lot of infrastructure to
allow other people to scale up
you know their you know their systems
through you know large number of
machines
and achieve you know high parallelism
uh high performance and store lots of
data
um and so you know as a result you know
what the current state is basically that
you know
it's a very active area of research
as well as you know development
in fact these are so hard we're so
active that these are difficult you know
to sort of
keep uh uh keep up to date you know
there's a lot a lot of developments
and you know even in this class you know
we're going to spend
some full semester in distribute systems
you know we're going to only you know
be able to sort of look at you know a
number of small
uh fraction of like all the stuff all
the kind of different systems actually
that people are building in practice now
one thing that is cool for us uh you
know
as you know the teachers and students of
distributed systems is that uh
the people that built these data centers
uh early on um
even though they were building the
system for their own internal
infrastructure they published papers
about it
and uh we can read those papers and so
in fact you know
during the semester we'll read a number
of those you know papers that were built
by people
that you know really had large scale
distributed system challenges
uh and you know we can see how they were
solved and learned from them
uh this accelerated even more with cloud
computing where
you know in the early days of data
centers many of these services were
internal
uh for you know the you know you know
from microsoft or google or amazon or
yahoo or
for them themselves with the rise of
cloud computing you know
these services became public services
that were used by other people
and so suddenly there's even more sort
of systems infrastructure
uh that is well documented and usable
uh and so we can even you know we will
study some of those cases too
uh and so if you sort of look over these
sort of four decades you know there's a
tremendous rise
you know uh of the importance of
distributed computing as i said
earlier i did my you know doctoral
thesis in distributed systems actually
somewhere in the 1980s
and it was like a it was an important
field but not uh
didn't blow you away in terms of
significance and uh
and the practicality you know were sort
of limited to more of these local area
clusters
uh and now you know it's just like
completely booming
research field and development field
any questions a little about the
historical context for distributed
systems
okay let me talk a little bit about the
uh challenges
and uh many of them you're gonna
face head on in in the labs
so so why is it you know hard
and worth you know basically spending a
semester
uh learning about you know distributed
systems
uh and there's sort of two things that
drive
you know the complexity and why
distributions are hard one
is there are many uh concurrent
i parts these data warehouses you know
today the computer is going to run you
know ten thousand hundred thousands you
know computers in uh parallel and
sometimes you know all in the same job
like we see in the map produced paper
today which is like from the early
nineties
you know two thousand machines you know
trying to work on one single uh problem
um so there's a lot of concurrent you
know it's a lot of concurrent software a
lot of things happening concurrently and
you're very hard to reason that through
like what uh and
understand why you know things are
correct and this is compounded
by the fact that you know these two
systems must deal
with partial failure
so uh you know one of these machines
actually might go down
uh but that doesn't mean that the whole
competition stops in fact you know
the rest of the machines probably
hopefully can continue running and maybe
you know
take over from the responsibility of the
machine that failed
uh but this drives you know these two
things together
to basically drive complexity because it
becomes harder and harder to reason
about why you know the system actually
is working
and particularly partial failures make
things very complicated because one
system one part of the system might
think that another part of the system is
down
but it's not really the case you know
the only thing that might actually
happen is that there's a network
partition
and so both sides of the system you know
basically
are keep on computing uh and maybe
interact with you know clients
uh uh maybe even interact with the same
set of clients because the clients can
talk to do both parts but you know the
two and the halves cannot talk to each
other
and so this this is a problem known as
the split brain syndrome
um and that you know makes you know
designing and distributed systems and
protocol statistical systems that are
complicated as we'll see
and so there's really sort of deep uh
intellectual problems here
then the final sort of really aspect in
terms of challenges
it's actually tricky to realize
the performance benefits that in
principle are possible
with distributed systems
so so far i've actually been talking is
like you know you want to increase your
capacity or you want to run things more
in parallel you buy more machines
or you buy another data center and you
know
of course you know only when the task is
completely embarrassing parallel
uh does that work and often in practice
that's just not the case and so actually
achieving that sort of
high throughput and throughput scaling
with the number of machines
turns out to be uh not straightforward
at all
so that brings me to here's sort of the
next topic like why
you know it takes six eight to four at
least
you know
um you know so i think there's four
reasons
one it's interesting
and as i said like hard technical
problems and with very powerful
solutions
so heart problems
but powerful solutions we'll see you
know those solutions you know through
the term
second reason is they're used in the
real world
and there's an enormous amount of
appetite you know for people that
actually understand and can build
distributed systems
if you're a grad student or an undergrad
and thinking about research you know
it's a great area because it's a very
active area of research
there's still many open problems and
as we go through the semester you know
we'll encounter them
so it's a good area for research and
finally you know if you like building
things
uh it's sort of a unique style of
programming and so
uh in case of 824 you're going to get
hands-on experience with that
by building uh you know distributed app
and distributed systems in the labs
and you'll discover that
one is hard to get them right and you
know it sort of
builds up another skill type of skill of
programming that you might not have done
in the past
let me pause for a second here and see
if there are any questions
uh also feel free to post in the chat
i'll try to monitor chat if there are
questions there or
you know raise your hand if you have any
questions
uh and i'm sure the tas will also be
paying attention to the
racing hands and the chat so in case i
miss something
you know they'll remind me
any questions so far everything is
crystal clear
i'll interpret the silence as things are
so let me talk a little bit about the
course structure
after this sort of quick introduction to
distributed systems
so the core structure is as follows we
have lectures
like the one today and basically focuses
on big ideas
the lectures are typically driven by a
paper that we all sign
and these papers are often a case study
of a particular big idea that we're
covering in lecture
uh can we the papers are all published
or posted on the schedule page and uh
you know for most papers we ask you to
answer a question
as well as ask a question and we'll try
to you know cover those questions or
answers
uh during the lecture and so it's
important you know part of the reason we
do that is because we'd like you to
read the paper in advance of the lecture
so that we can go a little bit deeper
into these papers uh so uh i strongly
encourage you to uh
to read them before class
um the so another component of the class
is
the labs the programming labs um
there are four of them uh they're split
in parts
but the four four major ones one is the
mapreduce lab
that we just posted today and that's due
next friday
um and where you build basically your
own mapreduce mapreduce library
uh that's sort of similar to the one
that actually described in the paper
uh the second lab is a
lab that focuses on replication um in
the presence of failures
and partitioned networks and we're going
to implement
replication using a protocol
that's called raft
and this is a lab that consists of
multiple components but at the end of it
you know you'll have a library that you
can use to
what's called you know which is you can
use to build replicated state machines
namely
uh replicating uh a state machine
on multiple machines so that if one of
them goes down one of those machines
goes down that
the service actually keeps running and
you're going to use that library to
actually build a replicated
service and in fact you're going to
build a replicated
key value service
uh in lab free so lab3 is going to
basically use multiple machines
uh you know for fault tolerance or for
applications to build one surface
uh unfortunately you know as well a lot
more is that you know just replication
doesn't give you more performance you
know because uh
these machines actually have to perform
the operations in a particular order
uh and so uh to actually get performance
when we're
in lab 4 you can build you're going to
be able to shard it
key value servers
and that basically consists of many
instances of lab 3
for running currently and basically
taking care of a part or a chart of the
key value service
and so that you get parallelism and so
you can actually use this you know to
actually
drive throughput uh and furthermore
we're gonna actually move
you know keys or key value pairs you
know from one machine to another machine
in response to what load changes um
so the labs basically you know laughs
two three and four uh built on top of
each other
so if you have a bug in lab2 that might
affect you actually in lab four
we provide test cases for all of them so
all the test cases are public
and regrade you in those test cases so
you submit your solution we run the same
test on our computers and double check
you know that you're
passing uh the test and if you pass all
the tests you get full score
uh it turns out you know these are these
test cases are tricky
and will try to
tickle all kinds of corners in your
systems and so it turns out they are
actually reasonable uh hard to pass
and so uh and they're tricky to debug uh
you might actually have in a particular
corner case an error and it may be
very difficult to track down when does
that happen and why does it happen
so you know how to fix it and so my
advice for you is to like start the labs
early
uh it's often the case that you know you
just start the night or the two nights
before
uh you're gonna have difficulty uh
passing all the tests
uh because you're gonna get stuck you
know trying to debug one particular
aspect and won't run out of time to
basically
get the other test cases to work
the there's an optional project
so instead of doing lab four you can do
a project
uh and the idea of the project is that
you can work together or collaborate
with a group of
two or three students and do a project
here in your own and so the projects are
part of the forum you're similar type
systems that we read about in the papers
uh you propose one that you would like
to build uh
we'll give you some feedback uh and
or tell you well maybe you should just
do like do lab four
but if you're just excited about doing
project you know we certainly like to
stimulate that
and uh you know you should start
thinking now and then hopefully we can
have some discussion
and you know settle on something that
will be cool to do
uh okay finally the one other component
of the
course is actually two exams
uh one roughly halfway uh the semester
on one in uh finals week
and you know we expect your course you
know to do all the labs
uh submit the read write homework
questions for the papers and and do the
two exams uh if you look at the
web pages for six eight two eight or six
eight two four uh you'll see exactly
the balance in terms of grading for the
different components you know the labs
count for most
uh the two exams i think are 20 or 30
percent and then
some class participation but the details
are
on the web page to get you through the
semester
uh and help you along uh we have
excellent
uh course staff uh we have four tas uh
we're all running office hours and to
help you basically you know you have to
relapse
and let me do a quick round maybe the
tas can
introduce themselves so they at least
know who they are
lily you want to go first uh sure
so i'm lilly i am a third year grad
student in petaas and franz is actually
my advisor
so i know just how good he is at
teaching so you're in for a treat
um yeah i'm looking forward to working
with you this semester
i'll pass it off to david
hi everyone i'm david i am a second
semester i mentioned i took
624 last spring when it was like half in
person half remote
um so hopefully we can get the best of
both worlds for the semester i'm excited
oh yeah by jose hi i'm jose i'm a
fourth year graduate student working on
machine learning problems and
i took this class my first year as a
grad student and i
really really enjoyed it so yeah looking
forward
yeah i'm so i use datum pronouns i'm a
first-year masters student in pdos like
some of the others
and i took this class few years back i
had a great time taking it so i'm
excited to help
everyone learn it
okay thank you so there's a question in
the chat
how is the dcp systems how does the
system with the lab run
is the machine systems simulated yes
we're basically
uh simulating many many machines by
running many many different processes
in fact the labs have their own rpc
library
that like pretend you know you're
running on uh separated
physical machines but in fact you're
running many many processes on the same
machine
okay any questions so far before i
continue into the direction of actually
some technical content
uh is the the result of lab four
is it similar to any existing
um like programs that exist
yeah in fact you know what you would be
building has a lot of similarity to sort
of popular key value services
you know think reddit or you know some
of the other ones
um you know there will be differences
that we'll discover when we go through
this
semester uh but the key value is a
pretty well-known
and a common uh service inside of a
data center and run by many companies
and a couple of very popular ones that
used by lots of people
and they basically struggle with exactly
the same issues as you're going to be
struggling with in the labs
we're going to build a one that actually
has pretty strong semantics
uh sometimes a little bit strongest
medics and some people have to do some
practice
and you know we'll discuss why why that
happens too but yeah it's very close to
what
people do in practice raft is widely
used in practice for example
any other questions
yeah it's a good question about the labs
again if we
have a bug on um lab two
that maybe doesn't even get caught by
the testers somehow
um would do we get a uh
like answer for the following labs or do
we just continue to use our code
yeah no you're going to continue using
your code
we did our best you know to make the
labs the tests as you know as
good as possible and but i'm sure
they're cases that we you know that
it's hard to do a completely good job uh
uh
and uh but you know every time we
discover something that we missed you
know we basically improve the tests
uh so you'll be building you know once
you pass the test
you know we're optimistic that you
actually have an implementation that
actually can support the other
use cases that we're doing during the
rest of the semester
it's not uncommon for people to rewrite
rewrite their implantation once or twice
as you will see in lab two and lab three
you know the structure you know you have
to
spend quite a bit of time thinking about
the structure of your application or
your library
and you know as you sort of learn you
may want to go back and redo it
to help you along a little bit uh this
year we're doing something different
than we've done in the past years
i'm going to run a couple of q a
lectures where i'll share
we'll share our solutions uh with you or
we'll
walk through our solutions and hopefully
that will you know
tell you a little bit about you know you
can learn from that and see how that
contrasts with your own solution and
maybe you know
pick up some ideas for future labs
any other questions
okay again interrupt me at any time
i'd like to make this more and more
interactive
we'll take probably a couple lectures
but hopefully we'll get there
okay um i want to
talk a little bit you know sort of set
ourselves up for the case study from
today
but before doing that i want to talk a
little bit about a
bit of perspective for the class our
focus in the class is going to be on
infrastructure
and you more or less could tell that
from the labs that you know where
we just discussed uh so
you know there's going to be somebody is
writing applications uh on these
distributed systems and we're
not really concerned too much with the
applications at all uh we're
going to be mostly concerned with the
infrastructure that supports these
applications
and the infrastructure falls out in
three different categories or very
broadly speaking
storage infrastructure so like
devalue servers just file systems that
kind of thing
computation
you know some frameworks to actually
orchestrate or
build a distributed application uh and
an example
i guess the classic example is mapreduce
you know that we'll talk about in a
second
and then i guess the third category is
communication
and we'll spend less time on
communication uh there's almost more
topic of
you know 689 network systems uh but it
will show up
you know in the sense you know there's
gonna be some contract you know between
the network system and the distributed
system and and that will
uh be a serious topic you know for
example uh first day we're going to be
talking about
remote procedure call our pc
uh and that's like the building block in
which all labs
are built uh and that's sort of our
communication
model and the questions there are you
know what kind of semantics does
actually the rpc system provide you know
is it at most ones
exactly once at least once and we'll
talk about that in
on in first days lecture uh but that's
where where sort of
communication and distribute systems you
know intersect
um so if you look at these three so
basically storage you know to store data
for
uh durably uh you know computation to
run computations and communication to
actually have these different pieces
communicate with each other
and so those are the three basic you
know things that sort of
uh from which we built the stupid
systems and what were you looking for
are sort of abstractions that have been
proven to be very helpful
in building distributed systems
there's an abstraction like our like a
remote procedure call or like a
mapreduce library
or in a storage system like a key value
service
and often you know often our goal will
be to make the abstractions
distributed abstractions look very much
like you know the sort of normal
standard sequential abstractions
uh that you may familiar with so for
example when we build a storage system
we want our basically the stupid storage
system more or less behave
like you know a single machine
sequential
uh storage server like your regular file
system on your laptop
uh except you know that you know we hope
that the storage system is more
fault tolerant you know because they use
replication maybe much more high
performance because you use many many
machines
but like the behavior of the system that
we're looking for is sort of similar
with the abstraction we're looking for
is similar to a single one turns out in
practice this actually is very hard to
achieve
and you know we'll see that you know it
looks like it but it's not exactly
and this is a topic that will uh show up
multiple times
in fact you know that brings me to sort
of like the main
recurring themes in this class
that we're going to see over and over
and the main topics are fault tolerance
not surprising and that has sort of two
aspects uh that's usually to define a
little bit what fault tolerance means
one
is availability so we're going to be
looking at
techniques
we're going to be looking at techniques
to
make systems highly available and so
what we mean that is that they
they continue to deliver their service
despite you know there are being
failures
and so this is often expressed as like a
number of nights you know
0.999 reliability um
and so that's going to be one aspect of
fall tones the second aspect of the
photons that we care a lot about is
what i'm going to call recoverability
and when a machine crashes or fails
we like to uh bring it back into the
system once it
reboots you know so that we can keep up
the availability because we didn't like
repair the system
then basically all the machines would
die one by one until we have zero
machines and then we have no service
anymore so it's important that we
repair the distributed system the way we
repair the distribution system is
basically when the machine comes back up
you know we want to it needs to recover
its state and then you know start
participating back into the distributed
systems and it turns out
uh that is actually hard uh that's a
hard aspect
and the key techniques you know for
availability is going to be your
application
and the key technique that we're going
to use for uh
recoverability is basically you know
something called logging or transactions
uh writing things through durable
storage
so that you know when the power goes out
but the machine comes back up afterwards
you know we're i
have the data still there on disk
so that's the fault on site
the second part is you know something
what i'm going to call consistency
um this is basically the
contract you know that the server is
going to provide or for operations
with respect to concurrency and failure
and
uh so loosely speaking you know what we
uh
when we think about consistency
basically the ideal is the
the same behavior as that a single
machine
would deliver and so we have a
replicated fault tolerant high
performance file system consisting of
many machines
we like the behavior to be almost
identical to the sequential machine
and so the key question always here is
sort of the form
let's say we have a key value server you
know does the get
operation return
the value of the last put
and if you run a single machine and you
have nothing you know concurrent
operations so you run every operation
one by one
like you do put put then get that again
then again
then of course like you know this is
this question is trivial to answer
you would assume that the cap will
return the value stored by the last put
but once we have concurrency and with
failures and we have many machines
this is actually not so obvious uh you
know what the right what the right way
uh what
what the what a good contract is and
we'll see actually
uh many different contracts uh we see
ones that have strong consistency you
know they almost behave
like a sequential machine or ones that
have a very loose
guarantees
and provide very different semantics
for example they provide eventual
consistency eventually you will see
uh a get will return the result of a put
but not immediately and the reason
uh there are sort of different types of
consistency that's directly related with
performance
you know often one of the goals of the
civic system is to deliver high
performance you know scale for example
with the number of machines
um and you know to achieve that
performance
uh that's sort of almost in conflict
with you know consistency and fault
tolerance
uh you know to actually achieve uh
strong consistency requires
communication between the different
machines
which might actually reduce performance
similarly you know
to achieve all tolerance you know we
need to replicate data that means we
have to
communicate data from one machine to
another machine and if we ever have to
write that
data also to durable storage you know
that operation is expensive
and so the replication can cost the
performance
and so uh achieving these sort of free
things at the same time
uh it turns out to be extremely
difficult and in fact what people do in
practice
is they make different trade-offs you
know they will sacrifice some
consistency to get better performance or
maybe some fall tolerance to get better
performance
and so we'll see throughout the semester
a wide spectrum of different types of
designs
uh that you know make that trade-off
differently
just a small note of performance there's
two aspects to it like one is throughput
so you buy more machines hopefully the
throughput scales with the number of
machines
but there's another sort of part of
aspect performance that's basically
much harder to achieve which is like low
latency
and this is particularly important like
in these websites where you have
thousands of thousands of machines
and you know maybe one user request you
know when you click on a url
actually causes a lot of these machines
to participate
and if one of those machines is very
slow you know maybe it has
you know some mechanical issues or maybe
the disc is not working
100 or to some other aspect where it
doesn't really
really really work well that one slow
machine
can cause the whole user experience to
be slow
and this is often referred to as tail
latency
and there's a concern that will show up
over and over you know
throughout the semester has been
discussing different machines and
even shows up in the today's paper uh
the mapreduce paper
so one other final topic that will show
up a lot uh
at least in the class particularly in
the lab is implementation
aspects and here it's really like how to
manage you know concurrency
how to do remote procedure call
implementation
and just building the super systems by
themselves going to have actually
serious implementation challenges and
that will come over over and over and
over
now throughout the semester and partly
is because you know we want to achieve
performance consistency and fall
tolerance and depression
crisis crashes and concurrency which
just makes
just drive complexity
so those are the main topics any
questions
about this part
okay then uh let's sort of dive in and
look at the the first case study uh
through the mapreduce paper
and this is a illustration of many of
the topics
in the 6824 you know we're going to be
talking about fault tolerance we're
going to talk about
uh performance you know tail latency uh
all kinds of issues that
actually uh receive throughout the
semester and we'll see one cut
or one system that deals with that
so good illustration of many of the
topics
the paper is also very influential
although you know google internally
doesn't use you know map producers
described in this paper exactly you know
they have you know systems directly
derived you know from this mapreduce
system that they are still using
day-to-day uh there are other
uh libraries that look a lot like uh
mapreduce that are widely used uh
it also inspired different types of
computation models uh
then map reduce itself and we'll see you
want to do more
later in the semester so hugely
influential paper
uh and then finally it is actually the
topic of lab one
which is another good reason to talk
about it now many probably have
you have seen the map reduce paper uh
you know shows up in 6033
if you're an undergrad here at mit uh
otherwise you might have seen it in
other places
um yeah but you know we're going to go a
little bit deeper
uh than for example six or three because
you actually have to implement
your own mapreduce library and and as
always
when you implement something uh
problems that you know you might not
have really fought hard about
uh before you know certainly start
popping up and so you're by the end of
it you really understand
that produce
any questions
okay let me give you a little bit of
context you know for uh this paper so
this paper is written by you know two uh
engineers from
google very well known
and the context is sort of these early
data centers
so google has a search engine
needed to build uh the reverse index of
the world wide web you know to basically
allow users to query the internet and
these these kind of computations you
know take multi-hours to run
uh and they you know process terabytes
of data
holding our computations
a terabyte of data paired bytes of data
and so think web indexing web crawling
all of particularly web indexing
so it's one of the driving application
uh and you know as google
you know built these sort of uh
applications internally
uh you know like sanjay uh and jeff dean
you know the two offers
uh you know they were very good at that
kind of stuff uh but they discovered
that basically
there were many other google engineers
that you know wanted to write those kind
of
certain types of applications too they
wanted to be able to write their own
data analysis
over all the web pages that have been
crawled
uh and so uh and they realized you know
that writing these kinds of
applications was difficult uh because if
you're running multi-hour computation in
many many machines
it's very likely that one of those
machines will crash you know during that
computation
and therefore you know you have to build
in some plan for fall tolerance
and and you know once you start doing
that that basically requires that you
basically you know have taken something
like 6824
uh and able to build you know these
kinds of uh complicated systems
and their goal was to basically to get
out of that sort of
dilemma and make it basically easy
for non-experts
to write distributed applications um
and so that's the motivation for this
for this paper and why they're very
excited about it
and so the approach they take that that
produce takes us
is uh it is not a general purpose
library you know you can't like
right take any application and uh use
mapreduce to actually make it basically
fault tolerance
and so uh it has to be written in a
particular style namely using these map
functions
and reduced functions and those
functions are basically functional
or stateless uh and
but those are you know the programmer
writes the sequential
code
uh and then hence you know these two
functions you know the map and the
reduce function to sort of the framework
and then the framework the mapreduce
framework deals with all the
distributedness
so it will arrange that you know the
application or the binary for the
programs or run on many machines or
install the vending machines runs in
many machines it deals with load
balancing
it deals with certain machines that are
slow it will deal with the machines that
crash
and so the application writer itself who
wrote you know the map or reduce
function
don't really have to be concerned about
this at all and they basically get all
that stuff
uh if you will transparently uh and
again you know to make that happen
you know the library is actually not in
general purpose so for example if you
wanted to write a key value service you
couldn't use the mapreduce library
because it assumes a particular
computational model and you know your
application has to fit in that
and the computation model that you know
it fits is like you know something that
they saw a lot at google which is like
people wanted to do uh big data analysis
on basically you know all the web pages
in the world
and there are many types of computations
that just have to process lots and lots
of data
and compute values based on that data
so that's sort of the type of
applications that the mapreduce
targets any questions about the sort of
context
and the motivation for this paper
okay let me proceed
so let me first draw sort of an abstract
view of what's going on
and then we'll dive into more detail uh
so
um so the view that you sort of need to
have in uh in the background
uh to understand actually how mapreduce
works
which is going to be very important for
you uh when you're doing lab one is
there's a bunch of input files you know
whatever f1 f2
f3 let's say of course they're going to
be many many more in google's case you
know but
just for pedagogical reasons you know
we're gonna and the
site of the size of my display i'm gonna
just have three files and
uh basically ever for every file you
know is processed by this
map by map function so one written by
the programmer
and you know produces some output uh
some intermediate output
so for example the classic example to uh
discuss mapreduce is word count
it's basically counting how many times a
word occurs
in the data set where the data sets
consists of many many many files
so for example like you know we're
running the word count function
on file one and it will produce for
every word
uh and and a key value pair and the key
value of error consists of the key
which is the word and account one
and if a appeared multiple times in this
file f1 then you know it would be
multiple and records multiple key value
pairs a1
um and so maybe you know this file
contains none of many words you know
maybe it has you know a
one and b one so the file contains two
words
uh you know similarly you know the
function the map function for
uh does the same thing for the file f2
and we'll produce some key values and
let's say
maybe there's only the word v appears in
the file
once and maybe you know f3
the map function also runs into file f3
and
let's assume that's just where the
phrases assume that a
shows up once and you know the word c
shows up once
so basically you know these map
functions all run in parallel
completely independent of each other
there's like no communication between
them
on their input files so this is going to
give us you know ultimately high
throughput or you know anxious
scale to much much much much bigger data
sets and they're produced on these
intermediate
values uh these key value pairs like a1
b1
you know b1 alone or a1 and c2
and then so the second step you know
this is often referred to as the shovel
is that basically you know you're going
to run the reduce
functions on basically each row so here
we got
the row of all the a's and we're going
to run
a reduce function
and then the reduce function basically
takes you know the one key
aggregates all the or the reduced
function gets its input the key plus the
aggregated values or
not the aggregate development the
combined values you know from the
different outputs of maps so in this
case
uh the reduce function would get you
know two intermediate results you know
both
a with the key a and two values one and
one
and in this case in the case of a more
count you know we just add them up and
so
you know it would produce the value you
know key value pair a2
and we're doing basically we're doing
basically what we do is we're doing we
do we
run the reduce for every you know row
and so this will produce you know
whatever v2
and then similarly you know at the end
you know c1 for the last one
and again you know the once we've done
surf to shovel you know these reduced
functions can totally run independently
of each other you know they can just you
know
process you know whatever road data they
had uh
and uh be done with it and so the only
sort of really expensive you know
piece in this is is this shovel in the
middle
where uh the reduced functions
uh need to obtain
you know their inputs from basically
every mapper
so when all the mappers are done you
know the reduce function basically
gets you know uh needs to contact every
uh
mapper uh extract you know the
output for uh the output from the mapper
for that particular reduce function
and uh you know sort you know by key and
then you know basically run the reduce
function
and so basically we're sort of assuming
the the as the paper
points out the expense of operation is
really uh that shuffling of data between
the mappers and the reducers
any questions about this abstract
picture
sorry i had a question so um
is there i know that not all problems
can be expressed
with a in mapreduce stage um but is for
example
like sorting an array is is it possible
to
yeah sure yeah so sorting is one of the
applications that they uh
tout a lot actually in the paper and it
would be uh
something that's totally done with
mapreduce so basically you split the
input files correctly many things the
the mappers uh sort their piece
and then uh they split the output say
like r buckets
and then introduce functions you know
basically sorts that particular art
bucket
and that gives a total sorted file
and in this case you know in swords is
interesting because basically the input
the intermediate uh values and the
output are
uh the same size like in some other
functions like maybe the map function
will reduce
the intermediate state uh to something
much smaller than the input size
in the case of sort that is not the case
okay let's look at the paper actually
and get a little bit of sense actually
how you write them
now see if i can actually
that's just annoying
lost my menu let's hold it one second
okay it's not so cool give me a second
to ah here we go
safe good here we go let's
okay can everybody see this
okay there's a couple questions uh
let me postpone some of these questions
today because i will uh
see them in and we'll discuss them in a
second in more detail
if i uh don't answer your question here
please ask it again
so the first thing i want to do is
actually look at one of the examples in
the paper
of a map and a reduced function
corresponding to the word count example
that we just sort of abstractly
discussed
so here's the code for the mapping to
reduce function
you see that the map function takes a
key value
the key is really not that important
here it's the document name so
f1 or f2 and string the value is
basically the content of the file
so all the words that actually appear in
the file f1
and then basically it goes through you
know the disputed piece of code goes
through the words in the file and has an
intermediate value it
emits you know these uh a1 b1 c1 etc
like from the programmer point of view
correctly you don't really see these
intermediate
t value pairs at all uh you just write
this one simple
map function and then uh the reduce
function
uh is also more or less as expected you
know the
it takes two arguments you know the key
you're like a
and values in this case reward count
that would be one one one one
so the number of times that the word a
actually showed up in the intermediate
output
and basically what the function does it
just goes over the iterates over the
list of values and basically adds
one plus one plus one plus one and then
emits you know the final result
and so that's basically you know so you
can see from this code right like the
programmer basically almost writes you
know complete
straightforward uh sequential code now
this application is
you know very simple admittedly uh but
know the code
for even more complex application would
also be straight you know sequential
might be more code but it would be
straightforward sequential code
and in this code the program doesn't
really worry about the fact that at all
the machines might crash
you know there might be loading balance
that's just basically all taking care of
the mapreduce library
so and so you know the hope and i think
this has proven out to be true
is that this actually me but lots and
lots of people to write you know
distributed applications and process
gigantic data sets there like could no
way fit on a single machine
like for example the whole world wide
web
does that make sense in terms of
you know what the programmer actually
sees
okay let's talk a little bit about the
implementation
so i'm using the diagram here from the
paper uh
so the the uh so we got the user program
so the user program is like the map and
the reduce function that we just saw
uh you submit the map and the reduce
function to
uh the uh you link it with the mapreduce
library and then
forms a binary and then you give this to
the
google job scheduler and uh it will
basically
uh find a whole bunch of machines uh and
run
what they call workers there so like you
know
the scheduler will uh in the for example
in the evaluation as we'll see in a
second you know they're about like 1800
machines
uh on these 1800 machines you know the
schedule will run a worker process
that actually uh does the actual work
and invokes you know map and reduce
functions
uh when when when appropriate
there's one other uh process that is
important uh
in the paper called the master process
in the lab called the coordinator
and the coordinator baker orchestrates
the workers
and hands jobs or maps jocks
to them so like the terminology here
is that a complete application is one
job a map reduced job
and then a reduce an indication of
reduce or an inification of
map is what is called the task
and so you know basically you know the
coordinator
will assign files to
particular workers and the worker will
then invoke the map function on that
particular
file and that will produce some
intermediate results
now here are the intermediate results
and those intermediate results are
stored
on the local disk of the machine that
actually runs that particular map
function
and when you know a worker has run
completed a particular map function
basically tells the master i'm done with
that map function
uh and uh you know and it tells them
the mass of where the intermediate
results are um
then at some point when all the sort of
maps are basically done
you know the coordinator will start
running reduce functions
and the reduce functions will collect
you know the intermediate results you
know from the different mappers
from the locations that are specified in
the
sort of the result record um retrieve
that data
sorted by key and then basically reduce
run invoke the reduce function on every
key
and the list of values and that you know
produces an output file
and that is the you know there's going
to be one output file per reduce
function
and you know you can aggregate you know
there's output files or concatenate the
output files to get
the final output and that's sort of the
structure the input files live in a
global file system
that's called gfs although google uses a
different global file system now but you
know
the paper uses gfs and we'll actually
read about gfs
next week and the output files also go
into gfs
uh the intermediate files don't are not
stored in gfs that are stored on the
local machines
where the workers run
any questions about the sort of rough
sketch of the implementation
uh i have a question about the process
file for the remote read
so in the remote read process is the
file extra
actually transferred to the reducer yes
so the exactly the so the intermediate
results are produced or stored on the
disk of a
machine that runs the mapper or that map
function
and then the reduce goes out and
basically fetches
its you a set of keys from every mapper
and so that point you know the data is
transferred across the network
so the network communication that
happens is here
the reason that there's little network
communication no network communication
here at all
is because the workers uh the way the
coordinator assigns uh files to workers
is that basically
uh the worker is run on the same machine
so every machine runs both a worker
process and a gfs process
and the workers are basically assigned
to or the map functions run on the
machine that actually has that file
locally stored in gfs
and so basically this actually
corresponds to basically local reads you
know through gfs to a local disk
uh and then the files are produced
or mapped or produced into uh the
intermediate files are stored on local
disk too so there's no communication
happening in this
sort of this part of the picture and
then when the reduce functions run
they actually retrieve the files across
the network and then
write it out to gfs
and there's going to maybe some network
communication here when the workers
actually produce the files in the global
file system
i have another question um is the
is the coordinator responsible for
partitioning the data and putting it on
each uh worker
or no another machine no not really the
basically the the mapreduce one you run
the user program you're basically saying
like you know i want to run it on f1 f2
f3
f4 or whatever all the input files
and those input files live in gfs
and so the part of the job specification
you should say like which pro
input files need to be processed
okay
sorry how does the um
the sorting work that's
like who does the sorting and
the the mapreduce library uh does a
little bit of sorting you know before it
hands it off to the mapreduce
to the reduce function so for example
the intermediate results might have
like you know basically maybe all the
intermediate cells where keys a b and c
go to one worker and you know they're
there you know there's just a whole
bunch of uh
key value pairs like a1 you know b1
you know whatever a1 again uh
you know c1 whatever and basically what
the mapreduce library does it sorts it
first by key
so first all the a's together and then
all the b's together and then all the
c's together
and then basically concatenates all the
values for one single key and hands that
off to the reduced function
thank you
okay so uh i want to talk a little bit
about fault honors now
and sort of go back to
could i ask a question about the map
reduce paper real quick
fun so is the larger idea that
a lot of functional programming could be
reduced to the mapreduce
problem yes okay so
yeah okay sorry yeah in fact the name
hinzadak right because basically your
took you know the notion of the map and
reduced function is something very
common in functional programming
languages
and used widely in functional
programming languages or any sort of
functional programming style
and so the they basically you know
that's where the
inspiration came from
okay so actually there's a good second
with two fault tolerance
uh because the
the idea is that you know if an uh
worker fails then the coordinators are
in charge of noticing that the worker
fails and basically
restarts that task and so
the coordinator
reruns and reduce functions
of course the coordinate itself doesn't
really run them but basically the
coordinated decides you know that a
particular
map function needs to be run again
because it
appears to the coordinator that the
machine that it handed you know the
task to actually uh is not responding
and so the typical thing is like you
know if the machine doesn't respond to
some certain amount of time
the coordinator is going to assume that
machine crashed uh
and so uh and that and that means uh
that
uh uh when another worker becomes free
and you know is looking for a new
new task then we'll hand out the same
task that it actually handed out earlier
and hand it out again
and so that's sort of the basic plan for
fault tolerance is that
uh if the coordinator doesn't hear about
a particular uh
[Music]
worker reporting back that you know the
task is done it will re-run the task
again
so an interesting question is like can a
map function
can map run twice
and even complete twice
is it possible in this framework that
you know a particular
mapper will run twice i guess it
is because if the machine is down you
can't really tell
at which point so how many of the
map tasks that it executed
during the specific map reduce instance
were actually completed so you would
just have to we run all of them i guess
yeah yeah so mostly we just think about
this one task at a time but
uh so the machine like does one task
then
goes back to the coordinator asks for
the next task and that might be another
map task
uh and so when the coordinator doesn't
hear back it will say like okay i want
to ask another worker to
run that map test too but it could be
the case that there's a viewpoint
exactly out that the
first uh worker the first machine didn't
actually crash
i just happened to be a network petition
or like the word coordinator was not
able to communicate with the
machine but it actually is just running
happily and actually doing the map task
and it could produce you know an
intermediate set of results
uh so the same map function can actually
exactly run twice
and so it's actually one of the reasons
you know that map reducer functional
is because that's okay if it's a
functional program right if you run
the same program on the same input if
you run a functional program on the same
input it will produce exactly the same
output
so it doesn't really matter that it runs
twice you know one
in both cases will produce the second
exactly the same output
and so this is where you know this
functional aspect is actually really
important
it basically has to be functional or
deterministic
because you know every run of this map
function must produce the same output
because we're going to use one of them
and do the total you know in the total
computation
so similar can a reduced function run
twice
um yes i believe so yep yeah exactly for
the same reason right i mean if your
machine runs
the reduced function is no different
than a map desk there's really no from
the fault tolerance perspective there's
no really big difference between a map
desk and a reduced task
if you know the machine the running the
reduced desk uh
doesn't report back but happens to also
we're going to finish the job
another machine might run be running
exactly the same reduce function
and they will produce output now the
only sort of interesting aspect in
this is that you know both reduce
functions will write you know to an
intermediate we'll write the
final output file into gfs and if you're
you know paid attention to it you will
notice that what they what they do is
actually they first produce the file in
an intermediate file in the global file
system and then do an atomic rename
uh to name
move the file or rename the file into
its actually final name
uh and because again it's atomic you
know one of the two reduced functions
will win
but it doesn't really matter which one
wins because they're going to produce
exactly the same outcome because they're
functional
um so just to double check so uh if we
have a machine that's doing a map
task so a single machine can do like
multiple
math tasks so let's say that it's doing
like 10 map tasks
and it's in the seventh task and then
for some reason it fails
and then the master knows that this
machine failed so then the master will
order
for all of the seven map tasks that were
completed to be re-executed
uh distributedly maybe on different map
machines
except you know that's right uh although
i think in general it just goes
one map at the time so basically one
machine runs one map function or one
reduced function not multiple
okay awesome thank you um but after
a worker is done running the map task um
does it
immediately write its file somewhere
that's visible to other
machines or does it just keep that file
and its file system for the time being
it keeps a map function always produces
the results of the local disk
and so it sits in this local file system
right so then even if you were doing map
tasks one at a time
in the scenario where you did multiple
um and then the machine crashed you
would lose the intermediate work
right no it sits on the sits in the file
system so when the machine comes back up
you know maybe the the stuff is there oh
i see so the data is actually in store
durably
oh i see okay
and the map is the or the reduce
function directly talk to the map
functions the
machines that actually have the
intermediate results okay so
let me talk quickly about a couple other
failures
uh i noticed all the questions you're
asking are great questions right in fact
these all will show up when you're
actually implementing what mapreduce
you'll have to decide exactly how you're
gonna
do things so a couple other things can
the coordinator fail
i don't think so that's correct yeah
all right like you're the cat
excellent yeah the the the coordinator
can
not fail uh so basically when the
coordinate fails the whole job has to be
rerun uh you know in this particular
implementation they have no plan for
failures of the coordinator um and
that's what
making the fall according to more fault
tolerance is actually a little bit more
tricky correct because it actually has
state
uh state that gets modified you know
every time a map function completes or
reduced function completes
and so it actually turns out to be more
complicated and so basically
uh in this particular library the
coordinator cannot fail
and we'll see later in semester
techniques that we could use to make the
coordinator fall tolerant if we wanted
to but they decided not to do so
one reason they decided not to do so is
because like a single machine
uh they're hoping basically that the
single machine that just runs the
coordinator is unlikely to crash while
it's very
likely that one of the thousands of
machines that run some mapper will crash
okay how about slow workers
sort of another type of failure right
now we've discussed this issue of like
where machines might be slow because
like some other computation is running
on it like gfs is also running on the
same machine
maybe it actually is using a lot of the
cycles or bandwidth
or maybe there are like problems with
the hardware itself
is there anything special that they do
um i think i recall reading something
about uh
when the job is getting somewhat close
to finishing the coordinator will assign
the remaining tasks to additional
machines
just in case there are like machines
that are lagging
and then they will take the results that
finish first
yeah exactly so these slow workers are
called stragglers
and what they do is like they sort of do
backup
tasks so for example when they're close
to the uh indeed as you say when
you know the computation is almost done
to say like there's a handful of reduced
tasks left or a handful of nap task left
uh the coordinator actually just
basically runs a second instance
or maybe third instance of that task on
a separate machine
and it's called that's totally okay to
do so correct because you know it's
functional
and so it's not no problem we will run
the same computation
uh several times because it will reduce
exactly the same input same output
because it's given the same input
and the hope is that like one of these
other guys you know will
finish you know quickly and so therefore
then we
we're not the performer is not limited
by the slowest worker
but basically the fastest of the ones
that got replicated
and so this is like one of the issues
where like you know basically this is a
common idea
to deal with stragglers or to deal with
tail latency is to try to
basically replicate tasks and go for the
first that finishes
okay i think this is time to wrap up uh
so you can uh to
go to other other classes uh but these
are some of the major issues
uh that show up in the mapreduce library
and you know you will definitely be
struggling mostly you know
the hard part of actually implementing
the mapreduce library is actually doing
the fault hollands aspects
and but you should keep in mind as
you're doing that all the programmers
that are using your library or would use
your library don't have to worry about
all the distributedness
uh that they that you would have that
you have to deal with
so you're in the unfortunate situation
uh you're not the target of the
mapreduce paper you know
making your life of running mapreduce
applications easy you're in the
so that side of the equation here you
actually have to deal with the
distributedness and
become an expert okay
um i'm i'm going to hang around for a
little while so people want to go feel
free to go if you want to
ask a couple more questions you know
feel free to do so
and i'll see your first day