okay uh good afternoon
uh check double checking
people can hear me
yeah yeah thank you okay good
so good afternoon good evening good
morning good night wherever you are
uh so i'm going to talk today more about
draft
and we want to cover different uh topics
uh which are going to be relevant to uh
labs
so first of all i want to talk a little
bit more about log divergence
uh we sort of had a cliffhanger at the
end of last lecture
where we got in a discussion of figure
six i want to resume uh that discussion
i want to talk about log catch up and
what happens
if uh how do followers
catch up then a little bit of a
persistence like what state
must be uh
what stadium graphics must be persistent
in storage uh which has been really
really relevant for 2c and 2d
uh and also to talk about
livestream snapshots
yeah if there's any questions please
feel free to ask
and then finally i want to talk about
linearizability and correctness
criterium that uh comes up quite often
and
is in the paper used also in a bunch of
places
and this will allow us to talk a little
bit again about like how does a service
use raft
um so those are the topics on the plan
we will talk about
uh any questions right now please feel
free
and of course always jump in at any
point
okay so um so we saw last
week we started talking about draft you
know we saw that the leader had sort of
this job of replicating its log
onto the uh on two followers
and uh but you know due to crashes and
leader election
uh the state of the system you know the
logs can actually quite uh
can diverge quite quite a bit
and figure six is an illustration
you know why uh how that could happen
you know the
leaders can go down they may append some
more entries and so there's a whole
bunch of different scenarios
uh uh that our system can end up in
and so the figure 6 or the 57 actually
shows a bunch of those and the
and the main reason for that figure is
that
it actually sharpens up the leader
election rule
once the leader goes down and we need to
elect a new leader
uh there's actually some restrictions
that must be applied
to actually make sure that we can
converge on the right log in the end and
so first of all
one part of that is that any leader
needs to achieve a majority
and this is a part about the idea to
actually avoid
this brain split syndrome or split drain
syndrome
uh so that we can actually make sure
that you know in any
two subsequent elections there's going
to be at least one node
that participated in uh both uh
majorities because that can only which
two majors must overlap
and that node must have actually have
you know the operations from a recent
uh from the recent term the majority is
important
but turns out you know it's absolutely a
little bit more shuttle uh
you might think uh that like the longest
log that should be sufficient
because the longest log it has must have
most information so
we just picked that as the next leader
and then we're in good shape
and that turns out to be not the case uh
and uh and so uh and
the and the leader rules a little bit
more subtle you know it is majority
uh put plot plus at least as of date at
least
but up to date
so uh so if two uh you know the leading
election is running
uh a follower is like
the candidate is starting to run a
leader election approaches a bunch of
followers
and then the followers respond with a
positive vote
uh if the candidate actually is at least
as up to date as they are
and what that means is that the last log
entry uh
must actually have uh the same term
or in uh if you know they actually have
the same term
the longest one sort of wins
and so so that's the leader election
rule and you know we looked at the sort
of this problem last week
uh as part of the homework and like what
happens if you know
this note you know that was about to be
the leader actually is dead
um is gone you know and who could become
leaders
and you know we quickly discovered that
you know the there's a bunch of them
that cannot become leader
and but then there's potentially a
number of scenarios in which some
can become leaders and so in particular
you know we
identify that a can become leader uh c
can become leader
indeed you can become leader
um and so then uh and so this is
probably the most important part of this
whole discussion right like who can
become leader yeah
there's questions um is there let me
hold that
okay so who becomes that's the most
important part so there's a bunch of
different scenarios in which
a can become a leader there's a scenario
where c become a leader and a scenario
where d become become a leader
then the discussion folks a little bit
are like well at least there's one
particular scenario in which one of
these can becomes leader other you know
multiple scenarios in which they come to
the leader particularly this focus this
discussion focused on
uh a because
like one way that a can become a leader
is when
c and d are down
right because if c and d are down uh a
will talk to
b e and f uh form a majority
um with f4 uh it has the
most up-to-date log you notice that you
know
even though f is a longer log that
actually is not
uh the most up-to-date one and so oa
actually will succeed in becoming
the leader and then things proceed from
there
but there was an interesting question
that came up is are there other
scenarios in which a can become a leader
in particular
or is there scenario where like even if
c and d are up
or reachable or participate uh is it
possible that a becomes a leader
um so we see d and up and so the
question is does c and d
always vote for a if a is the candidate
and it turns out this answer is slightly
complicated
it is not completely straightforward so
if a
starts this election you know presumably
it will start the election in term
seven
and so even context is c and d uh you
know c
will be perfectly fine with that because
the uh
the a is at least up to date uh
and uh uh and so we'll
be able to achieve a majority but you
know it is possible correct the d
uh there's one additional rule that you
know if
um uh d actually has
if a follower or if if a follower has a
higher term as seen in higher term
its current term is higher than the
of the candidate then actually can it
can stop the election because
uh it will respond saying like hey my
term is higher
than your height my term my current
terms higher than your term
and so therefore you have to become a
follower so a will then we
change back from candidate to follower
and this can happen correctly in case of
d
this d might actually have seen term a
and we can't really tell from this
picture what actually the outcome is
going to be
but let's assume that for example uh you
know the
uh it has run uh
once uh uh and acts has increased its
turn to eight
it didn't become succeeded leader and
then its current term will e8
and so it will vote you know when a
actually asks to
for its vote you know d will say no i
won't vote for you
and furthermore my current term is a so
a will receive that message
it's higher than as7 and so a will
actually
uh step down and become just a follower
and at some point later presumably you
know d will run
its election timer will go off and
actually it will run
and so the short story of this you know
that the morale of this you know really
this picture is that
uh it's absolutely possible that ac and
tv can become leader
in different types of scenarios um and
that's probably the main thing to get
out of this
um professor yeah so
um i i just want to ask because i i
think i i'm not sure if i understood
correctly but
like you said a might be elected in term
seven
is it not true that it cannot for any
reason be elected in term seven
um even if d was down right because
people like like d
like already got a majority right in
seven
d got a majority in seven because it
actually was able to
uh get something done so presumably
right you're right you know the
good observation so it has to be the
case that you know there's a number of
people that actually already in turn
seven correct
yeah and the picture's just incomplete
you know we don't really know what the
current term is that people have seen so
far
yeah right well
yeah i mean the only thing is like i
think like
a majority of the servers already voted
for someone in term seven so they will
yeah so
presumably a will go to term eight uh
and you know we'll run you know the
election for term eight but you know for
the same reason d might already be in
nine
right and so it all depends on what the
uh current term is what these actually
these participants are in
but the main conclusion correct the main
top level conclusion is that
a can become leader certainly when c and
d are offline
uh c can become leader and d can could
become a leader
thanks
good okay um
then uh let's so so we now know that the
you know
the uh the raft can sort of end in
states where
uh the logs are diverged and so that
needs to be repaired and
like one key component of the wrap
protocol is to do
that like log ketchup as they call it
so i want to talk a little bit about
that
and this is basically what you sort of
uh have to deal with
in uh part b of the lab
and so i may be easy to illustrate this
uh with this
picture um and so let's uh it's gonna
make it a little bit simple
uh let's have three servers
and here's s1 uh it has you know
term three in index 10 is index 11
it has no entries in 10 and
11 12 13. here we have
s2
and s2 has entries you know 3 3
and 5. and so this is index
10 11 12 and 13
13 just to make it complete and here
is s4 or sorry s3
and let's assume we're in the scenario 3
4 and 10 11
12 and 13 and i'm not showing like the
indexes before 10 you know because
they're not going to be very relevant
and you know let's use the timeline
these different services
and just let's start out like assuming
that s2 becomes the leader
because it has the highest uh uh
it is mostly to date it has the highest
term number in the last log entry so it
becomes leader
and now we need sort of uh the the
understanding how about the protocol is
to synchronize
these particular logs and the way you
know this almost happens is sort of as a
side effect of you know either
the append entries because new log
entries are appended or because of
heartbeats which basically are pent
entries
with zero new entries so let's assume
that the
leader actually sends a heartbeat out in
fact it does it correct after after
reelection immediately sends out a
heartbeat
and so it will send out a heartbeat and
the heartbeat
you know basically has no log entries uh
but it also
indicates two other pieces of
information namely the previous term
so the previous term which in this case
is going to be five
right so and the previous index
is going to be 12. so
it sends it off to the leader s2 sends
it to s3 and s3 looks at this
and says like well let me look you know
my previous term is actually
a uh is uh is not a five
it's actually uh and so
it actually sends back in the message
saying no
uh you know i'm i'm alive in principle
but you know i i
you know i cannot do your repent so i'm
not up to date
and um so now s2 you know has some
information to actually bring it up to
date
and the way it works is to serve two
variables that are of importance
one for every uh note
s2 keeps a variable next index
and next index when it initializes when
it becomes leader
it is sort of an optimistic variable it
just assumes
that the logs are actually up to date
and so
uh when uh s2 becomes the leader
it actually just sets it to 13 you know
the same value that actually
it has for itself and that's perfectly
fine
uh because it's just a guess about what
actually the where
s3 might be and that's where you might
be behind and then you know
because there's no message uh the leader
actually learns that
and so in fact you know when it gets
there's no message uh
in the unoptimized version so i'm gonna
first talk about the unoptimized version
the leader just decrements uh the next
index by one and so
it decreases 13 to 12 and then you know
at some point we'll send another
you know entries and this time around
you know it will actually
say okay well next in this 12. you know
i've got to send you know login to e5
and you know the previous term is going
to be
3 and the previous index
is going to be 11.
and so when uh s3 actually receives this
message you know it checks the previous
term it's free the previous index is not
11. that all works out
it sees that it has to append five and
so it will erase
you know the four and stick a five in
there
and uh basically respond saying yep
good
and so at this point uh the uh
the leader knows that actually the log
is up to date because it's got an
okay message back so then there's the
second
variable that plays an important role in
all this
which is match index
which raft also maintains for when the
leader also maintains for every
uh follower and so there's a next index
you know for
s3 there's an x index for s1 and similar
there's a match index you know for
s1 s2 s3 2. and this one is sort of if
you can think about this is pessimistic
or a lower bound so when the leader
actually you know
uh becomes a leader it actually sets the
value just to zero
and to indicate that basically as far as
it knows uh
the s3 doesn't really have any log
entries at all
uh and so it hasn't delivered any log
entries to
uh the application and so for s2 also
has to be very careful about what
actually it can be delivered to the
application
because you know you need to know that
at least the majority
of the followers actually has a copy of
a particular log entry before it can
deliver it
uh and so it just starts out to be uh
pessimistic
uh but then once it learns you know that
for example
uh once it learns actually that the
uh follower is okay and we've
got an okay on the append message i can
actually update you know the
pessimistic uh lower bound or the match
index
you know from zero to actually 13
because it has learned that uh the
follower is actually up to date till 13
and that is the next index that is
expect
is you know 13. and at this point in
time you know basically it has learned
from two different
it knows that the that particular uh log
entry e5 is actually now replicated at
least in two nodes
and so you might think well good it has
been replicated in two nodes
we can deliver to the application
because the majority clearly has it
and we're in good shape and
unfortunately
that actually turns out not to be the
case it's close to true but not
completely true
and this actually has to do with figure
eight
so i want to talk a little bit about
figure eight and the real reason what's
going on here would
make this slightly complicated and you
also should think you know it's a little
bit fishy
so this leader s2 just erased a value
out of the log off
s3 and you know somebody put that in and
you know you know
erasing it you know it seems a little
bit uh you know
dangerous and as it was and
so there it turns out there is a corner
case uh
where uh you have to be a little bit
careful by when you deliver
when you declare a message actually
committed
and it turns out that basically um
yeah so figure eight illustrates that
so let me talk a little bit about this
erasing
log entries
and what we'll see is that the rule for
actually when the message can be
delivered you know to
the application is a uh is
slightly more subtle than just counting
uh
the replicas and so
let's see actually get figure eight i'm
gonna load it in
okay so here's figure eight um and so
it's your usual structure
okay let me get back to the question in
the uh uh
in the chat in a second so
here's a figure eight and so let's walk
through what the the scenario here is
correct in
figure a uh you know log entry one has
been committed
uh by everybody uh you know the
s1 or s2 became leader in
uh entry in term two uh they committed
uh or they started depending on entry
two um
hasn't been committed yet uh because
it's not a majority for sure
then in b what actually happened you
know s5 wasn't disconnected hasn't heard
of this term two
uh became a leader in turn three
appended an entry to
uh its uh log that certainly is not
committed because there's no majority
then we end up in uh c uh maybe uh the
s5 actually got disconnected again uh s1
uh becomes a leader uh in term four and
it starts replicating you know
entry this this log entry two two other
nodes
and uh and in fact you know it delivers
it you know
it gets back you know like it's like we
saw in the previous slide uh
it knows it's actually on s2 and it
knows it actually is an sv
and um and it turns out you know that
actually
you might think okay well you know as
one knows
you know that actually uh the free free
notes
actually have a copy of this particular
entry and so i might be able to deliver
it and it turns out that's just
not true and
there's a more subtle reasoning
that needs to happen to actually uh
commit and namely
you can only commit oops i'm sorry
you can commit
after the leader
has committed
one entry in its own turn
and if we think about this you know
number two uh
it actually isn't term the leaders in
term four and
and so the the the commit rule
uh wouldn't allow actually uh committing
two immediately uh
to the surface uh because that actually
is
one from a previous term and not from
the current term and so for example
your code to decide whether actually
something can be delivered on the
applied channel
needs to take to this account and the
reason you need to take the account is
illustrated by dne
uh where basically what can happen is
that
you know for um s1 actually you might uh
we might actually end up in a different
situation where
uh d actually becomes the
uh after um
d actually becomes the leader after
example as one of example is pretty
particularly
disconnected and it might actually start
uh
connecting it can form a majority and
actually it starts copying
its particular uh its entries to
actually
uh it erases you know the twos
and actually copies it's three in like
the entry for its term free
into uh whatever used to be two and this
is the erasing that you know we talked
about on the previous slide
and um and so we'll see actually that
even though the t
was on the majority of the nodes it was
on the majority of nodes that got erased
and so the rule and therefore the rules
as i stated here
uh because once this is illustrated by
e you know once actually uh s3 s1
commits an entry in its own term
uh and so it knows that every no there's
a majority in its own term
so at this point it can actually deliver
four you know through the application
and as a result of that you know any
nodes that were committed in previous
terms
can also be delivered you know to the
application
so we see here that this raising of log
entries the basic commits
makes the commit rule quite slightly
more complicated
and that's just the design decisions
that the designers of raft
uh made you know they could have done it
differently
uh they could have counted and made
basically two survive if they wanted to
but they decided to go for this
particular approach you know on the
ground so they think it's simpler
okay so this is a subtlety that will uh
show up
you know in the test cases for the labs
and so you have to
be a little bit careful with your commit
rule
and that you implement it correctly
okay so
so far you know if we go back to this
particular picture
the uh unoptimized version of this
protocol
um is uh a little bit of a bummer
right like uh if you think a little bit
about this
let's look at actually what happens with
uh
s one um so
let's say let me switch things so let's
say s2 tries to bring s1 up to date and
we'll do the same thing
you know send in the pen entries you
know with nil entries
uh past term you know previous term to
be five
and previous index to b12
it will say no right because
i actually use that index you know
previous index is actually a 10 with
term three
uh so it will uh this guy will
decrease its next index you know going
from 13
to 12. then we'll do the same thing
again
and we'll send uh i guess it's going to
extend
5. block entry 5 it will send the
previous term to be
free and index previous index to be 11.
it's going to get a no back you know
then the index goes to from 12 to 11
and now basically it's going to work and
so what we see here that basically for
every
log entry we're going to have a round
trip you know sort of one of these
append entries
and uh it turns out you know that can be
expensive
left with uh and the real question is
like you know can a follower be
be far far behind yeah and
let me ask that we're positive for a
second and so you can reflect and
think about that case is it possible
that a follower can be far
far behind for a given leader
um if a new machine joins the cluster
yeah i have a new machine
the new jumper cluster is a good example
any other cases
a machine crashed and is only coming
back online after several terms
yeah exactly you know maybe it comes
back after a date right
so it might be far far behind and so
that would mean like in
the vertical and the unoptimized version
that you're going to go back one by one
from the log entries
so that's a little bit expensive and so
the paper actually discusses an
optimization
uh so to catch up quickly
and uh and the the idea basically is
instead of
like uh backing off you know
as i said earlier the the next index is
basically an optimistic it's just a
guess right and
it doesn't really have to be that
accurate um and
and so the observation is that you know
we don't really have to go one by one
back you know
it's perfectly fine for example to go a
whole term back and then technical sort
of logical maybe not just the
you know the notes you know you know
it's a couple terms back and so we back
off a couple terms and then you know
we'll
scan from there so to illustrate a
little bit how that works
uh let me use the following example uh
and i'm just gonna to
two servers uh even though there might
be you know we need three to sort half a
majority but
let's assume there's a third one and it
just plays happily along
uh so here's s1 here's s2
and let's see you know we this guy has
five five five
and this is one two three four
five indexes uh and
you know let's say this s2 has four
it's basically all sixes so basically s1
is you know
quite you know behind correct because
the only place where they actually line
up
is in the first entry in first
which is term four and so in the
unoptimized scheme
we would back off like one by one one by
one until we finally got there
and to optimize this uh the
paper describes an optimization uh
unfortunately the optimization is not as
described in the same amount of detail
as a figure two and so in fact
you know you will in uh for 2c it
actually passed 2c
you do actually have to have uh this
optimization
a form of this optimization implemented
but your reasonable free actually how to
implement it because the paper actually
doesn't describe very precisely you know
which
how you should do it and you will have
to do a little bit of work but the basic
idea
is as follows and just instead of just
voting or just saying no
or yes as we on the previous slide the
uh rejection so if you say no
the rejection includes a little bit of
more information and that
and that information is going to help
the leader to basically back off quicker
uh and so it includes something what
they call
the conflicting term and the response in
the conflicting index
and the conflicting term is basically
the
uh you know if let me actually make this
a
little more clear let's say we have s1
the timeline
here's s2 uh so s2 sends a
you know a selected leader in seven
correct because it has the most
up-to-date
log it sends a message you know to s1
you know a heartbeat
and in the heartbeat it will say you
know the previous term
was six and the previous index
was uh five
and now when s1 gets this you know it
looks at this log and sees that actually
the previous term was five
and so instead of actually and so it
will include in response you know the
conflicting term like the term uh
yeah where it conflicts on in that index
and that was five
we're gonna final entry and then uh it
also includes what the first
index of that term is in this log so we
look at this
term like a 555 and the first time like
the index five showed up in log is that
it index two and so we'll
include that two and we'll send that
back you know to the
leader so here if f2 was our leader and
so we're going to send back
you know five comma two
that's the conflicting information and
the leader uses that information to
basically skip
backward further in fact you know it
skips back you know from so
initially its guess was next index
for s1 uh was six
and based on this information it
actually scales it back to
two so it turns it into two and then the
next append entries
uh is going to include everything from
two
so it's going to include you know five
five five
and previous term is four and previous
index is
one and now as one
can make one swallow false swoop
basically copy you know the new lock
entries over
you know the entries two three four five
and that's one's back up to date
so this basically you know reduces the
number of sort of heartbeats you know to
catch up a follower by one per term
instead of one per entry
any questions how do we make sure that
we like
don't you know overload the bandwidth
because imagine if you have like
a if you're trying to send back like all
of these log entries could that cause
problems in terms of like packets that
are too large
yeah so a great question because it sort
of indicates
an alternative scheme right that you
know back here
uh is that instead of actually making
this optimistic guess you know why make
a guess at all
just send everything you know the leader
could have sent like the it's whole log
and it would be perfectly fine and then
basically you know any of the followers
can
fish out than the ones they need right
uh and that would be an alternative
implementation and
presumably we don't like that
implementation because the log might be
large
and uh and that would be problematic
so i think you know the basic guess here
that's going on
is that uh in in the normal
typical situations the followers are you
know hopefully reasonably close together
and so backing off a couple entries is
actually sufficient
and if not then you know we might as
well back up one term
but not all terms and so we'll send the
log entries for one uh term and that
might be a lot
right that might be a lot and we'll see
in a second like how we get around that
right like snapshotting is going to help
you know reducing the number of log
entries that we have to send
so there was question do you need to
implement this sort of a version of this
optimization
scheme in lab 2c and the answer is yes
at least i believe i haven't been able
to pass the test without like
implementing some optimization
so i have a question so i in my code i
did the optimization by backing off to
like to the commit
so i made the uh the reply include the
last commit index and then i started
from there
um is that much worse you might
run into trouble and uh so the the the
tests keep track of how many bytes you
sent
and gives you a budget and if you're
like uh
go across that budget you know uh by too
much
then uh the tester will say like well
you're just sending too much
data yes
because in your scheme it might be the
case that i think you will send more
data than really necessary
whatever necessary means but
there is a question in chat yeah uh
did i say draw the wrong thing uh yeah
six six six six
sorry thank you
six six six i don't want the follower
overriding the leader's
log entries sorry about that good catch
any questions
okay
okay so the let me talk a little bit
about the persistence
uh we have one question in the chat
first okay um they're wondering
why the rejection has to send back the
rejected term number as well as the
index
um uh
well that depends very much how you
actually implement the
how what kind of state you maintain on
the leader
and how the leader decides to back off
um
do you need to know send some terms back
because you need to ignore i mean if
your response gets delayed for a long
period of time
uh you certainly should reject you know
uh information from terms that are
completely not relevant anymore
um i so this is a slightly vague answer
but
it's really very much dependent on
exactly how you implement it
okay persistence
and we talked about persistence a little
bit uh
uh in the last round of the first draft
lecture where
you know we noted that you know the
follower can only vote for one candidate
you know per term and therefore
it needs to remember it's uh who it
voted for and what actually the current
term is
um but there's sort of a larger issue
around persistence
uh and that came up in one of the
questions one of you just asked which is
uh you know what happens on reboot
and there's sort of two possible
strategies you can think of right like
one strategy is
strategy one is you know basically the
note
uh joins sort of freshly
so joins basically when a
node crashes and comes back up
it just doesn't participate anymore it
has to rejoin you know the
the raft cluster uh and that means you
know
when it rejoins you you should have to
replay
uh the log or it basically has to
receive every entry in the log
and then replay that
and of course you know like if a note uh
has been down for you know the note
crashes and is down for a day or two
days or
even if it just goes down for a second
uh but you know the system has been
up for a year that number mean like you
have to replay a lot of log entries
and so that's a little bit annoying and
so people prefer that
strategy two which is
you know you can back up and
you just basically participate again
so you catch up from you know you
basically you start from your
persistent state
um the idea being that like you know if
it's just a quick reboot
uh when you crash you come back up on
whether it was quick network failure
uh and so maybe you know the rest you
know moved one term along
uh you basically have all the state and
you know should be reasonably quick to
catch up so then the real question is
like what needs to be
what state needs to be persisted across
reboots
um you know we already talked about
voted for that needs to be
persisted
because you're not allowed you know to
vote for another
uh candidate in the same term
uh and but the rafting contains a little
bit more information
it also maintains the log on disk
or in persistent state and uh the
current term
and for each one we should have asked
ourselves the question um
you know why maintain a persistent state
because like it means that
whenever we update that state you know
whenever we append an entry to the log
or whenever we
increment the term or you know whenever
we
change for the word we actually have to
write to disk and or to stable storage
and stable storage is expensive
and so it's very likely that example
the the writing uh to stable storage
could be the
it could become a bottleneck so we're
already talking about voting force i'm
not going to cover ground but
let's talk about the walk you know why
does the log have to be written to
persistent storage
if we reintegrate
another way of correcting let's say we
don't write at these stable stores what
would break
yeah uh there's someone in the chat uh
uh she answered this question which is
you could lose the majority on the
committed right entries right
so here's the scenario uh we were
the draft replicated the
uh operation on a majority of the nodes
uh so somebody you know majority of you
know is actually uh
committed to actually uh delivering uh
we haven't delivered having accepted
that that log entry
so the leader uh sees the commitments
it uh delivers the message with their
operation on the applied channel to the
servers
the service obj executes the operation
and lets the client know the operation
has succeeded
so now you know basically we exposed the
fact that this actually operation
was actually uh replicated the majority
of nodes to the client
and so if we're not if the followers
that actually received that entry did
not put it on first
on disk uh and uh so that when they
reboot they still have it we could run
into the case and then
exactly that's the answer in the chat
that you know we lose the majority on a
committed entry and that entry will not
be delivered on the
remaining replicas uh to the surface and
so the client will see something strange
where
it sees that an operation that it did
actually happened or a little bit later
actually doesn't that operation hasn't
happened
and so it actually is important that
this actually is unstable storage and we
basically promised
the leader to commit it
and we cannot back out of that promise
okay any questions about this
why do we need to remember the current
term or on disk
does that need to be stored stably
um well the term um
you vote for a different person in every
term so if you don't keep track of what
term it is then you don't really
you don't actually know who you voted
for right yeah exactly you know
you know when you voted for it that's
one problem also current terms always
have to go up
right you cannot go down in term because
you're going to use that to detect
rpcs from state leaders and stale
candidates but this always has to go up
okay
any questions about persistence
which is more about the way you laid out
stuff
but you say these two strategies right
playing the log and uh starting from a
persistent state
and so the way you describe
starting from a persistent state um
do you like do you um
replay like like
i guess it doesn't say in the slide like
if you
does that assume you also have like the
the
snapshot of um of your state
i have not talked about snapshots at all
yet which we'll talk about in a second
that's actually the next topic okay but
the point is
okay the two strategies after uh a note
crashes
there's two ways to treat that node one
is a complete new node that never
existed in the system
ever and so when it comes up you know
you you
you add it to the cluster as if it's a
new node so basically the cluster goes
from
you know let's say you started with
seven nodes one guy crashes the cluster
has six nodes
it just happily proceeds you know
whatever the other nodes do the
replication
and all that kind of stuff and then the
seventh node actually
comes back up and so there's two ways of
you know
they enjoy you know one way is to say
like well i just forget everything i did
ever
i'll uh i'll join the cluster again and
the other six nodes will bring me up to
date
that will send the log to me and i'll
redo the operations
and that can be costly even with
snapshots
so the second strategy is to say well
you know if the same note 7 comes back
up again
it tries to reintegrate with its ex with
its persistent state that it has
uh in the you know and basically in the
hope that you know if for example it
went down for like you know a couple
nanoseconds a microsecond or a
millisecond
there's basically not much catching up
to do at all because it already has
all the state um
but it would like um
aside from the log there's also like a
state machine right that you've been
like
applying changes to so yeah let's
talk about that so there's i think
there's the next topic okay
um i think so
you know what about service recovery
sorry i actually have another question
on persistence
yep um when does the server decide to
persist
ah good great question uh you know what
do you think
i'm sure you thought about this
i mean i think uh a simple answer would
be every time one of these variables
changes
but that seems like a very costly
thing to do uh yeah i think that this is
the correct answer
uh whenever one of these variable
changes you actually uh flush it to
a disk or you write it to the in our
case correctly in the labs you know you
write the
to the persister module
okay and it does so for example when the
leader you know uh
accepts an entry you know through start
and appends it to its local
it's log it actually has to persist that
like that that entry
all right and so does the persisting
work incrementally
so it like once you get a new log entry
um you append
or just like take the entire state and
like rewrite it into the file yeah
but okay in real life you know repent
right and you would not rewrite the
whole log you would just repent that one
entry to the lock and that's actually
one of the reasons that logs are cool
uh because you know you can just sort of
append at the end uh
incrementally uh in our
lab you know the whole thing is fake the
persister actually doesn't really
persist
uh you know it keeps the object around
you know between
crashes because crashes are also sort of
fake you know the tester basically you
know
stops nodes and restarts them and
basically gives them the new state
but in the real system uh you would
depend
so the log would be a file and you would
append an entry to the file
thank you
yes you know we actually you all have to
uh in a real system you know if you
append a log entry your first pentalog
entering then you respond
like so in the append entries if you
update the log you have dependent
uh so if pen entries on the follower
that receives a new set of log entries
it appends them to
its local persistent log and then it can
respond because you you
it would be bad to respond before
appending because
then you might lose you know the if you
responded before pending you might run
in a situation where
uh just before actually the actual pen
happens your crashes
and so you actually did not persist the
log entries
and so you would you know you could lose
committed entries
okay okay so how about
service recovery right so the service
keeps his own
state uh like for example in library
you're implementing a key value store
and so the key value store maintains uh
basically a hash map from key
to value and you need to replay that
state
and again there are two possible ways
of going about it one strategy one is to
replay the log to actually reconstruct
that state
so basically if you're uh
this is sort of similar to the strategy
one on the previous slide you know you
just take the log
you just replay all the entries in the
log and that
should you know basically create exactly
the same state
uh as if uh
as of before right because you know the
whole point correct of this replicated
state machine approach is that uh
the all the operations are executed in
total order the operations have no side
effect
so if you start in the same state like
nothing and you replay all the
operations you should end up exactly in
the same state
as any other node and so that's one
possible
and so that is one way to recreate the
state
and you know obviously this is expensive
you know if you know the service
actually has been running you know for a
couple years
and you will have to replay the logs you
know from the beginning of time you know
that is not you know so
uh desirable and so you know clearly
people do
don't really follow strategy uh one i'm
gonna follow another strategy
and which is like basically making
periodic snapshots
and there are two reasons to do that one
to basically reconstruct you know the
service state in the fast manner
and the second reason to do that is to
be able to
compact the log you know even the the
raft state itself
uh can be cut off
or the front of it the prefix can be cut
off and the basic observation is that
if the application is running for a
while and it just has applied say the
first thousand operations or the first
million operations
um then the state that is constructed at
that point
uh the states will contain
all ops you know say through i
where i may be a thousand or a million
whatever you know whatever you
that's so uh and so one way to think
about
is is that there's sort of a duality
between
state replication and uh log replication
or replay
um the you can save the state after a
thousand operations and then you got
exactly the same thing as actually
reapplying or redoing every operation uh
from zero to the fast
and so this means that like once you
have a snapshot and you store the
snapshot stabling on disk
in persistent state you can cut off
you can delo you can cut the log
through i
and so this allows you to control the
size of the log
you know basically by uh periodically
asking the surface to actually take
snapshots and then you know the service
telling the raft library yes i've taken
a snapshot through i
then rath can say okay good i just don't
have to remember anything from i
or until i that means of course that the
snapshot has to be stored on stable
storage
and this is also good for recovery
correct and so it makes our recovery
scheme slightly more complicated than i
just described in the previous like you
know what it has to happen is that
uh when a follower you know comes back
up
after a quick you know say reboot uh it
loads its persistent state you know that
includes you know the persistent state
that we talked about on the previous
slide that's this information
uh but also it's last you know
snapshot installs that last you know
basically loads that snapshot into
memory the surface does
and then you know we can sort of replay
any log entries to basically bring the
follower up to date
okay
any questions about this um i had
i had one question i'm not sure if i'm
gonna be able to phrase it super clearly
um but i guess like i was under an
impression
so i guess like does this not break some
layer of abstraction
that previously existed between the the
application on top of raft
and raft itself where it now needs to
understand how to state machine
like how to apply commands to the state
machine instead of just like
giving commands to some external state
machine
yeah great observation uh
clearly you know there is some uh you
have to play together right the raft
library and the surface
uh because first of all if the service
lies about like you know gives us the
wrong information about like how far it
has applied then you know we
get inconsistent results but anyway so
we we don't assume wires anyway but
that's clearly the case
that the surface and the raft library
have to cooperate
and you can call it a an abstraction
violation
uh i think the reasoning to do it is to
limit the amount of state that the raft
library has to maintain
otherwise the raft line wouldn't know
when it can cut the log
and so there's basically no way around
it that the servers actually tells it
like wow
i got a snapshot through i and so it's
okay for you to
uh remove log entries from zero for i
and you'll see that and so uh this is
maybe a good point uh this this is going
to come up in 2d
right what lab2d is gonna is all about
snapshots and
lock uh compaction as it's also called
in the paper
um the there has to be some api
between the servers and raft to be able
to collaborate
and basically in 2a and 2b that
api are in fact even in 2c that api is
extremely simple
uh the only api that exists is basically
delivering log messaging on the apply
channel
right and almost nothing flows down from
the surface to the raft like
other than that the service may start uh
and a raft
uh you know tries to append an entry to
the log using rash start
uh and you know and so in 2d uh
there has to be a little bit more of a
an api between the service
and um draft library and it turns out
like
you can design that api in many possible
way there are quite a number of ways of
doing it
there's not particularly one and the
paper doesn't lay out what api you
should use
uh then the page actually says nothing
about this
and so it's up to you to uh something's
up to us you know to figure out what the
api is and
you know to be able to do 3d you know we
have to declare
an api between the servers and raft
and you know you'll see uh once you do
2d you know that that
uh that api you know has some funny
might be a little bit more uh different
than you might expect it and uh
and you know we had to pick one
particular api and
uh uh and in that api
there's an operation called you know
conditional install that
uh you know has uh semantics that you
know allows you to
change the wrath state in the service
state atomically in one single operation
uh and uh and and that partly you know
that operation exists
uh know to try to limit the
abstraction by releasing
okay and it turns out you can do it in
different ways you don't really need
uh you could have written it in
different ways but you know we you know
our personal thing is actually one of
the more simple ways of doing it
but that will become more clear in 2d
and you'll see indeed that there's sort
of a
interaction between the service and raft
in a way that they have to play along
how could you repeat when raft
communicates with the serves in the
snapshot process
so the snapshots are driven by the
surface
so the surface just says once in a while
to draft
i've made a snapshot here's my snapshot
and this is a snapshot includes all the
operations through i
and then raft you know writes the
snapshot
and truncates a blog you know to i and
writes all that information to
the to disk
uh and that's basically all what happens
sort of in sort of regular operation you
know periodically snapshots happen
snapshot happens
then there's the other case you will
have to consider is like when a reboot
happens
and so when the follower reboots it
actually uh
reboots uh from its persistent state and
so including its snapshot
and so when the follower reboots you
know basically loads you know the
snapshots
from a memory from a persistent disk and
actually reconstructs
the application state the key value
store and you will do this in lab three
so this is not going to be an issue in
lab two
the only thing that is going to be an
issue in lab2 is that
because the followers because the
uh because the
log has been cut right like you know
instead of like having all the entries
from zero to i in the log
plus more so i you know n uh the
log has been cut you know from i to n
right
and uh it doesn't look part of the log
compaction
that also means that if a follower is
far behind like for example a new node
joins the system
and doesn't actually have uh the
beginning of the log nor the
snapshot then the
raft has to communicate the snapshot you
know to that follower
so in the case that the follower is you
know before i
because there's a rejoined lab and they
rejoined the the
draft cluster uh the
leader actually has to send the snapshot
you know to uh
the follower and the follower basically
start from there
and that will show up in 2d and so
there's an additional
rpc called the snapshot rpc
or install snapshot rpc and that's
described in the paper
and that you will have to implement in
2d
in fact this brings me to a good point
actually let me first go to consumer
basically brings me to the homework
question
which is uh
here's the uh install snapshot rpc for
equivalent of figure
2 but then just for the snapchatocracy
and you actually have to implement that
um in in 2d and one
issue that came up in the which was the
homework question for today
is isn't every possible uh in raft
what avoids it if it's not possible that
the state machine rolls back
yeah so for example a leader sends maybe
you know
maybe an old snapshot shows up you know
at a follower
is it possible that you know
if it's possible if and that the
follower would install that snapshot and
then implicitly basically
roll back the state machine right maybe
it already has seen more information
uh you know clearly that seems not right
and so really the question is
you know how does rap get around it and
so maybe this is a great place to
actually uh do a quick breakout
and you can debate you know that you
know that
homework question for a couple minutes
five minutes and then
we'll come back and uh we'll talk about
uh a little bit more about snapshots
really would it be like no lily um
how about i try you can make it okay
yeah hold on i'll probably have to make
you uh
uh
host and then you can do it
okay you should be host now awesome
all right it should be should be okay
thank you susan thank you
you
and i'll go ahead and make you um make
you host again yeah that'd be great
thank you perfect
let me see i gotta share my screen
okay everybody back online
you're good to go i mean somebody can
respond but be great
okay great i hear that you know
sometimes uh
people because of the breakout rooms
here i just randomly dropped out of soon
unfortunately
past rooms breakouts but hopefully
uh i don't know exactly what to do about
that uh
i guess we're a class of fault tolerance
it's a little bit unfortunate that you
know people get just dropped
okay so uh any uh
i think there's the one more question
this time around was you know reasonable
sort of straightforward you know clearly
it has to be the case that you know you
cannot
uh install an old snapshot because you
know a
service that might have had a more
recent snapshot might have responded to
the client saying like yeah your
operation succeeded
uh and then if you would restore an old
snapshot then
uh you basically back out to the state
and the client would see there's
certainly an old version of the
server so that's certainly not legit
uh and so it is a little bit uh you
should definitely reject old snapshots
but you have to be a little bit careful
uh if you know the follower has a log
that goes beyond
the snapshot you have to keep that
remainder part of the log because
basically you have promised to a leader
that you have accepted a message and so
you can't delete
the the rest of the log that's not
covered
by the snapshot
okay
okay so then uh let me return
we had a question actually okay go ahead
so it says it says in the paper right if
if the follower receives a snapshot
that's a prefix of its log right yep
um the the log entries covered by the
snapshot
are deleted but the rest are kept yep in
that case
um it is it's a state machine
the state machine wouldn't be
overwritten right in this case
okay so the interesting question is like
how does the uh
snapshot get communicated to the
uh state machine and as you can see in
lab three that it goes over the applied
channel
and so the uh the state machine will get
the snapshot over the applied channel
and then it's up to it to do the right
thing
okay okay thanks
okay good just a follow-up on that sorry
yeah um
though i i was a little bit so that
makes sense to me the part that i was
confused by is
in the in the figure 13 like the box
that describes install snapshot rpc
yup uh on six
it says if existing log entry has the
same index as the term snapshot glass
include entry
um
hold on i might have just misread it
okay
why do you keep thinking about it then
what can you yeah if i have if i have a
question
i'll ask you yeah i'll take it offline
and we'll do it right after lecture if
you want to
okay i want to go back actually for for
a couple minutes you know that we have
remaining and talk about
actually using raft which is sort of a
discussion that we're already
basically having here uh for
a service okay so again i'm going to
focus on the replicated key value
service that's
going to be the topic of lab 3. and so
just to
go back to almost like one of the first
you know boards that i
drew at the beginning of the wrath
lectures uh here's like our
boxes you know that correspond to the
three replicas
and each replica correct you know has
sort of split
two pieces one is the surface part
and one is the raft library right then
we know that basically they communicate
these two
through the apply channel unless the way
the information flows from raft to the
surface
service
and so clients you know interact
you know with the service you know not
directly with raft so we have a client
here
you know that sends an operation like a
boot operator or a get operation to the
service
the service receives you know this
operation and it basically calls
start
you know for that operation quick then
raf does its chit chat
you know with you know the other graph
libraries
you know messages can flow back and at
some point the operation is committed
and then it actually is you know
raft will say okay this operation is uh
to ready to be committed
sends it on the apply channel and the
service then basically execute the
operation
and send the response back you know
after it executed the operation it
responds back to the client saying like
well
the value for the get you know key 20
you know is this
right so this is a get operation or put
and this is basically the value for the
get or you know okay
would succeed and we also discovered in
the last lecture that
uh it might be the case right that the
client you know sends an rpc
to uh the service and the you know the
rpc disappears
so the client must yeah most recent uh
and by the time it resends actually you
know the leader might not be the leader
anymore
and so in that case it has to sort of
redirect itself to another leader
and so basically what there is a little
bit of code the way to think about this
there's a little bit of code at the
client side that sort of understands
replicated state machines a little bit
uh and it maintains some information
it maintains like who's the leader and
who are the other followers
and so that can switch you know between
them if necessary
we also uh last time we talked a little
bit about that it's possible that you
know
operation can be duplicated right
because you know the
the the client may send an operation put
operation to the servers
and but you know the client doesn't get
a response
uh but the servers actually received it
so it went through you know went through
the
whole operation sequence uh you know
starting the rafter append kind of going
through the
graph motion and then basically sending
it out in the fly channel
and so basically the client actually
might you know send the second one
and you know the and basically for the
repetition
uh you know that might actually go
through you know the
graph library too it comes out in the
applied channel and so you know you have
to do some duplicate
detection you know multiple ways of
doing it but either way you have to do
duplicate detection
so in addition to uh sort of maintaining
some state about like what
uh the leader and the followers are uh
the put and get also actually have an id
uh an id associated with it and the
client needs to maintain what is the
last
id that it actually is trying to get
through and that is used to actually do
duplicate detection
and this little piece of code is often
called a clerk
you know the clerk that interacts you
know with the service and that does a
little bit of work you know to
collaborate with the server to actually
get the right thing done
and so we have multiple clients all have
uh you know a cleric library if you will
which is a go package and you know the
clients basically talk
putin gets you know over that interface
and inside of the clerk actually
maintains these ids
or maintains one idea for the
outstanding you know put and get
operation as well as some information
about like who's part of the cluster
okay does that all make sense
so that's sort of the basic structure
correct and like how raft fits into a
larger uh picture
the one question that comes out always
up uh is like what
you know what is the guarantees you know
that the servers
and the clerk together make uh to the
clients about these put and get
operations
so this really means you know what is
the correctness criteria
and the and the way we always have
described this so far we've been
reasonable sloppy about it
uh where i've been sloppy about it and
the main thing i've said is like well it
should behave
like a single machine
but even that is over a little bit of an
imprecise definition because what
happens is two clients basically at the
same time
you know execute a prude or get
operation and what what actually is the
correct outcome
of these operations so we really need to
sort of a little bit more preciser you
know i think like
behaving like a single machine is the
right intuition but we need a little bit
of preciser
uh definition and this definition you
know you saw the term
uh used in the paper this definition is
quite is called linearizability
and linearizability is basically a spec
you know specification of what
what values the put in a get operation
can return
particularly just in since put doesn't
really often return an operation is
really what get can actually return
and it basically says like what are
allowed things to be returned and what
are things that are not allowed
to be returned independently by actually
how you implement it it's just like
purely a specification
and it basically has three components to
linearize ability
linearizability says like if you have
look at some sequence of operations
and some of them executed concurrently
it has to be the case that there's a
total order
so you can arrange all the operations in
some total order
operations two
um it has to match real time
with that i mean that if an operation
completed
before a second operation started uh
even if those operations are different
machines it has to be the case that in
this total order
the first operation shows up before the
second operation
and that sort of makes sense right like
if it behaves like a single machine and
you start an operation
after another operation then the single
machine would always return the results
of the the first
operation so and then finally a read
operation
so this is like in our case in the key
value server it only has one read
operation name we get
but the read operation should always
return
the results
of the last right
so in our case you know we do a get
operation and
the put operation uh happened well
before
it uh and completed well before then
that get operation should observe the
last
uh should observe the last uh put
okay so this sort of uh uh
these are the three conditions you know
that whether determine
uh whether a system actually has
linearizability and
you can think about linearizability as
well well this behaves like a single
machine
so let me make it a little bit more
concrete because this is a little bit
abstract
and the way basically people
think about linearizability or like
argue that a system has realized a
little bit is
looking at particular histories or
executions and then see
and see if you can use histories if you
can turn that into a total order even
though the operations actually might
have actually
uh executed concurrently so let me give
you one example
a very trivial example uh so let's say
we have you know three clients c1
c2 c3 and they do a bunch of puts and
gets
so typically the way you know you
basically say there has to be some start
point where the operation started and
there's some end point where the
operation ends
so for example when actually the client
actually gets the
return from the surface and so let's say
this is right operation
you know do a value to the variable x
and we write one to it
so the client one started at some point
in operating right operation to the
variable x to write one
and it ends you know at some point here
you know maybe he did the second one
uh and writes two to it and then maybe
we have
all the action and with linearizability
is when operation happens
currently so some operation starts you
know before another one actually
finishes so for example
we might have the following operation
client two does a read operation
in our case would be a get and there's a
read
you know of x and the value returned by
this operation is two
and then we have a similar sort of
situation where our client three it
actually starts in operation the read
operation
and it reads x and it returns one
uh let me make this a little bit more
clean
the read operation uh actually returns
before
you know the write to operation starts
or ends
and same same from rh1 and then the
question that always comes up
is this a linear revisable history is
this linearizable execution
uh and if it's lunarizable then
basically it means like if this could
happen on a single machine too
so could this happen on a single machine
we can just like abstractly think about
it without actually having
you know is this a legit outcome for
basically what we need to look at is the
outcomes of r2 and
for c2 and rsc3 you know is this a
legit execution um i'm not
sure i don't really know what it means
for a right to
take uh like a long time um
well like you're about to take a long
time for that matter if you think about
the uh
from the client perspective send a
request to the service so that's the
starting of the right
and it got a return value uh at some
point from the servers and that's the
end of the write
and so in between all kinds of stuff
happens great it went actually into the
servers the servers you know put it into
draft rav ran we went to the applied
channel blah blah blah lots of stuff
happen
we don't really care about exactly what
the implementation does at some point it
got a response
and so you can think about this you know
there's basically free concurrent
clients you know they
issued concurrent operations and we were
wondering if this is actually a legit
outcome
i don't think this could happen on a
single machine because
the right uh for two it
finishes after the read starts
oh sorry yeah yeah that's right uh but
it seems like the ride should happen
before the read
and um in this situation it
it couldn't happen if the ride started
after
if there is if the right finish it after
the rise
restart it yeah yeah okay so one what we
need to think
one way to think about it is that we can
move
you know we have to construct a total
order right and we can construct a total
order where all the
you know the operations line up then you
know it's a valid linearizable history
and so so let's construct a total order
and then go back to this question that
you just asked
so a total order here's a total order
that i uh
i'm gonna so i'm gonna do first the
right operation
then the read x1 then the right
x2 and then
rx in the read of x2 right it's a total
order
all the operations are now happening
sequentially
and you know we usually need to check
whether it is our opera this total order
is correct
we're corresponding to the
linearizability definitions well it has
to be the case that operations that
start
uh if an operation starts after some
other operation ends it needs to be
after in the total order and so we're
going to look at this
let's look at this here this one must
start
after wx1 and that is true correcting
this total order
rx1 must you know start after
w x one because it actually returns you
know the value
right then exactly in our total order
that is also the case
rx2 you know must start at wx2 because
it observes the result
of this right and you know that's
perfectly fine too right
now we can basically one way to think
about it is that you know
even though they executed this way we
just rearrange things to sort of fit
uh the total order and so uh if we think
about this
then this is a total legit uh execution
where you know the operation format of
the order and so this is like what what
a single machine would do something
machine could execute the right double
xl on read x1
write x2 read x2 and real perfectly fine
okay so let me make me helpful to
think about the history that is not
linearizable
so let me look at the second one
uh and i'm gonna come back on this on
the first day anyway so
don't worry if this uh not makes sense
yet but here's another one
uh i got c1 uh
same thing right x1
i got a c and then here right
off x2 and
there's going to be a read that actually
goes
in x1
and up sorry 3x2
and then i got a c2 c3
and the c3 uh starts after
the the other read and returns one
and the claim here is that it's not
possible to construct a total order that
you know matches
a linearizability and uh
in one way you know one indication of
this is that this read
right that returned x1 started after
the reap that returned two and i will
make this a little bit more precise
later but in a
real you know single machine system that
could have never happened
right because uh that would have meant
that the value
changed between rx 2 and rx1
and you know with these few operations
that we
have on the board it has to be the case
that
this rx1 happened after that write
and this right must have happened after
the upright
uh because they're in total they're we
have to respect you know the ordering of
the single
of c1 and so there's no way to basically
slot
you know eric urge one in the total
order
you know according to this picture it
should go
after rx1 um
and but that can really not be true uh
because if it
got rx after rh1 that name is also after
wx2 so that must have read
two and not one so this is not a
linearizability
not a linearizable history in
execution
another way of saying that is that
basically what what is rxn returning
here is really returning a stale value
correct and that is not allowed um
if a machine behaves just like a single
machine or a replicated service behavior
like a single machine
and so i'm going to come back you know
this to on the lecture when
next week when we talk about zookeeper
because this is going to be a very
important like this notion of
linearizability sort of a thing that
shows up probably in the paper and this
notion of state of values also shows up
probably and since i'm running out of
time and there's gonna
i'll resume that next week
okay
any further questions and people who
need to leave please you know feel free
to leave
and in fact i hope you did i want to be
responsible for that you miss
other classes is this uh
considered like what type of consistency
is this considered to be like strong
consistency
this is considered to be a basically
strong consistency
and what it really is is sort of a
precise definition of what strong
consistency is
uh so like our intuition about what
strong consistency is namely behaving
like a single machine
the precise definition that people use
in the technical literature
is linearizability
um how did they decide to to have
that property like why did they decide
to have that property uh there's a
couple of things here one reason
you know uh the reason okay so it makes
sort of sense you know so if you think
from this point of view
like you want to behave you want to make
a replicated system behave like a single
machine
or unreplicated machine and you want to
only allow outcomes that actually
correspond to executions that the single
machine
could have done the next linearizability
is a very intuitive
definition for that the database world
has also some other
terminologies like serializability this
is also a term that will
show up in the uh term later uh and
basically the only difference between
sort of linearizability and uh
serializability is that serializability
doesn't require that
matches real time and so people have
sort of different definitions of
strong consistency if you will and the
one that we'll see
most probably is linearizability which
corresponds closest to like the machine
behaves
the replicated service behaves like a
single machine
thank you you're welcome
i have a question about um
what happens during like a network
partition
yeah so i know like so if a leader gets
partitioned completely on their own
they'll eventually climb out but if they
have sort of like
a few followers with them they'll stay
the leader
and they won't be able to commit
anything because they'll be in a
minority and they'll be a new leader and
they'll be
so um will that leader ever
sort of recognize that maybe it's a sale
leader
or do we just assume that eventually if
the partition goes away
um it'll figure out because like i'm
worried if there's a client that's
talking to the sale leader
what does that client do
the the the what okay so this is a great
question with this picture here
hopefully it will help
uh so the client will talk to talks with
this guy correct like who's the leader
you see the picture double check that
you can see it yeah i can see it thank
you okay
so let's say you know this first box is
the leader client talks to that leader
the leader can't commit any operations
correct
uh and so it won't communicate anything
on the apply channel and so it will
never respond to the client
right because there's like no operation
actually its operations are now being
executed
so the client will just retry and just
keep retrying forever
until until the client actually
maybe tries another uh you know
one of the other followers correctly
that maintains you know who else is
actually in the
group or uh until the network
um heals and then the leader actually
could commit an operation
ah gotcha wait so it doesn't doesn't the
leader immediately reply though saying i
got your request
or does it it waits until it's committed
in library it doesn't
uh communicate with the client until it
actually has processed the request
and which means that the operation
actually has run through graft and come
out of the applied channel and has to be
executed by the surface
okay
does that make sense yeah so then so
then the client could just implement a
timeout where they're like if it's
if it's a certain amount of time and
they haven't received the commit assume
that maybe i should try a different node
and then if it gets the new leader or a
follower of the new leader
it'll it'll be back to normal
this clerk that's exactly what this
clerk sort of does
you know sort of plays along with the
service to actually uh do what you just
said
got it okay thank you
you're welcome sorry can you repeat
again what the clerk does
the clerk is a little bit of like a stub
or like a
little library that the client links
with and so the client calls puts and
gets
and the clerk actually is the interface
that it talks to and the clerk can
keep some information like who's part of
the
uh raft cluster and so we're all the
leader who's the leader and who are the
followers at least what it thinks is the
leader and the followers
and uh when it sends in our rpc
you know to the service you know sends
it to the leader but it thinks it's the
current leader
and the service in the whatever things
the current leader the leader might
actually respond saying like hey i'm not
their leader you should send it
somewhere else
and then it will try one of the other
and updates its information
it also will tag every put and get
operation
that it receives from the client and
that sends the servers with the unique
id
so that the service can do duplicate
detection
and this all comes up in lab free so
you will see there in lab 2 there's no
real clerk
because the tester basically sort of
sits on top of the directly on the raft
interface and doesn't really interact
through the clerk but in lafrey we'll
interact through your clerk
so how did the clients generate unique
ids
uh i think they conflict with each other
uh random big random numbers
all right so we're just guessing and
hoping rather than actually guaranteeing
some sort of like incremental
uh one way to make it more guaranteed is
for example take your ip address
and append and random number
a question about the homework question
yeah
so i thought that it could go backwards
in time like i read the paper and it
said
on page 12. let me pull it up um it said
that the
if there's a conflict right then the
follower just discards this entire log
and it's also preceded by the snapshot
so i wonder why uh again let me
let me guess i i don't really know
exactly the sentence what you're
referring to and i have to look it up
again
oh it's on page 12. it's at the uh it's
towards the end of page 12 the second
column here so the second to last
paragraph
so the log can go back right but not the
state machine
not oh the log can't the law can go back
but not the state machine
oh is the state machine like what you
the committed entries right
the the yes the law can go back because
of income
uncommitted entries can go back this is
like this whole erasure stuff that we
talked about earlier
okay so actually the log can go back
yeah
not the state machine which is basically
what you
committed already yeah and the log can
never go it will never go back
we will never bail out and committed
operations correct it can only
bail out of erase uncommitted operations
yes that is right
okay got it and that's what worship can
i ask a question about the
third slide yeah that's the one right
before this one um
so could you just uh walk me through
real quick
uh what match index is doing on the
right like when s2 is communicating with
s3
okay so it starts out as uh zero
yep so the whole time s2 is
communicating with whom
that's three yeah so basically okay so
here
uh match index is zero right like so and
let me write it down as zero
yeah okay and then it gets a no back so
match index stays zero right
okay uh nothing there but now it gets an
okay back so what does that imply
that that you know what what did it send
it send an
uh heartbeat correct with four index 13
uh and uh included
so and the uh
s3 responded okay and so it means that
basically s3
is up to date through until 13 correct
that is next
index that it actually has that expects
for team
and so the s2 knows now that its log
matches until 13 after this message
is it until 13 or until 12. it matches
till 13. so the next thing that will be
sent will be go in
index routine so so the next index
and the match index are going to be 13.
yeah the next index is not used yet
correct means empty
so basically the the way you know they
you can do it either way correct you can
either say the last one or the you know
first
that's going to be or the the first next
you know
one and in this case they go by the
first next one
so in this case both of them are 13 for
the next fun yeah absolutely so
basically if you could think about this
at this stage right before like all the
green stuff has happened
the match index
for uh 3
is 13 and the match index for itself
got it awesome
thank you you're welcome
oh actually okay can i ask a follow-up
on that
so when it sees that something matches
so for example here on position uh
11 it saw that it matches then
is it it is a guarantee that everything
before that matches
two yes right because hold on double
double check you're talking about this
message
yeah yeah about like when it says okay
it checks
uh index 11. yeah yeah right because
that is the whole reason that this
previous term and previous index are
communicated correct to the
follower to make double check that it
can only respond to
okay if it is the case that uh
in the previous index 11 actually turn
free
and if that's true that means that
basically everything before that must
match
and this is like this whatever their uh
their whatever the
statement they call the this invariant
that
is we maintain that like if something
matches it like one index then
before that must match too
oh okay okay this is the ingredient okay
oh and i had another follow-up question
it was related to the question today
on the lecture question that i wrote i
asked about the copy on right
for any snapshots and i think i don't
really understand what is being
copied is it is it the page table
or is it something i think i think i
respond to your email and i'm
so okay the scenario is
um snapchats can be expensive because
the
snapshot might be large it's a gigabyte
you know
uh key values uh page table i'm sure
update but if it's a gigabyte you know
key value store
then you know you need to write that
gigabyte you know to disk
right and while you're writing it to
disk
if you don't do anything clever you
cannot process any other put and get
operations
that come in through the uh
the channels let me actually pop up this
uh
picture correct so basically search
decides some point to take a checkpoint
you know it's a gigabyte you have to
write a gigabyte to disk you know that's
expensive
so the plan you know the i think the
plan that the paper is hinting at
is that what the service does
it you know calls fork
so when it makes wants to make a
checkpoint calls fork
and forked case a copy of that process
right so now we have the operating
system
running and we have now basically two
processes uh that correspond to the
server you know to this application
correct so the server's raft
service raft and this is the copy
the child the operating system uses copy
and write
so when it made a copy of that second
process
it just copied the page table but didn't
copy physical memory
right so basically these two processes
share the same physical memory
which holds you know the our key value
store right
and so now the idea is that the child
when it starts running
it starts making a checkpoint or
snapshot
i can just write out you know the key
values for the
the key value store to disk
and in parallel you know the parent can
you start processing new
you know get input operations
because if it does a put operation and
it wants to modify the
it will write you know to uh the pages
that correspond to the
key value store that will result in a
page fault right and so the os will get
a page fault and so the ios will copy
that page
uh at that point and then you know the
first
repair process can just update it and
this is all transparent to the child
right because the child
you know had a consistent snapshot of
the whole address space at the point of
the fork
so this allows basically the parent and
the child to run concurrently
still make a consistent uh snapshot and
the
parent to actually make process new put
and get operations
is that more clear hopefully oh yeah
yeah okay i see so
the we copy and write the memory that
holds
the key value store
okay okay okay i see yeah this makes it
very clear thank you so much
any more questions
yeah i have i have um i guess this is
sort of
a weird scenario and i'm not sure if
this could actually
but what if so imagine that we're always
in the same term
and then you get to a point
where um some nodes have disconnected
but they're still the same term
the leader is still in the same term and
then then at some point they will um
they will do a snapshot and then all the
logs will be compressed
and then they keep going forward and now
the logs
are being populated again and then let's
just say
15 logs have been added and then after
they um compress them and then they're
at index they're index five again and
then the other nodes join back in
and they're also at index five of the
same term
is that a problem like how how does
it's almost like they're on a on a
snapshot epoch
of some sort okay so snapshots
correspond to an index
right so yeah so okay let's say uh just
drive the drive like maybe
drive your scenario so we got a server
that has some
log and you know maybe
i think you know you talked about 10 and
it took a snapshot at 10.
yeah yeah so let's let's tell you that
basically yeah
so basically the first nine operations
or maybe including 10
are in the snapshot
and then okay so there's another note
that
is same term
so all these entries have the same term
right like whatever
you know one one one one one one one one
right yep yep
and uh so this node actually but
this node has only through 10 right then
this guy has four 15.
let's say i think that's what you're
saying actually is a year or no ones but
here's a one
step well i think my um
my thought is well here's here's a
question i could answer when you take a
snapshot do you reset your index or do
you keep counting
you keep that oh okay i was imagining it
was like an array
and you saw your index goes backwards
so that if so that would be possible for
you to have two different entries in the
same term
with the same index yeah that's not
allowed absolutely
right exactly yeah okay i i see so
okay okay that that makes sense remember
reset the index
yeah when you cut you know like this
part of the log you know the index stays
at 10.
got it got it and so in fact you know
when you do this in 2d this is going to
be slightly annoying
now because you presumably take
advantage of the fact that the start of
the log is at
zero and what you're now going to get is
that the start of the layer of zero log
might be 10.
you will have to yeah you have to have
an offset of some sort yeah you
have to exactly you have to add that
offset everywhere
yeah oh and then and then last thing
really quickly the i think the reason i
was confused earlier
was in the in the code uh
for lab two yeah there's a comment that
says we're supposed to return
immediately
from start yeah yeah well you know oh uh
yes
meaning you okay so let me go back to
this picture here
and hopefully it's getting really
crowded
uh so do we get an operation correct and
we do the start operation we call start
oh return immediately doesn't
necessarily mean reply
is that yeah exactly yeah exactly it
just means reply back to your
return to the service not to decline
i see i see okay
gosh i yeah i guess operating under the
assumption that a return
always is necessarily a reply but that's
not
that's not always the case no it's not
the case i think this will become more
clear in lab free than
you know in lab two with just a laptop
yeah okay well thank you
uh this was really helpful oh you're
welcome happy i appreciate it
yeah have a good one yeah you do
bye good luck with the labs