good afternoon good evening good night
wherever you are
so today i want to talk about farm this
is a paper from
2015 so i want a little bit more of a
recent paper
and then it's really a research paper
and the topic of the research paper
is trying to explore some ideas and
technologies to get high performance
transactions
and with a high performance just to uh
make sure that we're on the uh
roughly what we're looking for uh high
performance from that means
they're getting 140 million
transactions per second uh on this you
know t80p
benchmark using 90 machines
and so uh you know whether this number
is impressive of course you know depends
on
the numbers you know and so anybody
remember like how many transactions per
second spanner could do
anybody
so if we remember in the paper there's a
certain uh interjection there you know
took about you know
depending on what you did you know 10 to
100 milliseconds so
you know 10 to 100 uh transactions
uh per second and so
uh the numeral transactions that farming
can do
is in a completely different order of
magnitude
and that partly is because they're
completely different systems uh
spanner tries to do synchronous geo
replication across the world
and farm actually everything runs in in
a single data center
and so the applications that have been
targeted by
farm and spanner are quite different
spenders targeting
applications that cannot tolerate
the crash of the data center like you
know the f1
ad serving database while spender is
much
very well far much much more targeting
sort of like you're
if you were using mysql or some other
sort of
database database system and you want
much more high performance
transactions then you know as far as
sort of a
possible design or a possible
alternative
they do provide a strict serializability
which is similar to the
external consistency that uh
spanner offered and so the whole goal is
to get high performance so there's a
number of ideas you know they're going
to
achieving high performance uh one they
shard
that's probably the main you know
standard technique that they use that
was going to give us
performance for example if you know
different
records are on different charts and the
transactions
touch the different charts then these uh
transactions can just run in
parallel and so um if you have 90
machines you know you get
90 times uh you know the performance of
a single machine
so sharding is sort of the starting
point but then there you go much further
so they use non-volatile
dram and this is to avoid you know the
bottleneck of having to write to
uh stable storage devices so in their
design you don't actually have to write
in the critical path to an ssd or a disk
uh and so they avoid the whole cost of
doing so and which can be quite
expensive and that's what for example
you think about your uh
implementations of raft you know they uh
they
they store or make data persistent uh
and typically you know making something
persistent on a stable storage device uh
you know in the order of
you know 100 milliseconds of
uh a few milliseconds you know to you
know tens of mills
to 10 milliseconds if you're actually
using magnetic disc
but an ssd you know sort of uh sort of a
millisecond
um and so given the time frame they
operate you know that we just do two
costly
so they use something what they call
non-volatile dram this we'll talk about
in a second
um then so that gets us rid of the
storage
uh access cost and so the next
you know two bottlenecks they address is
cpu bottlenecks
and network bottlenecks and for that
they use
a technique called kernel bypass
it basically avoids the operating system
for to talk to the network card
and then they use network cards that
have a special feature
called rdma
that allows the car to read and write
memory from a remote server without
actually having to interrupt
you know that remote server and so this
gives us really low latency uh network
access to your remote server
or to remote memory and this is where
partially where the name farm comes from
you know the r stands for remote
and for memory and the f is for fast
um so those are the the sort of the
technologies they use um and then you
know to be able to really exploit these
technologies uh this drives them to
a design that uses optimistic
concurrency controls or occ
uh the short version of this so
optimistic
um and in contrast to many of the
designs that we've seen so far where
they use what we're typically called
pessimistic currency control schemes and
pessimistics controls
the schemes basically acquire walks uh
on the uh the objects are being touched
by the transaction
and so when they get to the commit time
they
own all the locks of all the relevant
objects and just go ahead and
complement while with optimistic
concurrency control you don't actually
acquire
locks in particular in a farm you don't
require locks on the
read transactions and
uh when you then go commit you actually
have to validate that
you read you know the re you have read
the most recent objects
uh and if so you can commit and if
you're not you know you have to
board and you know maybe try again and
the reason they use optimism concurrence
control as we'll see in a second is
really driven by the fact that they want
to use
our dna um
okay so then the final comment i want to
make on this is sort of an overview this
is really a research prototype
so unlike uh spanner you know which is a
deployed
system that you know it's being in
active use
uh farm is really a product of the
research arm of microsoft
uh microsoft research trying to explore
new ideas you know to
see how to see if one can achieve higher
or really high performance transaction
systems and this is just a very active
research
people would just love to have the power
of transactions
and but also the the performance
okay so that's sort of a short
introduction any questions so far
okay let's uh talk a little bit about
the setup
for farm and so there's basically
90 machines
90 of these guys they're connected uh by
a high-speed
data center network uh and you'll see a
particular one
i'm just going to draw that as a single
line
of course it's a switch network
internally
and uh and basically charts
you know the data is sharded across uh
these uh different
uh machines and the the
level of sharding happens at the
something else called the region
so region is two
gigabyte
and you know those regions are sharded
across in different networks
and the different machines the regions
live in memory
so this is just drm
and not in for example on the disk and
so
basically uh the total data set
of your database actually has to fit in
the joint
drams of the machine that you're using
so if your data set is larger than your
current set of machines you have to buy
more machines to get more dram so they
can actually fit
and again the reason why you know they
want to use dram is because you know
they want no one really bottlenecked by
the performance of uh storage devices
and uh so of course you know machine can
fail
and if the machine fails it uses a loses
a drm
uh and so therefore they use replication
and so they
replicate regions across multiple
machines one machine is the
primary for a region and the same
machine
region might be replicated on another
machine which is then a backdrop so you
use primary backup for
uh uh for replication
and so this is region one you know
region two
you know the backup might be on the same
machine as the primary for
backup for region two and here you know
we have the private
region too and so this deals
you know so that one machine has a
kernel panic or some device and goes
that
or you know just crashes you know for
some other reason
then uh there's a second machine that
actually has a copy
of the data and just could proceed from
there of course
then we need some you know way of
keeping track of the mapping from
uh regions to uh
primaries and backups and so they use a
configuration
manager a cm that sits on the site
and she himself actually is coupled you
know with a system that we've seen
before
zookeeper and it's really the
zookeeper and the configuration
management that keep track
of the mapping
you know from region number
to the primary and whatever the backups
for every region okay
um now there's one
uh series problem of course here uh i
talked about like well primary
we have primary backup replication great
so we have false
then i know one mission can fail now the
machine can take over
uh because except you know the one sort
of tricky case that this scheme can't
handle
so far is when there's a correlated
failure for example there's a power
failure of the data center
and all machines now go down and to
handle that case
basically the dram uh has
sits on a ups where every machine sits
on an uninterruptible power supply
so we're going to draw this as like a
big battery that sits on the site
and uh the battery basically or the ups
you know provides enough energy
that uh if there's a global power
failure
uh the machine can keep running for a
little time and in that little time
uh the machine can actually store you
know the farm will actually store the
data on
on ssds or basically it just flushes you
know the content of its memory
all the regions all the transaction
state
all the logs for the transactions it
actually flushes it to an ssd so if
there's a complete power failure
of the whole data center the data center
at some point will come back
up and they can load you know the memory
contents of the machines from the ssd
and start basically running again and so
this is basically the only place
where the ssds are being used
to deal with a correlated failure of
many machines in the data center
any questions so far
okay now let me say a little bit about
the software
so in the regions so we have a region
here
in this region objects live
so you can just think about an array
region as an
array of bytes you know two gigabytes of
bikes and in you know the variation
bytes
objects live and objects have a unique
identifier
an oid and the oid of an object is
nothing else then
it's region number triple
the region number and then the address
you know within that
region
uh associated with every uh object
there's a little bit of metadata
for that particular object and the
particular
uh for the object header contains
a 64-bit number
and the number consists is basically
a version number
in the bottom 63 and then a lock bit as
we'll see
in the top uh bit in the high order bit
so every object has this uh you know 64
bit number i'm just going to refer to it
as a
version number and then we'll see in a
plays an important role
in the optimus frequent currency control
um the way applications
uh use you know this system
let me say a little bit about that so
what sort of the application programmer
interface
so the api is your starter transaction
then you read some objects
so they're going to read a call and the
read call takes an oid
as an argument uh
the application then the object can
manipulate you know change the field
in the in the object or whatever add one
to it
and then at some point right
the object
right there update the object itself
using the right call and then you know
commit it when you're using through tx
and commit
um you know it might also be the case
that uh
the transaction needs to abort or
because of the optimism currency control
and in that case
uh the application will typically just
retry the transaction um
and so in the transaction the way it
shows the transaction here there's only
one object manipulated
but the transaction could manipulate
many many objects those objects could
live in
uh different regions and uh
and so there you know they have to have
some plan as we'll see for running some
two-phase commit like
protocol uh to do atomic operations
across
uh objects living in different uh
regions
any sort of questions about the api
and the setup
uh sorry the address oid it is
the address in the machine itself
yeah which is the uh or the offset uh
within that region
okay because regions can move correct
you know
if they re-replicate it or the
configuration manager redesigns the
mapping
uh the actual address where the object
lift might change
uh so this is a region number plus an
offset
so if i'm a little bit better here i
should set off it
sorry i have another question kind of
that
um what was the design choice or design
thinking behind making a global address
space
uh did you have everything in
dram
i'm not sure that answers your question
but uh
the whole goal of them is to actually
run the transactions on an in-memory
database
you know sort of this is a whole trend
of set of databases where all the data
is always in memory it's called
in-memory databases
uh driven by the fact that you know dram
is reasonably cheap
and so that would allow you to basically
run transactions
without actually having to go to
persistent storage and
they're basically jumping on that uh
train of in-memory databases
i see and that requires like a global
address space that they all share
the address space is per machine right
uh the
uh every machine has its own address
page from zero to whatever
uh and the uh
the the objects are really the global
numbers for global names
thank you
okay good so let's uh talk so so far
uh i think you know we basically sort of
established that you know
they sort of gotten the stable storage
devices out of the way
and so there's no bottleneck for
reading writing storage devices because
they're basically not using them
other than in this one exceptional case
when the
power fails and so the next set of
things their focus on
is trying to reduce
cpu utilization or try to be very
efficient with the cpu and be very
efficient at the network
and the there's two uh key ideas here
that
are pretty well known so the first one
is kernel bypass
and the the story of that is reasonably
simple
so we have farm that runs as a user
level process
on top of windows the windows operating
system so here's the operating system
so let's move a little bit on the side
so here's the operating system
and the operating system of course has
you know all the features for scheduling
processes from a virtual memory
a standard operating system and it also
has drivers for hardware
devices and like one of the hardware
devices
is a network interface card
and you know typically you know the oss
driver
inside of it that uh
programs in the network interface card
so the reach and write registers on the
network interface card to basically send
like send a packet
or to reconfigure the network interface
card et cetera et cetera
and so the typical way you know that you
know applications interact
with the network cart is they make you
know system calls
you know to do the kernel and ask the
kernel to basically send a packet
uh and that you know involves you know
the operating system that follows the
tcp stack the network stack
uh and it tends to be you know quite
expensive
um and so they want to avoid this uh uh
this overhead you know go in entering
the kernel running tcp etc and the way
they do that is something there's a
technique called
a kernel bypass and if the network is
sort of a collaboration between the
network card
and the operating system and basically
what it does
uh is that the cues that the network
interface has so here's a set of queues
for example send queue and the receive
queue those queues are basically
directly
mapped or into the address space of the
application so the application can ask
you know
operating system please you know take
some uh
cues that the nick has and map them into
the address space of the application
and so you can just think about this as
huge as basically is directly accessible
uh from the user level application so
the user level application you know can
basically now read and write
you know commands or packets into the
network interface card
without actually having to involve the
operating system at all
and so this cuts the whole operating
system out of the picture and
improves you know performance
considerably
in the case of farm uh they also don't
want to use interrupts so
one way of delivering a packet correct
is the packet comes in the network
interface card delivers an interrupt
to the operating system the operating
system then alerts the application that
the packet has arrived and informally
try to avoid that cost and the way they
follow that cost is basically
they pull the receive queue
so there's basically an usual level
thread you know that
sits in the farm application and it
basically does nothing else than sort of
reading
uh the receive queue to see if actually
packet is available
and so that requires no immediate
vibration so that avoids the use of
interrupts uh and uh you know at the
cost of basically having a polling uh
threat uh that's you know sits there
doing nothing else and pulling
and environment turns out there are this
thread actually switches back and forth
between running some application code
and
pulling uh the nic so that's sort of
kernel bypass
and you know this is reasonable standard
some people may
some of you may know familiar with the
bbjk which is a data plane
development kit which is a development
kit to
basically leverage you know kernel
bypass so there's a reasonable standard
thing
and it's available on many operating
systems
um so then the next you know sort of
piece of technology that use
uh is a little bit also well known as
widely standardized
many network cards uh supported uh
or more high-end network cards supported
and that's
something that's called rdma
which stands for remote
remote direct memory access
and the basic idea is that uh you know
this requires
uh nics that actually understand uh rdma
and so you know here with cable here we
have
nick on the other side the operating
system may be sitting on top of it
you know we here we have farm
and then um and basically you know the
application on this site on the center
side you know can basically put
a particular packet into the send queue
um and you know send an rdma
packet so basically somewhere it is a
bit in
the header of the packet saying like hey
i'm an rdna packet
and then the nick will send it over to
the nick the destination deck
the destination x sees that this is a
special packet in rdma packet
and looks at the instruction that you
know goes along with the rdma package
and so the instruction might be
you know read a particular memory
location or write a particular manual
location
so here so for example let's say it's a
read operation
and the read operation essentially takes
an address
and it allows the nic to basically
read that address straight out of
memory out of ram so for example let's
say you know here
we have our region you know with objects
in it
and uh the
sending uh farm uh application can just
say
okay i want to read you know the the
this particular address you know which
makes it correspond to this
address with this object o and uh we'll
send
an rdma packet to the neck on the other
side
the next is that there's an rdma packet
and
you know basically reads you know from
memory the value is stored at that
particular location
and sends them straight back you know to
the
source and what is cool about this
technology
is that uh the nick can do this without
actually
interrupting or interfering with the
server at all
uh it doesn't have to generate an
interrupt it doesn't have to run any
code
on the uh the processors that run the
operating system in the application
instead you know the nikkei has firmware
uh that runs you know executes those
instructions
and loads you know the uh values stored
to those members
at the requested memory addresses you
know straight into a response packet and
essentially responds back it back
and then of course on the receiving side
you know that will show up in the
receive queue
and so far i'm you know at some point
you know we'll hold the receive queue
and see actually you know the result of
that
rdma
this this particular version that i've
been describing here
the paper refers to as one-sided
rdma
and that typically refers in the paper
to uh
uh read operations
um
yeah go ahead sorry professor can you uh
can you repeat
how how the polling of the um
like nick cues works on the on a client
or yeah on like there's almost
nothing to it uh the the
client uh just has a thread that reads a
particular memory location
and uh which indicates whether a packet
is arrived or not
and when the nic receives a packet it
sticks it in the
receive queue and as a side of set
setting in the receive queue you know
the
flag the bit you know turns into a one
and the application knows oh yeah you
know there's a packet there
um is it a specific thread that you know
that paul's all
like yeah and they're they're in their
system they have specific threads that
actually
are dedicated to pulling uh the cues
thanks sorry i'm not confused here so
does the knee cooperate with the system
or is it regularly doing the job
like as in any regular leg um
this is not a you know whatever your
standard nick right
there's a nick that supports both kernel
bypass and
uh remote direct reaction and rgma
uh and typically for nick to support uh
kernel bypass it means it has to have
multiple receive send queues
and it just gives a pair to send the
receive queues to an application
uh and it cannot like of course you know
you can't have
a send receive queue for every process
running on your machine
so typically there are like 16 of them
or 32 of them and you know get some of
them you know to a particular
os basically allows some applications to
own basically
uh a center receive queue
so much and that also means there's some
specific support for dma
and make that all work out so you know
so this requires a nick that is
reasonable sophisticated although it's
in a reasonable standard these days
okay so that's one-sided uh rdma they
also use
rdma to do writes and
to actually implement rpc and so
there's a they typically call this write
argument in the paper it's basically the
same thing
except you know the sender can put in
the rdma packet
uh saying like oh this is the right
operation and right you know the
the following bytes to a particular
address and
the paper uses two places or two things
where
rights are actually going to uh objects
are never really
written directly with rdma but there's
two other
data structures that are being written
with uh right rdmas
one is a log
and you'll see the role of the log later
and this is like related for the
transaction so it has commit records
locking records uh et cetera et cetera
and so if the source you know wants to
append a lock record
uh to this particular log you know it
can just do right
you know rdma and uh and then
the receiving nick will just you know
add you know the
new entry in the log you know to the uh
specified location
okay um and so that means like the
sender
and there's one of these cues and one of
these logs is per
uh send and receive a pair so that the
sender direction can manage
and know what the beginning and the end
of the log are
then in addition to that there's some
there are message cues
and also a one pers pair
and these are basically used to
implement rpcs
so if you want to do a remote procedure
call
the client the the sender
makes and write rdm rdma packet right
you know the data the message basically
into the
remote message queue there's a thread
sitting
on the destination site that is
basically pulling that message queue or
pulling all the message queues if it
sees a message you know it processes the
message
and can then send a response back using
a write rdma
uh and this turns out to be uh you know
cheaper you know
implementing root measure calls using
rdma that turns out to be cheaper than
basically
uh using sort of a standard rpc package
that you know uh since uh
just package using a regular nick but
without rdma
and has a thread on the other side you
know the response
okay um so is there any validation step
here to make sure that
you're you're only writing to a region
of memory that's like expressly allowed
for rdma you know it's like you don't
write applicate onto application memory
or something
yeah so there's all kinds of you know
this is sort of the high level idea
uh there's all kinds of details here um
so when
uh you sort of set up one of these rda
in order to do these one-sided rdmas or
write rdmas
you first have to do a connection setup
so there's a negation
negotiation step between the sender and
the receiver
uh to set up uh basically like it's
almost like a tcp channel except you
know rdma
doesn't use tcp but it sets up a
connection-oriented
reliable ordered
channel and
so the security checks and access
control checks are happening at the
point of the setup
so would you have to do that between
every pair of machines
yes so that would become really costly
to add
um like one machine to a large cluster
right
we have n square rdma connections
and otherwise you would have n-squared
tcp connections
not clear there's a major difference
there
um so ju so just to clarify so the
message and the logs basically they both
sit also in memory they just sit in
different places
than where the objects sit yeah exactly
so if you do
this is sort of here on the right it's
sort of a picture of the memory layout
of the
farm process you know there's an uh
region table or an object table well
there's regions
in the memory of the server
these regions have objects in them and
in addition to the regions there are
message queues
and there are logs see
and also for the nick to support the
direct access from
memory so since here we don't have any
software involved since then it can
directly access the
uh the memory without even
notifying the application or the os
shouldn't be some coordination on the
hardware
level uh or at least some support uh
also from the processor
uh to this uh feature
yeah so there's uh basically you know
the nick can read or write
uh uh read or write uh cache lines
uh atomically and so uh to support this
you know there is an
uh an interface you know to the memory
system
uh between the nic and that has to be
carefully set up you know between your
os and you know when the connection
setup is done
i say thank you
um sorry the right to rdma on
the right side that is in red what
happens there
so uh the sender the left machine
can do right rdma which basically sends
in right rdma packet
to the right side you know the the
destination
and the nick you know sees that this is
a right rdma
packet and will write the content that
came in over the network
to the address that's specified in the
right rdma
command
but that would be just and so there's a
reload so the remote machine can just
write the memory location
the set of addresses on the destination
machine without actually having the
server
you know being involved other than doing
setup of course
yeah thank you um
so quick question so the the
um the queue the queue in the
nic is only used for read rdma it's like
the right
writes directly to memory and the
receiver
yeah on the on the uh okay so they're on
the right rdma as you
maybe noticed in the paper there's there
can be an acknowledgement coming back
uh so if the sender you know sends uh
does the right rdma
it can wait from an acknowledgement from
the
receiving nic that actually indeed
performed the right rdma
okay thanks
and that will play an important role
any more questions about this part
so this is sort of a cool piece of
technology you know that has
come into existence pretty quite
widespread
uh in the last decade and basically they
want to leverage it
because it allows them to get very know
designing the
latency to actually do one of these
one-sided rdmas
is about five microseconds
so very low latency uh
much much much faster correct than for
example reading or writing a disk
uh and uh not much slower you know
slower than writing your own
our uh memory uh but you know pretty
fast because it allows you to do
uh if it's one microsecond you could do
a million packets per second
which is pretty impressive
okay so this so far basically standard
technology right
cutting edge but you know standard
so the
real challenge that this sort of paper
addresses um
is actually how to use you know rdma
you know both right rdma and one-sided
rdma
to actually doing transactions so the
challenge is this paper addresses
transactions using rdma
um and you know
to sort of see that this is a challenge
you know we sort of have to think a
little bit about all the
protocols that we've seen so far so
protocols for
you know for transactions
uh two-phase commit et cetera
all those programs and protocols have
required sort of service site
participation
and so for example uh you know what i
mean with that
is you know the uh a client sensor
request or the transaction coordinator
sends a request to one of the
participants
uh for example to require a walk on a
particular
object and you know just waits you know
on the
on the server or the receiver until the
lock actually becomes available
or you know runs you know the server run
some validation
step you know to see uh if the
transaction can be committed or not uh
and so
in all those cases basically uh if you
have some server-side precipitation that
means that you have to run
code on the server
and you know that is sort of counter to
what rdma gives you right your rda
actually uh doesn't
uh really provide you with the ability
to run code
on the server and so the the the the the
designers or the authors of this paper
have to come up with sort of protocols
that allow you to implement like
two-phase commits
and transactions in general to without
actually or
trying to reduce you know server-side
participation
so that they can at least do some part
of the operation using rdma
and you know some using remote procedure
calls as usual
traditional would do in a traditional uh
designs that we've seen in the last you
know a couple weeks
and so that's sort of the central
challenge uh
in uh in this paper uh and this
pushes them uh in this direction you
know
to solve that problem uh the high level
strategy that they use
is
the high level strategy uses optimistic
concurrency control
and and really really where
this shines for them is on the read
operations
because basically the basic plan is
we're going to read objects
that are part of the transaction without
you know acquiring locks
make an example require walks and that
would mean uh
interrupting maybe the server uh the
server has to do some work
and then you know maybe block the client
into the election the lock is available
and then uh return the object and you
know that is not really uh
suitable or messes up nicely with uh
or lines up nicely with rdma
and so they're going to go to an
optimistic scheme where
basically reading objects is not going
to require any locks at all you just can
fetch an object
uh and start using it and as we'll see
uh you know of course you need to have
some mechanism to discover whether
you're reading an old version a new
version
and this is where the version numbers
are going to play an important role
so when you read an object uh in forum
and you get the object back then you get
also the
version number back for that object and
then
the basic idea is that at the point of
commit
uh we're going to do a validation step
to check that the
objects being have that you regret at
the beginning of the transaction
or actually haven't been modified and so
during the validation chat instead
we're basically going to check for
conflict
and the conflict is basically if the
version number uh
has been incremented you know since you
know the
uh coordinator actually read the object
so the version numbers are different
are different then
the transaction is aborted
and if they're saying are still the same
that basically means that nobody
no other transaction actually modified
uh the transaction
the object and then you know we can
actually go ahead and commit
and of course in the case of abort you
know typically will happen is that the
client you know will maybe run run the
whole track
transaction again perhaps waiting for a
little while
before uh actually doing it for for some
random in a period of time
so that's the basic uh plan right so
this is just this optimistic scheme
so that reads can uh completely exploit
our dna and as we'll see in fact
regional and require any state changes
on
on the servers at all
and so this is basically sort of the you
know the basic idea behind you know
figure four
except you know as we'll see in a second
there's quite a bit of more
complications to it
and so this again sort of the i think i
used this phrasing a little while ago a
couple lectures ago
so the optimistic scheme in contrast to
the pessimistic scheme is
you're basically going to assume that
you're allowed to do the operation
and if it turns out you're not allowed
you sort of apologize and abort
uh in the pessimistic case you basically
first ask for approval to do the
operation by acquiring locks
and then you know you basically
guarantee that at commit time you can
actually commit
okay any questions about optimistic
concurrency control
at this high level
just the question about the version
numbers how do they ensure that
two different op that there's like
consistency across different objects
so that you're not reading one object
and then like later reading another
object but those
but a transaction modified some of those
in between
yeah well uh that's a great question uh
and so we'll
let's uh i think we're going to get out
of is we got to dive into
actually figure four and which i think
should be the core of this paper
so let's look at figure four
and
oops not that one
[Music]
all right you're figure four
i'm going to spend quite a bit of time
uh basically talking about figure four
yeah uh so the first you know thing
let's get it oriented
uh in this figure four uh you know we
see uh
so we have a a transaction coordinator
the c here and really the direction
coordinator is the
application and the application runs on
the same machines one of those 90
machines
but the way you're going to think about
it for the rest of this lecture is that
it runs it in a separate machine i don't
really care about it
that much okay and then uh
there are different charts in this case
there are three shards
you know one two and three and each
chart
is replicated twice once in the primary
and one's on the backup
um then you know we'll see that this is
the execution phase of the transaction
so the transaction has two phases
one is the execution phase and that's
the commit phase
uh and during the execution phase this
is like where the transaction just runs
so does it begin
uh does it read uh for example in this
case the three objects are being read
you know one that was located
whose primary is in uh one object that
is actually included in shard one
one object that's sitting chart three
and one object that sits in chart two
all right region two and uh
the we can see actually you know we look
a little bit ahead
uh we'll see that the for the two of
these objects are actually being
uh written and one of them is being read
now so the
object form number you know sharp three
this is just a read operation
these are right operations or these are
read operations but
those objects are going to be modified
so basically
as the transaction runs you know it
fetches objects from different machines
modifies them locally and then you know
in the commit phase
the changes are being applied and of
course you know the whole challenge here
is that in the end we want
to achieve straight serializability
um and in some ways
the protocol
for at least writes almost follows like
sort of very similar
two-phase commit protocols that we've
seen in the past you know there are
differences in the details
uh but the basic strategy is the same uh
and you know
we can sort of uh so let's assume that
now we're done with the execution phase
so we're
we're at the end of the transaction and
so the transaction is going to try to
commit
the transaction there could be two
outcomes you know there's actually you
successfully commits or it actually
aborts
uh anyway you're bored because like some
other transaction ran concurrently
and modifies one of the objects that we
either read or that we're trying to
write
um and so the first thing
the so the protocol the commit phase
basically has
five steps you know the locking step the
validation step
the commit backup steps the commit
primary and then the trunk and the
truncate basically runs
uh almost uh lazily and so it's not
particularly important
basically for our perspective basically
the point of interest of where things
are stopping
is here so that's sort of where the end
of the transaction uh
is okay so
um each of these objects as i said
before you know when you read them has a
version number so near the version
number
um and uh there i modify this is it
locally then at the point of this you
know when
when the so this is the commit point
where when the application calls and
transaction uh
the the protocol this whole commit phase
protocol kicks in
um and so the first thing it does uh is
what's called the locking step
step number one and the goal here in
this step is to basically acquire locks
on all the objects that are being
written
uh and so we can see you know based on
this diagram that
apparently two objects are uh being
written namely
um the you know this object correct
because the context is the primary of uh
shard one or region one
and then uh this object is being wrapped
uh that is actually located on
region two right and apparently the
third object that we read you know from
primary free
it's not being uh red because it doesn't
participate in the locking phase
so in the locking phase uh
the the arrows actually have all kinds
of different meanings
so these dashed arrows are
one-sided rdmas
so those objects are being we have rdmas
they're just fetched from the remote
uh memory location uh and brought
locally you know to the
into the memory of the uh the
application or the coordinator
um the uh
the solid ones are right rdmas
and uh
and in this particular case
they append on lock uh entry to the
to the the log of the primary so the
primary has a log
every primary has a lock so i'm just
going to draw it like this
and actually use a different color
so here we have the primary eye we have
a log
and basically uh the the
the coordinator now it's a commit record
oh no sorry sorry the lock record is
called
to uh the log i'm going to make it a big
record so i can
write down what's in it and in it is the
version number
of the time of the red and when the
object is read so that version number
that came out here
that goes back into the log record the
object
id that's being read and the new value
for the object
and so this record is just appended you
know to
the uh you know uh
primary one and primary twos uh log
using uh a right rd main and so there's
some threat
sitting on those machines that looks at
these logs and then actually does some
operations
so in this particular case if there's a
thread sitting on the
uh on p1 and p2 that you know
monitors or spins or pulls you know this
log
and sees there's a new log record and
then in this particular case what it
will do
it will try to get a lock on the object
you know that actually
is listed in the uh
in the transaction so somewhere there's
an object
and that object has some data in it and
it has this lock bit
and the version number in it
and so p1 you know has one object you
know that is being
uh modified by uh the coordinator
p2 has another object that is modified
by the coordinator
and basically the uh
the primary charge is required to walk
on the
uh on the object using a test and set
instruction
and so it will try to set the log bit
uh i'm using testing set instruction and
if the log bit was zero
uh uh before
and the log bit was zero and
successfully set the bit to one
uh then it knows that the uh
the army knows that it actually required
the lock and in that
case and we'll send them one rd main
message back
uh to append a message you know to the
coordinator's message queue
saying okay you successfully acquired
logs
for these particular objects if
the transaction uh if the the locker is
already taken
by another transaction and then at that
point in time the transaction
uh is aborted uh and so uh so when the
primary eye
you know tries to get the walk finds out
that the lock is already set
using this test and set instruction then
that lock
so the try lock will fail
and the
the primary will add a message to the
queue of the using right to the queue of
the coordinator
saying like i you know i could not
acquire the locks
and the coordinator in that case will
report the transactions
any questions so far
how are the are the locks obtained
through zookeeper
no these are uh there's there's other
set of locks using suit keeper that's
really for the configuration management
like the
uh the mapping of uh
uh region number two uh primary and uh
backups
these are just in-memory logs uh that
the
uh primary maintains so in the address
space
look a little bit back correct uh we
look back at this picture
uh there was a region has objects every
object has
some data and uh a header and in that
header there's basically
a 64-bit number uh that where the
top-level bit
is the lock bit and the 63 other bits
for
the version number uh what if the
primary
goes down does the backup have the same
locks of the primary
if the primary goes down the whole uh
what's going to happen is that there's a
whole reconfiguration protocol
uh happening in a new recovery protocol
the end result of that is that in this
case the
we hope that the injection would be
aborted correct because it never made it
to the end
uh we'll we'll get to photology in a
little while so let's
shoot for uh i'm gonna go talk about it
in a couple boards and i'll talk about
full tolerance
thank you
um so the version numbers are per object
right
sure per object yeah
exactly
okay good so um question
um why do they choose to abort the
transaction rather than blocking and
waiting for the lock to be released
uh because they have read uh old
material
they have not read the laser's material
uh value
and so the transaction has to board
oh i see because the lock means that
it's going to change
the next time well they asked for the
walks after really
written the object right so the
coordinator modifies the object based on
some version number
uh submits a bunch of writes uh assuming
that has read the latest version number
and so by the time uh the uh
the commit starts to happening and you
try to get the locks and you discover
that somebody else is blocked that means
somebody else already modifying it
and so that would violate serialization
right
so in fact at the point you get the lock
here that's sort of the serialization
point for right transactions
okay so this this point uh the
transaction has acquired all the logs
for all the
objects is modified so so nobody else
can actually
modify them at this particular point in
time and so that's sort of the
serialization point for the right part
of the transaction
make sense yes thank you
good okay so now uh you might have felt
like oh why not do the same thing for
reef
correct and you know get the lock for
the read objects uh
get the lock from the objects that are
read you know check the version numbers
and you're in good shape
and the reason that that is actually in
separate phase namely the validation
phase
uh is to basically avoid these expensive
bright rdmas right you
if you look at this vertical step you'll
see there's a writer dma
then the server actually has to run
something and it basically does
the acquiring the locks and then
responds with another write our dma so
here this this is a full rpc
that actually required server
participation and as we'll see in a
second
in the to handle the read and the
objects that have been read
uh the the firearm uses this validation
step and that validation step
just used one-sided rdmas and so there's
no real server involvement necessary
okay so uh
what happens on the so we're basically
at this point the you know
where we're here the transaction
coordinator actually has the
red blocks and now the only thing it
does is it validates the read logs or
basically the read version numbers
and so it uh for every object that is
read but not modified
so in our particular example that's only
one object correct this is the one that
actually is being read
the one at region three
uh so it sends it basically there's a
one-sided rdma
to read the version number that 64-bit
number
for the object that's being read and
when it gets it back
uh when it gets it back here it checks
two things
um if the lock is taken or so the lock
bit is set
that means that some core that is a
concurrent transaction is being
is trying to modify it so at that point
adjuster boards
uh and so the whole transaction aborts
again
if the first number is identical and
it's not locked
that means that no other transactions
are using at this particular point in
time
and the
the transaction can proceed basically
all the objects that are being read and
modified
have the version number at the start of
the transaction
and nothing has changed yet and so it is
okay for the transaction to commit this
is really you know the true
generalization point
and since you know the transactions
numbers are required at the beginning or
the version numbers are read at the
beginning of the transaction
uh the you know the transaction will
commit in the order of the version
numbers basically
and uh they also will get basically
strict
serializability because any transaction
that will start after your transaction
commits will have a higher version
number so therefore it also will commit
later
okay so this is the point basically
where
the transaction coordinator says uh you
know at this point
you know the uh we know that all the
we have the we have acquired the locks
we have verified validated the
version numbers for the read objects and
so this is basically the commit point
or the start of the commit point so at
this point the transaction is going to
say
okay i'm going to go i'm going to go
commit
and you know there's a multiple uh
messages necessary in the commit points
as we'll see in a second
and those are mostly for fault tolerance
reasons
um and so at this point namely
uh only the primary you know has been
the
only the primaries have been contacted
of the
uh of the objects that are being
modified but not the backgrounds
and of course you know we want to ensure
that uh and write you know
once a commit uh will survive uh
failures right the system is designed to
uh handle f plus one failures
in our particular designs there's uh
one backup and so it can only survive
one failure
and so what happens in this uh final
phase to commit backup phase
is actually we're gonna write to the
logs of the primary of the backups so
the backups have log so here's backup i
you know similarly there's a log entry
in it and
uh what we're going to do is
write what's called the commit backup
record
[Music]
and the kabit backward exactly has the
same information as the
uh locking record that we saw earlier so
in it
it's going to be the version number the
oid
and uh the new value
okay and this is you know like before
this is actually done using a right
rdma
now the backup doesn't really have to do
any operation
at this point like the server side of
the backup doesn't really have to run
anything
i just need uh and and so the
the here's this trick uh were the
basically the center weights on the
acknowledgement of the neck
and so this you know doesn't this is not
a one-sided
or a right rdma this is just a nick
acknowledging that it got the right rdma
and that the right rdma has been
performed
and so that basically acknowledges you
know when we get this particular point
in the protocol
the transaction coordinator knows the
object is in the log of all the
primaries and the objects in the
in the log of all the backups and so now
we're in a good position in terms of
fault tolerance correct because
um if any of one of the two fails then
the other one can actually apply the
right operation
then there's one more step
that needs to be performed and that is
the
commit primary and we'll talk about a
little bit later in more detail
but this is the final step where
there's one more log record written in
the primary namely a commit record
[Music]
and the commit record just assessed the
transaction id that actually is being
committed
and so like every i didn't write that
down in the other records but every
record has a transaction id so that we
know which transaction we're talking
about
and uh and again this uses the same sort
of strategy there's a
right rdma to append
to the uh to the log
and you know there's an acknowledgement
the nic acknowledges
the the right rdna and so but it doesn't
require
any interrupts or there's no the server
itself is not being
interfered with just the nic is involved
in these two operations
then as soon as the one of the
nics acknowledges the commit
record on one of the primaries at that
particular point in time
the transaction really truly committed
so this is the true commit point
the commit starts basically here and
this is actually the actual commit point
and at that particular point in time the
transaction coordinator informs the
application
yes your transaction has committed and
uh is done
then you know of course your point later
the logs need to be cleaned and
shortened up and truncated and all that
kind of stuff and this is like the
truncated
uh phase and that's basically piggly
back on later
walking faces and validation phases
and so i'm not really going to talk
about it at all but basically it is to
truncate the logs
so that they don't grow unbindedly
uh sorry but the hardware
acts they just go directly into
into the neck of the coordinator
yeah so let's go back to the rda picture
right
so if a right rdma happens uh
so you're gonna write rdma the sender
the coordinator was running here right
and here's maybe one of the primaries or
the backups and
so the right argument goes in you know
writes maybe an entry into the log
the nick does that the nick sends an
acknowledgement back
and the coordinator will see that
announcement in the received queue
and so as soon as the coordinator sees
the ack you know for
uh it's one right rdma
it can proceed and knows that the right
argument they succeeded
so does the right rdmas only write to
the log
they they're in two cases
uh they're both used for these message
queues and for the
uh the log append
um so when we say that that a right rdma
has been performed we mean that it has
been attended to the log
and not actually executed necessarily by
the application
that's correct that's correct so for
example you know to for example to do
the
for the backup to actually uh perform
the update to the object you know it
needs to read the log entry and then
apply the update
i see and also for the lock bit for
every object so since everything resides
in
memory and we have like 64 bits for the
version number plus the lock bit
so i'm assuming that it can fit in a
single memory address
but we can still have the problem of
let's say like the processor
fetching that memory address into the
register uh and then maybe if we have
like a multi-core
uh machine then another core fetching
that uh
like that same address and then both of
them flipping from zero to one
so uh so i'm assuming that there's some
support from the hardware there
yeah so like as i mentioned a little bit
earlier the primary when it acquires
so the primary is actually involved
correct in the primary on the
uh there's the coordinator sense so
in the lock step like this this step
correct step one
the primary or the coordinator sends an
uh
a right rdma to the
to the primaries asking the primaries to
lock
the object and
the primaries answer explicitly with a
message
that reply and so this crucial
step that happens is at the primary when
it actually tries to get the lock
and that lock uh is set you know the
reason this is a one single 64-bit
number
is so that you can use intestine set
instruction which is atomic
to set the walk so if two
uh so this is never the case like
there's only if two
tests and second structures run at
exactly at the same time one is going to
win the other is going to lose
i see thank you and that's a crucial
point
right i've started a question
about the blue commit point yeah um
wouldn't it so should i let me uh maybe
it's better to actually uh
open a new slide with the picture again
and just uh instead of scribbling even
more over this
let me let's get one more picture so we
can talk about other scenarios
a little bit bigger
okay uh so you're worried about
let me see yeah the commit point between
step
after step two but before step three
yeah so here
um here's the decision correct you're
right starting to commit and then
basically here's the actual complete
point
where okay um yeah i guess
i was trying to think about the scenario
where
wouldn't it be possible for a completely
separate concurrent transaction
that writes only p3 to get interleaved
to like start and complete in that space
and then wouldn't that no wouldn't be
problematic
yeah it would be problematic but it
can't correct because when it writes it
has to get the lock at some point
and when we get the lock we check the
version number and the lock bit
but does the read does the read the p3
affect the version number and lock it
no no it just gets the version number
but it's like okay let me
hold that question we're going to come
back at this and then we'll see
what actually happens all right sounds
good thanks
any other questions
this might be like a separate scenario
but what happens if um
uh you know after the execution phase
uh you know it tries to acquire a lock
and then crashes right after that and
the lock has been acquired but no one
else after that can acquire it
yeah okay so well first of all that
machine disappears from the earth
correct and the memory content is gone
too
and in the whole recovery protocol that
is described in the next section in the
paper
kicks in and that protocol in the end
will
abort that transaction
so it actually will get cleaned up
just another question uh so so here like
the coordinator
is the client right like it's the
application yeah well
yeah it is sure and so the client is
basically doing
all the steps of like log value that
commit yeah yeah yeah so
you can think about the application is
running on the same set of 90 machines
right and you know running this
transaction
which apparently you know writes two
objects in reach one
and runs the protocol and
so um i guess what's confusing is
so does the primary not communicate with
the backup directly
it's the no it's actually indeed the
primary does not directly communicate
with the backup nice
other than during the recovery protocol
there's all kinds of communication
happening but that's not shown here
so the coordinator just uses the
configuration from the zookeeper
yeah yeah yeah okay so going back to
this very first picture
uh and you know there's all kinds of
stuff you know related to this too that
i'm not talking about
uh like this precise membership and all
that kind of thing uh but basically the
suit keeper and the connection manager
really decide okay well this is this is
a configuration
the current configuration we're running
in these are the regions
how they're mapped and prime engine
backups and all that stuff
and in any failure it happens you know
there's a whole reconfiguration process
going on in recovery
okay maybe i'm going to skip the
breakout room
uh so i can uh go a little bit further
uh
the question you know i wanted to answer
the question uh in the
uh that was asking the post in the
lecture and i'm going to as a lecturer
question and
i'm just going to do that by talking
about an example a transaction and this
also comes to the earlier question about
uh you know what happens you know two
transactions run and read one version
and then it commits and all that all
this stuff so
uh so this is really the topic here is
going to do we get strict
serializability
and what i'm going to do is like i'm not
going to give you a proof you know never
getting straight around very ability
instead what i'm going to do is i'm
going to walk for one or two examples
uh to get build up some intuition and
hopefully that intuition you know sort
of convinces us you know that
things might actually be fine so let's
let's look at the following transaction
we have t10 begin and this transaction
is you know
like in the beginning it reads an object
adds one
and then write
the object and commits or
ends of course commit by fail
so that's the transaction and you know
we want to
ask ourselves like what are the legal
outcomes right what are the
outcomes that are correct
uh so what are the possible outcomes of
this injection
[Music]
what could be the state of let's say x
started at zero
and we're running two transactions you
know t1
and t2 what are the possible outcomes
that are
uh fine
um either one of them could commit or
both of them could commit
yeah and so we can have access to
correct we both commit
uh action one is a possibility one
commits and you want another award for
example they truly run concurrently or
something
and any other possible outcomes
yeah zero if you know basically both
aboard correct
maybe there's a crash okay so those are
the three legal outcomes
um and so that's you just have to make
sure that is the case so
let's say p1 runs and so it does a read
operation
it gets x back maybe at version zero
same thing
with t2 it reads you know uh
access zero and so it gets
basically to run through the concurrent
and you know this is the question i
think this sort of was asked or in the
last question we do
lock effects we do a lock effects and
um and here's sort of the crucial step
correct because at this particular point
uh
there are we're trying to get the locks
on object
zero and uh can both succeed
in reading x
oh and getting the lock um not at the
same time
no so one is gonna one is gonna succeed
correct
and so let's say the first one succeeds
and gets the walk
that means it can commit right so this
guy will commit
um and uh what happens with the second
guy
um the second one if it tries to obtain
the lock at the same time that the first
one is holding the lock it will abort
and stop
um if the first transaction goes through
all the way and the lock is released
then it will obtain the lock and then
check to see whether
the version that it has for x is still
correct
um and it will find that the version has
been changed and then it will abort
yep yep good this is exactly the the
true the two cases
so let me talk about the validation case
in this in a second with a slightly
different example to make it more
interesting
uh but this is the basically the outcome
correct
good and so even though these
transactions
mean this particular picture ran you
know exactly at the same time
uh they're actually getting ordered and
one wins and the other one loses
and that means that the other one that
lost can run again it will run then read
r
axis one and then hopefully succeed in
the retry
okay
okay so um
uh
okay let me do one example and then i'll
stop and i'll resume on uh
on on thursday uh let's see what time is
it 24. let me actually just stop here
and then i'll do a second example that
answers that earlier question uh on on
thursday
and uh also talk about fault tolerance
i don't want to run too much over time
uh anybody that has to go please feel
free to go uh
and i'll see you on thursday uh anyone
who has would like to ask
more questions you know please feel free
to stay and i'll try to try the best
to answer them as you see this is a
complicated paper
uh and i'm glad that we're going there
we're able to go in sort of depth we're
trying to really understand at least
the the protocol for normal operation
so like that i just like when i finish
this lecture and
if you see your first day or if you have
any questions please hang around
i had two like the high level questions
one was
um this this whole
hardware structure that you're using
would it be
useful at all if you're using it with
pessimistic and currency control
yes you know i'm sure you could make the
pessimistic foreign also better because
your rpcs are just cheaper correct but
the real thing
and i haven't gotten i haven't been able
to point this out yet but i was planning
to
what i can do now is if you look at the
read-only transactions here
so read-only transactions so you view a
transaction that basically only reads an
object or
multiple objects
what's the performance how good is that
like how well is that going to perform
um probably pretty well since you only
do the
one-sided yeah correctly if you look at
the object that is stored at
uh region three correct which is the
object that's being read
the only thing that happens is one-sided
reads
or one-sided maze correct
and there's no uh rights uh
nothing at all uh so uh those
uh because of the uh this
because the read operations don't
require logs there's nothing to be
written
the only thing that needs to happen is
this validation step which also is a
one-sided rdma
so read-only transaction can just run
with two one-sided rdnas
and and that's where the big one comes
from and
and the reason that that bitcoin is
there is because of the optimistic
currency control
so i think basically to exploit our dna
sort of two is foolish
fullest and i'm trying to make read-only
transactions really really fast
they got went to optimistic concurrency
control
okay i see i see it makes sense another
question was about
like security is this thing isn't going
to be secure if it's
um i guess the bro someone already asked
about this but
the part where the neck just reads
memory
it seems a little scary so yeah yeah
yeah it's totally scary
uh and so there there's there's some
bunch of interaction uh
between you know when the rdma
connection is set up
uh the operating system in the
application
so the operating system won't allow you
know the nic to write to any
arbitrary location it will tell it you
know here the address is
here's the vm virtual memory addresses
that you can write to
okay so you can make that product yes
exactly question about the
performance yep so if you have so
the reads are are quick because of the
one-sided rdmas
yep but if you have a lot of rights
happening like
a lot of data and contention um oh yeah
that's still the case
or no correct like what happens if you
have contention
actually we saw this in this particular
case correct
yeah if there's one
and we have a lot of potential one of
the transactions will abort
so this is really good for transactions
that don't contend
or not writing to the same records or
same objects
and even the reads right yeah even the
reads right because the version numbers
might change
so what's like the main um i guess use
case for
there's a lot of you know okay so
there's a lot of studies independent of
this paper about pessimistic versus
optimistic
currency control and you know clearly
from the two benchmarks that they use in
the paper like tpcc and tatp
there's not a lot of uh not a lot of
conflicts
so this is actually submitted maybe by
different users or different clients and
they basically touch different tables
so i have a question if there's multiple
clients
doing transactions on the same objects
um how so that they want to do a right
rdma right to
to to the log um
is it possible that there would be like
a conflict like you know like one of
them will write over the other log
or no no no no there's one lock per pair
uh okay so every this is exactly the
reason why
and and then uh but when the
transactions like time
is it like you know like to provide
serializability
is it timed um based on what
on the version number uh there's nothing
like true time or anything like that
here
just logical numbers like in the same
way as in lab trick right where you have
logical sequence numbers for
implementing your
key value store conversion numbers
basically play the same role
well if two number of two transactions
got the same
um number then only the one that got to
the commit
point first just going yeah okay
yeah this is this case right one will
abort the other one succeed
if there is a message queue that is
basically established between every pair
then how do you know uh so then you
would have like multiple
message queues given primary how do you
know which order to read those in
um so you don't read them out of order
uh
there is you read all the messages from
one source in the same order correct
because they're all going to be
in one cube so one source writes to one
queue
uh multiple uh machines
might write you know concurrently to uh
different cues
and you don't know what the order anyway
is so
it couldn't affect the uh correctness of
the protocol
i see so we don't rely on the orderings
of the
incoming concurrent messages that's
correct you know you pull them in some
order and then
you pull the cues in some order and
that's the way that the way that they're
going to
be processed got it
um i also have one more more specific
question
there's a part where a sentence in the
paper that it provides lock
block free reads which we've just talked
about um but it also says it all
uh also provides locality hints which
enable programmers to co-relate related
objects on the same set of machines
yeah and i do not understand that like
the latter or part of the sentence
uh okay so i i have to look up the
details what it is but i think what it's
referring to
is that if you like if your objects are
all kinds in different regions right
like
let's look at this picture here then you
would have to talk to lots of different
uh primaries right so like your object
one is in this primary
object two is at this primary uh and if
you were touching many of this
if you're touching always a cluster of
objects together it would be nice if
that cluster of objects is all at the
same primary
so you only have to contact one primary
instead of many
i see thank you
any further questions
so this so farm is like not really
suitable for
long transactions right um because
that's
because yeah yeah you're worried
the long transactions that you get
conflicts
i mean it also is assuming i guess
read-only transactions since we really
optimized for them right
yeah absolutely many transactions you
know
people have done studies and you know
and you saw it in spanner paper too
correct
where a large fraction of the
transactions are read-only transactions
but that's clearly a property of the
workload
um i had i think going back to my
earlier question i think
i realized i was misunderstanding
okay basic about strict serializability
yeah um
is it so uh strict so okay so here's
here's
the situation um say there's one
transaction that begins first
that writes um shard one shard two and
read shard three
and so that that begins like first in
time okay right
um and then say there's this second
transaction
that begins after transaction one has
started
yeah like here yeah and it writes
z so for before it
uh writes you then must have read z uh
yeah yeah and so red z what version
number doesn't read
uh the state the same one
um and then say reads then it tries to
write z
yep um and then say t2 commits before t1
commits
uh yes okay so this commits yeah
and then t1 commits after 22 minutes oh
i'll try to commit correct
and now we'll start doing this whole the
whole walk for the validation and blah
blah blah correct
so before before so what's going to
happen correct is you know
i was going to give you this example uh
there's an example that i'm saving for
next lecture but
yeah basically what happens correct c
one would be z will be going at one
at this point the z will be at version
one correct
so the validation phase will run after
the commit that's what you said
right and so here's a validation of z
and you know it has zero correct and
then now it's one
and will this transaction will be abort
okay so this is what i was wondering
about then so
because after the validation phase
passes
there's a period of time
after the validation uh phase passes a
period of time passes then it commits
what if this validation happened before
t2 committed so it still saw the old
version number i cannot happen because
the uh
after the validation uh uh after the
commit
after the commit has completed correct
the
commit backup you know has recorded and
the primary have come or
have made the change before the
application is returned before the
commit returns the energy has been
updated
um wouldn't or i guess what i'm saying
is
isn't it possible for t1's validation
phase
to happen before or i guess maybe what
i'm trying to say is
isn't it possible that t2's commit
happens between
t1's validate what happens after t ones
validate but before
t t one's commit
uh clearly you know there's a risk
uh and this must be excluded uh
and it's excluded uh so okay so you're
worried
let me just construct this case maybe
i'll come back to you next week when
we're gonna talk about it anyway
uh but i think you were worried about uh
let's see if i could get the picture
back
uh years over here we did uh
so this guy
committed so he's basically doing the
commit phase correct this is t1
of
uh so t2 is about doing is here
correct and then t1 is coming in
before uh everything happens
before d2 it finishes correct so right
so like t1 validation also comes in here
so actually maybe okay let me rewrite it
and then we'll get back to you okay
okay that's exactly what i wanted to
talk about
okay all right thank you you're welcome
so just make sure
you're asking about t2 being like in
between stage two and three of t1
yeah yeah exactly
well in that case then t2 we could we
could serialize it as t2 coming before
t1
right yep so
let's let's get let's get back to this
on the on thursday here because i have
an example for that and exactly where
this is going to go over top of this
sorry in the validation stage you just
read the
read the version number yep
and serializability allows us to reorder
transactions
yeah but strict serializability not
correct like even uh if a transaction
structure analyzer requires that even
transaction starts if somebody
after somebody committed that
transaction is also committed after that
transaction
with this vertical guarantee because of
the version number
got it thank you but strict
serializability
doesn't it's like if t2 ends
it's not enough for t1 the end after t2
ends t1 had to have started
or maybe i need to think about this more
but yeah i think that was this is always
tripping you up it's like there's also a
a
a rule about when the transaction starts
yeah yeah well
well what happens in real life right
right this actually starts at some
particular point in time and
basically if if t1 uh
if t2 starts after t1 commits
right so so then it must be the case
that t2 observes
you know t2 t1 changes that's trick
serializability
right but what happens if t2 starts and
commits
solely within then it's a concurrent
transaction and either outcome is fine
okay okay what the answer is for you
yeah yeah yeah
yeah i think that's what i was confused
enough
when they literally when t2 starts
before
t1 commits it's considered a concurrent
transaction
and so t1 or you know t2 can observe
either it can be
ordered before or either after doesn't
matter okay okay
okay thank you i think it's also the
answer to your example
right right okay thank you okay
we got it anyway already you're saying
if
t2 start is like between the t1 start
and
in right like yeah like and then you
know can we could be go for it or after
it doesn't matter
okay okay that makes sense oh can i ask
a little just six questions
yeah i remember in in 6s oe1
you post these slides too
yes yeah yeah i didn't do that here uh
you'd like to be on the website i think
slides are useful if
if you just need to like look at the
slides you don't need to like scroll
through the video
okay um you're the first asking that's
all
this is why i haven't done it okay yeah
i'm happy to do it i
do shave them all
thank you so much thank you it was a fun
lecture thanks