thank you okay good afternoon
good morning good evening good night
wherever you are
so today uh i want to talk about the
zookeeper
uh and with the this background the
paper that we uh
you know was assigned for today which is
from 2010.
um and um so this is going to be
referring back the last couple lectures
i think we dove in quite a bit of detail
into draft including uh
looking at code uh the lectures from now
on are going to be more
conceptual and exploring ideas
uh in distributed systems you know
through papers
and the zookeeper one is particularly
relevant
to us uh because it has a little bit of
a relationship
as we'll see with lab3 and so it will
allow us to talk about a little bit of
some properties of uh lottery and
particularly uh linearizability
uh but the zookeeper system uh more
importantly
it's interesting because one it's a
white media system
in practice
well beyond apache well beyond
yahoo there's an open source apache
project
that is still active uh
and what particularly what's interesting
about it uh for for us
uh in this lecture today is actually
high performance
and with high performance i mean much
higher performance than
uh what actually lab three is going to
be
uh and we'll talk a little bit talk
quite a bit of the detail about this
and there's sort of two reasons why it
is high performance one uh it is
declined operations are asynchronous
uh and really what high performance
forms here means is that we can
the system can process many more
operations per second so it's really a
throughput
metric uh and the second reason you know
it's high performance is because
uh it uh doesn't provide strong
consistency
uh so it doesn't uh it
has an instinct consistency
definition and it gives us some freedom
to execute basically read operations on
any replica
and therefore reconforms can scale
then the second aspect you know that is
interesting from zookeeper is
in addition to being high performance it
is sort of a generic
what they call a coordination server
and the the point being here is that you
know there are many applications
uh where you need to sort of keep track
of like who's part of this cluster and
who is the master
now so think about the mapreduce or if
you think about
the gfs that the master in gfs needs to
keep track or like for every chunk
you know who are the servers that
actually serve they cannot search the
chunker from whom the service
actually is the master and so tracking
that sort of configuration information
you know comes up in lots of different
distributed applications and zookeeper
is really designed
you know to support that kind of thing
so you can just sort of outsource all
the configuration management
uh to see zookeeper uh and then you know
focus the
rest of your application development on
other aspects of uh
your distributed system okay so that's
sort of a
brief introduction you know the the
topics that we're going to be talking
about
and as a huge role feel free to
interrupt at any time
uh uh or you know post something in the
chat message
let me actually pull up the chat
okay good uh so just to you know
just start from the basics zookeeper is
a replicated state machine
in the same way that there are the
replicated state machines that we've
been seeing
um and so let's just draw the usual
picture
uh we have some surface uh in this case
it's going to be you know zookeeper
and ck it
receives requests from clients say
create
you know create a z note uh and
basically the way
uh it interacts uh uh
to distribute these operations it has
sort of a separate library you know
think about this as the
raft library their case is called zap
basically you know the leader you know
sticks the
operation into uh you know the
equivalent of the wrath library dot you
know talks
you know to you know other
libraries on other peers uh
that basically creates you know a log
you know that combines with all these
operations and all these machines
and then the operations are out of the
log of feedback you know to the
throne so in our case would be the apply
channel
to the service the server supplies the
operation response to the client
and so we have basically running
and uh so far you know in
the labs you know we've been focusing
mostly you know lab two is all about you
know this part
implementing uh in our case raft so
instead of zap
and for the first order at a very high
level you know you can think about
zab just being another raft you know
providing sort of similar
guarantees although you know implemented
quite differently uh
you know it provides uh an order of all
the operations
despite uh failures network applications
et cetera et cetera it doesn't suffer
from split drain
brain all other sort of things that we
should associate with the
raft library um and
you know what we're going to be focusing
in lab 3 on is actually implementing a
service on top of it
and so this paper talks about the
discoordination services keeper and
we're going to actually implement in
live free the key value store
and the data structure is just the map
you know from keys to values
and so the operations that we're going
to be supporting are you know put in get
so the client submits put in get
operations you know to the
surface the server runs them through a
raft uh
and then applies them one by one to the
key value store
and in zookeepers you know the
structures are slightly different you
know there's a treaty of z nodes
uh but the basic operation is the
appliance the same you know
the the lower layer the lap or
the zap library or the rav library
orders all the operations they're
applied in the same order on all
replicas
because they're applied all in the same
order there's no non-determinism
the resulting state on each of the
replicas is going to be identical
okay so that's sort of the basic uh
setting of this paper and sort of also
the relation
part of the relationship between uh lab
free
and the zookeeper service itself i'm
mostly going to be talking in this
lecture on
focus on the zookeeper part itself and
not talk about zap
uh because you're going to assume you
know that's sort of similar to what
we're doing in lf
and what we're doing in lab two
okay um i want to talk a little bit
about
uh what kind of performance would you
observe
uh if you once you finished lab three
and
uh would measure you know how many putin
gets your operation can get through per
second uh because like one of the
achievements of this paper is this high
performance so let's think a little bit
about that
so let's assume you know there's a
operation coming in
and you know put that variation comes in
by the leader and so we're just going to
go for the normal case like the standard
case where everything is working no
network failures no partitions nothing
everything works out perfectly
here's the leader you know we've got two
followers
and you know just by now you know that
protocol you know probably inside out
you know the first thing of course it
happens like you would call the leader
call start
uh to start actually writes uh
the put operation to its uh
to the log in the leader and then the
leader you know propagates its log you
know to the other
followers and you know we saw it before
and that actually happens in parallel
but we're saying let me draw this
slightly differently
um basically it launches a bunch of rpcs
uh almost instantaneously to the
different
uh followers each follower of course you
know we'll
append the entry to its log so that
requires a right you know
persistent storage uh same thing here
and then they respond back
and so here's the response back and in
this case
if a majority has responded the leader
can actually apply the operation
so the leader will actually apply the
operation here for nut
indicator so do the put
and send the response back to the client
so what we're curious about
is like how many uh puts per second can
we actually get
you know in this
in this uh setting and i know we think
about it you know the uh
you know when you do grass grows you
know back of the envelope calculation we
don't really care exactly about the
the exact numbers but uh you know one
round trip
uh we need at least one round trip to
actually get the majority great leader
needs to talk to at least one follower
to actually maintain the majority so
we're going to have at least one round
trip
messaging
uh in uh then you sort of need to look
at the rights to stable storage because
those tend to be expensive
and you'll see you know in this case
we're going to have two rights there's
going to be one right at the leader
there's one right at the follower at
that point we have at least two nodes
that have a copy
so one of the things will be committed
uh
if no further failures uh and so
basically
you know to a minimum we're going to
need to write
so that's sort of the base and the best
you could do correct at least in the
sort of the simple scheme that we
discussed
discussed here there's a referendum we
can think about like what the cost is
um and in a round trip you know maybe it
was running in the data center networks
or not across the internet
you know maybe you know that actually
comes down to one millisecond
uh we're roughly in the neighborhood of
a millisecond maybe a little bit faster
but we really care about it as we'll see
in a second so we're going to do two
writes to stable storage
and rights actually two stable stores
tend to be expensive and you know
defensive coordination like what medium
or what technology you're using for
stable storage let's assume like we're
using ssds you know sort of pretty
typical
and then you know presumably one right
he's in the order of maybe two
milliseconds you know we got to really
make sure actually the right
ends up on the in the ssd so it probably
has to be a synchronous uh
right so it means like two milliseconds
for one right you know so two
right would be roughly you know four
milliseconds
so we added up you know it's going to be
five milliseconds
and so how many operations per second
just to see if anybody's still awake
200 yeah so there's gonna be 200 puts
per second
any questions about this doesn't make
sense
okay so now let's look at zookeeper
what's the round trip for in the rights
i'm sorry i missed it
we have the formula the right the right
there's no round trip there's one round
trip
correct to talk from the leader to the
follower and the two rights one at the
stable storage for the leader
and one at the stable store install a
stable storage of the follower
and the two rights add up to four the
round trip to roughly one millisecond so
the total is five
milliseconds for one put
okay let's look at zookeeper
and again the metric you know that the
paper is interested in is the throughput
throughput metric where basically the
clients have many many many clients
and uh they pump uh you know many
requests
to um to suit keeper as much as possible
and uh a pipeline pipeline them
aggressively
and so uh so let's see what the
results of that is and so let me pull up
you know the graph
of the paper
and you know look at that paper a little
and let the graph a little bit
so a couple things to presumably to
observe you know on the
x-axis is the percentage of read
requests as we'll see in a second you
know this is going to
be important uh to distinguish read from
write operations and so variety
operations are really operations that
modify
any right operation that modifies the
state and read operations or
operations don't modify the state at all
so in our uh
in lab three terms you know put would be
in a right operation and get
the read operation and on the y-axis
is the number of operations per second
and let's look at the case of free
servers
and so the first thing you're going to
notice is that
at zero reach so only write operations
so that wanted to modify the state you
know we get you know roughly
21 000
operations per second as throughput
right
and you know we look at you know if the
system only has reits
that actually gets a lot more you know
it gets up in the uh
you know whatever the 67 year age region
and in fact what really is going on is
that the number reads
for the pre-put in terms of read to
scales with the numerous servers
so uh the if your free servers
you know you get three times you know
the re-performance of one server if you
have five servers you get near the
uh five times the re-performance one
server
that's of course not true with rights
correct like in fact if you look at this
graph
you see that if with more servers the
right performance actually goes down
uh and you know the reason for that is
presumably
the uh the leader has to chat with more
servers to actually get this operation
through
and so when we're purely doing write
operations
uh we're actually limited and we cannot
get expect more performance than a
single server and the fact that the ad
servers are going to go
down in performance
and so this 21 000 you know per second
even for a single
uh uh for you know write operations
um with uh a configuration of free
servers you know there's an impressive
number like this quite a bit higher than
actually the
simple sort of calculations that we did
for uh lab three you know library will
never get in that will not
get close in the neighborhood at all um
and so you know we want to understand uh
we want to see in this design what did
the designers do to actually
get that kind of performance
and so the two as i mentioned earlier
there's sort of two key ideas
uh one everything is asynchronous or the
clients
can submit many operations to raft
or you know zookeeper sorry uh in a
single shot
uh so they're all pipelines so basically
when
the way to think about it the zookeeper
client basically says
please start executing this foot and
doesn't wait in the response
of the put that just you know
immediately issues the second put and
then the third and the fourth and the
fifth
and so for example a lot of these put
run will be batched all together maybe
even in a single message all be
transferred to the
leader and the leader will apply them
all at the same time
and in fact it will leader will write to
the persistent storage only once you
know for this whole batch of operations
so instead of having one right
or per operation you're going to have
one disk right for many many many
operations
and this is one reason you know they get
this uh you know very good performance
on write operations and then the second
thing
is they do something special for
read operations they allow read
operations
to be processed by any server
so instead of running all the operations
through the leader
they allow operations to actually be
processed by
any server so
and then the latter one i want to talk a
little bit more about it
uh and i think i wanted to think about
you know
could we do something similar like let's
say we want to do lab free
and we're going to do the same trick and
we want to look at
basically reads from
any machine or any pier i guess it's
just
so the picture would be as follows and
we have a leader
we have the two followers we just stick
to the case of three
and we have a client
and uh we're gonna like consider what
actually could happen
if you know we sort of easily follow
this strategy where we're gonna read
from anything so here's our client
the leaders actually you know when we do
books you know they all go through the
leader and so the client you know
basically does a read
and let's say you know this was done
and at the same time or roughly after
after the put was done the client issues
a get in the talks to one of the
followers an arbitrary one let's say
for this case it does not talk to the
leader and
then you know we're the follower
response
and the question is like what value does
the get observe
so what's the possible values you know
that the get can observe now let's say
that you know we're reading whatever
the key x and that initial the value of
x is zero
and this put actually put x to one
and what are the values that get can
actually return in
if we don't do anything particularly
special
um so just a question here about the
setup so uh if we're assuming that draft
is the infrastructure here
and get it's just another command then
wouldn't the
follower just redirect the client to the
leader to put the get request
through the leader no no so the goal is
correct we're not you know
we could do that there's a lot of things
we could do but like the the
we want to get this perfect scalability
so to get perfect scalability
the follower cannot talk to the leader
for read operations so basically read
operations are executed by
the individual followers um immediately
without no communication because that's
another way we're going to get perfect
scalability
so they're not even communicating with
yep so i'm just doing the native plan
let's say like our goal is to get
perfect scalability like you know
zookeeper does
and we want to understand like you know
is that difficult or easy or what does
that really mean
and so the first you know font
experiment is like we do absolutely
nothing
at the leaders the followers the
followers get the
read operation to execute it and return
the value awesome
and what can you know so another
question is what values can be returned
by the
again the client observe in this picture
can be either because maybe they put
then
then make it through the desk of the
leader yet yeah so it could be you know
so
you're either going to return zero or it
could return one
right so it can return stale data
it's a possibility um
what's uh let's say you know we do the
uh let's say it returns
uh one so this get you know returns one
use for uh a fat experiment and then the
client does another
get
i'm not going to say to where that get
is going uh
but you know um
and what values could we see
in response to that get assuming there
are no other rights it should be a one
right yeah unfortunately
because i have three servers if i had
five servers
uh why is it different
okay let's make it different
uh so certainly can return one correct
that we agree on that
because if the follower talks to the
second get request
you know talks to uh
a follower that actually has seen the
put operation which the majority of them
have seen the put operation we're going
to get a one back correct
and the real question is could it see a
zero
even though it observed the one earlier
i mean you could see a zero even in the
case of uh three servers right because
let's say that you have the majority of
servers okay let me let me do it first
the five case because it's simpler to
see
are we assuming that the client always
asks the same
peer or no there might be a little
network petition or a disconnection for
a brief period of time so you know
doesn't have to talk to the same peer as
last time correct yeah so in that case
uh
it can talk to a different peer who and
that peer may uh respond with zero
and that's consistent exactly so this is
possible
so you know we're gonna have to sort of
strange behavior correct in this
configuration where
you might see a recent you know in the
first case we might see actually a
recent value
and then we read actually something from
back you know back in time
yeah so we do nothing
special uh and we just like naively read
from any uh appeared and you know we
have sort of two side types of problems
i mean the get can return scale data and
the
the get return data even from back in
time
and so sorry wasn't this possible also
with three followers
because the majority was the leader and
one follower and you could ask the other
one
if you've seen the one in uh
yes it could be possible uh absolutely
the three would be possible too
i think v5 is much more clear that this
is possible
um okay
so uh so then we're gonna go back and
sort of think about a little bit of
this behavior correct you know returning
those values
is that okay and this is sort of an
interesting question
and it depends of course like what you
mean with correctness
uh and what you know if something's okay
it depends like what our correctness
definition is
and the correctness definition that
we've sort of been peddling you know for
the last
couple lectures or since the beginning
of the term is this notion of
linearizability
and roughly what that means
uh we talked a little bit about it in a
week ago
you know it behaves like a sort of a
single machine
that's the intuition that we've been
using since the beginning of the
semester
uh but you know the definition of
linearizability is a little bit more
precise
uh and sort of tries to nail down what
it means to behave like a single machine
and so
when something behaves like a single
machine you know first of all it has to
be the case that even if the operation
execute concurrently
you can sort of order them in a total
order so it's possible to construct the
total order
of all the operations because in the end
it's a single machine so
if it behaves as a single machine
there's only one machine virtual machine
that can actually uh
perform the operation so a total order
of apps
and there has to be some properties true
about that total order
and so one property that has to be true
is that the order matches real time
in real time really what i mean is that
if an operation completed
before another one started
then no that first operation has to go
before the second operation in the total
order
and then there's a third property that
the read
operation read op returns
value of last right
and that's sort of the official
definition of linearizability and you
can just think about this as sort of a
more
precise uh more precise statement of
this you know first thing this intuition
namely the whole thing behaves like a
single machine
now we want to go back and you know
think a little bit about
uh the scenarios that we had just on the
on this whiteboard
namely these two cases of scale data and
back in time
i think about the thinking whether
linearizability allows them
right and so let's first focus on the
first one
so we have a client one correctly for
you this the way you would like draw
this out and reason about
linearizability is you know you draw a
diagram for this form
where you know the left bar is the start
of the operation the right bar is the
acknowledgement
you know to the client that the
operation actually executed and in this
case you know we started saying
i want to put to x and i put the value
one
then we had another client or you know
the same client
let's do it draw another client you know
basically did the read and that reads
started
well past the put operation so this was
a get of
x and um we had one case where the get
of x actually returned to zero right
that was the
first possibility
and so that's what actually happened on
the previous board and now we want to
sort of think about this
is this execution allowed by
linearizability right this is the
correctness definition that we're
looking for and we want to see this uh
execution this order of operations
that happened in practice you know at
least we have seen that as possible in
practice is this allowed by
linearizability and that is our
correctness criteria
and is this a lot like your eyes melee
no no why not well
because the c2 client operation started
after the
c1 completed so in the total order you
have to have
put x1 and get x and it should be one
because it should read the last way
yeah so basically in the total order
that you construct you know this guy
you know this operation must be after
that operation
because it started later but then you
look you know that violates rule number
three correct
that the operation returns the value of
the last right that's actually not the
case it actually returns an
earlier value so this is not
linearizable
does that make sense
and of course this totally matches our
intuition right because this is a single
machine just could not have happened you
know you wrote a value to
the single machine and then you read it
back and it's certainly another value
it's actually previous value so there's
not a lot
okay let's do a second one like our
other example so we had a client one
again just to put i'm going to draw a
little bit
more compact because i don't have much
space
and you know we do uh put then we do
there's the read where the get we get
the room turns one
so we're not in the first case but in
the second and we're in another case
and then we have a gap that returns zero
and so that's the second sort of case
that we looked at correct at this
this picture you know the back in time
case
and again we can ask ourselves the same
question is this allowed
by linearizability
um no because the read wouldn't be
during the
valley of the last right yeah yeah it's
a pretty uh
straightforward observation correct you
know this is absolutely not the case in
fact it's almost simpler in the first
case because like even you know these
operations have to be in this order
uh but you know that you know could not
have happened but i would violate uh
rule three right
okay good so you know this is give you
some intimation of like you know what
linearizability means you know how you
reason about it and basically
uh if we don't do anything special and
we do this naive scheme
if you were implementing the lab free
and you followed this naive scheme
then uh you would not pass the test
because you know the test assume
or our goal in lab 3 is actually to
provide linearizability for putting gets
and so the scenarios like these ones are
just not allowed you know your
implementation has to be
in a way that these results cannot
appear
does that make sense so we're gonna in
lab three we're gonna
uh shoot for linearizability
and what is one easy way of getting
linearizability
how do we can ensure that putin gets
operational and linearizable
well i mean if you do actually only use
one machine
then it will be linearizable right yeah
so what's the easy solution
we run all the reads you know through
the leader correct
so basically an easy solution to get
linearizability and in fact that's what
we're going to be doing in lab3
lab3 what we're going to be doing is
you know reach or get operations
get ops go through the log so they go
through raft
and as you observe you know it seems you
know if they really go all through one
machine
well it's not they might not go through
all one machine the leader may change
over time
but we know that the leader is always
total order quicken that the log is
total awarded
and so we're going to be able to
construct you know a total order that
actually has
you know the order matches real time and
all the reads to return the values of
the
last right because basically the raft
protocol
will guarantee that all the entries in
the log
are in the total order right
and of course the rough protocol has to
do quite a bit of work to actually make
that all happen
and but despite you know network
failures
despite uh network uh um
splits you know the raf protocol will
guarantee us
that basically all the operations happen
in this in the total order
in fact you know the whole replicated
state machine approaches or based on
this idea correct that like all the
oxygen locks in the total order and
applied in the same order on all peers
and as a result
everything looks uh looks kind of like a
single machine
and so the easy way to solve this
problem is to run all the reads you know
through the
the leader uh whoever deletes at that
particular point of time and that will
give us linearizability
let me pause for a second here any
questions about this
uh sorry it matches real time it just
means that if operation one
ends before operation two starts
then one is before two yeah yeah that is
our
graph you know you will see that this
will happen automatically correct
because
the uh if the if an operation actually
completely finished it that must have
been the case that the leader responded
you know back to our client and then if
the client started the operation later
and must end up later in the law get
deleted
so this is going to be a practice true
and
also uh so just to double check and
maybe reiterate so the uh so in lab 3
all of the client requests are going to
be synchronous
you know so yes okay absolutely
okay good so uh you know one downside of
this
scheme you know that we would go back
actually if you read the raf paper very
carefully there's an optimization for
read-only operations
uh but even that optimization requires
some
uh some communication and so
like if we just follow this naive you
know this straightforward plan to
actually get linearizability
um you know does this what does that
mean for performance you know we go back
to sort of thinking about you know
contrasting into a zookeeper
yeah is for example the number read
operations is going to scale with the
number of servers
not because now everything has to pass
through the leader yes
exactly everything has gone for the
leader again so you know we're no matter
it's a little bit undesirable correct
and so it gives you an interesting
question is like
you know how is it possible that like
the um
super zookeeper gets this great
performance and like when you see that
the simple scheme reduction doesn't
really work
or at least violates linearizability and
so
one uh so we want to talk a little bit
and like to understand what doesn't
really
how does google get this um and so the
first thing to really realize and this
is the probably the most important part
is that a zookeeper
does not provide linearizability
it basically changes the correctness
definition
and so the zookeeper service is not
going to behave like a single machine
uh you know it's going to have results
that would never happen
on a single machine so the particular
so what is it what does it provide well
it does provide linearizable rights
so all the uh operations all the right
operations actually you know go through
the leader and you know go through the
log and are appended to the log every
appear in the same order and so they're
going to also be applied in the same
order so we still have this replicated
state machine
uh approach or where we apply all the
right operation all the operation to
change data into uh
uh
in the total war but uh there's a couple
more properties
uh so but it does not provide
linearizability for reads
instead it sort of provides two sort of
a different property
which is that all the operations appear
in fifo order
uh in five a client order
this partially has to do with the
asynchrony you know the client may
submit
multiple requests uh one by one
uh without waiting for a response and
you know zookeeper will guarantee that
if you submit you know if client one
submitted a request and then client one
submitted another request
then that second request will appear uh
later in uh the result will observe the
result of the first
operation um
and so in particular you know rights go
into client order
and then reits have where all the action
is where the instant properties are
the reas observe
last write okay so reads uh can we
observe
last write from same client
and so this sort of makes sense you know
basically this sort of says like
you read your own rights yeah so if you
do the right operation you immediately
follow the read operation you see at
least
the the results of your own rights
but for rights from other operations
from other clients
the zookeeper does not guarantee that
property instead what it guarantees
is that the read will observe some
prefix
of the log
and uh so this means correct that you
can actually see
stale data
because you may you know read from a
follower and that follower
has a prefix of the log but not like the
last entries in the log
because maybe it just got lagged likes
behind a little bit
uh and nevertheless that follower is
allowed to
return uh a value because you know the
only thing that
you know zookeeper is going to guarantee
that actually you know reach observe
uh a prefix of block
so the operations can now go out of
order you know once they in the log
and you cancel reach can't like read
uh operations out of the alarm in out of
order it really has to be a prefix
prefix of the log and then there's a
second requirement
that you cannot do no reads from the
past
and that really means like if you saw
some prefix one
and then you issue like a read style
prefix one and then
you read a second tweet then that second
read
has to see at least prefix one plus more
and it might be no it might be just
prefix one but it cannot go back in time
so it cannot see
a shorter prefix than prefix one
and so this basically so so if we look
back at this picture
uh the zookeeper will allow this
in certain cases namely if the two
clients
are different but it won't allow
this up this you can never have back in
time
okay um so i have
a question a conceptual one so we have
these two consistency guarantees the
linearizable rights and the fifo client
order
so if we ignore the second constraint
for a second and if we only focus on the
first one
does it uh does the definition of
linearizable rights actually make sense
since the definition of linearizability
depends on having a read operation and a
right operation
so yeah hold that thought for a second
uh because the the the
the way they define linearizable rights
is not basically the rights are a total
order
uh and but there is a relationship
between the reach and the right so hold
that far for a second okay
uh we'll come back we'll get to that in
a in in a minute
like in one board i want to make one
board in between okay
sounds good okay so
just like uh let's look a little bit at
how
zookeeper actually provides these
guarantees um
and you know so if you get the intuition
you know uh
how you could implement this uh the
paper section not very explicit about
how they implement this
and certainly i'm going to give you sort
of a roughly best guess
so there's a zookeeper client
that runs on the client machine in
lottery we call this is a clerk and so
this is a piece of software
library sort of that works collaborates
you know with the service
and uh in the zookeeper in the paper
terminology
basically it is the thing that has the
session so
when you join when a client wants to
connect with the super servers you know
it creates a session it connects you
know
using the session information to the
leader and maintains you know state
across the session so we have a leader
uh in uh zookeeper as we'll see we have
followers you know basically this is all
sort of similar
uh to what we're used to from lab you
know two
and you know does a client get issues
right you know to the leader
you know because the rights are going to
be linearizable in fact the
rights basically follow exactly sort of
roughly the same strategy as
in the raft library so there's going to
be a log
and in the log are all the rights are
entered you know so whatever
you know there's some slots let's say
the leader you know pends this
right you know in this particular uh
index
so this you know has an index uh and in
the paper they refer to this index as
the
z x id
so i think you can think about the cx
basically as the index in the log
and uh when the leader you know
basically commits
uh an entry uh right you know to the
log you know it returns the zix id back
to the client
and so the client maintains that state
so associated with the session is
basically you know with cxids you know
the cxid at the last right
okay and so
when the client later on does a read
and the read you know it doesn't have to
go to the leader because that was the
whole goal to get more uh performance so
maybe
the read actually will go you know to
one of the followers
and but the read will be tagged with the
cx id
that of the last write that that
particular client has done
and so what does that mean well let's
say this follower is behind correct and
it has two entries but it hasn't
actually observed
you know the right yet because whatever
the leader maybe committed it through
this other follower
and what happens in this case is that
this read
the follower won't really respond
immediately instead you know it will
wait
until i've seen you know the z-axis id
and as soon as you've seen the cxid it
actually will respond
now of course there's going to be
another client uh
and so maybe at some point that this
right will come through
uh and um and maybe now the read you
know the client does another read
and so it hasn't seen no any other zx
uh and maybe like let me make one more
follower
let's say there's yet another follower
and that actually has not observed you
know
that that final right yet or actually
let me
so there's going to be another let's say
there's a other client
that sticks in some other right that's
the scenario i want to talk about
so there was another client that
actually appended a w
after the cxe you know it is right here
uh but it was not observed that
particularly right you know what we have
here
is we got the
uh we got the two slots we got the right
but then the green ray hasn't really
shown up
at that particular follower so if the
client now issues a second
you know read and maybe that goes to the
other follower you know it has the same
zx id because it hasn't seen
any new you know that client has not
issued any new new reds
it will arrive there you know that that
that guy is allowed to respond
immediately
because it has you know seen the cxid of
you know the
block that has seen the last egg id of
that particular client
uh of course it misses you know some
rights you know that from other clients
that are already being processed by
uh some majority of the servers but it
is not required to return that data
and so it can just return it and so this
might actually return then in stale
values but you know that is allowed by
the definition of you know the zookeeper
correctness guarantees um i professor i
have a question
yeah like first i i thought um
i'm not sure but uh i understood the
client reads like the session leads were
sticky
so they would like in general go to the
same
um
yeah but you know of course you know
there might be a little bit of you know
might be a quick network petition
or uh anything like it and so in between
time you know the
it might have switched to another server
okay
and then um in addition it turns out the
zookeeper does actually do some load
balancing
uh so but nevertheless it can happen
correct
right um the other thing was you said
right um always always go to a leader
um and and then the leader
um responded with the zx id
doesn't the leader have to like first
like reach consensus before responding
or in this
uh yes
i guess so uh you know you just have to
commit it because otherwise it's an
uncommitted break
uh uh so i think the exact protocol okay
i'm abstracting away a little bit in the
details of the protocol i'm just going
to sketch
how it works uh i believe you're right
you know that uh
it must return presumably after you know
the entrance is really committed
then um sorry last thing um you said it
always goes to the leader but i think
that the paper described like it could
go to like followers or right go to a
follower and then
yeah but it then ends up at the leader
correct
thanks just to clarify when you say
wait for zxid unlike for example the
second follower
or so second when we wait for zxid we're
actually waiting for it to be committed
right it's not sufficient to just get it
it must be committed yeah
got it wait but
um what like it would have been
committed
by the time it was like like a client
wouldn't get
an uncommitted cxid correct like ever
like oh yeah but just uh that's correct
uh
so if you know the this okay
at this point when the follower sees
this uh zx id
and the right is in that particular cxid
you know it must have been committed
because you know the client could have
not gotten that cx id
unless you know that option of that g8id
was committed
thanks um also so when you
say that uh from the read you you get
stale data so like the last
basically arrow uh but the client here
in the read
request it supplied the zx id within it
so
it's as if the client knowingly exactly
wanted that location in the
log that had zx id as its index
so didn't it knowingly just request that
prefix that specific prefix of the log
no but it really says you know what this
basically cxd says like
it's basically a counter you know going
back in time
and uh so the zxz says like you know you
have as a follower
you have to return me a result that at
least concludes the prefix
of the log through cxid you might have
more that'd be fine too
but at least through cxid and this just
stops that one case where you read back
in time
okay awesome thanks
okay so now you might wonder
uh you know so this clearly does not
provide generalizability and one reason
people are excited about linearizability
is because it behaves like a single
machine so it's easier to program right
like you know you do a good you get to
get you know you roughly know what
you're going to get
uh and then no pun intended uh but
here you know you certainly have a model
programming model that's different from
a single machine
and so uh you know how do you program
with this thing
and you know it turns out that basically
these rules
you know this correctness definition
that you know zookeeper has
are are basically you can think of those
like they're good enough
to actually do uh you know for the
purpose kind of to help programming
and so i want to talk a little bit about
that
so the real point is that you know with
linearizability you know it's pretty
clear that you know
uh that helps programming and writes you
know intuitive programs
here things are going to be slightly
different and we want to understand
actually if you know things that work
out well
uh and or whether it is like just pain
in the nectar program and just basically
completely unusable
um so so let's look at one of the key
examples
that i talked about in the paper um and
the first thing i want to do is like
basically ignore the sync operation
because like you can make
uh every operation actually linearizable
by just issuing a sync
like before you do the read uh but that
of course you know makes everything very
slow again and we're not going to get
our performance advantage so
basically we want to avoid doing syncs
and so i'm just going to ignore things
and like
program as if you know we don't have
scenes
so let's look at the following
operations so here's the right order
so we do a couple operations and this is
the case of the ready file so
uh we issue a delete
of the ready file
so for example this is a a new
uh master that becomes uh
uh uh becomes the new of
the new leader uh and so it needs to
write the
configuration information in it like you
know who's uh who are part of the
the the replicated state machine and who
is the leader and so it writes you know
some configuration files
right f1
write f2
and then does it create stuff
ready
and then other followers might hear
other
this is the read order
they can you know for example call if
exists ready
and so you give us this our operation
exists and uh
uh if uh ready exists then it will
immediately return true
uh and otherwise uh not and so you have
to wait
uh for one let's ignore that case for a
second let's assume that you know the
second client so here's the one one
client did the right operation the
second client does the read operations
and then if it exists then
the client reads f1 and then elite f2
and so the thing that we you know
we want to understand like you know what
values could f1
this read actually return
and i think the thing that we worry
about correct is it could return
could have returned some result of a
right that was done much earlier here
and we must have observed this right
i think the paper mentions that um the
reader can watch
certain things and be notified of
changes
yeah so let's assume that actually the
file exists so create actually succeeds
immediately so let's
talk about the notifications in a second
so this exists returns immediately
no watch is involved it just exists and
then we do
that second client there's a read of f1
um i think it shouldn't read whatever
what was written by the first client
because the operations are in fifo
yeah yeah right so the i think the real
thing that actually the
that so if we
saw this option what value correct like
for some right earlier that would mean
that we're reading back in time
right and that is just not allowed
you know the rules actually forbid that
um
this read you know must observe you know
this
uh that value of that write because this
read the previous
exists observed this right right so we
know
that you know this exist id must have
seen the zx id
corresponding by that create and so that
means that this read
will uh
must you know uh must be sort of see the
last
right you know that was performed in the
total order that preceded you know that
particular create and so
the the last right in that critical
order before that is this particular
right
right because all the rights are
actually linearizable
and so it must be the case that this
read f1 observes the result of the right
one so this is nice correct because if
like you know
some new leader you know became the
primary get raised configuration file
you know we know for sure that actually
we're going to see that last
configuration trial that was created by
that
by that new leader
so we see here an example that these
rules are sort of carefully chosen
uh that you know things that you might
care about uh if you're writing a
configuration service that actually
certainly work out
wait um sorry i i i
might have not understood what you were
saying before but
in this case if it exists like if the
checking exists ready
couldn't it read like stuff before ready
was deleted
okay all the writes in your total order
so this right is in total order that
right is in total order the creator is
in total order right right
so this read here on the other side has
observed that create
so whatever read is going to do it's
going to go back into the order correct
and like
observe the last right in that total
order and the last right to f1 is this
one
but is it is exists right no existence
is a read but exists observed this
particular right
oh you're saying it you cannot read it
back in time correct like this is the
whole goal
right but how did we know that it that
it observed that
exactly i told you that i said like the
file existed so it must be the case that
it observed it
it just returned true but it but it
existed before you deleted it right
yeah yeah yeah yeah but you know okay go
back to the second let me okay this is
the second case this is a good point uh
let me
uh talk about that so like there's
another scenario
i think this is the one you're worrying
about that could have happened and this
is where notifications come in
so the list will agree that this is
right correct
so the second case more rules
and this is indeed interesting i think
the case what you're worried about is
uh here's our reader again here's our
writer again
and the reader you know calls exists
on ready
and let's assume the file you know uh
is there and you know it does a read of
f1
right almost same as in the previous
scenario and now
like you know there's some change in
leadership you know there's uh the
there's a crash uh you know recovery and
all that kind of stuff is happening
and so there's a new uh primary
uh it deletes ready
uh you know it writes f1
it writes f2
and it's um where it creates ready
like as before
and let's assume that this is like this
reader a little bit delayed i don't know
something else happens on the machine
and you know now does the read of f2
and i think this is the fair the
question you're sort of asking about
because this is war itself right
because now uh there's a configuration
change
and if this configuration change gets
slotted in the middle here
right this read of f2 is going to return
the the new configuration as opposed to
the read of f1 that is going to return
the old configuration
and clearly things are going to be
messed up
that is not a scenario where we want to
be in so it'll be a terrible outcome
so and how does that actually you know
get
rectified or how does actually uh
zookeeper deal with this well
this is where the watchers come in uh
you know the pictures i drew in the for
future boards is not completely correct
you know in addition to
uh calling exist with this really it's
going to say watch to true
um and uh what that means
is that this delete
you know changes the ready file and we
have now set a watch on the ready file
and so when the uh ready file gets
deleted
you know by this new primary that
actually results in a notification
and there's a rule for this notification
and the rule for the notification is
that every notification
will be delivered before you know uh
rights that go after it and so
what has to be the case that you know
the uh this notification will be
delivered before the write to f1
so when so there's two possible
scenarios correct the notification gets
delivered
here or the notification gets delivered
like after the read of f2
let me move that read of f2 slightly up
or yeah so it's still happening sort of
in time
behind you know the write operation but
the notification gets either delivered
here
depending on the delays or it's going to
deliver to here
sorry um what's the exact wording of
that rule that allows this to happen
uh basically i think one way to think
about it the notification is like it was
almost like a write operation
and the followers you know implement it
yeah
so that the uh if your change happens to
delete the notification goes off that
notification is delivered to the client
and with that zx id
again the paper's not but i still don't
understand why this guarantees that it
can go like
before wait so the valid places for it
to be are
um before the right of f1 and also
like after the right of f2
right the the notification is delivered
after the the
after the delete of ready and before the
writes
and before the rise of f1 and f2 are
visible or end the create
for that matter oh i see
um
that's just the rule zookeeper has to
guarantee that
okay okay so so that means there's two
cases correct like the
notification gets delivered before the
read of f1 or after the read of f1
if you deliver if it gets delivered
after the read of f1
of f2 is there a problem
no no because then the read just
happened before the writes
yeah so everything is good so this is
this this whole block is happening after
the read of f2 is
perfectly fine and about here
um wait professor did you say that the
watch
is like a like write something
well you can think about it the watch is
not the right operation yeah i didn't
mean to
apply that but the right the watch is
executed with the appropriate sort of zx
id
uh that's associated with that right
with that modification
those are local right the watches are
you know yeah the watchers are local and
so when they're executed
uh the it's guaranteed you know that
they have it happened at the right when
the right is observed
or the client sees that the watch is
propagated with the cxid to the client
and make sure that they're executed
thanks
again the papers are slightly vaped on
exactly how it's implemented but you can
imagine different scenarios
but the more important point is like
this rule is guaranteed okay so what
happens if the
notification is delivered here
so the client is running correct you
know it doesn't exist the read f1 and
now this notification comes in then you
have to restart probably yeah
you have to restart
okay so what we see here basically is
that
you know the the rules you know make
programming definitely a little bit more
uh difficult uh but not impossible
right you know with a little bit of
careful sort of uh programming you know
you
and understanding the rules you know you
can actually get the desirable
results that's probably the application
wants what happens to the read f1 though
what happens to read f1 you start all
over
oh including that all right
as you'll see this is a trick that shows
up in those recipes quite a bit right
like this
idea of actually uh you know bailing out
and
starting over again okay good
uh so hopefully that gives you a sense
that you know for two things
there's sort of a even though you know
one people one reason like people like
linearizability is because it's very
intuitive you know very easy to program
with because everything behaves like a
single machine
but you know if you want fault tolerance
scalability
it's hard to get actually good
performance and so one way to get good
performance is to compromise on the
consistency guarantee
and in this case you know compromising
linearizability
and provide some other consistent
guarantee and as we can see you know
that's it
complicates you know the the user
experience or the programmer experience
uh but you know these rules and
zookeepers are carefully chosen
so there's still you know things that
can actually work out and
it's doable so it is possible to get the
right you know sort of
uh guarantees so then
there's another aspect to this
programming model that i want to talk a
little bit about now that is really
related to the coordination service part
and um and so the examples you know
that you need to again what does it mean
to be a coordination service
one good example is probably the vm the
virtual machine fault tolerance paper
from a little while ago that we
read and that had this test and set
operation
all right and the goal of the you know
the test and set operation was basically
to make sure that there's no split brain
because basically two clients would run
and one would win the test and set the
other one wouldn't and as a result you
know the the one that won the testing
set
could conclude you know that i'm that's
going to be the primary
and so that is sort of uh an example of
a feature that a coordination service
you know should be able to provide
uh and i want to you know just to make
that a little bit more concrete
uh let's think about like what lab three
could you get that with lab free you
know
basically sort of get this test and set
type thing well
uh so let's do a very simple case you
know let's say we have
uh here's our simple implementation of
test and set
and uh in lab 3 we only have put in get
operations right there's no other
operations so those are the two
operations so like how wide you write
this you know
uh maybe you know we'll do a put
you know to the key let's say master
and we put my ip address in that we get
p address of the color
and then you know we do get you know and
we say if the get
on master is
equal to my ip address
uh then you know actus master or act as
leader
actually this is our you know naive
implementation you know we don't don't
have many other choices because we only
have to put
we only have to put in a get and this is
how we're going to implement this
will this do the desirable thing
oh there's no atomicity between the put
in the gap so
maybe something has changed correct so
basically there could be two clients
correct they both could execute
the both books at the same time um
and uh and then observe uh
you know the uh in the
roughly they're doing it at the same
time and the interleave you know
correctly in both will actually return
get you know with their particular ip
address correct
and so we can get two leaders
and that's course not what we want so
the the main point of this
or an example is basically if you just
have put and get
it's going to be very hard to actually
implement the test and set
uh it turns out it's possible but it's
very complex you know you use baker's
algorithm you know you can basically
probably do it but not gonna be
ridiculous
to do that in a distributed system and
so
what zookeeper does uh it just provides
some additional
uh help to build these sort of type of
primitives
and we'll see you in a second um
the other thing that you know presumably
what you want to know and that library
does not provide any
uh support for if you're sort of a
configuration service or coordination
service is that
you want to know when somebody goes down
you know for example you want to observe
that like if the leader goes down like
somebody the other parties would like to
know like is the leader down so that we
could choose a new one if he needed to
and so uh at least for on the
applications the building
using that uh service okay so
uh so those are two things that we
really want you know one is you know we
want some
way of trying to get this atomicity uh
that's what we're looking for in the
zookeeper design and then in supervision
the second point we're looking for in
the cpu design is for
an application to learn whether some
node goes down
so let's look at the zookeeper api and
really you know what we want to look at
is the z node
api
and you'll see again that is actually
carefully designed to actually make it
possible to
uh do the things that were uh we're
looking for
okay so the way the system is organized
there's you know there are there's a
tree of z
nodes uh typically you know there's like
one
you know sort of app one has a z
node that might have some children that
correspond to the
machines that are part you know of f1
something like peer or machine one
machine two like maybe the irp addresses
or dns names
machine three uh and they might actually
have version numbers
associated or sequence numbers with them
and basically z nodes can be three types
one they can be regular so then they're
fault tolerance replicated and all that
kind of stuff and then they can be
ephemeral
and ephemeral basically means that the
node will disappear
uh automatically when the session
uh with that uh machine free uh goes
away
so either because there's a network
petition there's no heartbeats more
coming in from
machine three uh but at some point
zookeeper decides you know that session
is gone
and so then it will delete you know that
node uh
automatically and so that's for
ephemeral notes
and then there's a third one uh which is
the sequential
let's go back to in the third one your
type of notes are sequential
notes and that really means that you
know they have version version number
associated with them in their name
and uh and they're created you know one
by one
in under the particular uh z note uh all
the children will have
a sequence number in their name and the
notes are not ordered by that sequence
number
and so for example this might have
sequence number one this might have
sequence number two and this might have
sequence number three and if a new one
gets created it will have a sequence
number higher than three
okay and then there's a api associated
with that that way i want to talk a
little bit about you know there's create
which we already mentioned a little bit
you know it takes a path
uh it takes some data and flags
and the flags correspond you know to the
free cases
and then there's delete and in the
previous slide every little misleading
you know delete takes a path as before
but it also takes a version number and
exists takes a path and a watch
and then there's a get data
primitive that takes a path and a
version number
and we'll see that these version numbers
are the trick here or the key to
actually get our automatically
and then there's set data path
data and a version number
and there's also a call for get children
to get actually all the children
of a particular z node which
takes a path and i think a watch
and their sync you know basically are
sort of a cop out operation to actually
ensure that everything
you know if you really need strong
linearizability
okay so i want to sort of talk a little
bit about like you know why
you know this version number is handy
and so
let's uh look at a particular example
the simplest example i can come up with
is
like basically implementing a counter
um and so the way you know you would
write the
uh if you write you know okay so let me
actually first get the right solution so
while you know true
you know the way you implement increment
so this is the pseudo code for increment
of this counter is you know you do you
have
x v you know get data
up the counter
i get data you know count
and then uh if
you know set data
counts oops
so there's xbox one
and the version number and
if that is the case then brick so let me
uh
quickly go over this so to get data uh
returns the current version number
and the value uh of the key
so the key or the path you know the so
for the file count
it returns the value and its version
over that particular point when they did
read and then you call uh and set data
takes three arguments you know the path
you know the update the new value in
this case is going to be x plus one
because we want to increment you know
the value by one
and it actually passes in also the
virgin member and
the uh semantics of said data is that if
you know the version numbers
are still the same then the set date
actually happens
and otherwise not so what does this
protect against
um this prevents you from interleaving
the get and
set basically yeah so if like two
uh operators two clients did get at the
same time they would read
uh you know they do get at the same time
they get both back say you know whatever
x is zero
and version number zero x is zero
version number zero uh
then they do both put where like in this
case is set data
so the z data with you know whatever uh
x is one
you know version number zero also this
guy does the same thing
set you know one zero
uh and you know why and so both gonna
both clients issue those
two set operations or both set
operations can cheat
um well no
yeah why not uh because one of the
version numbers will be wrong
yeah right like so one of the two goes
first why does one of two go first
because all rights are linearizable yeah
all rights are linearizable so they go
in some total order
so you know we can pick one so let's say
this guy goes first or this
operation goes first so that will
increase the
uh that will increase the
uh the value corrected the one
from zero to one as correctly and but
that will also and will
execute because the version numbers
match right like the version number zero
is actually what the current version
number is
so the version numbers match the
increment happens and the set data
returns
are true and what will happen with the
second one well the second one the
version numbers won't match because the
virtual number will be increased because
because this previous set data operation
and therefore the second set operation
will fail
and so and then the client will loop
back and try again
and try to increment and
try to take another shot and doing the
increment incorrect so
what what happens in this case is
correct even though the two clients
executed the operation you know
concurrently uh if the interleaving is
bad you know the
this piece of code will actually do the
right thing the second client will try
again
and as the result you know the what what
the end value will be
you know two as opposed to one
okay
does that make sense
if you've done any sort of lock-free
programming in the past
uh then this might all look very
familiar to you and so this sort of a
style of lock for you
you're basically zookeeper to encourage
this sort of style of lock-free
programming
okay what i like to do
since i'm always running out of time the
last time i ran over time is i'll
want to talk at some point about logs
uh but i will do that uh next time
the next lecture and now let me just
sort of summarize what we've learned so
far
and then i'll talk a little bit more
about zookeeper in the
next lecture so
in summary
uh so basically you know this is a very
successful design
widely used uh you can you know download
it you know
it's on github you can play around with
it if you wanted to
uh and one of the things that is
interesting about it you know compared
to all the systems that we look so far
it has weaker consistency which with
weaker consistency i mean
it doesn't provide linearizability
uh and you know we're seeing that
basically as a careful
designed api at least we have seen some
aspects of the kevlar design api that
despite the fact that actually has
weaker consistency you can still
use it and in fact you know you can use
it actually for pretty important
applications you can actually use uh
zoom keeper as a configuration service
like this main purpose sort of keeping
track of like whose primary
who is in the uh what what's the set of
replicas
etc etc and so for this sort of crucial
operation of being a configuration
server that has to be correct because
otherwise you know we get the split
brain problem
uh the api is carefully designed so that
if you use the api
correctly um you still can implement
this crucial
uh application on top of it and despite
the fact that actually provides weak
consistency
and the cool part of that is that that's
this discrimination
you know like sort of careful designed
api and the weaker consistency
allows us to get you know zookeeper
really high performance
and we'll see later in later lectures
more of like this
sort of trick of trying to uh weaken the
consistency guarantees to actually
either you know get better
uh to get better performance or uh
you know be able to uh
continue despite network petitions
okay let me stop here and then i'll
resume
in a little while next time around the
weird lecture
any questions or again as usual
if you have to go you know please feel
free let go if you want to hang around
and ask for more questions you know feel
free
please feel free to do so
um sorry can you go to this slide which
said the um set
um the unsuccessful example for this set
and for the test and set
um i think it's two slides back this one
uh yeah um so you the
new design it's it is able to fix that
right
yeah you mean you're like with the apis
the version right yeah if you have no
like
exactly uh so i didn't get to do that
but that was the
point of the rest of the lecture is to
talk about how you can able to test the
set using the version numbers
and clearly the increment suggests you
can correct because this is basically
the same sequence
right all right this is the same thing
as the master okay
yeah exactly okay thank you so much
you're welcome i have a question about
this
version uh versioning to prevent lock
uh to to implement lock free programming
is this like
much more efficient than log free
programming because you still need to
like
re try the operation again and again
until it succeeds right
uh yeah like it maybe if tesla's set has
a similar property correct if the tests
have failed
and you wanted to become you know
actually increment you have to do that
again
so it's often the case in this lock free
style programming that you know you can
have these loops where you retry
and so if there's a lot of contention
you're going to get a lot of retract
of course if there's no contention
there's no retract uh
and typically you know these lock-free
algorithms actually are pretty careful
in how they do the back off
so they don't really try immediately you
know they have some backup plan
right but what benefits does this give
over a
standard lock because either way if you
have a lot of contention you're going to
be
like sitting there and retracting a lot
yeah so let's uh
so you know so uh the the increment
counter
is an example where basically uh you
sort of implicitly do the walking uh
because you will see
if we implement locks in zookeeper
like the using the zookeep okay if you
implement locks with the zoom keeper api
and then if you do the stupid lock you
know you're gonna also have this
contention issue
uh of course there's a way of
implementing the smarter walk that they
talked about like without the hurting
and then you can do better uh and so i'm
just hoping to talk about that uh next
time
all right thank you i think the real
point here is you know that you know you
can use these primitives to actually do
log free programming
like with the interface that the lab3
provides it's not possible
makes sense thank you