it's 105 so feel free to get started
whenever you
want to be ready
all right uh should we start then
please all right um hey everyone
my name is felipe i'm working with uh
catalina and today we're going to be
presenting
on our project on distributed private
electronic voting
um so motivating this project was you
know
actually sort of sort of easy given the
current events and
elections that have had to happen with
covet restrictions so
we asked the question you know how would
uh internet voting work
um and we're focusing specifically on
maintaining voter privacy um or
you know keeping votes private and so
here's a sketch of how
um a voting system might work uh you
have
a bunch of voters uh in this case you
know five
and then a vote counter and the voters
send their votes
uh to the vote counter and uh
the vote counter is you know maybe they
sent them encrypted or
some sort of security the vote counter
decrypts them
uh make sure that each voter votes at
most once and computes a winner
and so you know the uh key thing to
notice here is that
um in order for the vote count to
determine that every voter
votes admiral at most once each vote has
to be
in some way linked uh to the voter
which which is dangerous and so we're
gonna explain our threat model here
uh which is we're giving the attacker uh
two sort of
capacity or two sort of powers the first
is uh to create fell stop failures but
but not byzantine failure so the
attacker can crash
server but it cannot um
sort of make it misbehave and you know
whether it is a reasonable assumption is
a question for another
day um but we think there are other
protocols that deal well with these
issues we're not dealing with byzantine
failures
um the the second power we give them is
to passively spy
on uh on a vote counter and so this is
problematic because as we said votes are
linked
uh with with their voters and so a
passive attacker that's that's uh
that's spying on the server can sort of
de-anonymize these votes
um and so here's where we come in and uh
present our distributed voting design uh
we're first gonna deal with the first
uh problem which is um
you know the the adverts are crashing
the servers and so we are going to
uh have several vote counters and the
idea is
that each voter will send their votes to
all the vote counters and the vote
counters will use you know
the same protocol as before and compute
winners
uh they're the winner sorry um and
yeah it's this is good because another
certain crash
sort of like n minus one uh vote
counters
as long as one of them is up and running
we will be able to compute a winner
um however it's it's very uh you know
arguably
more unsafe uh for the second type of
attack which was like passively spine
because as long as you know as the
as the adversary the attacker can
compromise on even
one server uh you know it can
de-anonymize all the votes and so that's
where we're introducing
your secret chair uh for shamir secret
sharing we have
a voter uh that's gonna you know
choose a vote either zero or one uh and
we're gonna you know i'm not gonna
explain how shamir
actually works it's a cryptographic
protocol uh but we're gonna just
you know show up what it allows us to do
uh
you pass that vote through shamir where
you give it two parameters nmk
and it's going to uh create n parts
uh which allow you to recompute that um
the vote
the end parts look completely random and
in fact what is sort of powerful but
chemir is that
even k minus one uh shares give you no
information
about the original vote but uh given k
or more shares
you can use shamir to recompute that
vote
um so we're going to go into shamir
voting scheme
so uh yeah now for the chamber voting
so first all the voters are going to
choose their vote and
share parts to the vote counters not the
complete vote on the
different parts and so the vote counters
are going to receive the parts and when
they have the parts of
all the voters they are going to sum
these parts
and share the sum with the vote counters
so uh here it's important to note that
the sum uh it looks
completely at random and so by sharing
it with the vote counters
the other both countries they cannot
learn anything about the parts that
uh a received so uh this uh
like ensures that the privacy of the
voters is maintained
so they exchange their votes and when a
vote counter has received case sums
from other voters including their part
they can finally compute the winner so
using a
xiaomi secret sharing again uh black box
um
it will like uh recompute the sum and if
we get like something that is greater
than half of the number of voters then
the winner is one and if it is less than
the winner would be zero
um and yeah so we finally have a winner
um now some of the assumptions of our
scheme are
first that the voters and the vote
counters are well behaved and follow the
protocol
and their parts sum to what they say
some um
you know like good intentions and uh we
only handle uh
fail stop failures here with this
scheme so yeah now to handle some of the
scenarios first uh if we have a
uh unreliable network a scenario
um all of the rpcs that we send in our
servers are going to be sent
periodically until we receive
an acknowledgement that it has been
received um
and then to handle both failures so we
we need to persist uh all of the voters
uh like persist the parts that they
competed and
their vote um because if we like
recompute parts and then the vote
counters had different parts then the
correctness of the scheme would be gone
and they would not be able to correct
the sun
so it's important to like always share
like parts from the same uh
computation and not like change parts
and finally to handle the both counter
failures
um here we rely on the shamir secret uh
sharing scheme and so as we mentioned
before we only need
uh k servers to compute the winner so
uh the system is uh resulting to n minus
k crashes uh of vote counters
and now it is demo time so i'll stop
sharing screen and share
another screen
um so here is our demo um basically we
have uh five voters yeah here so
we have three vote counters five voters
and k is equal to two
this means that they the network is
unreliable
and now if we run it um
here um so we got three and we get that
the winner
is one we can also crash one of the
servers
um since k is equal to two we uh
can still compute a winner by having
only two servers up
and so now if we run it um we get that
the winner of the election is day one
again
and this is the end of our presentation
thank you very much for listening and
we'll take some questions
i'll feel free to ask questions
curious uh how extensively you test this
system
like do you have uh did you try it in a
much different other configurations
do you have performance numbers um
sure so we we did um
have like different you know sizes of uh
we create a whole test suite
and make sure to test like voter
failures server failures have different
like sizes
and um we don't have performance numbers
we didn't test that um but in terms of
like failures and
and different like numbers of voters
vote counters yeah we have a
full test suite and that's we should
have put the link on get uh for github
but
um we can you know send it to you if you
you want so you can
check like look over our implementation
on the testing
can you say something maybe a little bit
about like you know what ideas from 6824
were you able to apply in this system
other than using the testing framework
sure uh kind of do you want to take this
one or should i take it
yeah sure um uh so yeah here
um i guess this scheme actually comes
from a
pizza from the cryptography class and so
it was fun to like look
at it from a different perspective so
now we're not like
uh focusing that much on the on the
security on it but more like oh what
happens if the individual
like servers if they fail um and so both
like handling both
uh voter failures handling uh vote
counter failures
uh problems with the network um i guess
within other specifically partitions
because it would work similar to
vote country crashed um uh
but uh yeah it was it was fun to look at
this problem from a different
perspective
thank you yeah thanks oh yeah he has
something to say we're out of time a bit
so yeah cool
awesome uh well nice job thanks for
sharing up next we have a
presentation on private analytics
if kevin is ready to share that awesome
take it away are you ready
okay you guys can hear me and you guys
can see my pointer
yes right okay cool well hello everyone
i'm kevin
and today i'm going to be presenting
this very creative reading system called
sis
and this is a system for collecting
aggregate statistics in a privacy
preserving way
and so the last presentation was a good
lead into my project um so for the most
part in 6824
we've talked about how we can build
reliable systems in the presence of
byzantine or
philistine failures so servers can crash
and clients are generally well behaved
um but from this talk i hope you'll
learn some new concepts on how we can
build systems with strong guarantees in
the presence of byzantine failures
on behalf of both clients and servers
within the system
and the main tools that we're going to
use to achieve these guarantees are
cryptographic primitives such as
multi-party computation
and zero-knowledge proofs and also
distributed computing primitives such as
broadcast
okay so for simplicity let's say we just
want to build a system that computes
sums
so we're going to have an aggregation
server that stores a key value
store so the keys are just going to be
indices for some um
statistics and then the values are going
to be tuples of sums
and then we're gonna have a bunch of
clients so each client is gonna have
some identity say
it's client ip address it's gonna have
the index of the statistic they wanna
bump
and then it's also gonna have its
private inputs so the most
straightforward thing to do is we can
just have all the clients
send their inputs to the server as is
and they can compute the sums
but obviously this is bad because now uh
this leaks everything right
the server will learn the client's
identity it'll learn the index being
bumped
and they'll learn their private input
so we can do a little bit better um we
can compute these sums privately
if we deploy two non-colluding servers
and then we're going to have each client
secret share their input to each of
these servers so as i've said in the
previous presentation so each server on
each
secret share alone leaks no information
about the client's private input
but still the servers can add up these
shares and compute
a local version of the key value store
and then later when the servers want to
recover the actual sums
they can combine their local key value
stores to reconstruct the global key
value store
and this is a little bit better um at
least if one of these servers is honest
then the servers are still going to
learn the client's identity they're
still going to learn the client's index
but now instead of learning each
individual client's input they're going
to learn the sums of all clients and
inputs okay so that's better but still a
problem namely that this
identity index relation can still leak a
lot of information
so how can we fix this we can make
things anonymous so
we're still going to adapt the setup
from before but now we're going to give
each server a public key for encryption
and then each client is going to encrypt
each of their shares
and instead of having the client send
their shares directly to the servers
now we're going to have a layer of
forwarding processes in between
and so what's going to happen is the
client's going to send their encrypted
shares
via broadcast to these are these proxies
and the proxies will route each share to
their respective
servers and then the aggregation can go
as
as explained and so what are the privacy
guarantees here
if at least one of these proxies is
honest then the proxy will still learn
the client's identity
and it'll learn some timing information
based on when the client set the share
but nothing else because these encrypt
the shares are encrypted to the server
so they'll learn
nothing from that and then if at least
one of the servers is honest then the
servers will also learn some timing
information based on when the proxy
forwarded it
it'll still learn the index of the
statistic and it'll learn the sum
but most importantly as long as not both
a proxy and a server are compromised at
the same time
then this design unlinks the identity
from the index being bumped which is
exactly what we wanted
right so this is great but this also
leads to another problem
meaning that now clients can hide behind
the privacy and anonymity guarantees of
the system
to send bad inputs right so let's say
the system expected client inputs to be
zeros and ones
well behind this bill of privacy now the
client can send a secret share of like a
billion through the system
and now it can undetectably skew this
sum so clearly this is bad
and let's fix this we want to make the
system more robust so what we're going
to do
is we're going to have each client
generate what's called a zero knowledge
proof
over their shares and send these to the
servers
and then when these servers uh collect
these zero-knowledge proofs they can
interactively check
that the the client's inputs actually
the client's shares actually
uh re reconstruct to some well-formed
input
and because this proof is in zero
knowledge um it leaks nothing about
the input other than that it's
well-formed and so again our privacy
properties stay the same the proxy still
learns the client's identity
it still learns some timing information
the server learns timing information it
learns the index and learns the sums
but now we've protected the system
against malicious clients because it'll
only accept well-formed inputs
and so this is great um still there's
another problem which is that servers
can crash
and we can lose data so we obviously
need both servers to be online in order
to reconstruct
the global key value store and so if we
want to make the system
more reliable we can do what we know
best which is to replicate the servers
and so we can use a rast sign
replication or we can also use primary
backup style and replication the
question is okay with all this
replication
all this cryptographic machinery and all
this message rowdy can we still achieve
good throughput and it turns out that we
can actually paralyze the server step
here that does proof checking navigation
which is likely to be the bottleneck of
the system and so what's going to happen
is the proxies are going to hash
partition
their inputs to each of these servers
and then each of these servers in a sort
of reduced step
will combine their intermediate key
value stores to reconstruct the global
key value store containing all the sums
okay
and so now the final question is did i
implement all of this before the due
date
unfortunately no but i did make it much
of the way there so i'm going to show
a quick demo of the non-replicated and
non-parallel version of it
so i'm going to quickly switch to my
other laptop
i get to stop sharing on this one first
yes
cool okay so great so
on these right two terminals are gonna
be the servers so i'm gonna run them
this is implemented in rust um now i'm
going to hook up these two proxies in
the middle
and then on the left terminal i'm just
going to simulate a thousand honest
clients
and so what's happening is all the
clients are generating their input
shares and generating the zero knowledge
proofs
and sending them to in proxies and the
proxies are simply forwarding them to
the servers
and then here finally on the server side
they're going to be checking all of the
proofs
and if the inputs are in fact well
formed then it's going to add it to its
local key value store and then sometime
later when these servers want to
reconstruct
the final statistics they can just
combine their key value source to
recover the sums
and that's it for my presentation and
happy to take any questions
you have any questions from the audience
i guess i have a question um so like
with what you implemented so far
what sort of like which at what point do
you
um accept or what point do you tolerate
failures
and like stuff like that like can you
talk about the
reliability of your current
implementation
yeah so the reliability of the current
mission is
not great um mostly because the servers
aren't replicated
so for the proxies um because the
clients broadcast the proxies all we
require is that
one of the proxies is up so if we have
two proxies we have
uh we can tolerate one failure of the
proxies and we'll still get the messages
to
um the servers but if any of the servers
goes down
then you're just not going to be able to
reconstruct on the data for that
um is that only for sums or did you
implement it for like
any general function that operates on
all of those inputs
yeah for now um i've only implemented it
for sums but
basically with this additive secret
sharing scheme you can compute any
linear function you want and maybe more
complex ones are possible but
um i still haven't explored those yet so
it turns out at least in
practice some probably get you like 90
of the way there
numbers looked like performance numbers
yeah
so the main things we want to measure
are uh for the client side client
on computation and client bandwidth so i
have some numbers at least for client
computation
um generating these shares and these
proofs takes like less than
a few milliseconds so it's very
lightweight the bandwidth is just a few
kilobytes
and then for the throughput on the
server side um
i actually ran on ec2 but i only
allocated four cores to each
um server because i only had 64 cores
and i wanted most of them to be on the
client so i could
remove that bottleneck and so with four
cores i think
what is that probably like a thousand
queries per second
and then estimating i guess if you um
paralyzed by 20 servers for each logical
machine
they can probably achieve close to 22
000 queries per second but this is all
around run on the same data center so it
doesn't factor into
latency so like the actual numbers will
probably be a little bit lower than that
i had a question about your
implementation uh how did you do
so how do you um actually implement your
knowledge proof and code
like non-theoretical yeah that's a
that's a great question
i can send you the paper that i
implemented it out of
but um it's it's not too complicated
basically it's just a bunch of finite
field operations and so if you find your
finite field library you just follow the
paper
and follow the steps and it's uh
somewhat straightforward from that point
as long as you can decrypt the paper
okay and is that and is it possible to
like test that
um like like how would you know that
it's working or not working
yeah so i guess yeah i only showed the
simulation with um
honest clients but you could also
generate a summation with that with
clients that'll submit like bad proofs
and then
you can see them being rejected okay
yeah that makes sense
thank you yeah
great thanks pretty sweet um
is the next group ready to go
awesome okay
um hello um i'm shannon and
i'm nick and johan here so johan take it
away
thank you shannon so we'll be talking
about bookadocks pokedogs is a
distributive collaborative editor
it's similar to google docs but just a
little bit better um
so to move on to the next slide
okay so as you have seen in this class
achieving consistency is very hard to do
in a distributed system
there are many ways that consistency
could go wrong
so a very simple example is if the order
that you receive the rpcs is different
in each peer you might end up with an
inconsistent state
and there's a data structure um
called crdts which we use in our system
to mitigate this issue crtts achieve
eventual consistency by making every
single operation that you make on the
document
globally unique not just unique to every
single peer but globally unique
so if i press the letter a on my editor
it's different from shannon or
pressing the letter a on their editor so
for example here
even if um the bottom pier for example
here
adds a new turtle to a document
even if they receive remove requests
from the other two gears they will never
remove the gold internal
because the operation is itself
different from remove
so remove green internal is different
from remove
gold internal and this this is how we
achieve eventual consistency
so from here i believe nick is going to
talk a little bit more about
what is here how we implement your
entities
yeah so for book box we
chose to use a crdt called lc which
represents a sequence
of elements with variable length keys so
the goal
is let's say we want a sequence that
represents the alphabet and so far we
have the letters a
and c so one editor might choose to try
and add in the letter b
uh between them and another editor may
choose to try and add in the letter d
after c uh and the goal is that with
eventual consistency
um we'll eventually reach the state a b
c d
so the way that l c achieves this is by
using a start and
end token and then it gives every
character
in the document an individual token that
is between the start and the end
so we can insert h between certain end
and if we want the letter
i after h then we can insert that at
seven which is between four and eight
um now if we want to insert an
exclamation point between i
and the end of the document we can
insert it with the key seven comma two
so we increase the key length or to uh
to create a key between
two other keys that are adjacent so in
this way we can always create a key
between any two other keys um so we can
always
insert um now i'll seek
performs well in that it reaches
eventual consistency with
very little effort for coordination um
and
it has some optimizations that cause the
the length of the keys to grow
relatively slowly
um however uh some cons uh are that
in order to support deletion of these
elements it relies on causal delivery
and exactly once delivery
uh and we didn't really want to
implement this since it was based off
a number of other works so we used a
slightly simpler approach
which was a deletion set so this is a
grow only set where we add in elements
um so for instance to delete the letters
h and i we would add in 4
7 into this deletion set
then this whole state becomes equivalent
to just having the start and end tokens
and the exclamation point at key 7 2.
so we built the fukudak service similar
to how we implemented kb
raft we have multiple servers multiple
clients and
multiple clients they only talk to one
server at a time and
they continuously try the operations
until they get a successful reply from
the server
okay clients and servers both maintain
um an avl tree of characters in the
document as well as their own deletion
set
of removed keys we chose to
store characters in an avl tree for i
guess performance reasons
[Music]
the chain of events goes something like
this so the client will send an
insertion and deletion to the server a
server will update its own evl tree and
deletion set and persist that
and forward those updates to all the
other servers and clients and then the
server
will respond success to the client
so we're going to demo it
we build a very simple um ui for it
here so
johan and nick are also um accessing
this from different
lines right now so you can see them
typing
uh you can type something else i'm
typing here
[Music]
i think johan is typing hi
nick is typing something here
and we can edit each other's uh text as
well
and yeah that
is lukadox
oh
um you're happy to answer any questions
i guess
i have a question here i really like the
turtle theme that you guys came up with
this and i was just wondering where the
where the turtle theme came from oh yeah
so the turtle is
um nick johan and i all taught the web
dev class over iep and the
turtle is our mascot for the class and
we are inspired to build wukadox because
we use
google docs as a question document for
the students ask questions but it
couldn't handle
a load of over 75 users typing at the
same time
and that's how lucadox was born thank
you for
let's see that's cool i had a i had a
quick question
um and so first of all i got called in
the middle of the presentation so sorry
if you mentioned this
you may have but um so
first of all first question just to make
sure i understood correctly is the are
these these data structures which are
very interesting are they stored on the
client or the server
if they're stored on i imagine right now
the server is not replicated but that's
something you can easily do
but if they if they are stored on the
client
what happens if one of the clients fails
uh so the data structures are actually
stored on all the clients and all the
servers
um and so right now we're assuming the
clients are fully
trustworthy um and so if a client fails
any edits they haven't sent to a server
will
just be on their end until they come
back online in which case
they can send it and it will all achieve
eventual consistency
interesting all right thank you oh i had
a question
uh why elsic over other crdts
uh yeah we chose lc mainly just because
uh it was it was one of the first
ones we found and we wanted to get
started um and because
after implementing the logic of the
variable length keys there was really
not much more we had to do in order to
make sure that the clients and servers
stayed consistent
oh okay thank you um so beyond that it
was just like message passing and making
sure everyone gets all the messages
okay yeah thanks so how many servers
were you running with in this example
was it just one or was it multiple
there were three servers and three
clients each one of the
clients was connected to unknown to its
own server
so are using the servers for scaling or
for fault tolerance or for both
a little bit for both uh when we ran the
performance metrics
by distributing the load of the client
request across many servers you are able
to handle a little bit more bandwidth or
requests
however this is a trade-off because
eventual consistency will take a little
bit more time
because the servers will have to send
the rpcs to every single other servers
so in our paper we have like a whole
diagram and everything but
uh yeah how about how well does it scale
as you add more servers yeah so it has
the metrics on my other screen
so it's able to handle uh
[Music]
if we gave it two more or less three
thousand requests
across five clients and five servers it
achieved eventual consistency within
three seconds but this was
mainly because it was also on a computer
that's on localhost so the rpcs were
really fast
however that also means that all the
compute is happening on one machine
so there's it can go either way when we
put it on real hardware
um yeah another thing is that
um if you make too many requests at once
eventually it's kind of hard to achieve
so for example we tried to do
19 000 edits at once
across 100 clients and five servers and
it took around 32 seconds to reach
eventual consistency however if we only
did 3 000 edits across 100 clients and
five servers it only took around three
seconds
when you say you do whatever the 19000
or whatever that was
is that like sending all those at once
or is it like spread out over time
every single one is sent every single
edit is sent in parallel
and at least under testing interesting
interesting
i had a quick question so one of the
motivators is that collaborative text
editors like google docs
can't support like high scale updates um
current updates so why don't you think
they use an approach like what you guys
are proposing
i think google docs uses a similar
approach called operational transform
um which i'm not sure if it can be
parallelized as well
um and they probably don't want to
because they don't want to give us that
much server power
um it's probably just like for cost
effectiveness
i'm guessing
yeah i'm just happy with that
hypothesizing i
don't think the use case of 100 people
editing one document comes up too often
at least in the google google docs usage
so it's probably not something they want
to spend extra engineering time on
great thank you cool demo so up next we
have
egg scrambler if y'all are ready
[Music]
cool hello everyone my name is arvid and
together with ireman
and wendy we have been working on egg
scrambler which is
anonymous broadcasting using community
of encryption um so let's start with a
motivating problem
um we all know we all love mit
confessions so let's say that one person
in this class wants to submit a
confession
telling people how much they love this
class and so what do they do well
they submit this confession to a google
form and then
that goes to the mit confessions admin
and then that hopefully goes to the
facebook page
uh but now let's consider a scenario
where the confessions admin is actually
an mit professor particularly for
another class in core6 so obviously they
would not want this confession to be
posted
so they would censor it because they can
but it's like even worse because they
could
they could they're like an mit professor
so they could go to google
look look at their network traffic they
could look at the mit wi-fi network
traffic
so they could figure out who actually
sent this and then obviously they would
like to give that person an
f minus in their class um and that's
like terrible so so what do we want to
do well
uh we want uh anonymous broadcasting and
that's like a
common theme today it seems like uh and
so what is anonymous broadcasting well
we defined it as
a protocol to broadcast a message to
everyone
all the users without revealing who the
message comes from
so without further ado uh i will let
wendy
talk about how we do that
so yeah um the two main features of our
design are that it is decentralized
um and uses cryptography in particular
um commutative encryption is necessary
because otherwise
the decryption order will reveal the
original identities of message senders
um yeah so here's the protocol we
implemented
in short participants join the network
and encrypt and submit their message
which winds up encrypted by all
participants exactly once in the encrypt
phase
the scramble phase provides anonymity
because um as highlighted
because every participant encrypts the
messages
and randomizes their order finally
decryption results in the desired list
of messages from all participants with
no connection to identity
um so yeah if all participants are
honest this prodigal successfully
results in
anonymity while it is possible for a
malicious user to determine the center
of a message we believe that such
actions are detectable upon master
reveals
if people are interested there exist
other solutions to this problem such as
mixed nets and
dc nets next armin will describe the
structure of the implementation
so first we'll look at this assuming
that
we're looking at the high level
interface for someone trying to submit a
message and our interaction with our
service so let's say that you're the
person trying to submit a confession
you're this application client
so the first thing you're going to do is
send a start message
so that indicates that you want to start
a new broadcast round
and the service is going to ask all the
people who are participating in the
round
for a message and then it's going to run
this protocol
and then it's going to send the results
to everyone who participated
or if it's something like confessions
it's going to publish it
and ideally at this point it would be
anonymized
but this is a very simple view in
reality uh we're actually building this
on top of our raft implementation from
the labs
so the reason we use raft is twofold so
one
we implement the protocol as a state
machine
and so raft is among many instances that
are
running the protocol and so raft is used
to replicate the state
and then two when we're doing the
scramble phase we need to make sure that
each participant
is scrambling in a specific order so we
actually use graft as a
coordination mechanism to do this test
and set where they all proceed in a
single order
so similar to the kv store we have the
state machine
server that's reading the wrapped
updates and updating the state machine
with whatever the agreed upon state is
and we also add in
the state machine client which is
reading how the state machine is
changing
and then this client is what's actually
taking the actions to
progress the protocol in some way
and then again just as in the kv store
in order to progress the protocol this
client is going to contact
the leader server with the request to
the
state machine updates and then we also
implement the raft
configuration change rpcs so
servers can add or remove themselves to
the configuration and this means that
new people can join subsequent broadcast
rounds
and then also if there's a failure we
can cut someone out of the configuration
so that the next broadcast round can
proceed because our protocol requires
that everyone
is actually active in order for the
round to complete
and then finally we have the application
where the client says like something
like confessions running on your phone
will send these broadcast messages to
the clients and then it will
receive the update once the protocol has
completed so we're going to show a quick
demo
uh w recorded just let me know if you
can't hear
this
so now we're on to the demo so we start
out uh we're looking at wendy's computer
right now
and she's going to start the application
so she's basically going to start an
instance on her computer
and try it and um she's currently
sending the link for her configuration
into the zoom chat as we can see here
so now we're going to go to arvid's
computer where he's going to take that
link and then join the same
configuration
as wendy so he does that
and now he's going to start the round
um we're going to send their messages
and we have the rounds succeeded so now
ours is going to show that we can
seamlessly add in a new client so this
is both someone who's going to send a
message
and an entirely new raft instance so we
can see here this new instance quickly
catches up
on the left there and then now all three
of them are going to send a message for
this next round
and we get all three messages so we've
demonstrated that we can
broadcast over the network and also
add in clients at will
uh yep so that's our demo of uh
ice grounder does anyone have any
questions
this is this is a really fast one um at
this first of all this is a really cool
system
um second of all um so the application
is separate from the
client raft state machine correct
yes and it's like two different devices
um so i guess my question sort of is
um like in like the overall picture like
how you would deploy this thing why is
that
um i mean i imagine you could run a like
a raft state machine with a bunch of
phones
um and it might be poor availability but
you've implemented the configuration
changes so in principle couldn't that
really i'm just trying to figure out
what the role of the client is in this
whole thing the server is a cluster of
servers that makes sense the
applications that make sense but so
basically the client
it's it's basically just like as a nice
way to
uh like write the implementation uh so
like the server and the client you can
basically think of that as a server
uh it's just like in our like in our
implementation it made sense to
create this like abstraction um yeah
okay thanks
uh in order for the round to progress
all peers must receive
the message from all the other peers
where like n minus one appears
and so if you have like some very weird
partition where like
some subset is able to talk to the rest
of the subset
um how would that be resolved here
um yeah so if you if you like partition
into like
uh smaller than like if you all if
everyone is
minorities then then it would just be
stuck forever
um until you find a majority and then
once you have a majority you can
like they the they automatically submit
like remove server
rpcs uh whenever they don't get a
response from someone so then the
cluster like shrinks until it like the
the
non-responding nodes disappear
uh i noticed in the demo example you
gave you had one person who wrote
two of the messages and saw uh
someone else who wrote the third message
and that meant that you could that the
person who wrote two messages could
always tell what that third person had
shared doesn't that sort of defeat the
purpose of your protocol
yeah uh yeah so the reason why was two
messages is because we were running
um you're running both of those
instances on
the same computer um that is that is a
an attack though where
you know you you have it you you start a
round where
one person is controlled by everyone um
well like where like five of the servers
you can five of them submitting messages
are controlled by everyone and then you
know who the last person is
but um i think so i mean we can
currently consider that like uh
byzantine or non-byzantine failure so
the clients are acting honestly and
they're not trying to
gain an unfair amount of advantage in
the system and then
the attacker is someone who's listening
to all the network traffic
okay so you're not worried about people
involved in the system underwriting it
you're only worried about people who are
like peeking
in on the system and driving it
yes or like kind of so i think we're
like decently confident
that like uh if if there are byzantine
participants
then uh the protocol will fail and it
will like fail
like explicitly like and we but but it's
like there are like so many different
attacks so we're like not
exactly certain that that is the case
but we think so
but it's like in that case so for the
attack that just got discussed then
where someone takes control of the
cluster and
it takes over all the and essentially is
all of the clients
except for one of them and if you're a
leader you can control presumably
control who gets added and removed from
the groups you could
make that happen would that be detected
by
your current system no no
not not when it's like n minus one uh so
we need at least like two
if we have like two honest uh people
then then that would be enough
uh because they would be like like if
they were just disconnected from each
other
they would they could know that um
yeah all right cool thank you
no time thanks very cool maybe uh mit
confessions will reach out
uh let's hear from the
fault tolerance project
maybe that's a bad way of summarizing it
no worries
so yeah hi everyone i'm ariel uh i've
been working on this project with france
for a bit now so let's see
i can share my screen
uh and so uh yeah as you can see here
um a project involves getting fall
tolerance for free at the 9p interface
and i'll sort of break down what this
means exactly
in the next few slides um we started by
looking at
serverless computations so if you've
heard of some uh things like
aws lambda um or uh
gcp uh or sorry google cloud functions
um essentially what this does is instead
of having to
set a bunch of vms and scale them uh
with request
your customer load and everything you
can just write a small stateless
function
uh deploys your application to a bunch
of small status functions which are
triggered over http requests
um and then aws or google cloud or
whoever your
service provider is will handle the
scaling and all the infrastructure
management for you
um and this is nice because in theory
data center operators can
balance resources more effectively they
can get higher utilization
um and in theory it's easier for
developers as well all you have to do is
uh
is you don't have to worry about all
this kind of infrastructure management
and and sort of having enough headroom
and your number of vms and everything to
handle spikes in customer load
and things like this however the reality
is not as
uh as nice as the theory um
is in the end
in current implementations actually
building these complex
applications is quite difficult um
uh and decomposing them into these
stateless functions is quite difficult
in part because these lambdas these
stateless functions
lack rich communication privileges um
which would be important to build
complex applications
so uh they can't directly communicate to
to each other and
therefore systems that try to utilize
serverless functions
have had to sort of build their own
custom communication
solutions like maybe setting up vms on
the side that they run
everyone talk through or talking through
uh storage systems like s3 and this
makes them inefficient and difficult for
developers to
actually put together in a sensible way
um
all this complexity causes data centers
to actually manage resources quite
poorly
and and
part of the problem is that we still
have all these data center
resources segmented into a bunch of
local name spaces which are disjoint and
and you can't share resources across
them
so what we were looking at uh was
reviving
some work uh from uh past decades uh
called plan nine
um and planning essentially uh provides
a plan for unifying
data center resources and providing some
single system image
what this means is essentially when you
write your application you don't have to
worry about
what runs on what machines about
provisioning
vms or anything like that or
making sure that certain parts of your
application run on certain vms it all
looks like one
giant's uh namespace to your application
um so
your application knows nothing about
what hardware it's actually running on
or where
um other services are in the data center
um
and the way this is achieved is
applications and services communicate
through
a global hierarchical namespace um
services and resources expose a uniform
file system like interface you don't
have to worry about
implementing and calling custom rpcs um
and so for example in this in
this tree you can see here um we
have the top level root level namespace
and then
under that we have three services
registered we have an s3 service which
um you can use to connect um your your
landers to s3 you can
access keys uh keys or s3 keys and
values
through that we have an in memory file
system and
scheduler and so i'll quickly
yeah so so this is what the uh what like
a
typical 9p namespace would look like
we have done some work to implement uh
sort of example of this 9p architecture
um we have like a zookeeper like
configuration service which
hosts the top-level name space we have
scheduler and
a bunch of these np servers 9p servers
um
what these do is they expose resources
and functionality such as
the if we go back here this s3 part of
the namespace you can
write a service which connects to some
s3 bucket
and exposes it to 9p and this would be
like a nine p server
um and the uh rpcs or the operations
that use to
uh to interact with these uh different
services are all
uh the nine p operations so it's a very
small
well-defined set of of operations that
uh
you can see a few of them here such as
read and write remove stat
it's a small number of canonical file
system operations
so quickly demo what this looks like um
so for example here i can start up car
infrastructure
so i can look into you can mount this
namespace right into linux
so i can see some services
and different name services that we've
mounted here for example if i look at
s3
this is actually connecting to uh
an s3 bucket that we have um
you guys can actually see the keys in
the s3 bucket just as files in your file
system um
this is what the the s3 bucket over here
so if i want to create
or write a new key for example all i
need to do is say
cat oh
to
so instead of having to use aws's custom
library in order to write s3 i can just
write a file system or do a file system
operation to create a file and write to
it
and then in s3 this actually
should show up as a new key now
so we have test 456 which we just wrote
um so
uh where does the fault tolerance part
come in here well as i mentioned before
all these 9p services have a very
well-defined uniform interface
um there are no customer rpcs and and
this sort of gives us a very unique
opportunity which is we can slice at
this 9p interface
um to replicate unmodified services so
if all if i am able to replicate all
these operations
to different server instances of a
service then
um the service gets replicated free
without having to modify it at all
um so this is what we did what i worked
on i
um implemented a chain replication based
uh
fault tolerance scheme um
i use name d as like a configuration
configuration service you can think of
this as like a
kind of zookeeper and i replicated two
different services
without any any modification an
in-memory file system
and a service which exposes
durable storage from uh from local
machines
and so i'll quickly show that that
so let me stop this
so for example
i can
so i can start up a bunch of replicas
so if i look into the 9p namespace
margin linux
uh you see this memphis replica here's
where these replicas register themselves
so we can see that we have five uh these
replicas up
i can write to one of them um
okay so i can write to one of the
replicas uh and then i can read from
another one of the replicas and we
should
uh get the same result out so i wrote
a small string to a file in the first
replica we can read from the last
replica we should get the same thing
back
i can even
crash one of the left replicas
so let's kill one of these guys
uh we can see that
you can see there are only four replicas
left now in the name space can then
write a different string to this file
and i should
yeah so so now despite
uh the failure uh the service
automatically reconfigured
um and the in-memory file system that
the services
uh is based off of did not have to be
modified at all you can just plug in any
new service you want to
that that implements this 9p interface
and it should work out of the box
so uh i think that's
i think that sort of concludes uh my
presentation and
i'd be happy to take any more questions
you guys might have
i regret not wearing my plan 9 shirt
this time
i should have done it i'm curious though
um so i worked on something that was
sort of similar earlier this semester
except there was no
replication it was just an ip services
under
linux box why this is sort of an offhand
question but why change replication
um i imagine there are other replication
schemes that are available
for this sort of a thing and in theory
because this is 9p you could probably
bind
all of these replicas over the same
namespace so they look like it's one
machine but
why chain replication yeah yeah
good question you could in theory do any
uh any replication scheme you'd like
um under the hood uh i just did chain
replication um
uh because it seemed like a simple
starting point i guess so we could also
throw this on top of a
raft interpretation like we had from
class or anything like that
that's something fundamental about the
choice
does your system support adding uh
additional replicas after it started
yeah great question uh so currently no
um
that's a work in progress um
uh but yeah currently we don't support
adding additional replicas out of the
box
this is an open question it's sort of
like that you may not have this is this
wasn't the express intent of the purpose
but one of the things that's really cool
about plan 9 and 9p is that
you treat network connections like their
files as well so
you're like you have like mfs you have
from when i saw a scheduler queue that
was implemented just a set of files
um do you and this is sort of an open
question because the the question of
whether network stuff over file
interfaces is scalable
is difficult to answer but do you also
implement this in sort of that way or do
you use more traditional policy
interfaces too
like when the clients use this thing
they presume they use traditional
sockets and things to communicate yeah
yeah
yeah no good question so yeah everything
so all the
clients and services uh communicate over
tcp
um at the moment um and yeah
it is a good question as to whether the
9p interface is actually going to be
performed enough for what we want to do
with it
um as far as we can see now uh there's
not
so we've done some performance
benchmarking to see how
well uh like we've written a scheduler
uh
over 9p um uh and we've done some
performance benchmarking to see how it
performs and it seems to not add a ton
of overhead at the moment but uh
we can imagine those trade-offs changing
for different types of services
and uh and as the scheduler becomes more
or less oversubscribed
sure i guess i guess to clarify so
sorry i'm taking up some taking up a lot
of your time but just briefly
the whole nine people if you if you were
able to
and this is again very open but if you
were able to treat network connections
as files you have replicas
right you could have something for each
card and then shard network traffic over
those network cards which
i guess this is serverless anyway so it
probably doesn't make that much of a
difference
yeah forget it because you already have
that handle for you
cool thank you thank you
all right so let's hear about some
verification stuff if you're ready
can you guys hear me okay yes all right
excellent so indeed uh i'm going to talk
to you about my project which is focused
on
modular verification for distributed
systems so
let's start by uh answering the obvious
question which is why bother with any
other stuff
and i think anyone that's worked on the
labs for eight to four
must have discovered at some point that
uh getting distributed systems right is
hard
there's a lot of non-determinism caused
by concurrency and network failure
uh and that makes it very difficult to
exhaust we test to make sure that
there's no corner case bugs
verification is an alternative to
alternative approach testing to try and
get
correctness and in principle it can
entirely rule out bugs
with verification you basically
mathematically model your system
and then prove some theorem about that
model
uh and you know one of the the downsides
of verification is that it's
quite a lot of work uh doing these you
know formal proofs is by no means easy
and even if it was easy uh verification
still wouldn't be a perfect silver
bullet
for one uh in verification you have to
make sure that you get your
specification right
uh if the the mathematical theorem
you're proving about your system
doesn't actually say what you really
wanted to say then what you've proved is
useless
and relatedly you have to make sure that
the model that you have for your system
is also complete uh if if you fail to
model
some execution that can happen in
reality but that you don't consider then
your theorem won't apply to to the real
world
uh and some of you that are familiar
with some uh distribution verification
work might say
oh don't we already know how to do this
uh indeed distributed systems have
always been hard and
people have recently worked on projects
to try to verify
actual implementations of distributed
systems so some of these projects
include iron fleets and verde
however these projects didn't focus much
on modularity
or trying to prove reusable
specifications for components of systems
to try to build more complicated systems
out of them and
uh i'd argue that that's the way that
distributed systems are actually built
the way you build a distributed system
is by oftentimes using building blocks
like key value services and lock
services or zookeeper
and putting them together with some you
know added code and novel functionality
to build your more interesting and more
useful system
and our sort of thesis if you will is
that verification
can and should exploit this
compositionality
uh as one sort of target goal we aim to
prove specifications for
clients of systems prior work like iron
flute and verdi
simply reason about what the behavior of
the actual server side system looks like
and don't explicitly model or prove
anything about what the client programs
actually do and oftentimes there's a bit
of lodge in the client
that's crucial for getting correctness
and the approach we use is to use uh
advances in concurrent separation logic
which is a uh compositional means of
reasoning about concurrent programs
that's
lately become uh popular for you know
popular and demonstrate to be successful
at reasoning about real code so the
first example
that we worked on was verifying a
sharded key value system
uh the keys in this are you know
statically split up into shards
and shards themselves can be moved
between the shard servers
so it's very similar to lab 4 of 824
except that it's not replicated so
there's no there's no raft running in
this
and uh it's purely in memory uh besides
that uh
our system also has shard servers and a
coordinator server and
the coordinator is the one that tells
other charge servers to move shards
between themselves as you nodes want to
join or
as you need to re-balance uh the
top-level library that we
provide and that we want to prove a
specification for is
you know we call it a kd clerk which is
just a client object that
one can use and and can call these three
functions on
uh to actually interact with the server
so that you know there's a put you you
say what value you want to put in the
key
there's a get which will return the
current value in the key and then
there's a conditional put which will
only put the new value
if the old value is the expected one
and we aim to basically implement and uh
you know implement a linearizable key
value service and to prove a
specification
that shows that it's linearizable uh the
way you do this in the separation logic
style is basically by writing down
specifications that look a lot like this
so this basically says that if uh you
know the the object ck
is a key value clerk then you have
you know specifications for the put and
get functions that say
for example if you start running the put
function
with the precondition that uh k key has
value v
w then by the end of it you'll know that
k key key k
as value v uh similarly uh
if you do a get and you know that uh key
k has value v at the beginning then
that's the thing that's going to be
returned
and you're still going to know that
that's the value in the key i though
these specifications look pretty simple
and like you know you might think like
of course that's what a key value
service does
and that's sort of the point that these
uh top-level client specifications
are as simple as they can be and and
basically hide all the details of the
fact that there's multiple shard servers
and that
this clerk library might need to talk to
servers multiple times it might need to
refresh its information
about which server owns the you know
which keys uh
and uh we basically uh you know prove to
spec that allows you to forget all that
and
use the key value servers just by
calling these puts and gets and having
this idealized notion of what the
uh the key value mapping actually looks
like so i won't talk too much more in
detail about what the actual proof looks
like
um and instead should focus to focus
towards uh
the next thing we were interested in
doing which is actually doing something
with a bit of fault tolerance to this
so like i mentioned the key value
service itself is not replicated and
isn't false tolerant and so we started
by trying to figure out how to verify
the simplest possible uh false tolerance
sort of protocol
and we basically started with single
degree paxos singing through
degree backs is a classic protocol for
getting cassettes on a single value
so whereas with the raft you can get you
replicate an entire log and you keep
appending new entries to log
single degree paxos is the the crux of
multitaxes and
basically functions of right once
register uh if you want to
uh set the the value to something you
can attempt to uh to rights to it
and if someone else beat you then uh you
know that's too bad for you and now the
value's already been decided
and it's never going to change again uh
so we implemented and partially verified
a single degree practice implementation
and basically proved a specification
that shows that it's a write once
register
and the key idea in the in the
specification and the proof
is that when you commit a value in in
single degree paxos
you get irrevocable knowledge of what
that committed value is
and you basically know that from here on
out if anybody else ever sees any
committed value
it's going to be the exact same thing
that you see right now
and thinking about this a little bit
after we worked on the proof a bit
we started thinking that uh we sort of
noticed that there's a slight
generalization you can do to
single degree paxos which uh we call
monotone taxos for lack of a better name
and the idea is rather than uh gaining
knowledge about the exact value upon a
commit
you instead uh can we modify the
protocol
so that you only gain a knowledge about
a lower bound on the value
so uh basically when you uh
commit to value for example if you come
at the number 15 to this right once
register
rather than knowing that 15 is the only
value anybody else in the future is ever
going to see
you'll know that any value that people
see in the future has committed is going
to be at least 15.
and so of course doing this requires
having some notion of what
larger than actually means for the value
type
and the the key idea is a replicant
can always find out what the the latest
committed value is
and choose to increase it and other
replicas can continually find out
larger and larger lower bounds on
basically what the value so far
is and once we sort of came up with this
idea of monotone paxos
we uh realized immediately that we can
do log replication with this
so the the set of values v uh
we can choose to simply be all the logs
that you might want to replicate
your logs of operations and we can
define one log to be bigger than another
one
if the uh the smaller one is a prefix of
you know if l1 is a prefix of l2
uh and this basically allows us to you
know this sort of yields a protocol
which you'll sort of have to trust me
since i'm not really showing you the
code for it
uh in which you can gain information
about what the prefix of the log is
and over time you can add new things to
log by making it larger and larger
and that's pretty much exactly what we
mean when we say log replication
the problem with this exact protocol is
that naively if we sort of
implement the most naive version of this
monotone taxes thing
you would need to send around the full
log on every single rpc
in single degree paxos you send around
the full value on all the rpcs
and the the you know uh trivial general
generalization of it to monitor
access would have you send around the
full log that's not really useful
because logs can get larger and larger
and larger and
you know the beginning of log is no
longer relevant uh by the time
everybody's agreed to commit it and all
that
so you could try to optimize this by
only passing around a suffix of the log
and indeed uh there's a whole you know
sequence of optimizations you can make
to this
monotone paxos based log replication and
as you start doing more and more of this
you'll realize that this looks exactly
like raft
and in fact uh we aimed basically to use
our idea of monotone taxes
not to implement a new replication
protocol but rather to
verify a raft-like system so you know we
have this proof for single-degree paxos
we have this clear generalization to
this monotone taxes thing
and our hope is that we can use the idea
of monotone paxos
to basically verify raft directly as
opposed to relying on the
much more complicated correctness
arguments for raft
uh that have been described in sort of
other state machine type styles
um so this is sort of our you know
future work uh
and the key takeaway i sort of want to
leave
leave you guys with is that reasoning
both formal and informal about
distributed systems should be as
compositional as writing code
the way you scale writing code is
modularity and that's the way reasoning
should also scale
and that's all from my presentation i'm
happy to take questions
if the answer is too long you cannot
like link me in the chat but i was
curious i know there's a class in this
but do you have any resources for
somebody interested in getting into
fv from a software perspective like any
brief recommendations
um are you so yeah i guess i'm not quite
sure what the
so are you interested in like we should
message afterwards but like if you're
interested i guess
in uh the sort of most lightweight
versions of verification
i think daphne is a great tool to learn
because it's a pretty simple starting
point you can write
sort of real code and get a feel for
things um i think a lot of it a lot of
verification is pretty academic and
not super close to being really useful
with verification like this
uh so i'm not sure how useful it really
would be for real software engineering
just yet
but the hope is that one day it will be
thanks
did you implement uh this version of
paxos you're talking about
this monotone paxos thing uh
so yeah i implemented rather than
implementing like a generic monotone
factors thing which wouldn't really make
sense and go anyways
i implemented directly the log
replication over monotone paxos
so in you know in this mono this
monotone log replication thing all the
rpc center on the full log
so if you run it for a long time it's
going to get way too slow because the
rpcs are sending too much stuff but yeah
i did implement it uh and i think we're
working on actually trying to reason
about it
basically did you manage to
figure out how forward it actually ends
up being or how well it works in
practice
so i think the exact code that we have
right now is not code you'd want to run
and my like in a sense it ought to be as
performant as raft sort of is and
we don't really have an optimized
implementation of it so i haven't
actually bothered getting performance
numbers for it at all
it's probably pretty slow not really
sure
great thank you um yeah even if we
verify my programs i'm sure almost a
lock somewhere
um but let's hear from pp2
now
all right can everyone see great
so uh we are the pigeon protocol 2 uh me
jimmy jay timmy
and we are we present a simple
distributed file system
and the reason we selected a distributed
file system is that users oftentimes
want to store data privately
in a really accessible way without the
implications of using a cloud company
where you don't own your own data
so we wanted to create a solution where
you self-host your own data in
a fault tolerant distributed manner on
commodity hardware
and our file system is really similar to
franjopani except that it uses raft
instead of pedal
and the file system is on the servers
instead of the clients
in terms of file system parameters we
also have a 40 4096 byte block size and
a two
megabyte maximum file size we
theoretically have a 32 gigabyte maximum
disk capacity
however this is actually constrained by
your ram so if you only have eight
gigabytes of ram
uh you would have however much is left
over after your
uh after whatever your system takes up
and we support as many
servers and clients as we can within
reason uh obviously the more servers and
clients that you add
uh due to locking contention there will
be less performance as you start to
access the
same file over and over again and uh
in terms of performance well we were
very heavily focused on availability and
crash recovery so we didn't
we didn't measure performance and we
think it's probably pretty bad because
our
system is built on top of raft which is
not known to be the most uh performant
of systems
so uh over to j so
again performance is not the biggest
thing that we have but we do have very
very strong consistency guarantees
in particular we enforce posix
consistency which is a form of strong
consistency you usually see on local
file systems
so we enforce the invariant that after a
file write after you do a successful
file right
any read of your previously written
bytes from anywhere will return the data
specified by that previous right
similarly any new rights over that data
will be will result in
visible overrides of that data from the
perspective of other readers
so in order to achieve this we have a
data mode journal that is built into
this sort of block layer
uh that is again distributed with raft
and replicated
and which is effectively a right ahead
log that guarantees the atomicity of
rights
strong semantics in the presence of
crashes the same as raft pretty much
and also the concur the consistency
model that we offer above
so servers also in order to help with
this we issue distributed locking so we
can have this very primitive block cache
as you would see in a local file system
and also
you have you know leases to make sure
that there's mutually exclusive access
to all of these blocks
right so to allow our clients to use our
file system we created a posix like
interface
where users can interact with files we
mainly have four functions open close
read and write
open and close are pretty explanatory
they just
open and close file descriptors on our
file system
um read it just takes a file descriptor
and uh
reads a fixed number of bytes at the
current file position
write also takes a file descriptor and
reads uh and flushes
oh sorry write takes a um file
descriptor and just
writes the data to the file notice
but it's in a different way than a
normal posix right because
a um instead flushes the buffer copy
of the file and then appends the new
data on this so
instead of a normal posix right where we
just write to a file um descriptor
with a buffer and the number of bytes to
write it does what i just said instead
and we have a demo to represent uh
clients interacting with the system
so this is just a quick demonstration of
our file system being run both
serially and concurrently so what's
going to happen is console 1 or i should
say
left console is going to open up a file
called
tt just testing thing um
it's going to write something to the
file and then the console on the right
is going to read from it afterwards
per the consistency model they should
see the same thing as
the left console wrote and indeed
after a minute
we see that okay so the next thing
that's going to happen is
both console 1 and console 2 are going
to try to flush their local copies of
this file at the same
time this is not a traditional posix
write they're both taking the copies of
the file that they have
and trying to put them onto disk at the
same time so it's sort of like two
writes from offset zero
one of these is going to win and we can
look at the log
on the left console as it commits and
actually see after a moment
that both transactions run concurrently
they both take up different parts of the
log
but at the end of the day the left
console's transaction is going to win
so it was completely atomic everything
works
i think you got muted sorry i muted
due to time there are more there are
some limitations and features we can add
to our file system
so firstly we only have uh one root
directory so adding more will definitely
be a plus
um next we only we we should persist
blocks
to disk rather than ram because that's
what we're currently doing
but we should also consider um that what
we're doing has a lot of rights so it
could be pretty bad
if we just keep writing doing having a
lot of writes for just one operation we
also
only have direct inode blocks rather
than uh
having direct and indirect inodes so
that would be a plus to add those
and secondly um there should be a better
way for clients to interact
with this file system so there could be
a fuse layer or they could just be
better positive compliance in general
that concludes our presentation
you want to talk a little bit about how
you tested this
sure so we had a pretty at your
recommendation we had a pretty broad set
of tests we had so to begin each
component so each
you know the block layer right your
individual graph key values we had to
journal
and we had all these things we basically
mocked every layer underneath
each layer we were testing and tested uh
did sort of
unit testing you can't really call it
unit testing once you get high enough
um because you're so reliant on lower
layers being correct but
we we did as best we could from there we
did integration testing and
you know wrote out a set of partitions
one of those partitions is sort of what
you just saw
the most interesting of them there were
five of them you can see them in our
git repository and then we also to what
degree we could so
this didn't necessarily entirely work
just some because of some of like the
time limitations that we had but
we also attempted to do some stress
testing obviously performance numbers
aren't great
because it's not supposed to be great
but and as best we could so we're pretty
sure this is at least correct this has
been verified here
so one interesting thing is that you're
basically shooting for actually slightly
stronger
uh consistency property that posits
actually requires where there's two
proceed right into a single file there's
actually not much that
actually the rights actually have to uh
have to do
yes that was kind of accidental
but we were so it's kind of stronger
yeah it was accidental but it happened
so we were like cool
it worked the sort of i mean i think the
part of the so what sort of happened was
that we guarantee
we i posix makes the guarantees i talked
about but we also make the guarantee
that the block rights are all atomic and
i think that's why
we get this sort of stronger consistency
because of the whole
journaling thing yes you could get your
right overwritten if you do it at the
same time but it's always going to be
clean
if you have aggressive caching you might
run in and don't write immediately to
the
log then you might get different
behaviors right
correct this is why we don't
aggressively cache we have a block cache
of size one
awesome thank you very cool all right
our last group
is presenting a game framework whenever
you're ready
take it away
all right so we're sure that many of you
have played multiplayer games um in
quarantine
when you're bored so let's imagine that
you are
a small indie game depth company and
you're trying to develop a multiplayer
game
possibly that has either several
different rooms
something like chat penguin where you
might interact with other players in the
same room
or perhaps it's like matchmaking based
where you're in the lobby with several
other players
well so traditionally how these work is
that everything
goes it gets processed on one central
server but that central server is a
bottleneck
if every single player has to connect to
that server to handle the game logic
that server could get uh bottlenecked by
the number of requests that come through
and also if that server goes down there
goes your game
so what we're proposing is to create a
distributed game framework that
instead of that's also fall tolerant so
instead of having all the processing
being on that central server
we actually distribute the game logic
processing to several different worker
servers
but on top of that to be fault tolerant
uh so when
one of these like worker servers goes
down we need to be able to handle that
uh game logic and further move the
players um to some other server
workers so as part of that we need to
actually balance latency with fault
tolerance because
if we make everything stay fall tolerant
we
might run into um like each move taking
a long time to process so that's why
we're introducing pinguino
which is our fault our game framework
that addresses
all of the previous issues with
distribution frameworks
to dive a little bit into the system of
our framework let's
imagine the game club penguin so in club
penguin
a user that is assigned into one room or
one region
only really cares about talking and
interacting with other users
and the objects in that one room and
they don't really need to care about
anything else that's happening in
another room so there's no reason to
have
the request of every user be processed
by one centralized servers
so instead we decided that we will have
all of these
requests be processed across multiple
workers
in order to do this we have workers that
are assigned to different regions so if
a player is in one region
they might be talking with the worker
that is assigned to that region so for
example in here
the penguin that is in worker that is
assigned to the region for worker two
we'll talk with worker two only
but then the one in the worker end will
talk with worker
and additionally we mentioned we decided
that this wouldn't the
the relation between worker and regents
doesn't necessarily have to be a
one-to-one mapping
for some rooms that might be less
popular and have less traffic
it's possible that a worker can handle
multiple of those
so there's that type of relation that we
need to keep track of
and so in order to keep track of this we
do need one centralized
server which is the coordinator so the
coordinator will be keeping track of all
these mappings
and some of the mapping includes the
region to worker relation
as well as region the worker to their
replica
um uh relation as well as
the players itself so for the fault on
aspect we have that the workers will
have to replica
each and surely we'll type talk a little
bit more about
what kind of information is sent to the
workers
from their like to their republic later
but additionally
the coordinator because it is that one
centralized server it is also a possible
uh failure point so we have a
coordinator backup
and in here the coordinator's main role
is just to keep track of all of these
relations
of the game states so information about
the coordinator that changes for those
relation
will be sent to the coordinator backup
before being processed
uh completely completely so now
with this although we have that one
server the bulk of the traffic for games
usually
is players making moves and sending
requests to process those moves
and those are now divided across
multiple workers and the coordinator is
in charge of just the mapping and
sending heartbeat
to ensure that the workers are still
alive and can handle any failure cases
yep so in the case that a worker goes
down uh we have the coordinator handling
the reassignment of the players who are
in that worker
and because the coroner manages only the
region mappings
it's also easy for us to move around
regions when one of
us say like one worker gets overloaded
this allows us to perform some amount of
load balancing
as we mentioned earlier um cool so i'll
move on to what the developer api looks
like because another key feature that we
wanted was
for this framework to be easy to use for
a developer trying to
code a new game in it so we treat the
game as a state machine essentially
and so any move that the player makes
actually fits into one of two different
types of moves
so i mentioned earlier that we're trying
to balance a bit of
latency with fault tolerance so in order
to provide
a sort of choice for the developer we
have two separate
commands that we expose to the developer
the first is send fast move
so this fast move makes sure that the
move gets to the replicas as soon as
possible so the move gets
processed as fast as possible on the
worker
on the other hand we have send stable
move which actually
is a more fall tolerance move that we
expose to the
developer and this ensures this is
mainly used for
game critical logic changes such as say
transactions
so if you're buying something you don't
want like if you
if you've already spent that money you
want to make sure that you get like
whatever you
spent that money on in your game and so
we guarantee that if that move gets
fully processed
and on the game it's uh it's
stored on both of the replicas which
ensures that if the worker that you're
talking to goes down and the player gets
transferred to a new worker
that new worker will be able to
reconstruct the game including that
transaction
this guarantee isn't done for a fast
move which prioritizes the latency
aspect but you can also see here the
move structs
that the developer defines um are pretty
general so
in the game that will be that we kind of
developed as a
toy demo for our framework it's kind of
a chat penguin like interface
so each player is in several different
um
rooms and so within each room there's a
chat window that you can
talk to to interact with another player
um so the two type of main moves that
you can make in this game
are first like a move so a developer
would just define
like the xy and the username of the
player moving
um and so the chat message is kind of
the same where it's just like a shot
message that you send into the window
and so we in our game we've made chat
messages
a stable move and move as a fast move
so even if like say one move gets
dropped it's okay if you're like kind of
kind of teleports
but um we don't want chat messages to
randomly disappear because they could be
important messages
so with that i'll move on to the demo
which is a little bare bones but
should show off the functionality
so we have our super minimalist front
end um
and so when we move around the penguin
we can see that its first sun is a fast
move
um and the replica that same move gets
sent to the other replicas assigned to
the main worker so right now we're on
worker zero
it gets replicated to worker one and two
so we have two copies
um and the game server then receives
that change
and so then it can process that locally
and then
if we send a chat message
we also have uh the player username
identified with the chat messages sent
but this is actually a stable move so
it's not visible in the vlogs but the
stable moves wait until
those moves are actually replicated to
the workers it's not easy to see here
because
normally there might be some amount of
lag um
but when we do introduce some amount of
lag into the network the stable move
takes longer than
it does and now move it back to
some future work that we want to
implement
in terms of the back end uh one
additional thing that we would like to
do
is to allow the users to move across
different rooms
so right now uh upon a user um joining
the game and it being initialized they
are assigned to one room
but ideally if they want to move across
to it if they want to move to a
different room
then they should be able to talk to the
coordinator to be like hey i'm going to
go to this region now can we load up the
information
of the game state from that region and
then also now i'm going to start talking
to a new worker
and additionally we hinted at this
earlier where
we wanted to deal with region-based
worker load balancing so the reason why
we had that
uh why we did not go for one-to-one
mapping with
worker to region was to allow for this
uh
future work and we hope to be able to do
that in order to control
uh how much load each worker will be
based with
thank you so much
um so are your i guess you have two
actions sending a message
and uh moving so those actions are all
atomic
right are they like yeah
they should be they get sequentially
processed um and since they're like
individual moves
they uh most of the time they only
modify like some
variables and they acquire the locks on
those variables before they make the
moves
so you you said earlier that you have a
coordinator and coordinator backup
and the replicas can talk to either of
them
what happens if you have a network
partition that separates the coordinator
and some set of replicas
from the coordinator backup and some
other set of replicas so the coordinator
back up
in case of a network partition the
workers will be
kind of lost like the coordinator it's
not a matter of the worker being able to
talk to either the coordinator or the
coordinator backup
um they'll only be able to talk to the
coordinator and if a coordinator goes
down then the backup gets
brought up to actually start processing
so in that case of a network partition
i don't think we will be like the
workers that are isolated and away from
that
coordinator will not be able to be
processed with
the like the coordinator itself in terms
of the user side like
it can still be processed because the
player just needs to continue talking to
that worker
it's just that if there's any changes in
the region like this the state of the
game as a whole
that won't be processed yet yeah um
additionally i want to note that
uh if we have like a partition um the
coordinator backup essentially acts as a
coordinator for all the workers that it
can
talk to and this is fine because we want
the game to be like still running for
all of the regions in the workers that
the coordinator backup is talking to
uh this mainly becomes a problem when
they do reunite
and in this case um the coordinator
backup then uh takes all of its
uh like data and it can send it to the
coordinator and the coordinator can
locally resolve it because there is kind
of a an original coordinator and a
coordinator backup um and they know that
the backup was a backup of the
coordinator because it's stored
locally but
if the coordinator backup becomes a
coordinator then wouldn't it
for example say oh i need to make sure
that we have active replicas for all
these
um rooms that the that are in other side
of the partition
wouldn't you have the same room hosted
on both sides of the partition and be
able to diverge
uh no because each room belongs only to
like one worker um so like
so i guess like each room like can't
like the replicas for the rooms um would
get abandoned so
essentially what happens is like if a
worker like in the case of a partition
the coordinator wouldn't be able to
access like a worker that's in the other
partition
um so what happens is it oh i think
it'll like
move the replicas over but because the
players also can't contact that worker
um none of the moves would be processed
and so the the more recent replicas
after the the partitioned heals would be
prioritized
when healing that network
uh why did you decide on that api with
move and um sending a message
uh so specifically for this api
uh we wanted two different types of
moves two distinct types of moves
uh to demonstrate one with the fast move
and one with the stable move
ideally stable move is used more uh
like rarely and used more for
transactions that where it's okay for it
to take
longer but we want it to not be dropped
at all uh the easiest way to replicate
this in a like a simple front end was
with a chat message
um so it's kind of arbitrary but moves
for sure should be fast because
uh like we don't want it to be laggy
because
players move a lot
thank you
awesome thanks so much uh that concludes
the presentations great job everyone
this was uh this is pretty exciting
i have one more question for an old
presentation uh
if that's possible yep come here
um so for the leader i'm sorry for the
distributed election system um
i'm not familiar a lot with cryptography
but
i guess the system where you sum up all
the results of the election
on a vote on a counter server
this wouldn't that hide group attacks
for example if
i have two servers and then i vote for
different people on both servers but
then i coordinate with someone else
to also vote in the other way around
will eventually get the same vote vector
but i would have voted maliciously
against i guess
in this case it wouldn't change the
vote results or like the election result
but
i guess i would have acted incorrectly
so are there checks to make sure
everybody voted correctly
at each server yeah yeah
sorry so we actually don't handle
malicious voting which was which is
which is pretty big
and you know arguably pretty important
for a real world voting system
um but yeah i think
like you know the scope of the project
that we had and that we set out
uh it was just a little like too
complicated um
so we yeah yeah i think
we focus more like on the distributed uh
systems uh part
but if we wanted to like provide more uh
security like and for security
using for example like an idea that we
thought but then decided to not uh
do uh was having like a public ledger
where you can like
give a zero knowledge proofs that they
what you're posting like
adds up and is what you're saying that
it is and thinks of these things to
handle malicious
participants
yeah since we're running a little bit
late let me uh
let's end the class in principle anybody
wants to stick around of course
feel free to stick around uh i wanted to
say one or two things before closing
since it's our last class meeting
uh first of all i want to thank all of
you for participating even though it's
another cover semester
uh i feel i've interacted with many of
you uh
either from email or indirectly and
exchanged lots of information and i'd
love to see you at some point in person
and actually know who you are um the
uh but i appreciate all the
participation the second thing i want to
thank the tas
uh you know it's an awesome set of tas
as you probably have realized
uh probably for many you they figured
out some bugs and helped you get through
the labs
and so i ran applause for the tas
i'm very fortunate with this kind of
quality
and uh i guess the last thing i want to
say is uh i guess good luck on the final
and uh hopefully not too bad and
and i hope you had learned something in
684 and uh
enjoyed it at the same time and anyone
who wants to stick around please
stick around and uh you know more
questions you want to ask to the
different teams uh if the teams can
stick around too that'd be wonderful
otherwise this is the end
at least for the class meetings for
eight to four thank you all
thank you yeah thank you so much thank
you
thank you thank you so much
um sorry uh quick question
um one last question now
for real uh
i i um i was wondering actually for
logistics for the exam
um i emailed you yeah yeah yeah yeah
i'll get back to you yeah yeah i
haven't gotten to the point yet we're
dealing with the logistics of the exam
a couple i'm aware of you uh and two
free audits
awesome we have a plan we haven't
executed yet nor
shared any details oh yeah but it will
happen
sounds good
make sure you reach out
all right uh perfect thank you so much
for for everything for the class and
you know for the tas
thank you very much for all the quests
very fun i learned a lot thank you thank
you for participating
asking all those questions appreciate it
yes thank you this was this is an
awesome class i really appreciate it
thank you thanks for being active during
the class
[Music]
okay i guess that's probably it so i
guess let's
stop the recording