okay thank you okay so uh
that's a good afternoon good morning
good evening good night wherever you are
uh and i guess welcome to the last week
of the semester
uh so there's two more class meetings uh
today which we're going to be talking
about block stack and on thursday
uh well we we get a report from
the different projects from a number of
the project groups in
6824 and so today is basically the
last paper discussion uh
and so the topic is uh you know the
system that uh
we assigned for uh what i signed for
reading which is box tech
and really what blocks that represents
is an approach to
building decentralized
applications
and with decentralized what we mean here
is that
uh unlike in centralized websites you
know the sort of website owns the data
in decentralized application
applications the the system is set up in
a way that the users actually keep
control over the data
and not the websites and so this form
sort of a
trend in the last you know this is the
final lecture in this series or three
lectures on
decentralized distributed systems you
know we talked about
uh logs and signing or saying logs as a
way of constructing
these decent life storage systems uh we
sell bitcoin to see
uh as an example of how you can achieve
a consensus
in a decent life systems with entrusted
participants or byzantine participants
and so today we're taking one more step
up and actually look at like how you can
actually even build you know complete
applications
other than just crypto currency
the decentralized applications have a
long history uh
in the early 2000s late 90s there was a
lot of
to do around peer-to-peer applications
uh which had a decent like architecture
like napster
uh you know more recently uh you know
you're probably familiar with key base
which has a decentralized design uh
or a solid uh you know and
of course box tech and so there's a you
know quite a bit of activity
in this uh space of decentralized
applications
um the block stack is interesting uh
from
from the perspective of actually writing
decentralized applications but also
uh is an example of sort of a
non-currency use
or non-money use uh
of uh bitcoin of the blockchain
the bitcoin blockchain
uh and we'll see uh you know there are a
number of
aspects that are interesting than blocks
tech but the the key thing that this
what the paper focuses on
is actually uh naming how to build
uh a distributed decentralized naming
system
uh and of course the naming systems are
widely used you know think of dns
uh i think about where you know
kerberos you know there's tons and tons
of different uh
naming systems out there you know widely
used and this is just a different design
and where the most interesting part of
it again
is it's decentralized
now this lecture is a little bit
different than uh
sort of the preceding lectures or many
of the proceedings like there's many
machining lectures i sort of have to
flavor well here's a hard technical
problem
here's the solution to solve that
particular problem and
uh here we're in a slightly sort of
different position uh
there's a hard technical problem and we
have to build decentralized applications
uh but it's not you know even 100 clear
that is exactly you know the right thing
to do to build this central application
so it's extremely intriguing
um and it's also not clear that like box
vector is just the right solution to do
so
um and so it's much more uh experimental
uh you know blocksec does actually have
a user community and
but you know it's not like yet an
overwhelming success
and a demonstration that this is a the
right way to go so
in that sense uh this is
uh this paper in some sense is more
thought provoking
than giving actually a definite answer
to a particular technical problem
and so uh in some ways you know this is
a more of a
topic that sort of uh lends itself to a
larger debate
about you know the different views on
this kind of kind of design
and so uh during lecture if we get to
the
would we prefer to be fine actually you
know to have quite a bit of discussion
on different aspects and i don't think
there's going to be one right answer
and so anytime you have a question about
or want to argue about a particular
aspect of sort of these decentralized
app designs you know
speak up okay
um so maybe before uh you know
talking about decentralized apps you can
just quickly revisit you know actually
what's sort of the common paradigm to
actually build websites or build web
applications right and that's really
using centralized websites
the sites made itself might be
distributed across multiple data centers
across the world
but the architecture or the design of
the site is you know centralized you
know where we have
you know here's your typical website uh
it has
some applications and code you know
whether
gmail you know whatever twitter or
facebook uh
and uh that operates on a database
uh that contains you know user data
and we might actually have different
users interacting you know with the
sitting by web browser and user one
two uh they interact you know through
the application with the website you
know they you know create data the data
is stored in the database
uh other users may view the data and the
application displays basically you know
that data to
uh you know inside of the web browser
and you know the data might be
you know blog posts
tweets
piazza posts photos
perhaps even more sort of sensitive you
know medical
medical records
etc and basically you know the
application we're running on the site
you know to transform you know that data
from all the different users
uh into something that's interesting to
look at where basically integrating for
example the timeline
of you know many users into a single
timeline percentage to the user
uh you know organizing the tweets you
know doing ups and down votes
et cetera et cetera and
you know one sort of distinguishing
feature uh of this
sort of design is that the application
and the data's are bundled you know
they're only the control
of the application site you know whether
it's you know facebook twitter
you know google or any you know website
and really the interface between the
user or
the dividing line between the user and
the website is basically you know html
or the ui
now the application basically computes
you know whatever the user is going to
see and that's going to be displayed
inside of the browser
of course the application might actually
run inside of the browser not like you
know javascript but others are not
really
pertinent to this particular discussion
um you know it's still the application
is under control of the website you know
the programmers of the website write the
application
and the application basically you know
manipulates the dom you know fields from
inside of the web browser
and so from the user point of view the
interaction
the interface you know between the
defining interface between the
website and and
in the browser is still sort of html
and so this you know just this design
clearly is overwhelmingly successful
uh you know most websites a year
probably
actually probably all of the websites
you probably use are you know sort of
following this particular design
and then one reason for you know this
very successful design is we'll talk a
little bit more later is you know
because of the tight integration between
the application and the data and the
data from the different users so the
application has easy access to all the
users
uh data from different users and
integrated to me in creative and
interesting ways
um but there are you know you know it's
not completely perfect
you know this design and um and so those
are things that you know
you might wish could be slightly better
uh
and in some sense decentralized
applications is a response to those uh
sort of things that are
and it might be not 100 desirable and so
for one
and here's a very simple observation uh
you can really not create another
application you know so the
the the site decides actually how the
app looks like you know and that's the
ui you're going to get
uh and which is sort of very different
than
uh let's say uh on
your running application during your
laptop you know example you want to
modify and edit
the effects file but you get to choose
which browser or editor you're going to
use you know whether you may use emacs
you know vim
you know you can have all kinds of
culture wars about which one is better
than the other
but you get an option to choose which
one you want to use
and in this case you know that's just
not the case uh you're using gmail you
don't have
gmail is not the best example the
twitter you know twitter's going to
decide actually how the application is
going to look like
uh the reason why gmail might not be the
best example is because you can actually
download your email maybe you know
through imap and then run your own
uh email program uh but from any website
you know the the user in the application
data very controlled and you
have no control over it um
the website you know may change the
rules on who can see
and uh what data and it might actually
do without really telling you
and so you don't really have full
control over actually who
who sees your data but furthermore you
know the website actually might use it
you know your data to
uh you know generate revenue or whatever
to decide which ads actually display
and uh again basically snooping over
your data
right or in the worst case you know
maybe a bad employee
actually just snips over your data and
that's really sort of outside of your
control there's nothing you really can
do about it you know you gave the
website the data
that's theirs now and so this is
sort of the so these sort of pain points
uh you know it makes people wonder you
know is there a way of
designing systems then really not
don't follow this you know paradigm but
you know follow this paradigm of
decentralized applications
um and so in
this world view you know whatever we're
still in our internet the cloud
uh but you know we have storage
providers
and storage providers are basically
nothing really um you know sophisticated
where they don't really run app code
they just purely provide storage
you know ways of you know maybe it's
like your google drive or whatever
or uh amazon s3 but basically they're
sort of dumb
you know uh bid holders uh
the data maybe you know the user
probably wants to encrypt the data
but basically the real goal here is that
the user decides you know which storage
for
where the data lives and it keeps under
the control of the user
so whatever you know storage rider s3
might have you know users one data
um another storage divider might
actually have user two's data
or stores you know data on behalf of
user two
uh u2 and users f3 may actually encrypt
it so that the storage provider can
actually not read it
and control like who can actually uh
decrypt the data
and then you know the applications
really are in the control of the
user themselves and so you know when i'm
using a user here
you want workstation or laptop it runs
in an application
and you know here's you too
there's also another application may
actually be looking at maybe the same
data but like a slightly different
version of the application whatever one
photo viewer and another photo viewer
and basically to construct you know what
is actually
shown to the user you know the
application will fetches
you know data you know from different
users for example if you do
share the photos with u1 uh
then you know the applications would
integrate the photoshop you want to u2
by extracting or retrieving the
photos from the the different storage
providers
and here really what the sort of
dividing line is between users
and the dividing line is
is really this
there's sort of a dividing line between
the application and the storage so
there's a
storage api you know it has to sort of
be
uniform because many different
applications are going to use the same
storage i device you know maybe this
application
that creates to-do lists uh maybe it's a
photo list maybe it's a
twitter clone that this retrieves the
tweets from different users and
integrates them
and presents them to the user
and it's really that sort of single
storage api or
that that actually provides
the dividing line between the
applications
and the data and of course that source
api has to be quite general purpose you
can support multiple applications
but also has to allow sharing between uh
different application between different
users and different applications
no modulo or the permissions right
and so you know let's say you wanted to
uh build uh sort of a sharia
to-do list
then you know between user one and user
two then
let's look at this from the perspective
of usual one you know probably there
would be some operation
uh or some sharing operations in user
two and usually one saying like yeah you
know here's
the names of the my to-do list um
and you know user one can then download
you know the
user two's uh to-do list uh maybe check
you know the signature
on the file to verify that data was
indeed you know written by user two
and then you know integrate you know
that uh with its own
uh to-do list and you know present to
user one
uh a shared to-do list that contains
both the user ones and you should choose
to do items um
so that's sort of the general uh
view of actually building these
this decentralized architecture for
applications
any questions so far
okay so this is so so far hopefully
we've seen that you know
this address is one of the sort of the
major you know pain points for
the centralized approach but basically
the users you know stay in control of
the data
uh it's not owned by a particular site
anymore and the users decide
who uh which applications and who
actually get
access to data i know that's a desirable
uh
property um but you know the this whole
design is also with its you know set of
challenges
and so let me lay out some of them and
we'll focus on a few of them in the
context of block stack
and so those are two i think broad
categories of challenges
one sort of on the business side you
know what is the revenue model
you know what will uh you know get these
applications actually being adopted
and you know pay people money to
actually develop the applications
and so that they actually become really
good and
uh and people are excited about using
them
i'm not really gonna you know kind of
talk about that at all
uh uh but instead you know i wanna
motion focus on the technical challenges
and there are several of them
one is you know we go back to this sort
of picture here before
uh you know the storage api is sort of
the you know key
uh interface and uh you know the
interface has to be minimal it has to be
uh general purpose enough uh but in
typically it's actually you know it's
not the same thing
as you know the api that basically sits
here uh
you know between the application and the
database
let's do that hold on a second
okay hopefully everybody has seen
screening of the wards again
good um
the so there's a couple of technical
challenges you know
what i was going to point out is that
that storage api is typically not as
powerful
or you know that file system api is not
as powerful as sql
uh and uh and furthermore
you know not all the data sort of old
users is like handy
in a single place that you can run you
know arbitrary queries on uh to
integrate it in
you know whatever application specific
manners uh so
that's sort of a challenge that sort of
applications really rely on the power
of being able to run arbitrary queries
over all the user data that is in
decentralized application a little bit
harder to achieve because the data is
not spread out
over many maybe different storage
servers
there's also features that might be
harder to implement
like example if you want to implement
ebay then
uh users have to submit sort of uh uh
bits but you know we wanna don't
disclose those bits immediately
and so there has to be so some trusted
you know aspect to it that actually
integrates these bits and then decides
you know actually who's the winner
without you know disclosing those bits
beforehand
uh similarly there's a uh
sort of challenges around management uh
typically you know these decentralized
applications you know involve
uh you know crypto keys
and so there has to be sort of a you
know that's often
a killer seo some user loses their
private key and then
you know you can't use your you can't
get to your data anymore
uh and or somebody actually steals your
private key and then you know
they can get into your data um so those
are sort of a series of
uh sort of technical challenge you know
to make this actually really work
uh and one of them uh the one remaining
one which is mostly the topic of this
lecture
is naming
and sort of these broad set of
challenges are basically i think you
know challenges for any sort of
decentralized
application infrastructure and certainly
also in the context of
a blog stack uh but in the case of block
stack you know we're gonna mostly you
know we'll see actually uh
the importance of names and why naming
actually is a
a challenge okay so
just before we stop here for a second
and sort of give people time to ask any
questions in terms of
contrasting sort of these two different
ways of building
uh applications whether it's you know
centralized as in the sort of the
traditional model that we're probably
all familiar with
or this decentralized model
so what's the uh challenge exactly with
bids
so which challenge with bids
you need an application need to have
access to the user bits
uh but shouldn't disclose them right to
other applications
and so that means that uh the
the application like like i'm due one
i'm submitting a bit
uh you know i get youtube's bit but my
application shouldn't really be closed
youtube's bit immediately to me because
you know it wouldn't be fair
uh and so how would you do that so you
need some sort of form of a trusted
party or whatever some
protocol that actually makes that happen
thank you
the application runs in your models on
your workstation you can modify the work
in the application correct
uh sorry in the previous slide i think
you mentioned also
um app one being different from uh like
the two apps being different um what do
you
mean exactly well for example okay just
to make the analogy is very crisp
because this could be vim
and this could be emacs and u1 and u2
get to decide which application they're
going to use to actually modify
their you know data correct and you know
today in the sort of centralized model
you know it's not really possible you
know you can't have basically two
twitter apps you know where you were
like one way of interacting with the
twitter app and somebody else likes them
to do it in a different way
there's just a twitter app i see thank
you
i i had a question just about like the
design of the decentralized like
app like model is it is it necessary for
the app to be like on the
client side or could it you know could
you have like these like decentralized
apps on the like internet uh
side well you you could have a principal
on the internet it's like the key
issue and it doesn't really have to run
on the user's workstation when you mean
anything can run anywhere but it is
under the user's control
of course you have somebody who writes
it but the user gets to decide which app
to run
over what data right
so so the important thing here is is
that you know app
the chooser that you usually chooses the
app and like
importantly the app has access to any
storage provider right
thanks
okay any other questions
okay so names so
and this is getting a little bit more
into block stack
and then uh you know let me sort of sort
of lay out like the role the names play
you know first of all you know you have
to do list and you want to share that
with somebody else you're going to have
to be able to name that user from whom
you're sharing
and so there's a sort of mapping from
name to user
that's an important role there's a
mapping for
name to location of data
my to-do list app you know i share you
know the to-do list of usual one with
user two
uh and then uh you know what i wanna
actually retrieve usually one wants to
be two of user two's
uh data that needs to be a way of
actually naming the users to use uh
to-do list and actually retrieving it
and then
you know there's a assembly there's a
name you know to
public key uh mapping
you know when i do you know successfully
retrieve uh
user choose data uh you know probably
want to verify that actually was written
uh by user two and so i'll probably use
user2's public key
to verify the integrity of the data
retrieved because the storage providers
you know might be
you know can then be untrusted and but
that requires that i can establish
uh what actually uses two public key is
in in a reliable manner
and so uh so you should think about it
like in every step
of these uh decentralized applications
you know the name
uh plays a crucial role and
and the common name given in particular
for you know the
these mappings from names to peace which
is a
crucial piece is typically called the
public key infrastructure
and that is you know building actually
uh
any public key infrastructure is quite
challenging uh
you know you might be familiar with dns
sec you know there's a
particular way unfortunately the wide
web has a with certificates has a whole
public key infrastructure
uh kerberos is an example of uh
uh public key infrastructure and in in
some ways with the you know these papers
that's it
to do is just build get another you know
public key infrastructure that is
completely decentralized
and that's sort of the
key aspect aspect you know this uh
what's interesting about this naming
scheme
in uh in blockstack that's actually
provides a decent life publicly
infrastructure
let me try to explain a little bit why
you know this is challenging
so
the people refers to this in a couple
places and it says like you know
there's three aspects that you want uh
if you
want to general purpose and naming your
structure you want to be able to have
unique names
to have a unique name for every user
so that you can identify you know the
particular john or the particular
journal you're talking about
you on human human
readable names
so that's easy to remember and then in
this case
what block stack also wants is you know
decentralized
and you know the paper sort of makes a
point that it's
easy to get two of the three but it's
very difficult to get
uh all three of them and you know maybe
let's look at a couple naming systems to
see you know which two
they do get so let's think about like
email addresses
look at email addresses are they uh
unique names
yes yeah are they human-readable
yup yes are they decentralized no
no so you should just get two of these
guys correct but not the first one
uh how about random public keys
or maybe like if the paper uh uses
hashes of the file contents to actually
get a name correct for the
workflow so basically okay so random
public keys which maybe just public keys
to get the random but presumably random
so public keys are they unique
yep yeah yep uh are they unimaginable
no no are they decentralized yes
yeah you can generate them you know with
high probability in a unique manner
completely decentralized correct
so in fact you should have done that
more in lab three with these cleric ids
so here we get like again two of the
three but not the human readable one
let's see can we actually get human
readable and decentralized
can you think of an example
is that like uh peer-to-peer file
sharing
yeah it's not whatever it's not unique
the files but they're human readable and
decentralized
yeah nothing simpler uh you know think
about your phone
then the example for me always is a good
one is like your contact list
yeah you know the names in your contract
listed your remote you know
decentralized you know
you can have uh john you know
in the entry for john one phone number
and i can have uh another phone number
for my john entry
uh they're probably different people uh
but you know the the
you know i can pick the names in a
decentralized manner
and they're certainly unreadable are
they unique
no correct this is like you have your
list of names i have my list of names
and they may actually overlap
and still talk about different people
okay so you're sort of
what the paper is trying to get get at
that actually getting two out of the
three
uh is quite common or very easy
uh but actually getting uh all three of
them is hard
and uh and
the papers are like well we actually we
achieve all three of them
and you know we get the unique names we
get unreal and decentralized
right and in the way in some ways they
they get this is to basically uh exploit
uh the blockchain
so
so bloxtex approach
uh and really to be fair uh
it's really not black black sex
approaches really name
coins approach
that they sort of adopted uh the basic
idea is very simple
uh you know we're going to take
advantage of the existence of the
bitcoin block stack
with the bitcoin blockchain and
of course you could use any other
blockchain but like you know just for
concreteness
you know we're gonna think about the
bitcoin one and so
here we got our chain
you know transactions that's it in
bitcoin
uh you know grows over time you know
miners add new transactions
and the way we're gonna uh basically
create a naming system is we're gonna
just
uh post uh transactions that are for
different type
that basically claim a name and so for
example you know we might actually have
you know certainly special special
transactions uh
because every transaction actually turns
out in bitcoin has a metadata field and
you can basically stick anything in the
metadata field you want
and so what we're going to stick in
there is a name record
so we're going to have some transaction
and then we're going to stick a name
record in there
and we'll see a little in a second but
exactly the details of this name record
is
but in the case of block stack you know
it's basically a name
like six eight to four
and then you know maybe as we see later
a hash of the zone file
um and the basic rule in
this scheme is going to be that
the first one the first
user first name record basically wins
right so there might be a second you
know somebody else creates the name 684
later
uh and not because you know the 6.6824
uh shows up later in the in the
bitcoin uh blockchain and we're going to
basically ignore that one and you know
only
you know uh consider that the valid
name record for 6824 right and this
completely
you know plays off you know the fact
that there's basically
uh the blockchain is a log
of all the operations ever happened uh
they're in order
there's consensus in what order they
happened and so from that you know we
can basically uh construct
uh if you will like a database uh
database with all the names in the world
you know we just go through the
blockchain from the beginning of time
find all the valid uh transactions name
transactions
and use that to construct a database
with all the
uh with all the valid names and in some
ways
uh you know a number of people sort of
pointed this out like isn't this exactly
you know we've been doing like lab three
uh where you know we have vlogs like
graph you know provides a log
we stick operations in the log you know
we
[Music]
run you know the operations and uh
and that constructs another state you
know where the state in this case would
be
a naming database and there's you know i
think it's exactly that kind of style
uh in the same idea except the small
differences here correct you know we're
not using graph to get consensus we're
again we're using
uh bitcoin uh or nakamoto uh to get the
nakamoto consensus to actually achieve
uh one single
uh blockchain uh but in spirit you know
yes you know
it is it's very similar
okay um so let's think a little bit
about it
uh our free properties you know first of
all
you know do we get unique names
yes yes yeah we got unique names correct
because the first one wins
uh is it decentralized
yes yeah it's decentralized you know by
virtue of
uh bitcoin right
and the consensus and the log basically
makes sure that we can actually identify
what the
first name is so that we can actually
pick a unique name
this is human readable can't be
candy yeah i get exactly okay
certainly my stream uh 6824 is hopefully
unreasonable
ah okay so it seems like you know sort
of from the first
uh brought you know uh suite where uh
you know it looks like
indeed you know we got the the free
properties right got new marine ball we
got the uniqueness and we got the
decentralized one
and i think that really named coin was
sort of the first uh
naming system that uh demonstrated that
could be
that could be achieved in this way now
you know it's not completely perfect
right uh
like for example even though we got sort
of unique names and the union readable
we don't really know like what 684
really means correct and i feel like you
see 6824
then what what does 6824 refer to is it
like a
a part number or is it a class number or
anything we don't really know like how
to interpret names but you know they're
still human readable so it's not
completely perfect it's not like
identifying uniquely some
you know user in the world right or um
and even like you know whatever you were
done cash looking that doesn't really
uniquely identify
uh one person right so whenever you see
a name here there's still the
uh issue of like who it actually really
is
um and also there's sort of a similar
you know related issue why it's not
completely perfect
uh which is like um how do you find
somebody's name
uh and you know you know how do you find
actually you know what a casserole's
name
or uh and how do you know how do you
find that
how do you know which record actually
goes within which particular user
so you know although so although the
you know the system is uh quite cool
because it has this
decent life uniqueness and human
readable aspects to it and it's not
completely perfect and
these are generally issues with naming
general naming systems uh but certainly
true here too
and so it's not the case that you know
we're you know we sort of solved all
naming problems
uh in one single uh swoop we do have a
good standing position to
work with but you know it's not a
complete 100 hit
right so question so
namecoin all they did was add
essentially this like record to
the the like transaction
i think we did a little bit more than
that right they run their own blockchain
uh independent of bitcoin and uh
and and used that blockchain you know
purely for naming
uh and they had always a bunch of rules
about like you know uh
how much money how many name points you
have to pay to get a particular name
and uh there's all kinds of other
extensions
that i haven't really discussed uh yet
were mentioned
but they sort of you know followed this
particular approach and were the first
sort of to do so
in the many pragmatic issues that the
paper touch is on and
i haven't mentioned it all yet
any other questions
okay so let's actually dive in a little
bit on the
sort of the practical issues uh although
there's a slightly different nature than
we did once
we just talked about it really is by the
how to actually implement decentralized
apps
and naming system by leveraging
bitcoin
and there are a bunch of uh the bunches
of barriers or just
you know pragmatic issues there's limits
on the amount of data you can put in a
on data size in a transaction
so although maybe it's perfectly fine to
have a name
uh value binding into uh
uh into the uh into a bitcoin
transaction
you know we can't put like our to-do
list inside of the trajection and so you
know we gotta have some plan
for actually how that you know part is
going to work out
uh it has slow rights we know from the
last lecture
it takes a while you know for rights
actually or
transactions to propagate and uh before
they
consider to be really stable and cannot
be uh forked off anymore
you know we might be talking about like
you know four five six
uh blocks later in the chain you know
and your blocks ten minutes so you know
an hour later right
and so this is really not so cool if you
stick our to-do list inside of the
blockchain too uh because you know i
will modify my blog
my channel modify my to-do list like an
hour later maybe you actually observe it
so
that seems not so good and if we want to
go to more aggressive applications where
like there's much more data that's
manipulated you know we certainly uh a
problem you know
similarly you know in addition to slow
right you know there's also a low low
throughput a little bandwidth
in the numerator there's only a few
transactions
per second correct so we're going to do
a lot of writes you know through the
file
uh many times we're also we're going
running the
the the file operations through the
blockchain so
uh so clearly you know you know we got
to be a little bit you know if we want
to really build a general purpose
uh infrastructure for
decentral applications you know there
needs to be a more complete story that
actually allows us to get like
uh fast rates you know high bandwidth
rates uh
and gets around and you know basically
not run everything for the blockchain
the paper also talks about one other
final problem the ledger the
ever-growing ledger
uh and i'm not actually spend much time
without talking about that at all
uh but that's clearly also an issue now
if you wanted to
say the report in the paper you're going
to boot up a box take note
uh if you do sort of uh in the
traditional sort of bitcoin style where
you know you're going to run through all
the tracking transactions one by one
that will take a while before you
actually have build up your complete
naming record
and particularly in the case of block
stack is a little bit annoying because a
lot of the
transactions that are in the blockchain
are completely not relevant to block
stacks right there
uh there are whatever transactions for
completing some different purpose
uh and have nothing to do with uh the
block stack
uh approach but you know blocks tech if
you really literally were using
uh the bitpoint blockchain as your
fundamental thing you know you would
have to go through and
interpret the end of them and see which
ones actually you need to apply
okay so we're going to focus more on
sort of these the first couple
uh challenges which is like you know
basically what
we want to do is like minimize the use
of the uh
blockchain uh yeah so that we can you
know actually get high you know like
performance rights or
in decent bandwidth
does that make sense
good and that sort of gets us to the
core of the paper
which is like the pull up that diagram
so we can look at it
that's basically this diagram and that
sort of describes you know the general
approach
that the paper takes to address you know
the
challenges that i just laid out on the
previous board
okay so this is a complicated picture
and so let's uh go
for layer by layer and try to understand
actually how things work
so at the the bottom you know is the
yeah is the bitcoin chain
uh and in the bitcoin chain there are
lots and lots of transactions
and many of these rejections have
absolutely nothing to do with
block stack right down watch that here
uh and the block stack transactions are
sort of sitting in you know
you know particular blocks in the
blockchain
and then there's also the second layer
which is really the block stack nodes
that basically read all these
transactions
fish out the ones that are actually
related to block stack
interpret you know those operations and
you know build up
a blockstack database with names to
what turns out to be zone file hashes so
we look at these operations what's in
there so in every
uh bitcoin introduction as i mentioned
earlier you can have some metadata
uh this sits in the what's called the op
underscore return field
and in that up underscore return field
uh there is basically
uh an a name say
x uh plus you know the hash
of the zone file
and that's sort of the binding that sits
in bitcoin and that you know basically
blocks that uses uh
bitcoin to basically make that binding
from from name to a zoom file
uh unique uh uh
and uh in a decentralized manner
so as you know like in lab3 or
in any other sort of logging system uh
the these blocks tech nodes interpret
these
uh particular uh name uh transactions
look at the op field uh see that this up
field is for example to create a
particular name
and basically store it in the database
the you know the
the binding from name acts you know to
the hash of the zone file
and you know once a while as we'll see
in the second user may want to update
the zone file
so you might see multiple transactions
for the same
user updating basically the hash of the
zone file
and of course we want to minimize you
know these uh
changes because you know every change
you know to the
would require uh would require a
modification we're in a posting a
bitcoin transaction
uh and you know for many reasons that
are on the previous slide that's slow
so we like to try to avoid it
furthermore it will cost a little bit of
money
uh i mean because these transactions
actually need to be processed
and so um uh
so so the basic plan so this this
node layer this the the virtual chain
layer basically builds this database
of mappings from name to hash zone file
uh and of course also filters out all
the
transactions that are invalid or like
you know new access that's being created
after the first one
and then uh using the hash of the zone
file you know
which we got uh it locates uh
an application can locate uh the zone
file
and this zone file can come up from
anywhere uh and because we have the hash
of the zone file
when we retrieve a file that claims to
be the zone file we can recompute the
hash
if the hash is identical to the one that
we got sort of through uh indirectly
from bitcoin
then we know for sure that that is the
zone file that goes with
x and so okay what is that in
uh the zone files well in the in the
zone file is
yet another table if you will of mapping
names
uh to uris so for example you know you
might have a zone file which
has like maybe for the to-do app that's
an entry to do
and you know that points to a uri
where actually the data is located for
you know the to-do list
um and you know there's sort of two
types of jump files and one is what's
called
immutable and one is immutable the
mutable ones have uri plus
a public key
so uh and this is public key is the key
to actually validate
uh the whether the file is written by
the user x so basically the user x you
know publishes through the zone file
a public key for him or herself and
later on
uh when user two wants to look up user x
you know it gets the hash of the zone
file
the hash finds the zone file double
checks that the zone file
you know uh hashes to the right value
looks
inside the the the zone file finds the
you know the public key
of x and you know the uri
you know for the to-do file uh uses the
uri to fetch
uh the actual to do file uh check
you know the signature on the retreat
file with the public key
and if it all checks out then basically
user one two
knows okay i got you know user x
uh zone file and then it might be also
like other names in this zone file like
whatever you know usage to
your access tweets uh etc
timeline whatever you know for every
application there's probably an entry
and you know probably the applications
sort of agree on like you know what name
to use for a particular application
um so don't we lose the like data
immutability guarantees where like it's
possible this data could be deleted and
then
you wouldn't have the hash and the data
could just be lost so
you mean like the the zone file could
get lost
right like like with the chain you can't
lose data because it'll be replicated
enough places but here
four or four kilobyte or something in
that order and so they can be replicated
everywhere
okay then for the to-do
list okay the do file the uri uh the
basic idea is that
you might store the same data or
multiple providers for example you might
want to have like you replicate it at s3
and maybe you know you also stick it in
google drive
and uh one reason that actually blocks
that has a storage
service is not because actually they
store the data but basically you provide
a uniform api to all these different
storage providers
okay so they have does that make sense
okay so then there's a uh there's as i
mentioned zone files in two
ways uh there's another which i call
immutable storage and that actually
contains you know the uri
name uri
[Music]
public key
and the hash of the data
of the file and so
you can basically verify you know is
this indeed the latest version of the
the file uh because in this scheme you
get to update
you know x can update the file but it's
harder to tell uh
for user two whether that is actually
the latest version
uh the paper mentions that they're you
know you probably want to stick version
numbers in it
uh but if you really want to guarantee
it to be sort of the latest version for
a particular name
uh in if you're using immutable storage
you know then
the mutable storage contains the hash of
the file and
that uniquely identifies a particular
version of that particular file
that does mean like if you update you
know this record
then uh that really means you update the
zone file
so that means you have to republish or
recreate a log entry
in the bitcoin chain uh mapping you know
x to
a new hash hash zone file
okay so this is sort of the overall
picture uh for the
uh for the system and as you can see you
know
uh particularly like you know in this
to-do list site um
you know the user x can actually update
uh its uh his or her
to-do list without actually having to
publish a new
record in the in the bitcoin chain in
fact you know the only thing that really
has to be created in the bitcoin chain
is
just you know x's name uh and x of
course might have many other names that
are sitting in the zone files
uh and uh and uh but the
the the the system doesn't rely on
uh for every operation on the uh on the
blockchain
in which it gets around gets us around a
lot of these problems of
you know flow rates low bandwidth uh
and the limits on the uh and the limits
on the
uh on the data that actually appear in a
transaction record because the only data
really has to appear
in this transaction record is this name
plus the hash of the zone file
sorry uh how can do we find there's no
file if you only have the hash
ah it's a very good uh question we don't
really care uh
where it comes from and so in fact you
know they call this the routing layer
right this basically
you tell the learning writer hey i'm
looking for a file that has to follow a
hash
and then the writing layer has to
produce that file
and you can check whether you got the
right file by recomputing the hash and
see if that's just the one that you're
asking for
any other questions about this
so sorry just to clarify um operations
within this
file storage or these zone files is
still limited by the underlying
blockchain though right
uh yes or no uh
what are you thinking
or just like because modifications or
changes to like the file will need
like a new hash and therefore a new log
entry within the blockchain
so you still have to wait for that to be
quote unquote accepted which is like an
hour right
yeah although absolutely true so when
you make a change to the zone file
you know that that has to run through
the txn
but for example updating the to-do list
uh wouldn't have to
require an uh bitcoin transaction
you don't really update the zone file at
all you know you're just
updating the to-do list file and the
zone file only contains the name
to do and the uri plus the public key
but you're not updating any of those
i see but doesn't then we store also the
hash of the file so if we change the
content yeah that's
that's okay there are two cases for the
mutable there's the mutable storage and
immutable storage and uh
what they propose is that for immutable
storage like storage if you don't update
you can actually stick the hash of the
file in there but for mutable storage
you know that's going to see
a lot of writes you know you shouldn't
do that you should use this scheme
i see and then how is it possible to
validate with mutable storage that
you're getting the right data then
yeah so the presumably uh that's a very
good question uh well you
you can validate whether you actually
get data that actually was produced by x
because you have to pull the key for x
and you can verify whether actually the
signature on the to do file
indeed you know checks out with the
public key of x
so you at least know that x has written
it you may not know of this most recent
version
and so the paper sort of doesn't really
talk about this
you know in detail but basically says
you know you probably have to stick
version numbers in it
and so at least you can uh detect
drawback
uh but there's a little bit fake
actually i don't know how to uh how to
actually uh
you can't really assure that you
actually got the latest version
right so where are the modifications to
immutable storage
coming into uh your to-do file lives
here like in
like here's my to do file and
uh if an application my to-do list
application wants to update to to do
file it just goes ahead and does it
and uh and then signs it you know using
the public key and sticks it in
uh the uh
and sticks it in for uh for the given
uri
and would that be done through the the
routing layer as well
because you have you want to find where
in the storage
yeah so the user tool will retrieve uh
access zone file correct
and once it has accession file it knows
where
the file the to do file is because
there's the uri sits in the zone file
[Music]
so again and they can retrieve it and
check the signature about the uri are
there
is it only one uri per uh
name in the zone file or um i
don't know unclear exactly how it works
uh sorry i'm not you know i didn't look
check out the source code and like look
at the
specific form of the zone files
uh since we are publishing the public
key
together with all the rest of the data
in the xml file does it mean i can
just make up a private key
make like a matching public key and just
stick something in there and say
i'm user z because
i'm because i do provide the public key
so
can i not just lie well you can't
falsify the zone file correct
because the zone file the hash of the
zone file must
match the hash that sits in the
blockchain
so only the
person that actually entered the
blockchain record mapping
x you know to that hash zone file only
that person could have produced you know
that zone files
i see thank you
okay well so this is basically the big
picture
and if you got this is the uh if you got
this part then basically
the rest of the sort of details and
important but maybe less important this
is the key thing to understand
okay um i guess a couple things i want
to go over
in particular i want to talk a little
bit more about name creation because
there's a couple little details
that are actually interesting
so turns out the name creation actually
has two uh
parts to it first of all the user needs
to have of course some bitcoins because
you gotta pay
the reason you have to have some
bitcoins is because you know you gotta
convince
uh one of the uh miners to actually
include your transaction
in the bitcoin uh ledger and so it turns
out there are
two transactions for every name that you
create
and one is basically a pre-order
transaction
and in the pre-order transaction you
don't really list the name but actually
the hash of the name
so anybody who sees the pre-order
transaction doesn't know what the name
is but you know
doesn't know what the hash of the name
is and then there's the second
transaction which really registers the
name
and you know that basically contains the
actual name
for which we first publish the hash and
the hash of the zone file
and so why why
why is this done and this is actually
something that uh namecoin did
and they adopted it from namecoin why do
it in this way
because if you directly announce the
name then someone else can raise you
and uh try to register that name before
you
yeah this is a common problem it's
called the front runner problem correct
uh
there we go again sorry
um
it's the front runner problem uh it's
exactly
described let's say you know you're
trying to register google.com
and uh somebody sees you doing that and
of course you submit it to transaction
correct it's not in the blockchain yet
um for example a miner might actually
see it or you know somebody else that
actually sits in the
the bitcoin network and decides okay i'm
gonna run ahead and try and get my
transaction the claiming you know
google.com uh into the bitcoin before
you
and then i own uh google.com and so to
avoid that problem uh you first actually
have to enter the hash
into the bitcoin chain then you wait a
while
to make sure that the uh that that
record sits in the
bitcoin uh blockchain you may have six
whatever
ten blocks and then after that you're
sure that like you know the
you burn the name in the as they called
in the
blockchain at that point you actually do
the actual registration of the name
i got a question regarding that
so what why is it not possible for an
attacker to say
precompute internally the hash of
google.com and then
look through the blockchain and see if
someone posted a hash of google
yeah yeah yeah yeah absolutely uh so i
presumably you know this is
slightly more sophisticated than this
you know and then just period in the
hash there's
a bunch of other arguments that go into
it including the nons or something
otherwise you could make a dictionary
correct
and in some ways this is like really not
their invention but this is uh
you know as i said before came out of uh
came out of uh name coin
okay um so let's you know go back to
uh you know the sort of collaborative
apps for you know collaborative
collaborative decentralized applications
so we just go back to our to-do list as
an example
uh and just to see you know how it
really would work uh
you know so sketch out again how that
would work uh so basically you know what
two users correct
you know running you know the to-do list
app
give you one you know youtube
and they basically exchanged you know
some information with each other you
know basically saying uh
in some way your one has learned about
youtube's name and youtube has learned
about g1's name
and then sort of that that step of
course has to happen it has to happen
securely
in the sense that you won't really need
to know that that actually is youtube's
your name
then they can you one can or
uh you one can look up youtube's name
you know get the zone file from that
like find the entry for say the to-do
list in the zone file
uh again the zone file also contains you
know in the public key
and this might be not like you know
youtube might have many
public keys uh private keys uh because
you probably don't want to have like one
master private key that you use for
everything because if you use that one
master private key or somebody still you
know you're in bad shape
so typically i think in the block in box
deck they're sort of a
public private keeper application uh
so you know the new one basically you
can get your house due to his name
looks up the zone file finds the to-do
list the public key
and the uri you know through the
block stack file system which attracts
away the different storage providers you
know it actually retrieves
you know the actual name the actual file
you know checks the signature on the
file maybe version numbers
and and then basically use that to
construct
you know the the to-do list from u2
and worked out with you once and
similarly you know you basically you two
just exactly the same way i think you
know and as you one's name
and room and goes off and uh you know
you use one you
you once uh to-do list and you know that
way they can
have a collaborative uh application
and so for example when you do updates
uh it's file
then uh you know periodically you once
have to
gauche and retrieves the new uh
retrieves
the the to-do list and just sees if
there are any updates
does that sort of make sense
you see here i think this is like one of
these central points with decentral
applications
uh is these applications are built in
you know
quite a different way than uh the ones
that we were talking about very early on
correct
if we go back to this picture of the
centralized
site that we're building a to-do list
application correctly in the database
yeah that would be you one's to-do list
and you choose to do list
and yeah you know like the to-do list
app you know but basically you know
retrieve these uh the content of these
to-do lists with a simple sql query
and you know puts them together and
actually presents them to the user and
we see that like in this decentralized
scheme you know there's
quite a lot more mechanism involved to
actually make this happen
and uh and the program it doesn't really
have to sort of the same
uh ease of you know the sql interface as
uh as in the centralized case and so i
think this is a
uh one of the sort of maybe the sticking
points of these decentralized
applications
how can you make them as easy to write
as decentralized versions
okay so i want to leave some time this
time around instead of doing breakout
rooms
maybe just leave some time around time
for just questions or discussion
uh since this is a little bit more of a
sort of you know thought-provoking
type exercise then uh an exercise in
well here's your technical problem and
here's the right solution you know just
learn the right solution and then use it
and so
uh you know i just want to hear you know
people's opinion or
questions about sort of any aspect of
these decentralized applications for
versus centralized or the particular
design for block stack or any other
issue and we can debate it together
wait so what's the um the main
difficulty
in um instead of using like a file
system api to use like a
relational database well how do you
write a
how do you present the worldwide uh
relational database
i think all these user files
all these files and different users live
in all kinds of different
storage providers um and
uh you know you can't like room do
whatever uh
you can't do select across all the
storage device
providers regularly crazy
you couldn't also download all the users
data to your computer because that would
be too expensive
what about like uh like uh
like a linked data um data database
yeah you know again so i think this is
like
you're interested in this you know i
think there's an interesting researcher
actually to
pursue correct but you could actually
build
uh sort of uh you know scalable database
infrastructure
where users still control their own data
have the different locations yeah and
provide sort of a relational data type
interface
certainly blocks out blocks doesn't
offer you to you
i guess another question is um like what
are the benefits of this
decentralized pki versus like a web of
trust pki
which i guess is also decentralized yeah
so totally other you know i guess
maybe some points here correct uh you
know they're sort of the
their other weapon trust api a web of
trust
uh pkis
uh you know i mean the one i'm most
familiar with is
uh is um uh
key base
i think which we mentioned a couple
times before uh and uh
you know uh the keyboard is actually uh
we haven't talked in this in greater
detail but
uh one of the things that does also
challenge in these kinds of systems is
like how do you represent groups of
users
like we shot a little bit in the center
paper uh where you know you have group
names
all the keys for the group names and you
know how to create them and i'll manage
them and actually you know stick them in
you know how do you incorporate those in
the
in the the chain of records name
wreckage
uh and key base is a really really
really thought out story for that
uh uh and you know actually these are
very impressive
it's probably you know the sort of
probably
probably considered the sort of the best
sort of decentralized you know pti out
there
and the most thought out and probably
most widely used
so are there any benefits of doing it of
like block stocks
method or is it just more extensible uh
well one of the things that actually
blocks that gas correct is uh is this
uniqueness
uh properties because the web of trust
there's basically not a global naming
system you know
like you know it is like my to-do list
or my contact list
uh and you know whatever who i name
you know if i have a name john for some
particular public key that is my john
and uh if i said john to you it's like
in the text you know string
john probably resolves differently
differently in your
uh content list than the mine and so
in fact uh so key base is much more is
decentralized
uh but origin doesn't really go for
these sort of global unique names
now it is the case that you know key
base once in a while publishes the
hash of all the names of the complete
the merkle tree of all names in
in in the blockchain too uh so you can
sort of verify whether key base actually
is uh not playing in games
uh but you know the uh it's a much more
it doesn't really have global unique
names
sorry just a clarification question
earlier on in the lecture you mentioned
how
users have the basically they can choose
who to show their data to
um or who they give access to their data
to
um but i'm not quite sure i see how
that's implemented within
that system
yeah they're they're the way one way to
do it and
i i don't know exactly you know what the
block stack does
is that you encrypt the same data uh
for different users so i think uh if you
want to uh
share your data only with user one and
user two
then you encrypt it you know with the
public keys of usual one in user two and
then those are the only two that can
decrypt it
and so that gives you sort of extra
control lists
i see so you'd have to for each person
you wanted
to give the data to you'd have to
encrypt it with like their public key
yeah and you can get more sophisticated
about this
you know you can actually have group
keys and you know give
a group of users you know access to you
know you have a lock box
that uh has a group key in it and you
encrypt the log box with the different
users you know public keys
and then they get access to that lock
box they get the key out of it and then
they can decrypt the key so that you
only have to
encrypt the data only once instead of
multiple times
and you only have to decrypt the
encrypted lock box multiple times
thank you
um that would be done at the level of
the content of this
zone file right uh
yeah presumably or maybe the key that is
in the zone files build the key for the
lock box if you will
and again i'm not actually 100 sure
exactly how uh
how i block stack actually the the boxx
file system does
uh action control when it does it all
but other people have done these kinds
of designs
do you think uh systems like this be
able to compete with like the
centralized model in terms of
performance or scalability
and what would it take i i don't know
these are
good questions uh i don't really know
the answer it is the case correct like
even
the centralized sites is not that easy
to scale you know we've
written out quite a number of papers
correctly we should see how uh
how to make them uh scalable to millions
of users
and so you know
oh yeah miss getting anything to a large
large number of users is not easy
uh and uh certainly uh in the case of
the decentralized apps it's not gonna be
easy either but on the other hand like
if there's not
bite sharing like the user one actually
i only have a share to do this with 10
other users
that should probably not be a big issue
correct some ways you can think about
the decentralized architecture it's
basically sharded by user
and each app you know runs on one of the
user's computers
so it's like you don't need to like data
centers with
caches
so i don't know what the answer to that
question actually is
i would not be able to give you a
different answer
it's clearly the case that you know
people have demonstrated bigger
scalability we have sort of these
uh uh centralized designs uh
at least so far we've seen them in the
decent life once but you know one reason
of that of course is that
the the the centralized designs are like
the
widely used the most popular the most
deployed
cases i think the the
to me the decentralized design is just
an intriguing
design and that if it could make to be
work
you know it would be pretty cool
any other thoughts that people might
have for
i would like to argue about
i still feel like the storage aspect
is like the thing that that william will
was pointing out where
like you maybe have an immutable file
that's
the the user information but the mutable
file that you have
somewhere else yeah is like a a huge
problem um in so much that like i i
don't really
understand how you can assure redundancy
for the large amount of
mutable storage that you might have yeah
i think
i think the answer the redundancy may be
not that tough i think this the user is
responsible for redundancy
uh so if you're like you're you do this
you own a to-do list file
and it's your job to replicate it you
know multiple times you know the
block stack storage servers do that for
you but you got a range you know
basically for
uh space and the different storage
providers to
uh do that and so i think in the paper
they talk about like oh you're
replicated at maybe
uh google drive and then s3 and
presumably s3 internally does its own
replication right so hopefully you know
maybe you just actually store it only at
s3 and that should be pretty reliable
probably more liable than storing data
on your ssd on your laptop
and the zone files are small so they're
just widely replicated
and you don't have to trust the storage
provider
any other thoughts
i was thinking it's a little bit
wasteful that you have in order to
register a name and to use this name
system you have to
pay um yeah so i was thinking
obviously on a blockchain based system
you'll have to incentivize the miners
but i was thinking
maybe there's a different cheaper way
i don't know yeah i'm not sure
it seems in some ways you know that's
sort of the currency and this is also
are very coupled as a reason exactly for
the reason
you mentioned because you've got to have
minors and you have to incentivize them
now i think in general like with these
transactions they're pretty cheap you
know basically you know basically you
have to just pay enough correct that the
miner is actually willing to do to
include your transaction uh and you know
today you also pay for you know if you
want to register a name in you know
in dns you know you actually pay quite a
bit of money
it's not free
i don't know exactly how economics would
work out uh but uh
it's not obviously clear that this is
actually a much more expensive way of
doing it other than maybe you know
you're brewing the planet with
electricity at least in the bitcoin case
uh but you know maybe you should use uh
one of the stake of work
uh ledgers instead of the
uh
it will be possible just to swap it out
in
place of layer one yeah i think this is
like i think this is what the papers
argue correct like their particular
design is really not very dependent on
the
uh the underlying blockchain and they
could easily switch to another
blockchain in fact you know this is the
second blockchain that worked on correct
they first used namecoin
and then they switched to bitcoin and i
think the argument in the paper is
making uh we could actually switch to
another
uh blockchain we wanted to
what in particular is stored in the name
history
in the sorry what uh what's the question
uh
really oh sorry the name history in the
block stack database
yeah this this yeah i don't really mean
like these three different guys
i think yeah different version of the
zone file
so they're just like version numbers
yeah i think so
i'm not 100 sure but uh
it's like these correspond to the free
updates to the zone file correct here's
number one here's number two
and maybe they keep fusion version of
his own file around
any other topics that people want to
bring up
as we end sort of the election time
anyway okay so let's uh why don't we
stop here for people that need uh
need to leave can leave and i'll see
hopefully everybody on thursday you know
we're gonna see
uh eight we had eight design uh eight
projects
and so the eight uh teams will present
the first day
what they've done instead of lab
lab four and it should be and the the
projects are quite cool and interesting
so
hopefully you'll be in uh you'll be
entertained uh
and that makes concludes this lecture
hopefully uh
that's a bit of a the goal is a little
bit before provoking and you know sort
of
talk about uh designs uh the
decentralized designs of the houses the
nice property that the users are on
their data
and uh you know and we looked in the
context of
block stack at least one particular
design uh how they
did naming in a way that gives global
names unique names
and human uh readable ones okay
so that's the end of this lecture and
then hopefully we'll see you in first
time
which is going to be our final class
meeting
and if you have any questions please
feel free to stick around and
we can talk um um professor
um for the presentation um are we are we
supposed to do something like more of a
demo
or should we have like slides prepared
or a combination both
yeah you put books in so many structures
the thing you want to do is convince the
class and ask you know
what party they did and why it's cool uh
so demo is a good idea
uh the other you don't have a ton of
time so i think the typical thing to do
is that people have a few slides for
explaining
what they did and then maybe a quick
demo so to see how it actually
materialized great okay yeah thank you
yeah we don't expect you to whatever in
hours we're preparing for this correct
uh usually trying to share what you've
done
okay thank you
um i just wanted to ask so it's
like what is the reasoning behind
just having just using the same
bitcoin like the blockchain
and just putting the the transactions
for the naming
on there together with all the rest of
the things
right yeah i i think these are the
papers
so they started out they started out
building on top of name coin
which is a special purpose ledger for
naming
and uh they discovered basically that uh
there's sort of all kinds of security
issues with uh namecoin
uh uh and one of them being the
interactions they're not that many
miners
and so uh they observed that they're
basically their
miner pools that basically had more than
50 percent of the
capacity and work capacity and therefore
you could do anything they wanted to do
to the principal to the ledger and so
they wanted to sit on a
a blockchain that is widely used very
popular and not easy to overtake
by the adversary okay i remember the 51
percent yeah remember okay that makes
sense
um and i also wanted to ask about um
the uris they are your rights to
to the zone file storage system they're
not just like
um s3 something something right yeah it
could be
uh something a little bit more general
because it's actually interpreted by the
uh by the block stack file system uh
uh so and the blocker next stack file
system has back ends for the different
storage provider
whether it's s3 or google drive or
whatever
and so there's some naming scheme that
the the the
block stack file system can interpret
and then figure out like how to retrieve
the right
file from the the correct
uh back-end
this is just to make them the same yeah
exactly usually like an application
writer doesn't really want to
it doesn't want to care correct whether
it's stored at sv or google drive will
show you where
there's visually have to deal with that
thank you so much you're welcome
i had a question about why zuko's
triangle
is kind of like a think that people
think about a lot like it it seems like
if you can have like a client side like
interpret the human uh non-meaningful
data
that you can make kind of all the data
human meaningful like on the client side
to the user um and so i wasn't
completely sure like what
like what the innovation here is or why
like people
why this is necessarily like a trade-off
yeah
yeah well i guess this is the best slide
i can give you
where i can give you a whole bunch of
naming examples that basically have two
out of three but not all three
and uh and so for example like you know
uh the
you know we talked about key base greg
there's decent like you know
decentralized
uh human know but not unique
uh and now you're gonna argue whether
it's that important to have global
unique names
because like you know whatever you have
some global unique name like 8684
what does it mean and who's associated
with it
so if you're coming from that angle i
think that's a very valid question
so one of the things that has always
kind of bothered me when we're reading
through
these blockchain type of papers is like
what happens in 100 years when
the the ledger gets to like multiple
terror
i don't know if it yeah like multiple
terabytes or something
uh yeah we were just like not do we not
have an escape plan like
what's gonna happen then uh i don't know
hard to uh speculate hundred years out
into the future
uh presumably what you could do is like
you know put a checkpoint in the uh
i i can imagine multiple schemes getting
out of this
uh one you could make a checkpoint uh of
the state you know build on the ledger
and
include the hash of that checkpoint into
the ledger
and then as long as you can and
replicate the checkpoint
widely and then you can basically start
running from the checkpoint and cut out
the beginning
this is like not unlike you know what
we're doing in lab you know what draft
is doing correct
would the party that does that have to
be trusted or
what we did i did
presumably the clients want to go have
to go along
and you realize that they should get to
get that checkpoint and
be able to construct you know the
current state of the world
so i presume that would require some
critical change and presumably some fork
and
now this is not a huge issue correct at
least with the rate of bitcoin because
like you know the number of transactions
per
you know second you can do is actually
small like if you remember from the
bitcoin paper there's some calculation
like you know
what the total size would be if you do
this uh furthermore
if you remember correctly from the
bitcoin paper there's a bunch of
optimizations right where
you don't really have to remember every
transaction uh
for every uh coin you basically have to
remember the last
transaction for every coin and you could
do that by just remembering the
block headers instead of the complete
block
so bitcoin has sort of a built-in
solution to this problem
i see so the main bottleneck is more or
less when
new machines come up they need to verify
the entity
yeah after that then things are
relatively more optimized yeah
exactly thank you
all guys done it for today
thank you all see you first