okay um so
good morning good afternoon or good
evening or wherever you are
uh i said the plan for today is to talk
about the frontier ponte
this is a paper from uh 1997 so it's a
bit of an older paper the context of
this paper
is network file systems
and you know you should think about
systems such as you know athena afs you
know the android file system and athena
uh dropbox uh or a more modern version
of this
uh but the general goal here is to
basically share files between
a collection of users uh the frontier
pony itself
is not widely used or wasn't widely used
outside of the deck
and so the real the focus of the things
that you should get out of this paper
today
are free ideas and ideas that actually
will show up
over and over in a couple next couple
weeks first of all cash coherence
protocols for cash coherence
second distributed locking
and third distributed crash recovery
and these are going to be three ideas
that are going to be as i mentioned show
up in
the next couple of weeks in particular
we're going to read uh you know starting
next week you know two sort of heavy
duty transaction systems
and they uh build a lot
on uh you know some of the techniques or
to use some of the
techniques that actually franciupani
also uses and so
frontier pawn is sort of a more gentle
introduction you know to
these three topics before we get to
heavy duty
transaction systems and the id is also
in front of puns itself is an
interesting design
uh a from a distributed systems
perspective uh
it is a a cool system and let me
uh make that point by uh sort of
contrasting sort of the traditional
designs
for a network file system so traditional
or the most common network file system
design since if you think about like
uh uh afs on athena
you know you have a set of clients
and this is going to make a very simple
picture you have a set of clients you
know connected to
some network represent the network
basically as a single wire
you know sharing you know a number of
file servers
and then a file servers after the disk
and basically oh you know all the
complexity
uh although okay i'll get to catchphrase
in detail in a second the all the
complexity in the
this design is basically here at the
file servers
so the file servers implement you know
the file system operations open close
read write you know stat everything and
they
uh write you know things to disk in a
crash uh
resilient or resistant way and the
clients are really sort of dumb
or simple they don't really do much you
have to do some caching as they do in
afs
uh but you know most of it is uh they're
relaying you know file system operations
from clients from programs that are
running
like whatever the irs on your client
wanting it doesn't open close
and most of what the client does is
relaying those operations to file
servers
and one reason that the design is you
know popular is that because
you know like in terms of a security
perspective uh it is a nice design
because most of the
you know the file servers have to be
trusted but the clients don't have to be
trusted
and certainly in a setting like mit you
were like the machines are just in
public
and who knows who installs what kind of
software on it
you know that is a a nice property
project pony on the other end has a very
different design
and much more decentralized design
uh and in front of body actually a lot
of the the file server
uh is really there is actually no real
file server in this or literally sends
the work
but the clients basically implement
run the file server code itself so let's
say we have two
you know clients and most of the file
system uh
code itself like the thing that actually
has inode manages inodes
updates you know files creates
directories all the code
instead of living on the file server
looks like it lives on the
clients and the only thing that really
the the file server share is a big
virtual disk
and if you will you know maybe a good
image you have in your head or some
conceptual image you have in your head
is that the virtual disk is
basically like a big ssd drive uh
and and so the file servers just
basically share one ssd you know
one disk uh with each other uh now of
course internally
this virtual disk is implemented using a
system called pedal
and you know consists actually of many
machines
uh and but you know you get another
machine to replicate you know disc
blocks you know their
passes internally to make sure that like
it's uh you know all operations can
apply it in the right order
and all that kind of stuff but from the
outside perspective you know the
interface is really
uh read a block on writer block
and so it just looks like an ordinary
disk and
uh and so what is interesting in this
you know design if you contrast the two
designs
actually a lot of the complexity in this
design is on the client side
and you know one reason that you like
that or why the is that you know you can
grow
the file system uh with the number of
workstations so if you
increase the number of clients you know
you basically get more cpu power because
you get more clients and you know each
of the clients can drive around its own
file system
and so a lot of the really heavy-duty
computation can just all be done on the
client machines
and doesn't involve you know any file
server at all and just true that in sort
of in the left side the network
traditional network file system design
it's often the case that you know the
performance bottlenecks arise you know
in the uh in the file server you know
when the number of clients actually
uh becomes too large and often in that
case for example you split the file
system in
across different files in reverse okay
so that's sort of the
uh so from our perspective or at least
from a distributed systems in a design
uh frontier binding is interesting
because it's like much more
decentralized
than sort of the traditional uh network
file system designs
and the reason you know they sort of
wanted to explore
uh this design has a lot to do with the
use case that
they imagine or that they were targeting
so i want to say a little bit about the
use case because
uh there were a lot of questions related
to that in email so
so what is the use case the use case is
basically a number of researchers when
engineers
compiling
you know compiling editing you know
their programs or writing documents
and so it's really designed you know the
these papers from the
famous research lab uh in that time tech
circ
and you know deck circuit like you know
tens of uh researchers like
50 to 100 and they're really what
they're doing is designing a file system
for their use case so everybody uh
is trusted uh all the machines are
trusted all the software running and
they don't trust it
and so the security side of things is
really not an issue for that
uh all the these visitors are heavy duty
uh
computer users and you know and so they
want to
but mostly they're working on their own
private files you know they're writing
their own programs they're writing their
drawing documents um and so leaders want
to interact with the files with a high
performance file system
um of course you know they might share
otherwise
sharing would not be uh interesting uh
so they both potentially share files and
directories
and it shows up in two ways you know
they may
work together collaborate together on
writing a paper like the paper that
we're reading today
uh and so uh they want to have access to
uh the shared
files you know for the directory that
holds that particular paper
uh and so so usually the user sharing
and then there's a second form sharing
that like the same user might log into
multiple workstations
more than one workstation and so again
whatever
user one of the researchers who goes to
the public library of dextre
or their library and you know logs in
one of the public workstation with index
work
and it wants to be able to rewrite their
their files from that you know that
machine too
so that's the use case um and
this use case has sort of a number of
design uh
implications or you know design choices
that were motivated
you know by this use case
and so the one of the primary ones
that was motivated by this news case is
caching
so instead of leaving uh the data for
example all in pedal and every read or
write operation goes through pedal
uh they want to arrange it so that most
of actually the action happens in the
workstations
and so the researchers uh since they're
mostly working on their own private
files you know it seems like it'll make
a lot of sense to sort of capture the
data locally on the workstation
uh then as you read and write files
there's like basically no network
traffic really necessary
um and you can sort of uh write right at
high performance
and you know one reason one way they
avoid you know having sending a lot of
traffic to a pedal is they have a right
back cache
instead of a right through and so if
operations happen actually they just
stay in the cache and at some point
later they're percolated you know to uh
pedal as we'll see in the second
one um and so
combined with that like even though
they're doing mostly you know workloads
are going to be
sort of private uh where there's not
sharing going on
of course in the case they do share they
want to have strong consistency
or sometimes called you know coherence
uh and so meaning that for example if
uh one user writes a file then the
another user on the other workstation uh
reads the file it would be great if that
user actually saw
the changes that the the other
workstation the other user has made
and so they want string a strong
consistency
so those are the two design choices that
really drive
this design as well as just you know
basically
performance
so and maybe it's helpful you know to
think a little bit about like
what other use cases could you have
right for file systems and so maybe one
one good one that we talked a lot about
is to think about gfs uh you know would
give us be
a substitute for fronts and pinion or
the other way around like how do they
contrast
and one way to think about this is that
you know gfs is really a file system
designed for mapreduce applications and
so it's a file system where uh
files are not cached in fact you know
the files intend to be so big that they
wouldn't even fit
in the type of caches that we're talking
about the files are basically sort of
red you know sequentially
from beginning to end and that's it and
then maybe you know some other
uh computer will read that file because
there's some other map produce
application running on it
and so i think you think you're back at
gfs there was really no data caching
going on at all you know there was a
little bit of caching going on to
keep track of where uh the truck servers
were
but there's actually no caching of data
going on at all in gfs
so there's also no cache consistency
problem in gfs and so
there's a type of applications that they
were targeting that just didn't make
sense at all similarly in gfs gfs
actually it's not really a real file
system in the sense of the uh here you
know it was not intended to run like vi
gcc uh and so it didn't provide like
straight sort of passage or unique
compatibility yeah
in the franchise you can just run your
standard unix applications
and things just work out and the
applications behave
in the same way as if there was not a
distributed file system basically a
single file system
and again in gfs you know this the there
was
there's a was basically a little library
you know that actually application used
to read or write files
in gfs but it was not like you know 100
units compatible at all
so to give you a sense that you know
these workloads
privately really the design of these
different of these systems you know
in the case of gfs and it's the
mapreduce application that drove the
design
uh in the case of you know from tipani
or the shared file system it's really
collecting users they're working
on some shared file system but most of
the operations you know they're
performing are probably just on files
they own
uh and so it can perform locally
does that make sense in terms of
contrast and settings so you see
actually there are quite a different
number of file systems around you know
like in zookeepers yet another sort of
provides this file system interface but
it's not really a file system you know
it's like more of an
intended as a coordination service you
wouldn't store big files
in zookeeper
any questions about this uh setting
uh can you briefly repeat why having the
file server code running on the client
machine
uh enhances uh scalability
versus having the client and the file
server being on different machines
or on different uh yeah yeah so for
example if you know that i'd like to go
back to this uh previous slide here you
know on the left is the network file
system and correctly
there's many many many clients well
let's figure there's only one
you know there's let me simplify this
picture for a second and let's ignore
the second file server there's one one
file server so that everybody can share
the files and through that file server
then all these clients will be hammering
on that in a single file server
and so all the read or write operations
quick are going to be sent to the file
server the file server does the
directory look up
uh you know opens files and adjusts the
security checks
and all that kind of stuff so all the
computation really for the file system
itself is all happening
on the file server itself in the sort of
traditional network file system design
in the front economy that's not the case
okay confront you penny all the file
system operations are executed on the
workstations
and so we have multiple workstations
that basically you know the workload
that this file system can scale
or can support scales with the number of
workstations
i see and in the traditional uh
architecture so every file server
contains
or stores let's say a section of
the entire file system right so it does
so it's not the case that uh
every single file server has a copy of
the entire system
it's that it might be partitioned across
the files that might be across
like an example in a fast grid you know
there are different volumes
and you know file servers manage you
know different volumes and the data of
all the users at mit is spread across
the different volumes
but all the data like for one volume is
it going to be at one file server and so
if that file
volume gets hit hard you know you're
going to get forms bottlenecks
okay awesome thank you
any more questions about sort of the
setting here before we dive in
to more frontier planning
okay good so now the design choices they
made
uh immediately leads to a number of
challenges
right so i want to talk a little bit
about the challenges
and the main one you know that drives
almost a ton of the design
is let's say you have one workstation
workstation one
so in those days you know people had
workstations and laptops were actually
not
not really existed yet uh today probably
would be all kinds of laptops but again
so there's a workstation and somebody
like whatever reach a file
file f whatever you know the maybe the
grades database or the grades file
and so that you know basically that
means that that file actually is cached
you know inside of the
workstation and so the client you know
whatever
program running you know vi you know
gonna update and manipulate
the file and then you know sometimes
later the result will be written back
you know to
pedal the the the disk if you will
and so the challenges that are basically
around this module are free fault
uh one uh somebody else on workstation
two
maybe at some point do a cat event
you know get it to file f and of course
you know that should be the case that
you know
at least like we normally expect if we
have a traditional unix file system
that you know you will see the last
write you know to that particular f
so even though the right might have
happened at a different workstation
uh when the second workstation reads the
file
we would like to see that uh data show
up and this is what they you know
we're going to be roughly this broadly
comes to cash coherence
and other word synonyms for coherence or
cash consistency
uh which is like the term that we have
been seeing more uh
in the previous papers uh but in the
sort of out of the computer architecture
world actually the the term coherence
comes
comes from that world and so you can
think about them as
synonyms uh
two the second problem that you know you
uh
that's going to occur and we need to
deal with is that let's say that
workstation one
and workstation 2 both want to create a
file in particular in the shared
directory so like
here the workstation 1 creates a file
f in the directory d and workstation 2
also creates a file say g
in directory d and we want to
arrange it at least that like if
workstation one makes the changes and
then workstation two makes the changes
that like both files appear and that
like one file doesn't overwrite
uh say the directory uh of the other
uh or basically overwrites the directory
in a way that actually the other files
would disappear
so this has to so the second topic here
really is automatically
the operations of creating a file really
has to be
it has to be sort of an atomic operation
so that they don't get interleaved and
then we get
wrong results and then the final problem
uh that we need to deal with is that uh
you know workstation one you know might
crash
while doing one of these complex file
system operations
and so there has to be story you know
how actually the file system recovers
and so this is really a story about
crash recovery
so for example like in this first case
where like a workstation makes a file in
the directory d
you know there's actually a complex
operation you know the directory needs
to be modified
an inode needs to be allocated and i
don't need to be initialized
uh and then the i know number needs to
be written into the directory so there's
multiple sort of file system operation
involved in it and we wanted to be the
case that you know if the file system
crashes between
any of these uh steps in this sort of
complex file system operation
it better be the case that the file
system recovers correctly and what we
mean we file something recovered
correctly at least that it's internal
data structures are correct
and so for example that the inode is not
lost because it doesn't show up in the
directory
et cetera et cetera or like even that
the whole so the internal structures are
consistent
and so this is the topic of crash
recovery and so panel basically
we're at front upon he needs to address
you know all these uh three problems and
uh my plan is just go uh walk through
them
uh one by one and uh discuss how
francipani
addresses them any questions about the
top level
challenges
okay let's you know proceed so the first
thing is cash adherence
for cash consistency
and so the
key you know aspect in the solution that
francophone uses is that actually is a
lock server somewhere
and so and the lock server
basically has a table and for
uh every file and actually it's an inode
number but for every file
who has to walk at this particular point
of time so who's the owner
so we might have a file f and it
basically says you know it works and for
which
the lock server has a record that the
workstation one owns that particular
lock um and the lock server itself
is a distributed uh service and
you can almost think about it that are
sort of almost like zookeeper uh you
know it is a
uh it provides an acquiring releasing of
logs uh
it's fault tolerant uh in the case of uh
franciupani they do some taxes
based implementation uh but is spread
over across multiple machines
uh highly fault tolerant uh et cetera et
cetera
so that's the the the
lock server the turns out that the
workstation sort of also
keep a table for
their locks so here's workstation one
and you know there might be you know
let's say workstation one
cache is filed f and g
you know maybe h is cached by
workstation uh looks workstation one
where
h is maybe cached by workstation two uh
and then you know workstation one has a
similar table
and that list for where every file for
every lock that it holds
where it's either busy or idle
so like maybe f you know the lock status
is busy
and that really means that actually the
file server is just operating on that
file
so it's actively using that file and
there's a second state namely let's say
we have file g there's also cache there
and maybe g is actually in the state but
there's a call idle
and that means actually the g at that
point is not being modified
or not being worked on uh by the file so
for that particular instant time
uh but it's basically you know what they
call a sticky lock
so that if you know the file server at
some point soon you know it's going to
use
g again it can actually do so without
actually having to communicate with
pedal
or reload its cache or anything like
that at all because it has a sticky lock
it knows that nobody else actually has
acquired no other workstation has
required to walk in the meantime
so that's the sticky lock and it turns
out that
the the the the uh you know these are
the two building blocks that are then
being used to what they call
what's what is called a cash coherence
protocol and
a set of messages or a set of rules that
are being followed to actually uh get
cash consistency
and the basic rule is that uh you know
the
guiding rule is you know to cache a file
your first must acquire the lock
and we'll see that that should is sort
of the stepping stone for actually
getting
uh consistency or cash coherence
is i'm going to make a smaller
simplification uh
in the paper they described their
unlocks basically being exclusive or
read the writer locks i'm just going to
assume for the rest of the lecture that
they're exclusive it doesn't really
matter but
there's an optimization that basically
multiple workstations can have a file
cached
in read-only mode
okay so with that let me talk a little
bit about you know the
let's catch out the protocol
that francophone uses uh
and again you know cash coherence or
cash consistency
uh the goal actually for even though the
file system is distributed
it should behave like a single file
system so if you only have one file
server you know you want
basically that the same results will be
returned by the distributed file system
so you can't tell the difference whether
it's distributed or not um
and so this is actually reminding you of
like linearizability so in fact you know
i believe actually what the frontier
shoots for is actually linearizable file
system operations
okay so we've got the lock server
uh we've got workstation one
and there's workstation two
and uh there's sort of four messages
that are important here there's a namely
requesting a lock
uh granting a lock and revoking a lock
and actually releasing the lock so those
are the four messages that fly
between back and forth between
workstations and lock server and lock
server
and other workstations so let's uh look
at this let's say the lock server has
nobody has any locks at any time so
let's draw some timelines
and workstation in one wants to request
once they read write uh file f you know
basically send some requests for the
lock you know to the lock server for
file f
so the workstation but can't do anything
really at this point yet
uh the lock server node checks you know
if it's table and sees that f actually
is
not used by anybody at all it's gonna
list workstation one
as the lock owner and sends basically
message backs and granting
the lock for f so at this point
your workstation one exquired to walk
for f
now it can actually read and write where
now we can actually read you know the
file from pedal
and actually you can make modifications
to it too and all those specifications
just
stay local you know nothing really
happens it's a right uh
that cache not a right through cache and
so it just stays happily on the
on the client side uh in fact the
workspace you can even
release the lock you know here and
basically you know go from bc to idle
and so if it actually uh would need to
lock again for example once the right
after reading right half again you know
you can
actually do the completely local without
any interaction with the log server
but there's a slight simplification here
you know there's as we'll see in a
second
that the unlock has a lease associated
with it so the client at least has to
refresh the disk periodically
but it doesn't have to re-write or
re-re-read you know the file f
from actually paddle if the leads hasn't
expired
okay so so the instant case of course
happens like you know what if
workstation 2
wants to read the file f right so
you know what will happen let's say
workstation two wants to read and
basically it will do the same thing it
will
send an uh an acquire or a request
message sorry
request message to lock server saying i
want f
and the way it then works is that the
log server actually
looks at this table sees that f is
actually owned by
workstation one and then we'll send a
revoked message
to workstation one asking
the lock back so that will revoke f
and at this point uh pedal alex has to
do a little bit of
front defining actually has a little bit
of work uh because then we have to make
sure that workstation two observes the
rights
that workstation one is done and so the
way that is done is that basically this
instance of time uh
the workstation one writes actually f
you know to pedal
and we'll see in a second that actually
writing f2 panel is actually a slightly
complicated operation it's more
sophisticated than i'm just making it
out to be
but just think about it like at this
point workstation one is basically
flashing its state
related to f and a to pedal once that
actually is completed so like once
pedals are acknowledged that actually it
actually has received all the data
it actually sends a message back
releasing f
and you know once the lock server gets
the release of f you know that can
update
it's stable you know and allocate the
lock to workstation two
and sends you know a grant
for f to two oops
and at this point uh the workstation two
requires lock
and now it can actually read all the
information uh from
the file f and pedal at that point it is
guaranteed
that we'll see the latest changes to
uh the file f because the previous owner
must have flushed you know the state
you know to the um to pedal
uh before it actually released the lock
and gave it back to the walk server
and so workstation two is guaranteed to
actually observe those changes and so
here's where our strong
consistency comes in basically the
strong consistencies are tied
to the walk management
any questions about this
there's
okay one question in the chat let me
address the first uh would we need to
write to pedal when releasing both read
and write locks
why do we need to write to pedal when
releasing a read lock
uh let me let's ignore uh read write
the distinction between read and write
exclusive logs and read write logs
um and uh
and just focus on exclusive locks you
know the real the whole
reading is just a small app you know as
it happens an important optimization
uh but it doesn't really change the
designer system that dramatically
any other questions so this sort of
design
would be really inefficient if we have
like two different workstations that are
both modifying the same file
yeah you just get like cache bouncing
back and forth
yeah yeah you really if you're two box
stations or two different engineers at
dexter where you'd be banging on the
same file you know the
file would go back and forth uh
and and so this is not really suitable
so you can see here the influence of
like the
uh workload that they're designing for
uh you know their really assumption is
that basically
you know most engineers are working on
their private files and
you know once a while they'll share
files but they're probably not banging
on the same shared file
i mean you know we're not using git but
like you could imagine like if they have
a share of your
code repositories or you check out your
own copy of the code repository make all
the modifications and at some point you
write it back
i'm sorry just to make sure you said you
can release the lock
um while you still have the file in the
cash right
you can uh okay so
be very careful with what i meant with
releasing the lock there is not
releasing it to the lock server
but locally you know changing the status
from busy to idle
and since you know the lock is sticky
you know it still sits at workstation
one and the lock server are still things
actually workstation one has to walk
is that answering your question yeah
yeah thank you so what happens um
if the request from uh two comes
a while it's busy yeah that's a good
question
what do you think that happens does it
just reject it
no that's i think it doesn't reject it
but just waits it waits until
uh workstation one is done you know
modifying the file after
executing its file system operation and
then
uh the franchise code will release
locally the lock we'll see that someone
is waiting for it
and so doesn't change it into uh busy
but actually starts flushing all the
operations to
pedal and then releases the lock
so this comes actually nicely to the
second point uh which is this
automatically points and so maybe that
will make it more clear
let me talk a little bit about the misid
because it also uses
the same locks to actually achieve
atomic optic file system operations
so using locks
so when for example you do a create
operation like you execute the create
file system operation
or whatever create f you know whatever
the usual arguments
that there's of course internally even
though the application makes this create
file system called this internally
actually has multiple
uh file system modifications you know
for example you know the
directory needs to be modified actually
let me do it in a slightly different
order
we need to allocate an inode you know
for f
we need to initialize that inode
write the i node and then you know
update the directory
update the directory to add an entry
basically for
you know the tuple f and whatever inode
number
was allocated for f so there's a typical
way in which a unix file system
implements files and so we need the
range that these operations uh
happen atomically because we don't want
to sort of intermediate results be
visible to other
workstations and the way that happens is
using you know by acquiring those locks
we acquire the lock
for this particular inode you know for
example it was i know 10. so you require
a lot for f i'm just going to
use f as the lock thing but yeah
it's going to be an inaudible number and
then at some point it releases
the file system at the implantation
itself releases the lock
and again this releases a local release
operation it doesn't really
mean immediately uh releasing it back to
the lock server just
changing the status from bc to idle
and so so if at any particular point in
time
as we just ask you know there's a
request coming in for
uh you know revoke the lock
f that request is not actually being
served
until the file system the local front
sympathy file system and workstation one
has calls the local release operation
and then it sees that
when it does the local release operation
it sees that there's a
revoke waiting and so at this point it's
going to flush
you know its cache state
this cache state to pedal
and once it actually has from a floccid
cache state to pedal uh
it will uh grant basically the revoke or
accept the revoke and send back a
release to the lock server so that then
the lock can you know be
assigned you know to our workstation two
does that make sense
um so just to make sure so in this
create operation here we have to modify
the inode for so we have to modify the i
node for f and the i node for the
directory that contains fb
because we have to update the references
and so that means that
like technically speaking we're actually
holding two
locks and we have to release both of
them before we reply back to the revoked
request
yes absolutely so uh so again there's a
whole section about this over in the
paper and then really
talk about this in two but basically
they sort of have
not very coarse grain blocks but also
not very fine-grained
brush locks they basically have a lock
you know per i node
and you know the director's an inode
file is an inode uh and in fact the
director is nothing else than a file
with
sort of a specific uh format format
uh and so really the great f you know
would actually have to allocate
first allocate the lock or acquire the
lock in the directory d
and then you know would allocate or
acquire the walk on uh
inode for f and so to hold two locks
and as you probably have noticed you
know the of course if you assume you
have to acquire multiple locks there's a
potential risk of deadlock you know if
like one workstation
uh allocates locks into different order
you know you could have doc that lock
and so front supine follows the rules
that basically all walks are ordered in
a particular way
and you require the walks in a fixed
order
i say thank you i think the lock's
awarded by what number i node number
does that all make sense yeah so there's
a bunch of more complexity there
okay so the you know sort of
having discussed sort of the ethnicity
of file system operations at least you
know during crashes
you know if there's no crashes you know
at least it's guaranteed that these uh
operations should happen atomically
because the walks ensure atomicity
of course that could be the case that
like we're unlucky
right and sort of uh the workstation one
crashes like
right in the middle of these operations
so example it has allocated
allocated the inode it actually has not
updated the directory yet
and uh let's say the crash happens here
uh you know and if we don't do anything
special like
what is the concern that we might have
okay let me uh the concern that we might
have is that you know some
file system operation actually is only
partially applied to pedal
uh and you know that becomes more clear
if we actually think about
the scenario what actually happens in
this particular state
like when the state of the cache is
actually flushed you know to
pedal and so this is the topic of crash
recovery
it turns out that actually updating the
state in
updating the state in that pedal also
follows actually pretty careful protocol
and this protocol is typically called
write ahead logging
and this is a you know probably the term
you already have seen uh i mean you've
seen it probably in 6033
uh and uh you know pedal uses it too
it's a very common technique and it will
also play a big important role in the
subsequent papers that we'll see and so
a pedal is actually a nicer
reintroduction to
this idea of right-hand logging and the
way to think about writing you know i'm
gonna
it's a pedal's design of writer letter
hogging
use of right head locking is very
similar to any other right head logging
scheme
and so you know the way to think about
it as follows you know we have our disk
our virtual disk i mean you could think
about the disk as like a
long long array of blocks and
what they've done is they're part of the
disk is like reserved
as a log in fact in the case of pedal
there's a log per server but let's for
for now let's just assume there's like
one single log
and then there's the file system so
there's part of the disk is the user for
the logging you know part of the disk is
the file system and the file system
contains
inodes you know some data blocks
et cetera et cetera and the rule is that
when you update the state in pedal the
first thing you do
is actually you first log the update
so when uh if we go back to the previous
picture
and after at the point that the
uh uh friendship only on workstation one
i wanted to give back the lock you know
to the lock server it first has to
write its state you know to pedal and
that goes in two steps
the first step is log the uh update
the description of the update you know
to uh the log
to the log person so here for example
you know we'll get a record
that says like you know create basic
describes the create operation so it
will have
you know whatever allocate inode i know
number or whatever
basically the result that would have
happened if you allocate it i know
number and
the directory change
and we'll be a little bit more specific
in a second but that's sort of the the
update contains the modifications that
need to be made to happen
to the file system blocks to actually uh
reflect you know the change
so you first you know log to the uh
first log the update
and then once you have updated the log
then we uh the second operation that the
client executes
the workstation executes is actually
installing the update
um and uh and
the reason you know for doing it instead
of two steps is that
you know once you know you've logged all
your changes
then it's completely safe to update the
data blocks because they always will end
up in order to
update the file system because it always
will end up in a consistent state
um and the way to see this is basically
let's assume you know the client
workstation that was actually flushing
its state to
a pedal you know crashes right here
uh is that okay
yes because since everything is locked
the
hey what was it called like the demon
recovery service yeah
correct so yeah the demon just can go
back to uh
there's gonna be a demon when there's a
crash there's basically demon sees if
there's anything in the log if there's
anything in the log it just applies it
to the file system
and why actually do this in this way why
not just write immediately or update the
file system
because we can crash in the middle of
the update and we don't know
what we've done and what we didn't yeah
exactly correct so if you
sort of in our previous example you know
the allocating an i note is presumably
you know it's making some change
somewhere
like going through a nine-note block and
actually adding the directory
to uh or adding the file f you know to a
particular directory presumably updates
a directory block or a data block
somewhere
and so these are two separate rights
right through separate disk walks and
they're not atomic so we would crash
between one of the two
then we might have allocated the inode
but not stuck in the directory
right then basically what what what
happened if we crash and recover
it's basically we lose the inode unless
you know we could scan the whole disk
but that's
very expensive and so instead what we're
doing
is we're basically logging the two
changes first we're
we're logging a record describing both
changes first
and then you know apply the changes
uh so how do we ensure that operation
one is atomic so the first log to update
the first log update yeah that's
interesting so the the paper tracking
now
uh crisp on this but there's a couple
ways of doing it um
they mentioned that every uh
log record has a checked zone and
uh so they use the check show to see if
there's actually
so before the reader log record you know
they read the log record we compute the
checksum
just to make sure that the whole record
is complete
i see thank you another way of doing it
which is a couple way of doing it is you
write you know a couple blocks
like one two and then you're ready to
commit record and
the assumption is that running a single
block a single five in the 12
sector is an atomic operation so it
either happens or doesn't happen
and so either commit record says rights
are done or rights are not done
and so you can just look at the commit
record and if the commit records
is not there then you know that you know
the operation is
not completely recorded yet and you
shouldn't execute any of it
i see and also to double check to in the
previous
slide if the crash happens before we
flush things to
pedal then this is not a problem right
because uh
if the workstation crashes well the
cache goes with the workstation but
there's no inconsistent state for any
other workstation
that's correct yeah just the data will
be lost that's it uh
but it will since it's not written
battles won't be any visibility problem
so it's really you know the crash the
crash here correct
that one doesn't really matter in some
ways the one that actually matters is
the crash during this flush operation
thank you
okay so there's one subtlety
in front france pioneer which we'll talk
about in a second a little bit more
deeper
the detail namely that in france there's
a
lock per server
and that's sort of unusual and
we'll see in a second you know how the
one that actually creates some problems
uh and so we'll we'll see there's a
there's a small extension to the
protocol to actually
make this all work out okay
let me uh say a little bit about like
what is in one of those log records
because that turns out to be important
for uh
the crash recovery uh particularly
because
we have frontier binding as multiple
logs per server
so every log has a so your log basically
you know there are records in it they
have a sequence number
you know whatever security number two
one two
and you know what the end of the log is
if the next sequence number is not
higher one higher than
yours so there's another way to mark it
up
and basically in one of these records
you know is an array is an array of
updates
now describe the file system operation
and so it contains the block number
that needs to be updated so for example
in our case that would be
would be uh uh the i know number the
block that contains the inode uh that
would have been allocated
a version number is in that record and
we'll see in a second
why that is important and basically the
new bytes
for that block number and so for example
in the case of creating you know
file you know creating f there's going
to be you know two
uh entries in this array you know two
entries
one describing you know the update to
the inode block the one describing
you update to the directory block the
data block of the directory
and so basically what happens on the
gratification just to like make
you know it's abundantly clear right
when a request through the
vocal lock comes in you know the first
thing that happens is force the log
to pedal once then is done
send the updates or send the blocks to
update the blocks to pedal
and then release the lock
and this ensures that you know there's a
couple things that we need to sort of
think about
uh if there's no crashes in the middle
then you know this is just
always as briefly described really you
know the interesting case is when
a crash happens right after forcing the
log to p
uh before updating pedal
so let's talk a little bit about that
sorry what do you mean by new bytes
ah good let me
go back so with another mean the changes
to the
i know box so for example the i know
block
uh you know maybe you update you know
some part of the i know then you sort of
write down what the the whatever the
bytes
have changed like you know bytes zero to
five and twelve of the following value
or bytes you know 10 to 20 half the
following new value
what can those changes be like because
each one of these blocks is at most
512 bytes right yeah but the the
modifications that you make could be
like a lot larger than
512 bytes uh there's gonna be a record
for every uh
block so in fact in the okay so
a couple points uh first of all
uh data rights actually are not going
through the log so this is actually an
important point so thank you thank you
for asking that question
so when you write a file uh and the
application
recalls like write file f and a whole
bunch of data
all that data actually does not go
through the log
that just goes straight to pedal like
once you're flush the
state the only changes that go through
the log are meta update
changes so meta data changes
and what metadata means is really
information about files
so inodes directories that kind of stuff
that actually goes through the log
and so uh the description that you see
in here is really you know the updates
to the metadata blocks you know of the
file system
so inodes and directory data
and the application level data like the
the file blocks that actually constitute
a file
uh that actually those blocks are just
written straight to pedal and don't go
for block
so it's interesting to contemplate you
know what is the implications of that
like that design choice
what's the downside of not writing
everything through the log
first
the updates to the data they can be lost
they can get lost yeah what other sort
of
scenarios are possible so let's say you
know the file consists of 10 blocks
uh we start writing the 10 blocks you
know what's
in what what states can the file
actually end up
being consistent yeah well yeah
ecosystem could have some of the rights
none of the rights
all of them who knows what correct but
it's not guaranteed that all 10 of them
will be applied together
um is is so is this important when you
have like
like this like need for atomic right
or um yeah
like if you didn't need atom atomicity
uh with this like could we get rid of
that of the log
uh the the i think though so hold on
hold on the question in a second let's
first talk about the applications right
and then
we'll come back to that uh so um
okay um the uh
the so the applications can't really
write you know their data atomically
uh for your log because the the data is
now written through the log
and it's not written to the log and then
apply it so
so that means that for example if as an
application you want authenticity of
uh of your rights into a particular file
then you have to arrange that for that
yourself and this actually turns out to
be the case on most unix files in any
way
and so like in that way from japan it
doesn't really change the game
uh you know if you write a file on the
unix file system
uh you write like a vm image and it's
not guaranteed that like the whole
image is written consistently in one
single shot you know to the
file system um even when there are
crashes
so the typical way you know people solve
this problem uh
in applications is that you first write
a temporary file
write everything in the temporary file
and then do an atomic rename
you know to the destination file name
and so francophony basically relies
exactly on the same
uh setup uh sort of normal unix would do
so like transplanting doesn't change the
game and this is why
uh the rights of files are actually not
logged
you know through the log and what is the
advantage of not logging so clearly
there's a downside right because you
can't do file rights atomically using
the log you have to have your own plan
for
doing automaticity and what was the
advantage
well performance because metadata is
very small compared to the actual
user data yeah and also memory as well
yeah exactly so the uh so like if you
write
like a gigantic file correct you're like
saying the gigabyte file that really
means you have to write two gigabytes
right
first you're gonna write the gigabyte
from through the log and then you write
a gigabyte you know through the disk
and so basically this cuts in their
performance in uh pretty dramatically
and so which is why you know typically
you know the user data that uh is not
written for bluewater
uh yeah it's very important of course
when coming back to this earlier
question it's very important that the
internal file system structures
are kept consistent whether they are not
you know are not
uh inconsistent and so uh
therefore the metadata updates all go
through the log
and so then basically you know like when
you create a file you need to update the
i know block and you need to update the
directory block that's
guaranteed to happen together
um so would the data blocks updates go
between
step two and three uh
yeah i think that you just send them out
i mean they probably uh
after one they probably sent the data
blocks in parallel to
uh uh yeah as part of step two and
straight to pedal to the file system
area
okay so i
i had i had a question i think um
i don't remember exactly how big the log
was but i believe
it could span like two blocks
is that the price multiple yeah the log
is multiple records
um oh yeah yeah that's right like up to
two terabytes so
what happens if we um if we send
like a lot like part of a log and then
it crashes as as you're sending the log
when when we get like a
an issue with like that's exactly this i
want to talk about
good thank you uh so there's a bunch of
crashes that could happen right
like so uh so if we can actually
consider a bunch of cases like we write
a crash before writing to the walk
so what in that case what's the icon
um it's it's lost yeah lost
so uh then we're gonna do the scenario
like we crash after writing the log
what happens then there's actually a
slightly complicated scenario
is this after writing like the log to uh
to pedal
yeah then the demon
steps in yes and then the demon steps in
and there's a little bit of a
complicated story correct because
you know what uh so how does this is all
discovered like what actually happens
so presumably what happens is somebody
else wants the law the lock
correct on this file that you know that
the crashed workstation holds
and you know here's where the lease is
coming important right so
every lock has release and what the lock
server will do
it will not grant you know the the lock
server will ask
in workstation one please give me your
lock f back
uh workstation one you know it doesn't
respond because it's crashed
and what the lock server does
it waits until the lease expires from
the lock
and why does it wait until the lease is
expired
i i think i think in this case the um
the the server
that or yeah the server that crashed
like also knows
um it didn't like renew its lease so it
can clean up by like its own
yeah can clean up his own stuff so like
what is the sort of what's the
fundamental problem here that we're
actually trying to challenge almost like
the
the scenario that we've seen over and
over in previous lectures that that is
always a challenge
the partition no repetition exactly
it could be the case that you know
actually workstation one did not crash
but the lock server can't talk to the uh
to the workstation because of the
network petition
but the wire and the work says you can
talk to paddle and so it might not still
may
make changes right but what are we
guaranteed as you just pointed out
once the lease expires workstation one
will definitely not make any changes
it is not allowed to you know follows
the protocol it's not allowed to make
any changes anymore
and so this is uh so why the lock server
waits until the lease expires then at
that point it knows for sure that nobody
holds the lock anymore or couldn't hold
the lock and nobody's writing to pedal
anymore
and so at this point it will ask one of
the remaining workstations to
uh basically what they're called the the
demon
the recovery demon to recover to run the
recovery demon
and the recovery demon basically will
apply uh we'll read
the the log of the workstation one you
know it's log
and basically apply the operations that
are in that log
okay uh
the way to think about a daemon uh it's
just sort of like a
this is like terminology uh it's
typically just a surface
or server or sort of a process uh that
basically does sort of uh house cleaning
or house
cleaning tasks and those kind of
services that are sort of not really
used
continuously they're often called demons
so once the daemon is done then actually
the lock you know can be
the lock server can reassign the lock or
grant the walk to somebody to another
workstation
um but just to double check so uh uh if
you crash after
writing the log then you'll get and
you're gonna have a consistent state
when it comes to the metadata but the
user is not guaranteed to have finished
writing the user data yep absolutely so
there's no guarantees about the user
data
so the only thing the the guarantees
that like really the logging system
helps achieving is basically consistency
of the internal file system data
structures
okay sounds good
which is important correct because it
would be pretty bad if the file internal
file system data structures are messed
up
you know everybody might lose their data
okay so then there's another instant
case
uh what can happen okay so writing the
log to p
uh what happens if we crash during
writing the law
is this what you mentioned before that
like there are check sums and we can
check whether it was like complete or
not
or is this yeah so okay so good good
point uh
so so what happens in this case correct
is that a prefix might end up
in the the prefix it might end up in the
log right
uh but each of the and the prefix might
contain multiple
uh log records for multiple operations
correct like you know whatever secrets
number one secret number two
the multiple uh records uh if we crash
during
one of these wreckage updates you know
then uh the checksums won't check out
and so we'll basically stop
you know the the recovery demand will
stop at that record
so what will be in the log will be a
correct prefix of the operations so for
example you know the
create of file f is in there maybe the
create file file g is in there
but the creator file h is not in there
but each individual record that
describes one atomic you know file
system operation
and is is in there and is complete and
so
what will happen is that basically we'll
apply a prefix of the
operations that the workstation is uh
doing and we basically lose the end of
the prefix
or the end of the its updates you know
undesirable but you know totally okay
because you know in the other case we
might have lost in all updates
and in the first case we were clashed
before the log we would have nothing on
this
does that make sense
[Applause]
okay then there's one uh one more tricky
case
uh that you know we need to consider and
that has to do with the fact that
actually the pedal has a walk per server
or log per server
so i want to talk a little bit about
that and this is related to the
question in a post you know for the
reading
and this is about many logs and so let's
say we have
free workstations each with their own
log
so here's workstation one workstation
two workstation three
and workstation one at some point does a
delete
of a file f that happened to exist
before
then uh workstation two there's a create
of d and f and but that create remember
is written to its own log
okay so this this delete is written to
the log of workstation one this creates
is written to the log
of workstation two and now let's say
uh workstation one crashes
and uh and then workstation three
you know basically you know the recovery
team runs
you know for a workstation one
and you know the bad possible outcome
correct is that it would delete
replay the delete which would overwrite
you know the changes
uh that workstation two made to head up
right so that's the context and the
question is how is this fixed
and i think this the way i would like to
address this is by actually you know
having you
spend a couple minutes in the breakout
room uh debate this with each other or
any other aspect of
uh pedal if you uh want to
and so
lily or anybody else any of the other
tas
can you send people to breakout rooms
should i do it or yeah that'd be great
if you're good okay cool
all right
um i'll close them in about five minutes
yup five minutes would be perfect
[Music]
action
so
[Music]
everybody back
okay so just uh just uh quickly uh
re-summarize here so we have three
workstations
workstation one at some point deleted
the file
it's in the log uh workstation two at
some point later
created a created file f it is in this
log
and then one crashes and workstation
three actually runs the recovery daemon
on the log of workstation one
and of course it would be disaster if
the the lead would be replayed
because the later create has happened on
another workstation but it's in another
lock so the
demon doesn't know what how is this
problem solved
or how is this potentially disaster
avoided
we we said version numbers yeah yeah
jose can you say a little bit more if
you want to sure
um so like it's guaranteed because we
had the lock that the
operations have already completed for
for
um for server one yep
um and so the like the
version number for the log is written in
uh
in pedal like the last operation and so
the
recovery demand won't do anything
previous to the
uh current version number yeah okay so
let's say you're
absolutely right so we'll just summarize
this so we have two
logs correct that actually of importance
and we have some file system
state that sits in the pedal right so
these are the logs and then
here's the actual file system
and uh here was you know like this is
directory d
you know vector d was modified and the
file f was
deleted and that has a log number uh i
say
10. and
this is a workstation 2 and here is a d
that was deleting the fmd and here's
creating f and d and what log number
will be in this
uh entry
version number sorry
11 11 yep right because
basically totally ordered and the
locking protocol will ensure that
they're totally ordered
and on the in the file system with the
metadata blocks like for example with
the inode block for f
i know f what version number is going to
be on the disk
or in pedal
11 yeah in the case that actually the
operation was applied to the file system
it would be 11 correct
and so when the demon we
uh what rule does the demon follow
never replays something that's already
been applied
yeah now does it decide if it's applied
like a version number yeah the version
number right so if the version of it
only
reapplies an entry if the version number
in the log record
large numbered version number is higher
than the inode or the metadata
version number
and then replay okay
so in this case you know the recovery
demon will see that the
version number in the log bracket is 10
which is smaller than 11
or equal to 11 doesn't matter and so it
won't replay it and so this problem
cannot appear
so does the 10 necessarily not does is
that is it okay such that like the 10
is not on the ws workspace 2's log
yeah it's not there so like in the work
because the workstation 2
uh wrote actually the i know the after
you know workstation one and so it's uh
version number b11
basically when you do a prepare an
update the version number in the update
record is always
one plus you know the current version
number in the inode
okay this is a small question but what
does the d stand for and uh
directly to directory okay okay
we're creating a file in the directory d
we're deleting a file from the directory
d
and the update must include you know the
so many information about the directory
okay so um sorry i had a quick question
so
are the best version numbers like always
tied to the specific i know that's being
edited
yes okay that's only
the the version numbers for every update
correct like there's a version memory
for
the directory there's a version number
for the file i'm like showing this a
little bit wrong here
like if you go back to the log record uh
here basically there's an array of
updates and every update
in the array you know completes block
number the version number and the new
bytes
thanks
okay so just stepping back and closing
off this discussion of this paper
so it's probably the first paper that
we've read that basically in order the
system itself is not the one you know
it's not going
in dominant use and therefore it's
really interesting to talk about
uh but what is interesting about this
system is the ideas in it
and so cash coherence protocol
more cash consistence c protocol
uh distributed locking
the lock servers leases
uh granting and acquiring and
revoking and uh distributed recovery
you know where one workstation crashes
but like a demon on another
workstation actually does the recovery
and what
particularly interesting is it what's
interesting is sort of the interaction
between the three pieces
then they interact
and what we'll see in the next you know
a couple papers uh
next week particularly not uh not on the
first day but the the
papers after that which we're going to
talk about sort of heavy duty
pretty involved you know transaction
systems we'll see these three topics
going to come up
uh too and so hopefully this will help
you when
reading those papers should understand
actually what cache can earns is
what you know crash recovery is and uh
you know distributor locks are um and
the other very probably point
and that's interesting to make is that
you know the you know
pedal is really good you know for useful
for the particular
setting they designed it for
and the performance part of the paper is
a little bit hard to understand because
it's like for 1999
but you look at the graph you'll see
that the
file system basically workload can
increase with the number of workstations
and you know that's exactly what they
were shooting for and
you know and they achieved that goal
anyway i hope you find this
design interesting and sort of not your
usual design and so hopefully that's a
thought-provoking
and with that i'll stop of course you
know
stick around if you want to ask more
questions and otherwise we'll see your
first day
um can i can i ask two questions um
my first question was just in general
the cash coherence protocol here
is to not have one file cached
into places right okay
um and my other question was about the
there was a um a page
with the log i mean you had the log
um records there yep let me go back here
yeah yeah um and i was
i was wondering you said that each
each like record is
atomic but each record has a number of
updates
too right yes uh and again i think the
paper is slightly vague here what
exactly what it does
either it always fits in 512 bytes and
then a single sector for 512 bytes just
is uh atomic or they uh
use this checksum trick so uh
you re-two and five the final bytes uh
sectors
you recompute the checksum and compare
it with the checks on the store there
and if it's the right then
you know it must be a complete record
okay okay so if it's shorter than good
if it's not then you do the trick
okay i see yeah i'm not sure what they
exactly do
oh okay okay thank you so much
you're welcome
any more questions
uh if you go uh back or forward
three slides yep here there was a
oh maybe back one slide there's a
section where you talked about how
if a crash happens during the middle of
a right and we get like yeah a prefix in
the log
um that's like okay or something do you
mind repeating what you meant
there yeah okay so uh so
let's go back to this last picture i
just showed uh earlier
here so here we have our show the the
workstation one could have executed many
many file system operations correct
each one of them uh described by one of
these log
by an entry in the log so like the first
entry
it might be creating file f because the
second entry in the log might be
creating file g you know whatever the
third one migrating and deleting file f
and so there's a whole sequence of
operations because remember the
workstation just keeps executing uh
file system operations uh as long as it
holds the logs and
nobody else wants the loss and so the
log
could be uh containing a whole bunch of
file system operations
now for each file system operation for
each individual one there's a log record
and the log record you know is the
atomic file system operation the
description of the changes that need to
be made to the actual file system blocks
to uh reflect you know that file system
operation
and so what could happen correct is that
uh
the revoked message comes in the
workstation one starts writing its log
you know to uh panel but it just doesn't
get all the way to the end it just
happens to crash like somewhere in the
middle
like anywhere right in that case
basically a prefix of the workstation
log is on the disk
or in pedal and that means that
basically the last couple file system
operations are just locks
and only the prefix will be replayed
i see and we're just saying that's okay
yeah we're accepting that outcome
got it thank you because we're already
accepted to that outcome earlier right
because it could have been the case that
we
the file system crashed like right
before or right after we got the revoked
message but it actually didn't write any
log entries
you have to do to pedal
any more questions
i have a completely unrelated question
sure
go ahead um two eight to four but
i was wondering if you knew um anything
about
uh 6858 for next semester i saw
professor saldwich is going to be
teaching
uh 6 so 860. yeah i think we're
the current players not to offer 858 in
the
[Music]
fall but we're hoping
to offer it in the spring okay awesome
uh do you know what 6.060
is i i couldn't find much information
yet so that's a good question
uh it's intended to be an uh
undergrad security class okay
okay nice so like six eight five seven
six
eight five eight but um undergrad
yeah sort of like uh maybe an intro to
both six eight five seven and six eight
five eight
okay what's the number
it's an experimental number it's one of
these experimental ones because the
class doesn't exist yet
it will be offered for the you know the
goal is to offer it for the first time
in the fall
okay and um so is is it going to be
mostly like content from
like is 858 gonna keep its original form
or is it uh
you're asking me questions i don't know
sorry yeah
and i think uh the people involved in
in designing the class are people that
are involved in 857 and the people
involved in a fight yeah
i'm not actually involved okay yet
another reason but
um and they're trying to work out what
the curriculum exactly is going to be
and then of course it's going to have
some percolations for 858 and 857.
okay sounds good but eight five eight
and eight five seven are not gonna go
away
if that's the great
thanks you're welcome as a
question i don't know how quick it is
but um and the paper at the end of
page um or like right before section
seven
they talk about a case a failure where
uh with like the lease expiring yeah and
the server not really crashing
yeah and then talk about like um
basically that there's no real solution
to this well
there is a solution uh there's a real
solution
and okay it's like human intervention
yeah
okay so i think the problem here really
is this was the theme of the paperwork
like you know paddle and franchopani are
designed independently
and that has a lot of nice properties uh
and this is one where one one place
where it would be very helpful
hopefully that your pedal has some
support you know to help franciupani
along
and that support would be actually have
a time stamp on the right
two pedals so that pedal can see when a
ride actually is out of the
basically too old
okay so unless you do that you need to
like fiddle around with like the margin
yes exactly okay and what happens if
um like uh
that error occurs like outside of the
bounds of the margin
ah i mean that's a cool
basically you get an old uh right you
know showing up in uh
basically somebody else might at that
point gotten the lock on the file
correctly starting writing to it
and then this old write shows up and
basically presumably overwrite some part
of it
okay so we'll bring consistency
sweet thank you you're welcome