so the topic for today is uh
raft uh
replication formula protocol uh that
we'll discuss in quite a bit of detail
uh in fact uh we're gonna spend multiple
lectures on it um
and one because it's sort of one of the
core elements of uh
examples of uh distributed replication
protocol
so uh today i've been emotionally
focusing
on you know the material that is
necessary for labs 2a and 2b
so the election of the leader as well as
you know pushing the logs around
and then next week
we're focusing more on 2c and 2d mainly
the snapshots
uh and the lock compaction and you know
gives us opportunity to scan the other
aspect of
raft in fact we'll talk about rap one
more time
in the week after uh we'll have a
q a lecture
on uh you know two a and two b and so
we'll
talk about the actual solutions to the
labs uh to a introduce
okay so that's the plan uh and so i'm
gonna just dive in
uh with uh with the starting point for
today
the place probably to start is to
observe
that in some of the previous
case studies of replicated systems we've
seen in sort of a pattern
uh you know you look at gfs mapreduce
virtual fmft they all have uh
a single point of failure so even though
you know they're replicated systems
and they do replication for fault
tolerance
uh all of them actually have a single
point of failure
you know in the case of you know my
producer was the coordinator
in the case of gdfs you know the master
that hands out the leases for example
and
you know in the vm
fte case it's the storage server or
really the tester set server
and the reason you know why
as we discussed in the previous lecture
the reasons that actually there are you
know single machines instead of
replicated machines
is to avoid you know the split brain
syndrome
and you know for many systems you know
sort of i mean one way in this sort of a
bummer correct we're building a high
performance you know we're building uh
fault very fall tolerance systems
and and on all these designs actually we
do actually still have
sort of a single point of failure even
though our replication is used for many
other aspects of these system designs
and for many of the systems that we
talked so far about
you know this uh to avoid this
split brain center syndrome and actually
introduce a single point of failure or
maintain a single point of failure those
are
perfectly acceptable in many cases
because in many of these cases like if
the
the stored server or you know the master
goes down
you know hopefully uh it will it's only
a single machine so the chance is going
down the smaller than you know any out
of the chunk servers
and uh you know probably there's
somebody ready you know to be beefed up
you know in the case that the master
goes down
comes back up and can really make sure
there's only one master online
uh so uh you know many many
circumstances is perfectly fine you know
it will lead maybe to in a very short
day in time
but you know in some systems you know
that's really nice what are really nice
is actually if this
we didn't even have to have two single
points of failure basically we could
reduce downtime even further
uh and uh uh and
and increase up down and so uh
and that's really where uh you know the
protocols of the style protocols that
raft you know fits into uh
come into play but just before
diving into or talking about sort of the
key ideas in the protocol
let's remind ourselves why you know this
sort of single point of failure
leads or you know why actually
replicating
uh the sort of crucial single point of
failures like the test and set server
can lead you know to this split brain uh
problem
uh and so you might think you know why
did not replicate you know the single
point of failure
too so let's try to do that and then
we'll quickly see what
the the problem is so let's replicate
the test and set server
um and so so let's do a simple
you know just a straightforward case and
we'll just have
one replicated one test asset server
that's one and here we have s2 that's
the other replicated test
set server and just remind correctly
like test and set
it takes an argument new and the returns
the old value
and the goal is that if two clients at
the same time call test a set you know
one wins you know gets
basically uh falls back as the old value
and the other one will lose because it
will get true back as the
as the old value so let's just see how
this might work play out so we have a
client
that calls test and set and you know
communicates with the first server
[Music]
and we don't really know actually it
doesn't get the response for the second
server
so there's sort of two cases now correct
where you know why
if s2 doesn't respond you know there's
two possible reasons why that could be
the case
so one case could be s2 didn't respond
because s2 failed
and in some cases and that's really what
we'd like to be
doing is that at that point basically c1
just declares victory
you know since you know nobody else can
actually see observe you know the value
at
s2 uh you know we should be done we
could proceed
but the problem is that there's the
second case and the second case is that
there's a network partition
there's a network vacation between c1
and c and s2
so in that case really c1 cannot proceed
because there could be another client
you know c2
and actually communicating with s2
and uh and it would be terrible correct
if c1 proceeds in this case
because you know it might then update s1
uh
get basically the false value think it
succeeds
at the same time s2 communicates with s2
and also succeeds during the test and
set and so now we're violating the
our contract of the test and set so this
is this issue of this split brain
like when there's a network petition we
can end up in a situation
where both servers are up and running
and serving different subsets of the
clients and thereby violating the
contract with the specification of the
system that we're building and the real
challenging part here is that c1 just
cannot tell the difference between these
two situations
it doesn't know
where it actually is you know s2 is not
reachable because it failed or because
of the network position
and so that's sort of the uh conundrum
uh
that that you know that's behind all
this uh the the these
previous systems and why they sort of
use this single
uh why they don't replicate you know
these critical services
that need to be up to avoid you know the
to avoid the uh split brain syndrome
so what what can be done about this
and really the key problem here like if
i can do what can we do about network
petitions
how could we handle them and so there's
a key idea
that uh sits in raft and in many other
protocols that underlies
basically the solution or the why those
protocols actually
might succeed and really what it is you
know in sort of a nutshell
it is this majority rule
and just to give the example in the
context of the testing sets on your
server
uh instead of actually running the
server with two replicas which
i conveniently did i'm going to run it
with three
so i'm going to have sn1 s2 and s3
and the rule now is going to be that
like a server can a client can
consider an operation to exceed it if it
at least can update a majority of the
servers
so in this case you know we can send you
know messages if you want for the doing
testing set we said the message to s2
for doing the test and set
then we get back positive responses you
know from both of them
like a false in both the case then we'll
return uh false to
actually the application and the
application considered the testing set
succeeded
and of course we do it also to the third
one but the third one made actually you
know
the message actually might not arrive or
the server might be down we don't really
know but
actually we don't really care which is
because consider the following situation
scenario where we have the second client
also trying to do a testing set
well to be able to succeed it has to
talk to rep the majority
of the servers so whatever majority is
going to talk to
it is going to include either s1 or s2
and for s1 and a2 both of these
operations actually have to succeed
by sc1 so s2
or c2 will always observe the result of
c1's
operation because they're sort of an
overlap
yeah and we'll see basically in uh raft
this is exactly the same thing as
roughly what's going on right
like when a leader uh accepts or
a enter the an operation in the
in a log of the majority of the
followers then it means that a
subsequent leader that's going to come
out in the next term
you know will also try to acquire a
majority to get the
voted as the leader and as part of that
voting
you know there's going to be one server
one follower that actually has seen the
last operation
uh performed by the last leader
and so that is going to basically build
a building stone on which we can build
these fault tolerance services that can
handle network petitions
and failures or servers
while still achieving strong consistency
another way to you know think about this
majority business is that
uh if the network petitions um
there can be only one uh petition that
has a majority
you know there can be no other
prediction that has a minority and so
only the partition that actually has the
majority uh can actually proceed
another way of saying that another
implication of that is
it could also be the case there there is
a uh there are multiple petitions
and there's no majority anywhere and in
that particular case you know the system
you can just not proceed and uh
and clients talking to it basically have
to wait until you know the network is
healed enough that at least there's one
that there's going to be at least one
partition with a majority of services
um the another sort of
quick observation here is that uh of
course you may want to get
this particular scheme that i just
described the free service only
tolerates one
server going down correct there's two
servers going down nobody can actually
obtain a majority and so therefore
nobody can actually no client can
actually
get the operation through clearly it's
easier to extend this idea
by what's typically called like doing
two two f plus one
replication so if you want to tolerate
f faults instead of one uh you need two
plus f one for the server a server so
that at least you have always a minority
the majority if f fails and so in the
case of you know here
f is one and so we're running with three
servers if you want f to be
two you have five servers et cetera et
cetera you want ftb free you have seven
okay one other uh
thing that's maybe important to point
out and i came up a lot in the questions
you know what is actually the majority
uh and
the majority is the majority of all the
services
that are there you know both the up up
ones in the down ones
and so when you take a majority you
don't take the majority of the two if
they're only two alive you take a
majority of all the servers in the
system
any questions about this sort of key
idea
of can there be an even number of
servers like if you have four servers
with the majority of them be
three yeah if the uh and we'll see that
in the complications correct in uh
in a graph that you know if you know the
number of servers is reduced from seven
to six and because one is down and you
still want to proceed
you need a majority but you still need
you know four servers to actually
proceed
but if you can get the four servers then
you can keep them going
okay um any other questions so i also
have a
question about the majority so does the
majority consider the server itself
so supposing raft that's like the server
itself considering this
yeah yeah it's part of it so like you
know often as we see in a raspberry the
leader vote immediately versus
effort itself or the candidate votes for
itself
and in the leader when it depends you
know to its own log it
counts that as one so it's part of it
okay um so
there's quite a number of protocols
using this idea
and sometimes this idea is referred to
as quorums
or quorum protocols
um for the obvious reason
uh and there were sort of two you know
the state of the art for a long time
until like in the early 90s or late 80s
was there's basically no protocol so
basically we were always in the
situation of like this
single point of failure uh and then in
the early 90s there were two protocols
okay we came were invented roughly at
the same time
one is called paxus which is mentioned
in the paper quite a bit
and the other one is called view stamped
replication
sometimes called vr and these were these
were invented around
around 99. um
they didn't actually get much attention
at that point in time
because people didn't really have a
pressing knee to be able to sort of
completely you know fault alone systems
but that changed in the last 15 years so
in the last
15 years with much use of these
protocols
uh and uh in effect you know certain
interesting observations
in the last 15 years
and that's basically sort of 15 years
after these protocols were
invented so basically they sat on the
table or said on the shelf for 15 years
until
people actually had a real use case for
that
the protocol that we're going to be uh
mostly we're going to be implementing in
the lab and we're going to discuss in
the lecture and which is the topic of
the paper
is you know falls in this you know
lineage of protocol and it's called raft
uh and it was i think it was came about
or was written up in 2014 the papers
from 2014
and this is one of the more sort of
complete descriptions you know it
touches on a lot of different aspects if
you're going to build a complete
replicated state machine
um and explains those clearly that's one
of the reasons why we're using it for
the labs and you know for this
particular lecture
any any questions about sort of the sort
of the history here around
protocols
before i dive into raft
okay
so before actually diving into rap let
me first sort of talk a little bit about
how
you one would use raf to build a
replicated state machine
because that's in the end our end goal
and that will help uh reasoning about
you know what draft actually should be
doing for us and so
the basic way you would use raft and
we'll actually do this in lab 3
is let's say you have a server
and the raft is basically nothing else
in a library
and so in uh in our setting it's going
to be go package
and you know you can write a replicated
state machine by basically importing
that package
so here's we got you know here's a raft
at the bottom
and you know you build a server you know
using raft
and so for example in uh lab 3 we're
going to build a
key value server using graft
and clients talk you know to
the key value servers
and you know it's a bit you know put and
get operations
and the key value servers when it
receives you know one of these put and
get operations
it basically hands it off to raft and so
it basically puts it to the raft and
actually sticks it in a
what we'll see in much more detail uh
it'll put it in the log
i'll actually draw this slightly
differently
so appends it to the log
actually defends it to the end of the
log
and then raf internally is going to talk
to other servers to basically replicate
that log
and so here are some other servers
they're basically structured in exactly
the same way you know they have a raft
library component
and the key value server like in many
other replicated state machines that
we've seen
you know they're identical empty value
servers
and we're going to play the same game as
i know the other previous replicated
state machines we're seeing we're going
to basically feeding operations to the
key value servers in the same order
everywhere and as a result you know the
key replicas all apply the operations in
exactly the same order
you know we should say the same uh key
value stores being built
right so we have a key value store here
whatever key 20
that's some value we're applying the
updates to this you know table uh
exactly in the same order and all their
replicas you know things should be uh
should be good right we're going to have
identical replicas
so the way the raft is structured is
that one of the replicas is the leader
so
let me in this for convenience you know
that's going to be the first one on
this side and then just actually the
clients do talk to the leader
and then what happens next is that the
uh so the client talks to one of the
leader that leave the kv server the kv
server
appends a log entry uh to uh the raft
log
of the leader and then you know
basically communicates
you know with the other raft libraries
and those raft lighters do exactly the
same thing basically they append
you know the operation you know to the
log
to their logs
and send the response back you know to
the
leader and
you know of course you know all this
state is stored
you know the log and some other stage
stored on disk so that you know if any
one of them fails
uh they at least have the last part of
their log you know still
available and uh can build from there
so once you know basically and we'll
talk a little bit more in detail but you
know once
the the entry or the log entry is
replicated on you know free servers
then they can actually be delivered in
order you know to the key value server
so the every committed operation there
every log has an index or every
operation has an index zero or actually
one two three four whatever
in order and they're going to be
delivered in order to the key value
server so once an operator is committed
you know it's going to be delivered
to the key value server the key value
server performs the operation
maybe updates you know the uh key value
table
and then sends actually the leader alone
sends a response back to the client
so that's sort of roughly the sequence
of events that happens so
client sends requests to the leader
neither put insurgency in raft
draft you know chit chats with the other
servers
once you know it's replicated on enough
machines
then you know the it's considered to be
committed and we'll talk a little bit
more
precisely what committed it means and
then uh
uncommitted operation is delivered to
the key value servers and then
they execute the operation and respond
to the client or delete the response to
the client
so what happens on the failure
on a failure uh the uh when
a new leader is elected
and it will take over the role of the
old leader and so for example like in
this particular picture again it might
be the case that
uh you know this leader crashes
uh and you know this becomes the new
leader in the next term
let's see exactly what that means and
then the clients basically fail over you
know they will see
they don't get a response so they will
time out and they fail
over to uh the second leader the new
leader
and basically retry their operation and
so they insert you know that new leader
will take their operation
insert it back into raft you know the
same things happens as before
and maybe this time we get lucky and we
execute the operation without any
failures
now if you think a little bit carefully
about this that does mean that
a client operation might end up twice in
the log right because it actually may be
the case that the first time it
succeeded but just didn't get the
response
and so it doesn't know that it succeeded
we'll retry you know this
new leader will put the log put the new
up
the retract operation also in the log
and it will pop out
you know at some point you know at
a duplicate and so as you will see later
in
in the um lab 3 actually it turns out
that the
you know the lab you need to do
duplication to
detect duplicates
but that's mostly an issue for lab free
so it's not going to be a main issue for
now but it's just important to know
you know that sort of this is the sort
of general style
in which you know your one would
actually use rav to build a replicated
state machine
any questions uh about sort of the
how to use your app for replicated state
machines do you have a question in the
chat
yeah ah what's the typical number of
clients contacting the leader um
uh well there could be many there's no
real limit
uh on it what you will see you know it
could be the case that a single
machine can i mean maybe that's
implicitly what the question is
it could be the case that a single
leader you know can just not tolerate
the
is not capable of handling that many
clients and so
uh what happens then is that basically
the service gets charted you know you
shard the key
key value servers in multiple raft
groups
so for example shard one would be one
raft instance chart two rear draft
instance
chart three with your raft instance and
the client's gonna talk to the
appropriate
uh chart to be uh to apply their
operations and then that way we
can scale the server to many clients in
fact that is what lab4 does
how does the client know how to
communicate with the new leader after
the old leader fails
the client basically has a list of all
the servers that are in the system
so in this case we're running with three
servers everybody agrees they're only
free servers in the world
the clients know about the free servers
and uh
they try one randomly and if that is not
the client it will redirect
if that's not the leader it will
redirect the client to the appropriate
one the actual leader
yeah the answer is
do we assume the servers are like in a
geographically closed look
like close to each other or could they
be they could in principle be far apart
uh there's no real uh restriction on
that side
uh the only issue of course is if the
client if the servers are very spread
around the world
the delays to actually you know getting
a lock
record dependent you know will take a
little while and so the delays will be
long
what is the log entry being executed in
the kv storage
one uh once it's committed
uh by raft so once raf has decided that
you know all the enough replicas have
received it and it's now
no way possible that one has to back out
of that operation
then uh it's handed out to the key value
server
so the leader will first like execute
this command
and the leader will tell the followers
that this command is committed and then
the following
uh the leader knows well as soon as the
leader knows that the operation is
committed excellent can hand it off to
his key value server let me
let's talk about it right now and i'll
go in more detail as we go
so a little bit more of an overview of
the protocol so
previous board was sort of an overview
of how you use raft
to build and replicate the state machine
now let's look at the
raft itself a little bit in more detail
so we hear some timelines we've got a
leader
we've got two followers
so we're running the three uh the
client's gonna talks to the leader
uh the
leader has a log you know of all the
for the get operations you know when it
gets a new one you know appends it you
know to the end of the log
then it actually sends it you know sends
the log entries
to the new log entries you know through
the followers
and you know let's say you know that
follower two here's follower one
new follower two follower one actually
he receives this log entry everything is
okay it hence it to the end of the log
uh it sends basically an act back saying
yes you know i appended it
and at this point you know in
the raft view of the world uh two uh
servers actually have the log entry and
so
raft actually the leader can actually
commit the log entry
and so at this point you know the uh
the the leader can actually hand off
that request that they just
received they can actually hand it off
to the kv server
and the way actually the lab does this
or the lab infrastructure does this is
that basically
we have a channel a go channel uh
one single go channel where basically
the
graph go routines and the wrap go
routine that actually decides that a
particular
operation is committed it just sends
that operation on the
apply channel so that the key value
servers can actually apply it
now at some point later uh so notice at
this point
the the leader basically uh has
committed the operation
and it's perfectly safe for the leader
to commit this operation
because a majority of the servers
actually the majority of the peers
actually have received the operation
correct so there's even if there was a
failure
and we elect a new leader that's the
case that that leader or
one of the servers that is remaining
actually has the last operation
that was uh appended to the log by the
previous leader
so everything is good uh of course
really the last guy
you know the first follower will also at
some point respond and
you know say yes so this point
basically from the point of view of the
leader the operation is committed
except the followers don't really know
it yet because the followers you know
they only know that you know they got it
and that the leader probably has it
um but they you know they don't really
know
and so what actually happens is that uh
the subsequent operation
you know when the another client request
comes in uh the leader will append
another log entry and
basically sends you know a new operation
or a new append entry
you know to the followers and that
append entry
does basically two things it you know
provides the new log entry for the new
operation
but it also confirms that all the
preceding uh
operations or you know tells us which
operations actually have committed so
far
and so when f1 and f2 receive you know
these
this operation this rpc they know
that the operation has been permitted by
the leader
and therefore at that point they can
also deliver it you know through their
key value instance and know that this
operation is committed
um i i had a quick question so
um so when
the leader sends an operation over
uh and a server replies
does that mean that that means it's in
the log right
yes but what happens if you get a
majority like
you know a slight majority and then one
of those logs like one of the servers
crash
like our logs the logs have to be in
storage like in disk
yep so that's a very good question
correct so the the
every change to the log you know this if
you look at the wrap paper in detail
here
the some state is uh
must be stable and log is one of those
pieces of information that must be
stable
as well as the term number and a bunch
of other things
and so if a server crashes uh
no big no big deal really because you
know the majority of the servers does
have that
entry on their disk and when they come
back up they'll find it
i asked we have a question yeah so
what happens if for example follower one
replies
with yes and the leader commits
uh just before it sends the next
command to the remaining followers to
also commit it crashes
now the remaining followers don't know
that they need to commit because the
leader has crashed
so wouldn't this cause problems then
we'll commit it
right because one follower will have it
in his log
and as we'll see in the leader election
rules it will become the leader
and uh and it will propagate that depend
entry you know to the other
servers and then they will apply it to
okay
okay thanks okay so that brings me maybe
this is a good you know sort of segue to
the next topic like why logs
and just last few questions
all about that yeah i actually as a
follow-up to the last question
um so the server crashing like after it
has like consensus
uh crashing right like right before
committing
it could delay committing right
what do you mean with committing so so
um
like after it has consensus on a change
right after it has a majority
um it can
like the paper said you sort you
essentially
tell other ones like other servers you
tell them okay this is ready for
or sorry it's committed it's ready for
like um
like execution right into the state
mission
um so if it crashes before it tells all
your servers that it's ready for
execution
it could delay execution right it could
delay execution well i don't okay so
first of all if the leader fails at that
point nothing happens correct like at
least the clients can't you know proceed
with any other more operations
and so basically the if you want to wait
to think about it at that point sort of
wrap reconfigures itself
and likes a new leader and that's going
to be you know
f1 or f2 you know one of the two is
going to be the new leader and the other
one is going to be the follower right
and one of the two actually has received
you know the append entry that the
leader might already have committed in
fact it's kv might already have executed
no problem correct because one of them
has it that one will become the leader
as we'll see later with the leader
election rules
and that one will you know submit it to
its kv server
and we'll replicate it you know to the
other follower and then it will apply it
to its kv server
so in the end right they all will apply
all the operations in the same order
i i i agree like eventually it'll happen
but it could be delayed
right yeah could be delayed absolutely
the new lens has a complete log to all
the followers uh
it will just it will the way it works is
actually uh it will try to send the end
of his log
uh if one of the followers doesn't
recognize the end of the log it will
back off
and you know send more and more you know
earlier entries
we'll talk about it later but uh in the
end it could be the case that the leader
will replay its complete log to
one of the followers if one of the
followers has missed all the log entries
i gotta get me back to walks
so one reason you might wonder why
you have logs at all is because like the
the kv server you know it has a database
too correct you know it has a table with
all its information
uh and so why do we need actually you
know sort of this information twice
one's in the logs and one's in the
uh kp uh table and so a couple of
reasons for that
uh one yeah so you know a couple that
already came up in the questions
basically
one for retransmission
so when the leader you know sends one of
these append entries you know to one of
the followers that message might get
lost
and so the leader must be able to
re-transmit it so you need to keep a
record
of all the uh log entries that uh
that are sort of in flight uh
second reason you know it's probably the
primary reason first is like we need
order
and every uh attempt operation or every
uh command must be delivered in the same
order
at the same uh and all the replicas
and the log is a very convenient way for
us to actually maintain that order
so the second reason we transmission uh
the third reason is we need a
persistence
you know one of the followers might
crash uh
where actually all of them might crash
and then they come up again
and you know we still need to be in a
position that we can basically
retransmit log entries
to bring everybody up to date and uh so
the log must also be persistent uh
and finally we need sort of space for
tentative operations or tentatively
committed
with retentive commands uh
so as we noted earlier that came up in
the earlier questions
when uh the leader sends an operation to
a follower
the following actor doesn't really know
at that point whether that operation
will be committed so it just must stick
around for a little while
until it actually learns whether that
operation is committed and so we need
some space for these standard dev
operations and the log is a confusing
place to actually do that
um in the end you know what will happen
correct
is that the logs are identical
on all servers
uh you know they may be out of sync you
know during periods of time
uh you know one might have more entries
than other logs
but like if we sort of keep running the
system and then stop the clients
then at some point in time uh all the
logs will be completely identical
and that means that basically those uh
since they're all half the same order
all the operations
all the operations will be fed you know
to decline that the kv servers in the
same order
and the adk features will end up in the
same state
okay
okay let me talk a little bit about an
individual log entry
so really you know whatever we're going
to draw many pictures like this where
you know there's a bunch of log entries
you know starting zero
one two blah blah blah blah uh and if we
look inside of one of these log entries
you know there's gonna be a command
which we're mostly going to sort of
ignore we're not going to really think
about much about it at all and that's
the thing that's actually being
delivered to the application so that's
for example the putin or the get
operation
with its arguments and then the second
thing that's in there is a term
and this is basically the leader's term
so the term in which this particular
command actually was appended
to the log and one way you can think
about this
is that basically the term identifies
uniquely the leader that appended
uh the operation to the log because
during every term
there's only one single leader and so
the term id you really
basically implicitly uh uh signals you
know what
who the leader was actually appended to
the uh
to that that log entry uh
the number that goes along here so if
this is n or maybe like let me
use i here uh you know that's the log
index
so the combination of the log index plus
a term number basically uniquely
identifies the content of that
particular entry there could be no
uh two log entries that have the same
index the same term
and have different commands uh because
only a single leader you know could have
been in charge
in that particular term and that uh
leader you know commits you know attends
operations
uh will um commit a log interest be
overwritten yeah they might get
overwritten
we'll talk about it later but that's
certainly possible
um okay so you know if we look at this
uh picture sort of there are two things
that
uh and just part of the i guess an
answer to this question
there are two things that need to happen
we need to elect leaders
for a particular term
and we need to actually ensure that the
ensure logs become identical
and we have failures and we have leader
changes
and so we're going to talk about both of
these topics uh
and we're going to start with leader
election and then
talk about the making uh launch
identical
a little bit later okay election
election is really the topic of uh
and you know really the stories are some
ways you know straightforward you know
we have
you know say here we are a system of
three entries we have
uh a leader in you know term 10
we have a follower in term 10 so we're
sort of stable situation
and another follower in term 10 and
let's say the
leader crashes or you know gets
petitioned you know from network so
you know can't talk anymore what will
happen is that
the followers will start an election and
the reason they start an election is
because they're missing heartbeats from
the leader
you know the job of the leader is to
periodically
uh in a sort of fixed interval uh send
uh
an append entry to the followers
uh you know normally you know that might
be happening because you know a lot of
clients are active and so the
followers continuously get the pen
entries uh but if the leader doesn't
receive any commands from the uh
clients then it actually supposed to
send in a heartbeat
periodically and telling the basically
to inform
the followers that actually is still the
leader
and the heartbeat basically takes the
form of a normal append entry
except no new log entries um and so the
leader just tells us
later just tells the heartbeat like you
know my log is you know
this long uh and uh this is my last
entry
uh and if you know those match and then
everything is good
so if the leader fails then after a
couple of heartbeats
and we'll talk a little bit more in
detail about this um
there will be an election timeout
so the followers have a timer running
and and they reset that timer every time
they get a heartbeat or a pen entry
uh but if they don't receive uh any
heartbeats or repent entries
then at some point in time after this
election time out the
timer goes off and at that point a
follower starts an election
and just as let's assume that the first
follower reaches that point first
and what it will do it will you know
send it will increase its term number so
we'll set the term number to 11.
uh it will you know talk to itself if
you will
and uh be part of the uh
and will vote for itself and then you
know we'll
contact you know the other uh follower
and we'll also try to contact the leader
presumably the leader you let's say the
leader is down so the leader doesn't
respond
but the second follower does respond and
so at that point it gets two votes you
know one from itself and
one from the follower and in that point
actually it becomes the new leader it
becomes the leader for term 11.
and then it you know start thinking
basically clients fall over to that
leader
and you know the things you just
proceeded as before
okay now uh maybe it's
slightly there's a couple problems that
you might worry about but one of them
could be the following situation we uh
it turns out there was a network
petition between
leader 10 we're the leader for term 10
and the followers for term 10.
and so at some point that network you
know partition heals
and so maybe there are client requests
you know coming in still to
uh the leader for leader for term two
and ten
and uh now of course now it looks like
oops we might have actually two
uh leaders and we're back into the split
syndrome problem that turns out not to
be the case
because when the leader tries to
actually
you know send a pen entries to the
followers to followers that are now
in term 11 they will just reject you
know those
append entries and they will tell the
old leader that you know too bad
you know uh he's not the leader anymore
in fact they'll send a message back you
know saying no
i cannot do the append and
here is my current uh term number eleven
uh the leader receives that sees that
the term number eleven is bigger than
this term number ten
and basically steps down as leader and
becomes a follower
and they take up another election or you
know to basically
become part of a term that has all three
of them
but it basically and there's no chance
of a split brain problem
because you just can't actually get any
operations through
so no split brain
and the reason that we avoid the split
brain is because of this majority rule
as well as these term numbers
okay that's of course not the only
problem
that we might have another challenge
is we might end up
with a split vote
so like it was a particular picture you
know we had their leader maybe
you know he was leader in 10 his
petition of the network
uh here are our two followers
in ten and
uh and if we're not careful you know
maybe they will actually start you know
elections very close to each other
and so you know f10 you know votes for
itself
uh the first leah followed follow folks
himself the second leader
of the second follower vote for itself
then you know they sent
you know uh vote requests you know with
each other
and uh the rule is that you know you can
vote
one vote per term
so when you know the first follower has
voted for itself you know it has voted
for itself and so when it receives the
second vote request it actually cannot
vote for that folk request because it
already voted for itself
uh and so at this point we're going to
have split votes like this guy is going
to have one vote
and this guy is going to have one phone
and it won't do anything
uh and but at some point again you know
later the
there will be a timeout and then this
process starts again
and of course you know as part of that
process you know this is
election eleven election eleven resulted
in twelve it will actually go to
election number twelve
twelve and you know start trying to try
to do this again
now if you're not careful correct uh
this could just happen over and over and
over endlessly
you know basically every time you know
the two followers
roughly at the same time start this
election then you know we're not going
to
make foreign progress and so we need to
avoid this problem
uh is that the election timers are
randomized
um and so when uh the
followers you know set their election
timer uh in
the paper they uh talk about like
picking a value between 150 milliseconds
and 300 milliseconds a random number in
that interval
and every time you know these uh
followers and
basically reset their election time out
they pick a new number a random number
in that interval and
only when that timer then goes off they
run the election
and if basically you know the if
you know this interval is wide enough
the it's unlikely that like the first
person or the first follower that
actually gets the
the first uh follower whose election
time runs out
you know the the interval is wide enough
that you know
there's a good chance that it actually
will succeed you know completing the
complete election
before the second uh timer goes up
for another follower and so this avoids
you know this sort of
endless split vote you know we might get
unlucky and we get maybe one or two
split votes
but like over time you know that has to
be the case that uh
we in the end will succeed
there are a couple sort of and this is
important maybe for the lab too
there's sort of a couple pressures on
these election timeouts
um you don't want to pick an election
timeout that is too
uh short right because if it's too short
for example shorter than a heartbeat and
you know you might lose one message and
immediately you start running
an election and nothing bad happens uh
because you know you know we'll elect a
new leader you will go through the new
term and all that kind of stuff
but basically you know the during this
election the system is actually not uh
usable right the clients are actually
blocked so you don't want to
unnecessarily cause elections um and so
one of the things you want to do is
basically probably spit take a a
value that's at least bigger than a few
times and then a few heartbeats
perhaps maybe in a data center you know
we'll take a few
milliseconds sort of to do an rpc and we
may want to
wait at least you know so maybe three
four rpc around good time so that we get
a chance to
uh retry an rpc uh
uh without actually having the election
timer go off and sort of recover from
like temporary network fields
then you know we want to presumably add
you know some random value
to that uh grand valley to avoid
you know the split votes and so one
hand you know we want to make that
random value as big as possible right
because we make it big then
there are very little chance that
actually we will run into a split vote
problem but the other hand if we do that
then there's a chance that you know the
system may be down for a longer period
of time we might pick a big value for
the
election timeout and that means downtime
from the point of view of the clients
so we want to keep this you know short
enough
that the downtime is short and the paper
in linden eval section does quite a bit
of work
on sort of elevating you know what are
some reasonable values
uh for their particular setting and then
that's how they got to the 150 to 300
milliseconds
in the lab we're going to be originally
generous uh you know basically if you
recover within a second you're more or
less going to be good
with the referred for our test cases
okay i want to make one more uh point
about the uh
uh uh about the elections
um so you know another scenario that is
sort of important to consider is
uh you know we have a follower we have a
leader the leader goes down
so there was 10 this was 10. you have to
follow 10.
and we already talked a little bit about
it when
let's say this guy goes first it votes
for itself
uh and you know we the protocol records
you know
uh unstable storage why who it voted for
so the record you know records on the so
this
follower one this is follower two will
record
yeah it voted for in term 11 you know
for
fallout 1.
why is it recorded on stable storage
and why does the follower need to
remember that
that it voted in term 11 for itself
uh this way it doesn't vote twice if it
uh
fails yeah it might crash right like
right here
uh and uh come back up
uh and it should remember that it and
somebody might have
let's say it was actually there's
referred one guy in here you know a
follower or whatever free
uh and it already voted for follower of
three uh
then uh it can actually not change in
mind
right uh and so because in the end we at
the end of the term we need to have
we have to be in a position that per
term there's only
one leader and never never two and so
to ensure that you know every follower
must remember for which candidate it
voted and never change its mind
okay i guess there's a whole discussion
in the chat about uh
the timeout numbers and in relation to
the lab uh so
people can look there uh if they are
confused about this or otherwise
we can talk about elections a little bit
more because this is about the last
thing i want to say about
elections any questions about elections
a bit more general question so
in like the figure two of the lab that
says that for each
um server you're storing like the
current term and then who it voted for
but not the like current state of the
server like if it's candidate or
a follower or leader
so i'm wondering how they like is that
implied or
is there another way to figure that out
uh i guess
when you come back up you come back up
as a follower
and you know you start an election
uh and then that will in the end you
know at the end of the election you know
what you are
you either a follower or the leader
i see okay thank you does this make
sense
one warning about uh figure two uh
both really positive and then this may a
negative statement uh
anywhere in the figure two when it says
like you know you should do this
you should really do it uh so you cannot
admit
any detail that actually is a figure two
uh if you do that then undoubtedly
you're gonna fail some of the test cases
unfortunately figure 2 is not complete
and so you still will have to do some
thinking
so particularly like figure 2 doesn't
really say that much about like how the
replies are handled
of the voter rpc and the penta
proceeding and so
you will have to do some thinking sort
of to fill in the missing details
uh and so uh so there's two points here
like figure two
anything that's in there you better deal
with it and
but there still might be things missing
that you will have to resolve for
yourself
you'll be looking at figure 2 a lot
so from the description of the election
process there seems to be uh
like even for lab two a which deals only
with election there seems to be some
state that we need to store on
persistence
yeah so like for example like who you
voted for and
uh the term number yeah but when you
look at the code of lab lab2
uh all of the code that has to do with
saving the persistent state it says
above it lab to c
so is it that it's not that crucial
maybe to care about persistent
storage or should we absolutely start
implementing
these stories yeah i think in the first
couple tests we don't actually crash
machines
and so therefore it's not important and
until you see we're definitely crashing
machines
okay awesome thank you
okay how are we doing
everybody on on board
okay here we go uh next step okay so
uh one important uh thing to realize and
you know this came up earlier in the
questions and
i want to hit that now that topic hard
is that logs may diverge
verge
and they can be quite dramatic but just
let's get into it
for just a basic understanding and then
uh
discussing more details so let's do a
couple simple examples
uh so i'm gonna write things and using
the following notation i'm gonna have
three servers
as before but i'm going to cut all the
timeline business
and just like draw the logs
and you know we have
indexes so let's say these are indexes
you know there's a
preceding part to it where we're talking
about 10 11 12.
and so you know there's an uh term entry
in each
one of them so let's say all three
servers
uh committed or appended an operation in
uh term three to index uh 10
and you know uh and same thing happens
in uh
with index for 11. so one way to think
one way you could get this correct is
that server one would be the leader
server one appends it to its own log you
know then replicates it to s2 and s3
same thing happens for index 11 then in
x you know 12 maybe you know they're
also successful
invents one operation in that index you
know for each term so that's turn three
but then it crashes right and so now
we're in a situation where
uh one uh server actually has an extra
log entry in its log and the other ones
uh don't or maybe they will
one of them has it too but they are
definitely not identical
so that's a simple case correct like
nothing really particularly especially
going on
but there's much more interesting cases
you know going on so
another case could be you know one
server
again s1 there we go same scenarios s2
s3 and
let's say we have the following logs
so this is the situation we have in in
index 10. we have entries
at all servers for term three
in index 11 the first server has no
entry
the other two have an entry for term
three and then
last one number 12 you know we have
entries in
uh index four at servers two and three
with term numbers four and five so the
first question that we need to ask
ourselves is this possible
can raft end up producing uh
logs in this way the you know where the
in this in the same
log entry we have two different term
numbers
and same log index um yeah that's
possible
um so basically um it looks like
so like what is an area that produced
yeah so it looks like um
server two or server three was um
the leader for term three and then um
got some logs out to server one um and
then
shared another log with um only one of
the two servers
after which point it went down um
and then s2 got elected as leader for
term two which is still possible because
its log is like
up to date as as up to date as uh the
others
um and then again just to make sure so
s2 got elected for term
four right yes okay okay not term two
okay so s2 gets elected for term four
yeah yeah yeah and then
using s1 as a backup basically as the
follower
uh yes i think yep
um and then s3 gets elected for term
five before s2 can
put anything in the logs yeah another
way to saying it like maybe s2 crashed
right away
right after uh i got elected to turn
four
and uh so then there's a timeout then
let's say s3 was partitioned but now
it's back uh and at apple point
uh it will become uh it will it can come
into
turn five correct yeah
okay good so that's possible so it turns
out there are quite a bit of wild
variations uh possible so if we
like look at the uh
so here's the figure six uh for figure
seven sorry from the homework
uh and um
uh and uh and the homework asked
basically questions about the forum
uh like well what happens like this guy
in the figure 6 itself
figure 7 whatever it is i think it's
figure 7.
um the the scenario is being discussed
is like this the guy becomes the
top one becomes new leader and in the
homework we ask the question like what
happens if
this uh leader just goes away and
what are the possible outcomes you know
and the possible outcomes like
are so for every uh log index
you know the question is which one gets
rejected
which one will be accepted for sure
and which ones depends
and i think this is an important thing
exercise to do because uh once we
sort of understand what our log entries
are possible what are possible outcomes
you know it will
really firm up like our understanding
about how a raft actually is supposed to
be operating
what i'd like to do is like do a quick
breakout room and
i'd like you to identify uh
two possible outcomes uh that not
guaranteed
uh in uh in the corresponding scenario
so uh let me let's take a a
quick breakout room here section here
and let's try to figure out the answer
to the homework question
in five minutes
let me actually make you
participants
host i'll get new york
okay
um
the main ones
okay can everybody hear me again
can i get a positive signal yes
okay super okay uh so i hope
everybody uh got a uh had a good time
discussing this
um and so let's uh so this is really
this question about log divergence
and you know we see here correct in this
figure there are pretty wild
variations in
what can happen and these are all
possible as you know the
caption of the figure explains they're
all possible
scenarios so
the question in the homework and just to
quickly review that i'm sure most of you
already uh
i don't think we can see your screen oh
how do you do that
uh that's because i forgot to click yes
okay let me fix that i appreciate that
[Music]
okay ready to see my screen
yeah okay okay thank you sorry for that
okay so
uh so going back to this caption of
figure seven figure seven explains like
these are possible situations
and you know what we want to figure out
you know before talking about the
details about how the logs get repaired
uh you know what actually is possible so
assume that actually this top guy
did not get elected uh leader
uh you know in the caption of the in the
figure but like basically what what
outcomes are possible and they're going
to be what i mean with that
is like for example we look at f you
know it has a two
an index of an entry from term two in
index four
and the question that we want to ask and
understand is uh
the clear this is possible because this
could have happened you know what will
happen next
you know is it possible that this entry
will survive
so when we reconfigure we're like the
leader basically you know logs getting
being
you know put together in uh or
synchronized where you know
the leaders force the logs to be
identical is there a scenario in which
actually the
log entry the entry from term two will
survive
no no correct this will definitely be
rejected correct
and why is that the case um
there is entries from term six that are
already committed
um until f1 i will never be elected
yeah everyone will never be elected and
so somebody else will be elected and
nobody has a two in
term two in index four so it will be
overwritten with value will be
overwritten
um there will be a four over and yeah
there will be this will become a four
right so when later on when we talk
about sort of walk you know
synchronization or
forcing logs on the followers it has to
be the case that
this two turns into four at f good
uh so so this also answers sort of a
second question like you know
the entry from the index
four from term four is definitely going
to be accepted
uh okay then maybe more interesting is
uh this question about depends
you know uh so we know at least one
entry term that definitely got rejected
we know one term they're definitely
going to accept it
and you know are there any sort of in
terms and indexes any states that may be
possibly accepted
the seventh maybe yeah the sevens
so when would the sevens not be accepted
okay so the easy case scenario is the
second will be accepted correct because
d gets executed later
and then it will force it log on
everybody else
right so that's the case where seven
gets accepted when they get the seven
getting rejected
if c gets selected later and then d
is down and it is overwritten
yeah so d goes down c becomes leader
and then see these log entries are being
pushed on everybody else
entries and then whenever d and
so then that we're going to be turn
seven correct and at some point that
would be longer
and every d comes back up you know it's
you know entries are going to be
overwritten
all right
so seven is definitely possible but not
guaranteed
in the other case uh i had a question
eight could become leader
two right
a yeah uh
if yeah a group get leader if c and d
are down
well d and d don't even have to be down
for it to be elected later right
it just has to happen if it's the first
one
the longer is log correct if the term if
the two terms are equal at the end then
you pick the longest law
um but um
i think if if a is the first one to call
for an election
right like potentially b
f right if c and d are down they could
win the election
but if they're alive can't it also still
ah so let's say c okay let's d
is down let's do that for sure correct
because we know the d will win the
election period
does it have to like we know we know we
know it won't get a vote from d right
for sure but
but does it have to win well what do we
think
i i don't know what if a received vote
from
b e and f first and then receive the
role from
the done
yeah yeah you can get the majority
correct without actually d participating
even if the participated in the election
it's possible for
a to get the majority votes right
yes i think we just answered that
is it isn't there a mechanism though
where
if a candidate sees a
message from a another server with a
higher term number like stands down
yes from a higher term number but a has
if d is down
it doesn't have to be down right you
just have to get them first
yes yeah
but it will step down when it gets to
vote from seven or
uh d wait are you sure about that
because i don't think so um
well okay so if d at some point will uh
depends they're gonna start racing
correct the
the uh okay let me actually this is a
very important topic and so i don't want
to do it in
10 seconds and let me come back to this
at the start of the next lecture okay
this is a great point to stop
i think the state machine on in figure 4
clarifies it like a candidate goes back
to
follower if discovers a higher term so
if
if d wasn't down it will go back to
follower it won't
try to elect itself wait but i thought
that it would only go back to a follower
state
if it received an append entries from
a current leader like a request vote
is not the same so it's worth
knowing that there's a difference
between the term number that a server is
at
and the term of the most recent entry in
the log
oh yes like server a
can have most recent entering the log b
six
the term six but have its current term
number
be seven and the term number can
actually be arbitrarily high
yes correct that's that's correct and so
a could
start term eight and then get elected in
term eight
and that and whatever d tells it doesn't
matter because
if b's most recent term is seven eight
won't go back to follower because
it's a higher term than seven oh i see
so it could be a higher term arbitrary
thought
could could a go into um
into term seven its own term seven
if d was like partition like
if there was a network petition and it
didn't know about d
wait i feel confused like even if it
does know about d
why does that matter it shouldn't matter
like if if a promotes itself to
candidate and then
sends out a a request
a vote request um then
like d could come back and say like oh
well my latest log entry was at this
index for term seven
um but i don't think that hey
wait actually it doesn't even say that
right in
in the response to a request vote rpc
basically says like its current term
which would be seven
which matches a's because that wait
that's our hypothesis
and then um yeah if a started the
election it will be
turned seven
but a diva will not vote for eight yes
that's true
but i don't know i think it's totally
fine if d
is alive and gives a a response
to a's vote request like i don't think
that
deters a from being a candidate
um someone just put in the chat i think
the answer to that
so like grant said that as soon as d
rejects the vote
um a will revert to being a follower
because it will realize
that it has a lower term number but okay
so
not necessarily because again the
remember that the most recent term
on their log is not the same thing as
the most recent term
that the server keeps track of you can
have a higher current term
than the most recent thing on the log
and so if
a tries to elect itself in term seven
yes when it tries to contact d it will
give up
but if a tries to lock itself in term
eight which it would if it's already
seen that these
has reached term seven then
like a can get elected wait but
if d is if we assume that d is in term
seven
um like if a tries to elect itself for
term seven
then the we don't actually hit this case
because
um if the rpc request a response
contains a term which is strictly
greater than the current term you give
up but if they're the same
then it doesn't matter it will just
proceed as normal
that's great yes that's it do you get
entries get replaced by
whatever a is telling it so
uh at the end of section uh
like the election restriction section
5.4.1
graph determines which of the two logs
is more up-to-date by comparing the
index and term of the last entries in
the log
so wouldn't that mean that d has to
become the leader if we're comparing no
because d just does vote no but other
people might vote yes
okay so what about
go ahead uh what about the case where e
runs for election in term five for
example or
five yeah and then it gets a vote from d
saying no it would then update its term
right and stop running
okay hold on like this so you're
thinking about
he's starting an election for five yeah
and if it gets a response from
almost anybody it's gonna see that it's
behind in a term
right so it does update its term in that
case right
it's not going to append so another way
to ask this question who can become
leader
right in this you know from this you
know whatever from these
six abc through f who can become leader
can what f become leader no all of them
are up
can he become leader
um also no the only ones that can become
leader are a c
and d that's correct
possible leader
but can can a become a leader if d
is alive because because the because the
safety
section says that the rpc the request
for rpc implements the restriction that
it it compares the last log entries and
the one with the highest log entry
should become the leader no i i only
think
it it doesn't vote for someone
exactly so like they will never vote for
a
right or for anything else that's
exactly right
i mean it's also not true that like if
you have an
entry in a higher term than
another node that like you're actually
sort of like
better right because um i mean you can
be
like becoming leader and trying to
append
entries into the log but they like don't
go through so
well d is like when you go through okay
v
is live correct devoted against a
becomes leader d
a actually tries to uh well if
a won't contact d if actually didn't
vote for it
and so they would just proceed
so why could d have logs in term seven
if it's not the leader in term seven
d must have been the leader in term
seven correct
yeah i agree otherwise it would have no
log entries
i think i forgot so in this case was d
um was d a leader
in term seven who got disconnected and
then
the new leader got elected the one at
the top
yeah i think so actually let me take it
back i don't really
remember exactly the sequence i didn't
really pay attention much to the top guy
uh but i presume that is the case it
does say that he's
leader for term eight and that means
like
right on that log
i think the case we're looking at the
one where a has a higher
term number than d is a the
contradiction case and the safety
argument they
mentioned like i think they proved that
this is not possible
what is thought possible like that um
a could be elected be missing an entry
and have a higher term than d which is
the case here i think there's a
like the step proof that this is a
contradiction
i don't think so i think it's totally
fine for it to be elected leader
yeah i think the i think the safety
proof says that
a future leader cannot have
needs to have all of the log
committed committed yeah and seven is
not committed
exactly there's a whole bunch of
operations here that they're not
committed correct they're just tentative
and so
anything can happen to them and nothing
wrong will happen in the end
and the reason that the whole committed
thing works is because
if it's committed then more than than
the majority have
those entries and so someone who doesn't
have the committed entries could never
become elected
right that's correct yes that's exactly
right
yeah they discussed like yeah like in
terms of
only someone who has all the committed
entries can get elected i think it gets
more complicated with you know within
the people who have all the committed
entries which ones can't get elected
that's yeah it's always it doesn't
matter
are not committed then here right uh
so these two fours those are not
the the first the first two fours those
are
where what's your question they will be
committed yeah those would be committed
but then everything after wouldn't be
yeah those two fives will be committed
two six
and the two seconds
oh okay you only need exactly half
that's okay
exactly half is okay okay oh you need
another one over half
four yeah so the fives and six wouldn't
be committed
oh but you have the oh you have the
other leader right yeah
yeah okay oh let's not forget about
those right
i got it okay
i'll i'll come back to this at the
beginning of the next lecture because
some
some of you probably have to run to
another class uh
but uh i'll come back to this uh if you
have more questions feel free to stick
around
uh and you know we'll resume this
um can you say the log duplication
um again when could there be log
duplication
what i meant is that the leader at some
point
forces its log on the followers
i think i think you meant it on some of
the previous
slides uh okay so maybe yeah maybe uh
again one way i can't remember what i
said
sorry uh it is
it is a little more maybe a little more
um
oh it says they're deleted duplicates
detect duplicates oh yeah the technical
difficulties
yeah yeah this is uh this is not a raft
issue correct this is really uh a kv
uh key value service issue uh where
uh a client request you know might be a
client may uh
okay the client might not get a response
uh even though
you know that request actually went
through a raft because what happened is
that the leader maybe applied the
operation
to its state but before it responded to
the client it crashed
so the client will retry and will send
this request to the new leader
the new lender will run it for raft and
it will pop out of raft again
and so it has to be the case that the kv
server does duplicate detection
also this is like only if the client
didn't get the response i did yesterday
exactly
yeah exactly okay okay i see thank you
yeah then there will be no you will do
this in lab three
um i think i also asked this question
during the lecture but i
don't think i fully understood the
answers so i'll just repeat the question
the question is that um so you said that
the way commits work is that once the
leader commits it waits for a new client
uh message and then it just appends that
message to the log entry and sends an
append entry
to the remaining followers with an
additional message saying that they
should also commit all the previous
entries correct
yeah there's indirectly the protocol the
staff correct right
so my question is that what if uh the
leader commits all the entries
and right before it is able to send this
message to the remaining followers
the leader crashes uh it cannot commit
until it has a majority
uh response from all the from the
majority of the followers
i see so it at first like
even it sticks us through it log but
doesn't actually deliver to the
kv servers yet i see so it waits
from a reply of commit from all the
remaining followers and then it
recommends its own
yeah okay okay so there's a basically
there's this variable
last applied or commit index correct
that is actually maintaining
it only increases the commit index and
once it receives a response from the
majority of the followers
and all of the followers say that they
have committed their own
uh like they have committed the log
entries on their own servers
they will commit their log entries once
they know that the
leader actually has committed it
right so that's my question like how
would they know if the leader is unable
to send that message to the remaining
file
well yeah so then you know we basically
we end in situations that we just saw in
this figure seven
there's going to be tentative log
entries in uh their logs
and uh depending who becomes the new
leader
and what the log situation is you know
that operation may get committed or may
not get committed
i see okay yeah thank you
hi i had a follow-up question on this so
it says
uh the leader pushes a login entry it
gets accepted by majority but it crashes
then
later on uh this log entry can be
committed right
by some other leader it can it also may
not
yeah but say if it's get committed then
uh
how does the new leader know who was the
client who
requested for this log entry or how will
this client be qualified
in their
okay so there's a really question about
like actually how the kv server is
actually
stored in information uh with raft uh so
the scenario is client talked to the
leader the
uh the client uh the leader actually
committed
did execute this operation or not it did
not no it
didn't it did not so then one of the
followers later
uh uh will uh get this operation
maybe apply it uh it won't send a
response because it doesn't even know
about the client
uh but the client will retry right
because it actually hasn't gotten
response
it will contact the new leader and
basically enter uh
the same operation in the in the raft
again
and it will pop out again and then
the server will send the as we'll see in
the lab three it will send the last
response
in fact the servers remember the last
value that they sent back
okay um so if there's a get request you
know the first get request is executed
there's no response to be sent back that
get request actually but you will store
the response
in the in the kv in the kv server will
remember the response
so when it's easy to duplicate and then
then we'll send the response
so there will be duplicate detection
table that includes the response
okay yeah makes sense thanks
so welcome i was a little bit curious i
think i asked
uh roughly this in my question uh like
pre-lecture questions well
uh like how raft compares to other like
consensus algorithms in terms of
uh like optimizations you could do and
like as an example i was thinking the
only thing i could
sort of think of was uh batching yeah
and it seemed like raft is like
perfect for batching because the leader
could just like put you know more than
one entry on its log wait a little bit
before sending its next
entries then send the defend entries
with whatever batched
set of uh operations or whatever it
wants the the replicas to do
uh just trying to figure out like what
what are some of the deficiencies of
raft like
from a performance point of view well
rav does not do
that shape right and you know maybe you
could but i'm going to make the vertical
more complicated
and so they decided i guess okay i guess
the way i happen to have written
my like raft lab code like i sort of did
batching
implicitly because i would just wait a
little bit sometimes before sending a
pen entry so
i guess it felt like you don't really
need to do anything other than just like
maybe wait if you feel like it before
yeah you can have multiple ones
so yeah it's like
yeah um
i think it all comes down to performance
so you know there's a whole bunch of
optimizations that rap doesn't do you
know that some other systems do
like you know for example you might be
able to commute to your operations
because it doesn't even matter
uh in what order you do them uh so
there's a slew of optimizations
and around this basically do none of
that okay
thanks and it may be perfectly fine for
like the use case correct
all right
um you mentioned something a couple of
minutes ago that
log entry could be lost so is it
possible that like a client request
could never be executed but the draft
guarantees that
all the servers will execute the same
set of block entries in the same
sequence
uh so like that means draft does not
cannot be usable for like all
applications if we can
only if we can afford uh
some lost requests well
you know we have to assume that you know
the responses from the
from the raf servers as a whole correct
the kv servers plus raft may get lost
anyway
because the network gets lost natural
network may lost responses so the client
has to be able to repeat
we call it must recent uh must return
i see i see so like when it actually
commits a log entry and executes it
it replies to the client that it did
actually do that
yeah yeah so this is like a little bit
earlier we talked about this the the
duplicate detection table the duplicate
detection table has
uh the response that was sent or was
constructed in response to executing
that operation
any further questions
okay thank you so much hi welcome it's
great to have so many questions