okay
good afternoon good morning or good
night
um uh let's get started
uh today i want to talk about the
bitcoin
um the reason i want to talk about it is
it's also hard problem namely achieving
consensus
with byzantine participants
and you know it solves it uh some of the
byzantine i mean
participants that uh might be malicious
or adversarial
and uh it solves this problem in the
context of in
completely open systems you know people
can uh join and leave the system at will
and some of them you know maybe
malicious and yet you know achieves uh
consensus on
uh the order in which transaction
happens
does it actually in a very challenging
context of actually really uh
doing it in uh with money involved
the design uh you know looks a little
bit
like has aspects of sunder so in since
there's a sign log
of operations in this case the
transactions
uh but unlike in cylinder that actually
you know can handle
uh forks
and so most of the you know the many
aspects are interesting to talk about uh
with respect to bitcoin um but mostly
i'm going to focus on sort of the
sort of the distributed systems aspect
of this particular paper
this paper is a bit unusual or
quite unusual uh first of all this is
not a
paper out of the sort of scientific
literature that we've been reading so
far
it comes out of a different part of the
world
it is pseudo-anonymous
and it has a you know particularly gripe
you know with
financial institutions um and you know
you can have uh
all kinds of opinions you know about
whether bitcoin in general uh
and cryptocurrency in general uh but
from the perspective of receiving
systems this is a
mutually successful system you know this
is really truly
uh an open system that can tolerate the
listening participants and
achieve consensus and so really you know
the focus on this lecture is trying to
you know understand how actually to
choose that particular uh
aspect um any questions
just do before i dive in
okay so uh as just mentioned you know
the
context is here uh the financial
transactions
and so those are free overriding
concerns you know when
uh when transactions are involved where
money transactions are involved
first of all of course you know there's
a conservative outright forgery
where basically you know people cook up
you know transactions
out of thin air and answer them in the
log and you know
uh try to mislead other participants you
know that actually they're spending
their uh their own money
uh while spending somebody else's money
and you know this problem
is reasonable straightforward for
assault and in a very sort of similar
style to
sunder but basically signing operations
uh make it hard to actually forge and in
fact you know so the general setting
here correct is the same as in some very
well
you know the byzantine uh partition that
are very very
very powerful we're going to be assuming
that the crypto systems uh actually uh
work and or cannot be compromised
and so a lot of the core you know
functionality uh
or the basis of which you know we might
conclude that actually things are secure
are all going to come down to the fact
that the underlying
cryptography is correct so
that's one challenge uh the second
challenge which is the one that
the paper spends most of this time
talking about is double spending
so you legitimately have you know some
bitcoins
that you accumulated in a
business participant tries to spend uh
twice
uh that same bitcoin and of course we
want to avoid that particular problem
i do and the main ideas we'll see is
that
there's a public ledger or a public log
uh
of all the transactions you know so that
you can see if the transaction actually
uh without money was already spent in an
early transaction
and really trying to achieve uh
consensus on what is actually in the log
is at the heart of the the the paper
then uh of course in addition to uh
these two
there's sort of the obvious other
problem uh which paper doesn't really
talk much about and we're also not going
to talk much about
uh which is just theft uh where
somebody actually steals somebody else's
private key and therefore
can spend money or bitcoins uh using
that particular private key
and it turns out to be in practice a
serious problem uh
people store uh their wallets with
their signing keys on computers you know
computers can be broken into
and and therefore people can break it
over to steal
you know somebody else's money um and
another i think it's a serious problem
in
practice i'm not going to be spending
much time talking about it in fact
again i always want to focus on the
distributed systems aspects
any questions about the challenges
okay let's look at the transaction then
you know what's actually in it
so this is basically what is in the
ledger
uh i'm going to simplify this greatly uh
because some of the details actually
don't really matter to the discussion
that we're going to have
and you know the first order you can
just think about it is every transaction
uh is a record and that record has a
public key
of the user you know for which you know
the
the money is intended so this is the the
destination
um the hash
of the previous transaction you know for
this particular bitcoin
uh and a signature
and we have the private key
these two you know basically the
previous owner of
of that particular uh bitcoin and
uh and that sort of you could think
about this as the source so basically
u2 is making you know granting you know
bitcoins or
uh transferring bitcoins from youtube to
your one so that you're one that can
spend them
um of course there's all kinds of other
stuff in it like there's an amount in it
it's a fractional amount uh there are
many destinations and many sources
possible
you know many ins and outs uh
the reagans are basically all ignored
and just sort of focus on uh
the simplified description turns out the
transactions are
encoded also uh not sort of like sort of
passive records but
uh basically in a little scripting
language um and also going to ignore
all those aspects uh in this technique i
want to focus on this thing
and you know talk a little bit and show
a little example uh so that we get a
little bit of the handle of actually
what
what we're looking at in terms of the
challenge
so we're going to sort of look at an
example ledger and sort of
try to understand actually you know what
it means to be a bitcoin
or what a coin is uh because it's not
like you know
it's sort of a single thing uh actually
it really comes down to it's actually
you know sort of a sha-1 of the last
transaction that is sort of what a coin
is
uh so let's say you know why uh
owns a coin and received uh from
x and so that means that they're
somewhere in the ledger there's sort of
a
set of transactions that transfer the
money or the
coin or parts of the coin to uh y
and so let's see like somewhere maybe
there's an entry in the left or
somewhere in the some period of time
where x actually received
uh some bitcoins
and uh and now you know it's a
grandson or uh it has given it to uh
y so there's another transaction in
the ledger that basically records that
fact and so that might have the top key
of
y as the destination the hash of the
transaction six
so that uniquely identifies a shorthand
handle for actually uniquely identifying
transaction six and so we have the
ledger record that we think is
transaction six now we can recompute the
hash of that transaction compared to
the one that stored into section seven
and you know truly determined that
basically
uh transaction six what's the source you
know for this transaction seven
or it's based the previous objection was
to section six
for this particular coin and this is
assigned by
you know x um now
uh so this is sort of the situation
where you know y
obtained you know basically uh you know
some some bitcoins you know for an x
you know y wants to spend i think for
example maybe y wants to
buy a latte you know from z uh and so
it's gonna
transfer some money to um
z so maybe we'll see another transaction
in the ledger
which is going to be a form you know
this is one that actually y is going to
add
uh
z uh hash of the
you know previous uh coin
which is the last injection for that
coin so that's t7
and it's sent by y
um and basically you know c wants to
before again z actually hands over the
latte
to y because you need to do some
verification uh to
make sure that this actually is a legit
you know transaction
uh so you know we'll look up uh
you know transaction seven um and you
know compute you know the hash of it you
know double check that the
hash actually corresponds to the one
that actually is listed in transaction
uh uh in transaction eight
uh if you know the hash you know checks
out so there's action seven is indeed
you know
we believe that the one that actually
turned action eight refers to
uh you know z looks up the the public
key
uh in transaction seven for
y which usually is the public key y then
you know verifies that use that public
key to verify the signature
you know of this transaction and the
second zero course you know covers
you know the whole transaction and if
the signature checks out
you know then uh you know z can be sort
of confident you know that actually
uh the ledger you know contains a
transaction that basically transfers you
know some amount of money
from y to z and so at this point you
know the verification you know she
verifies
and you know if it's okay
you know whatever shift the latte
and if not you know reject
and again like before in uh you know
sunder
and in all these sort of schemes uh you
know we're relying here on the fact that
basically why
uh you know was careful with its private
key
yeah so yeah we we have to assume that y
didn't disclose in any way
it's private key
uh because if anybody has you know this
private key then basically anybody could
come up to signature
uh and you know he's able to spend
basically wise money
um although maybe from the perspective
receiver doesn't really care
um okay so uh
so that's sort of the basic plan
uh in terms of you know having a record
and uh you know this is pretty good
right i mean
there's a record of the transaction that
happened uh when c you know receives a
transaction they can check whether this
is a valid
transaction and uh um you know wants to
decide whether to actually
accept the money and deliver the goods
so one key challenge
uh now sort of left
you know we are seeing that outright
forgery is difficult uh
but you know we need to think a little
bit about the double spend and so
the double spending problem is as
follows let's say instead of you know
creating two
one record as in this critical example
in the transaction
eight z actually integrates over y
creates two records
uh one record is basically giving the
one that we just saw
i mean rt8
y2z uh with the hash of seven
now but let's see let's assume that
actually uh y also
tries to uh double spend its money so it
creates a second
transaction you know ta prime uh were
you know
the records is basically the same except
you know the money you know maybe goes
to q
and it has the hash of t7
and of course you know science by y you
know signed by y
um and now you know let's say you know
both q and z are
like a lot a stores uh if you know
uh z accepts to you eight uh
as it would because you know everything
will check out as we saw in the previous
slide then z would actually ship a lot a
to y
uh when q not knowing anything maybe
about this other
ta transaction uh since this ta the
transaction
you know checks out it's indeed the case
that you know the money
in t7 was transferred to why uh the
thing is you know checked you know with
the
the second year for why you know it's
valid and it will say okay great you
know
i'll thank you for the money i'll ship
you also a lot
and now so we're in this bad you know
position where
um why uh by double spending or
succeeded in double spending and
i've got two relatives you know just the
problem that basically the
paper is really focused on and trying to
solve
the basic approach is
yeah sort of similar to what you know
something was doing you know let's keep
a complete log of all
transactions since the beginning of time
uh
and uh in the logs and it contains all
the transactions
uh including in the order
right and so you know let's see you know
so we just sort of put the distributions
in
you know whatever here we have you know
t6 here we have t7
so if there's a public record that is
ordered of all the transactions you know
t8 or ta prime goes first let's say t8
goes first
and then ta prime goes in the log
and you know if this would happen then
you know no problem at all
correct because uh this was the
transaction from
y to z this was the transaction from y
to q
and uh you know basically when uh
uh q validates to you know when z
validates interjection everything looks
perfect as exactly as before
when q validates the transaction in
addition to the checks you know that we
just looked at
um it actually looks in the log you know
q who's in the log
so i like to see if t7 basically is
already spent
and you know of course you know scans
back and lock you know runs into t y
uh t8 and you know sees that actually
the money has been spent
so therefore it will reject you know t a
prime
all right so uh so that's
the basic plan and so basically you know
we reduced this one problem
which is like how do we actually ensure
that
um all participants in the systems
actually agree on this log and that you
know all the transactions are in the
same slot
everywhere uh and contain the same
content the same hashes the same
signatures
so that we can actually verify uh the
transactions you know using the scheme
that the
uh this is sort of laid out on this
slide
and so this is where uh the sort of
consensus problem
uh comes in and um sometimes people
refer to the solution here as the
nakamoto consensus protocol
now before diving into that protocol i
want to sort of sketch out
you know possible uh solutions that are
not going to work just to get a little
bit better sense about like you know
what the challenges are that
this sort of uh nakamoto consensus
actually
solves
so uh you know design one
there's not really design it's more sort
of an idea to sort of think about and
then reject
design one you know maybe is the easiest
design is let's assume
we have a server s and the server
actually just trusted
and then we have clients you know that
you know
submit transactions you know whatever t6
uh one
and they just submit you know these
transactions to the
uh to the structure server you know
after we all the
old clients you know trust the server
then the server can just produce a log
right with all the transactions in it
and you know order them appropriately
etc etc
so if we assume you know there's a
trusted server then this problem is
actually reasonable and
straightforward to solve and you know
that's the setting that we're in that
we're in great shape
uh you know we will replicate the server
using you know some rafter type
protocol and uh you know where i have a
full tolerance server
and you know really the only downside
you know to this particular process is
if the clients can just not agree
on a single trusted uh server and so
for example in the case of bitcoin and
where you want to do transactions
uh you know maybe the you know the rest
of the world will not uh
trust the u.s government to actually you
know implement this server correctly and
produce
a log and uh and in that case you know
we have
multiple uh different clients because
you cannot agree on a trusted server
then this this
solution this user doesn't work
so that's one uh solution uh it's the
easy one
but in the case of a decentralized
design where the participants
don't trust any central component this
is not a workable
uh solution so so now we could consider
you know using sort of the more
solder-like approach
to modify the scheme slightly and say
like okay good we know actually how to
deal with
untrusted servers in fact we read a
paper about last week
and so let's assume that this server is
actually untrusted
and you know we basically you know play
this undergame the clients
produce the logs read the logs from the
server paint the rockets to the
kinds of penta records to the log submit
it back you know to the server
and so the server is basically doing
almost nothing else that's relaying logs
you know between different clients
and you know we've seen in last week
that that x approach
works really well uh and you know can be
used
uh but you know it has one shortcoming
as we saw
namely the server can present two very
different views
of the world by basically forking the
log so maybe the log has some prefix
you know whatever p one two three five
six c six seven but you know it has
you know t eight in this one and has
another log
which indeed has t seven do
and t8 prime right and
so one fork you know we've got our t8 on
the other fork we have t8 prime
and now like we became really acetylene
in one particular uh
fork and uh the server sort of
persistently you know keeps the two
worlds apart
like the y's and uh z's in one area of
the world
accuse another in the world uh y
always gets the first sort of log and uh
uh and zeos gets the second one locked
or
the other way around uh then uh you know
then they will pretend they're good yeah
there was no money earlier spent in
t7 uh uh in this log so you know taq
will actually accept
you know t8 prime in this world and here
z
will accept you know t8 and so y
succeeded in actually double spending
and so uh so this design doesn't work
uh for the particular problem at hand uh
we need some solution this is where the
consensus comes in we need some solution
basically for
the untrusted clients to basically be
able to settle
on which you know fork they are on
okay so in so let's think a little bit
about that so like so think about a more
much more decent light design where you
know we're just going to replace the
server with a network of computers
and so this is there and this goes sort
of to
get you closer to the bitcoin design
where there's indeed a network
of you know peers that sort of all
collaborate
uh together to use or provide you know
this
single log although even though some of
the participants actually might
be malicious and try to do something
different and so basically the idea is
that you know when a client actually you
know have to
create a transaction you know then
transaction x was distributed
across uh a network you know of peers
the fact the client one might be appear
himself and so the transaction is
spread around
and uh you know everybody every node
in the network actually maintains a log
and
appends you know the transaction to its
log
and the problem that we sort of have
left is like you know how to agree on an
order
uh and you know we we actually have seen
you know this kind of sort of systems uh
before like in fact in raft you know we
had multiple computers
and they were able to agree on an order
correct and the basic trick
you know that would use so the basic
insight is you know to basically
compute you know some majority and have
majority of the nodes agree
that in slot you know 6 is going to be
transaction t8
and in slot 7 is going to be ta prime
and the and
that works great correct uh if we know
exactly how many nodes there are in the
system
uh we know there are five nodes in the
system uh
the new and then the majority is free
and so we receive a response from free
participants you know we know okay we
can commit that particular slot
and the problem really here is that this
is a decentralized system
that is completely open
the system uh notes might even uh
may leave and come at any particular
point in time and now like there is no
list of all the participants in the
system so there's also no
you know clear what actually what is a
majority in a system like that
um because it's completely open and so
it's like in the notion of a majority
you're completely ill-defined
um so you know we need some sort of
sort of like actual usual game of doing
uh voting on a majority and then accept
the result of the majority
is not going to sort of play out and so
this is the
the game that sort of raft you know even
though it's a consensus protocol
it's not going to really work out
because you know the uh the setting
we're dealing with
is a decentralized open distributed
system as opposed to sort of a closed
system as in the
setting of draft
does this make sense so far
let me pause for a second before getting
into the more technical part
all right
okay so uh so how does bitcoin solve
this problem
and the key idea is uh something that's
called
approval work
basically the rule is that
there's a amount of work uh a note needs
to do
to actually be able to extend the log
and uh and the basic rule is that
the winner uh in
you know proof of work the the
machine that's able to solve the puzzle
first
is it decides on the next log entry
and uh and and the basic idea that this
might you know you might actually get
some intuition why this actually will
work out
is because it's basically hard to
impersonate the winner
to actually solve the particular
proof-of-work puzzle uh
that needs to be uh to be able to add to
the log actually requires a real
computer
uh in a month roughly of you know
compute time
uh to actually solve the problem and so
if you can solve and demonstrate
yourself the problem you know you know
for sure that somebody actually spent a
month of work actually doing it
um and this is sort of enough of to
uh uh convince you know the rest of the
system that you know the
the uh the real resources were actually
spent
to uh append to be able to attend to the
log entry and and you can maybe think of
other
type of schemes or like you know
whatever you know the unique ip
addresses or things like that but all
those kind of things can be actually
easily falsified
uh and so uh and this sort of proof of
work
idea is sort of the core to demonstrate
that
uh yeah i can really you know put a
month effort in to actually
uh uh to to figure out what the next
door to compute be able to
to be able to append a log entry to the
blog
one you know just to get that
immediately out of the way one of the
downside of this sort of proof-of-work
approach
is that it actually wastes energy
and in fact if you're uh you know
bitcoin has become so successful
uh that a lot of people are down there
are you know mining and doing this uh
proof of work
uh the the you know energy bill or the
energy consumption
uh of all the combined
miners together is incredibly
significant uh
which is huge and so the
complete downside of this approach is
the the wasted energy
in recent years you know there have been
other
uh cryptocurrencies or other designs
that are based on a different idea
instead of proof of work they're
actually based on something that's
called proof of stake
uh and this is basically sort of the
game there is that like you know let's
say you own three percent
of you know the currency then
you get uh because of your uh you own
three percent you can actually
decide you know for three percent of the
log entries
uh which ones are going to be appended
and so the
uh and so this is a completely different
approach that doesn't
require solving uh computational
intensive puzzles
uh and that seems to uh
get quite a bit of actually uh attention
and you know there are
cryptocurrencies that use it and in fact
it looks like one of the more
major ones ethereum seems to be sort of
slated or
going in the direction of a
proof-of-stake approach
but bitcoin now uses a proof-of-work
approach
and so we're just going to proceed you
know with that design
any questions um
so let's uh so i'm just wondering of how
it's hard to impersonate the wenner so
let's say that we have
server a and server b and server a wants
to append
entry let's say e1 and server b wants to
append entry e2
so server a solves the puzzle and
publishes the solution
right and i'm assuming that the solution
is easy to check so
then server b uh sees the solution and
checks that it's correct
uh so it cannot work
that server b just simply republishes
the solution
with its own name and signing it by its
own name because the puzzle for
e2 is different from the puzzle for e1
right
yeah yeah exactly and we'll see uh you
know we'll get into this in more detail
in a second
uh this is sort of the basic insight you
know it's of course not enough
uh but it will turn out to be enough to
basically settle on a
fork so we're going to accept they're
going to be forks and then we're going
to
have you know bitcoin basically accepts
that there are forex like in
solder but then has a way of basically
deciding which fork to settle on
so i had a question about uh network
partitions
and i was wondering how like you know
if you were able to make a partition
like on the internet
which you know it's probably like
unreasonable but
if you're able to partition the internet
like the whole internet
and couldn't you convince like you know
um one like double spend
by like spending on both sides of the
partition
yeah the petition never heals you
succeed
like eventually you'd assume it heals
but then by then
right like you probably would have
gotten like something shipped or
yeah so in general so we'll see we'll
talk a little bit more about it but like
uh there are all kinds of there's ways
of creating forks and what you're
describing is basically fork that
persists for a long period of time
and you know we'll see the the basically
the
uh you know bitcoin basically produces
these blocks with transactions sort of
every 10 minutes
and you know if you're very conservative
or you want to be careful
not to be
avoid double spending or making sure
that there's no nothing with double
spend you generally wait
you know for multiple these blocks to
appear like five six or basically an
hour
before actually you decide to actually
accept you know the to say
oh yeah that this is i'm on the right
fork
thanks
okay so let's also see actually how the
pieces fit together um so it turns out
you know the you don't do a proof of
work you know per transaction
uh it'll be crazy uh because you got to
spend a lot of computational power
you know for them for that one single
transaction that will limit the number
of transactions you can actually do
per second and so uh the way actually
this is done is that basically
transactions are
grouped in blocks and the proof of work
uh
is done on a on a blog basis
and so we have our network
and the way it actually works is that
we're not making a lot of blogs but like
we you know
make a a lot of transactions we make
actually log of blocks which are called
you know basically a blockchain
and so here we've got our network you
know we have peers
all around the world and uh
you know the log you know is basically
you know sequence of blocks
and so peers have you know copies of
these you know they may communicate new
ones you know pen them
and distribute them and flood them
across the network
and so what is in a in a block
uh at a very high level again there are
many more details
that i'm just going to ignore it's going
to be the hash of the previous block
so p minus one
and so if this is block five you know
this is going to be then
uh you know b4 so b minus one
so the unique identifier of the
basically the previous block in the
in the chain the transactions that are
part of this block
uh and then announce
which we'll talk about in a second but
this is the thing that is going to play
a crucial role
in the the puzzle and the timestamp
and you know this is about typically
obviously a little bit but you know
think about this as a roughly a megabyte
you know block so basically the the game
is you know the
uh the period of collect transactions uh
then uh basically solves the puzzle
uh and once they solve the puzzle
they're gonna
ship the block to uh everybody in the in
the network
uh everybody can check whether the peer
actually solved the
puzzle correctly and if you know the
possible's correcting yourself
uh correctly in the transaction checkout
and you know everything the hash is
checked out
then they're going to basically accept
that block as the next block in the
chain
so a little bit more detail
uh you know when you know basically the
winner gets to the site
uh on the next vlog
so we have a new blog
and this is basically going to be the
proof of work which is done typically
the
the party that does the proof of work is
called the miners
and we'll see in a second why um
and basically the the game that
we're going to play is that the
miner has to compute a hash of this new
block
for that basically has
has n leading
zeros
so and the way you know the the miner
can do that is basically
by changing the nuts so basically the
miner makes the random guesses
uh four or nones uh computes the hash
and you know checks you know the number
of leading zeros and then
if the lean number of leading zeros is
you know and or larger
then you know basically that is a block
that's going to be accepted
the only way you can think about it is
that basically the hash value is below
some particular uh
particular difficulty value this end can
be tuned
over time as we'll see in a second later
uh to you know
adjust the difficulty um uh
and but on average you know what you
know the amount of work
that is necessary you know sort of that
they're targeting
is about like roughly a cpu month of
computation and it's not really
expressed in that way it's really
expressed in terms of number of hashes
you can do per second
uh but then it boils down to sort of
shooting for that kind of number
of course a lot of peers you know do
this in parallel you know
they're i think the network is currently
around ten thousand nodes so ten
thousand nodes might be
and there might be many more miners
i think the hundreds of thousands of
miners and you know they might get lucky
right when you know you
pick you know the right nuns very
quickly uh and some of them actually
uh uh get quickly and so
what they're shooting sort of roughly is
that you know that the first one you
know to actually solve the puzzle
now takes about 10 minutes
and you know by adjusting the difficulty
and the you know the the protocol can
sort of adjust you know the
time or the the the time it will take to
actually you know compute one of these
hashes and
so the energy that one has to put into
to actually solve the the
puzzle and so whenever
uh you know the whoever miner you know
sort of solves this puzzle first
basically gets to uh spread the block
across the network
and basically has sort of about 10
minutes you know to do so right and so
you know one reason
that the ten minutes is there is that it
will take a little bit of time to move
that one megabyte of walk you know
across you know the many many peers that
are in the network
and uh you want to make sure that
there's enough time to sort of
get the uh the block out
to many of the peers so that you can
avoid forks as we'll see in a second
and so before that somebody else
actually you know solves the puzzle too
um professor yeah so
um does the number of leading zeroes
that uh hash needs like to be accepted
by a node
is that number like set by each node
individually
no no no no this is part of the protocol
there's an agreed part on it
right right but it's consensus on the
about ns
um but what what i mean is like it's
part of the protocol but
like um
so so so you can change
well-behaved nodes will follow it but
they but but who calculate who
calculates it the
is it a central server that that
calculates the sand and sends it out or
everything oh no no
we'll see in a second later actually how
it's computed uh
but basically what i can give you a hint
about like how it's computed
one reason the timestamps are in these
things
uh is that like if the time between
blocks becomes too low then the
difficulty goes up
and you know these time sensor cores are
validated you know using the hashes and
all the kind of stuff and sit in the
blockchain everybody sees the same
blockchain
so they will compute you know the same
difference between the timestamps and
you know therefore
make the same adjustment in terms of
difficulty right
um and this is one of the cool parts
correct of having a log of everything
that's in there like if you know i have
some determinant of this
you could compute any deterministic
function of like the content of the log
right okay um so so it would be a
deterministic function but but at the
end of the day like
if if i like try and get away with like
sending
less than n like zeros
then each individual node in the network
should call me out yeah they will reject
your solution because
i don't have a real solution okay thanks
so what stops an attacker from just
constantly flooding the network with
wrong solutions
uh yeah the denial service attack you
know hopefully the the one of the
turns out that the checking the solution
is very easy right
and so it's easy to quickly reject an
incorrect solution
thank you and how how are the time
stamps determined dude
like does each block set the timestamp
on its own or
now the miner that successfully mines
you know sets the timestamp in the
block and what if they just set the
timestamp to be
uh like longer than it took
so that it becomes less difficult well
they can't lie too much correctly they
have a 10 minute window sort of roughly
to why i
i don't really know exactly how the
timestamp is checked i don't know
i might imagine this is solvable
okay peers get like the transactions
that
want to be appended to the block thank
you that's the next line
so so blocks and transactions
uh so let's assume like there is some
you know block b5
that already has been computed you know
that sits in the log
you know points forever two b four
and so we're a minor uh we're working on
you know we got a blog with you know
that is sort of
we're mining on so that has a bunch of
transactions
and uh we're basically you know trying
to compute
you know the solution to this puzzle and
so new transactions come in
right you know they arrive and so the
new transaction is actually
you know they call the memory buffer or
buffer they're going some buffer
uh and uh and basically they're gonna
uh when the next block now we're
going to be so at some point this guy
you know let's say this is one minor
minor all right so let's say minori is
the lucky one you know actually
uh minori computes you know the
new b6 and so at some point you know d6
is the new uh next head of the log
uh you know which contains a bunch of
transactions and so while you know sort
of minor i was actually trying to hash
you know computing many many many hashes
to actually solve the puzzle
new transactions come in and so soon as
uh
the minor i is done you know with b6 uh
it basically selects you know the number
of transactions puts a new block
together
a partial blog that's not the one that
is solved yet
you know transactions in from the pool
uh
whatever updates you know whatever an
instrument needs to be updated and then
start hashing on that one
and hoping to solve it so that that can
be added you know to the transaction log
at some point later if it succeeds
of course if somebody else succeeds in
solving the
uh producing b7 before minor i
you know minor is going to switch you
know to the d7 of that blog
remove any transactions that ended up
already in d7
and continues with the transaction that
are left and that are not in b7 yet
okay so that's sort of the plan
for how transactions and blogs interact
at a high level um
so as as transactions um
come in like you know you're trying to
calculate the nons for a block
uh that'll that'll like give you like
you know and leaving zeros
um new transactions will come in right
as
you yeah they're not part of that block
they're going to be sitting on the side
there for the next block
okay could you
could you add could you add them to them
i would change the hash right but
i mean you just need to keep trying to
get like a
nonce right you also have there's a
limit on the block size
you know the block size can't be bigger
than one one some
particular predefined console by
protocol uh
you know there's a bunch of other
reasons you know once you filled up the
blog you know with your transactions you
you keep going hashing until you know
you find the solution
okay or or you get and
or you receive a new one and then you
reject and you don't work on the next
one
okay thanks
so when when someone when a miner like
loses
and do they like like is it possible for
a minor never to make profit
out of this because they keep like
losing because they don't have enough
computers
yeah absolutely if i would start mining
with my laptop i'm pretty sure it would
make no money
in the transaction pool it is local
yeah every every node maintains this uh
transaction pool right as they receive
transactions from uh
uh from other nodes in the network you
know they keep that
transaction pool and you know they use
that transaction pool basically to
fail the next block so
and there are all kinds of rules you
know how you should select transactions
which i'm not going to talk about okay
so to a pen you need to tell your
transaction to everyone
yes or you you tell to a bunch of peers
and they
will flood it for the rest of you to the
rest of the network
so from my understanding uh when a miner
successfully
mines or verifies a transaction uh
they get rewarded because they did
this verification but they can also
lie when it comes to the time stamp so
let's say that you have two verifiers
and they're both working on the same
block
and they almost simultaneously verified
at the same time
but one of them was you know they lied
and they made the timestamp a bit
earlier uh so kind of they were
but the the the the difficulties chosen
for a period
of time like for the next like 20 you
know there's a whole bunch of series
it only changes periodically you can't
change it arbitrarily
so what's that i'm sorry i think i
missed that line
the difficulty is not changed on every
block
it is periodically changed after some
number of you know blocks
have been computed and so you know it's
done in the back you know everybody can
see what these timestamps are
you know every i think it's every i up
the exact number
of blocks is where uh uh when when you
know the difficulty is adjusted
i see okay thank you so at that point
you already agreed on all those blogs in
the past so everybody's in agreement
like what the timestamps are that we're
going to actually use to actually
compute a new
uh developer block
um so so i i had one um
one question about um like achieving
consensus i
i guess like all of this like relies on
like
pretty much every node running uh the
same code right or at least following
the
the rules very very precisely yep like
what happens if there's a bug
in like my code in the code that i'm
running um
you know maybe a bug in like a bunch of
different nodes
does that like throw off like like all
like notions of like consistency
potentially well you know the the the
as long as the majority is we'll talk a
little bit more about it as a majority
of the nodes actually
runs the right code you know everything
should work out right
but like if there's a trapdoor in the
code yeah you got a problem
like if there's a trebor in linux you
got a problem too
so so do does every node run
like the same code or are they different
no there are a couple different bitcoin
versions around we'll talk a little bit
more about it in a second
uh but there are uh sort of the main you
know core
uh they're called you know and they're
like it's like an open source project
like like linuxes you know it has
maintainers and you know
code review and all that kind of stuff
and mostly like the wallets and most of
the sort of the
appears will run you know one of the the
standardized version basically
thanks
uh okay forks so
uh so we know now like what the rule is
you know
who can actually extend uh the the log
uh or the chain the boxing you can still
have forks
again because it's going to mute our
chain whatever
b5 you know b6
and you know we you know somebody you
two might actually get sort of lucky
and so roughly computes you know b7 you
know two b7s at the same time so
here we go b7 prime and here we have b7
double prime
uh and that'll be problematic for us
right because maybe you know one of
these
this chain uh has the transaction you
know the
the the y to whatever y to z
yeah and maybe this one has no y to q
right then you know we we're on there
sort of make sure that we actually
settle in the end of one chain
so there's two reasons why this change
might develop you know one
is you know the people or participants
find the
the find the nons at the same time
or roughly at the same time and the
second one
is that you know there may be a slow
network yeah
and so you know a peer might receive you
know from two
that there are different ends of the
network at some point these two new
solutions
um and basically you know when a node
ends up in this situation
it basically does nothing and usually
keeps the fork around
and just waits to see which work gets
extended
and so you know maybe this fork the
bottom one you know will get extended
with you know b8
and then the rule is very simple uh you
know the
pier switches
switches to longest fork
and uh and so uh and so
basically you know all the transactions
you know they might have learned about
in this this work in the top fork are
just going to disappear you know they're
going to
not matter in the the system uh because
in the end
you know all those sort of good notes
will actually agree on the longest chain
and you know basically proceed you know
mining along the longest chain
that's the basic plan and so let's look
a little bit about like how
would that solve our double spending
problem
oh wait i have a question on the new
slide
yep i'm going to continue on the
previous slide in this slide
oh okay so um let me ask the question so
so even if the in the in the second
cause
like the slow network can't you um
detect that if you if the miner included
the timestamp where they
when they found the solution
okay yeah you might you know already be
suspicious or may
agree on what actually the next you know
what the right problem the right chain
is
but it will be confirmed later by future
blocks
and you know you use the future blocks
to really decide what the longest chain
is
okay
uh okay double spending uh
so let's talk about sort of two easy two
cases the first one is easy uh
you know y you know sends
you know the y to z
and y to q to some pier or to the peers
and basically what will happen correct
in this case is that if it's a
well-behaving peer you'll see like hey
you know two transactions
uh that actually spent the same money at
uh
said twice or this is going to reject uh
that so a peer that receives you know is
trying to
go or minor that it's going to construct
a blog and it will actually validate all
the transactions before they stick them
in the blog
so this will you know don't really this
is not going to work mine is going to
reject
a good binder
okay the second advice or the more
instinct i think cases
basically why since you know y to z
you know to some set of appears
and you know y to q
to another set of peers
and you know and you know that and my
you know maybe you know the maybe the
one pool is bigger than the other pool
uh but it could actually end up in a
situation where basically you know we
got the chain
like as before and basically either
once it appears you know computes you
know the uh a hash where
that includes y to q and the other one
computes a block you know that actually
contains y to
z uh and so this looks like a double
spending thing
and so if you're z correct like studio
is the person that is going to decide
whether to accept you know
this transaction and hand out the uh
hand up the latte
what you do is you're going to wait
and you're going to wait until there's a
bunch of more blocks that are behind it
so
typically it's five six up to five six
you know for a very valuable transaction
maybe not for a latte but if you're
buying a car
uh you know you really wanna make damn
sure that you're gonna get your money
and uh that you know why didn't double
spend
the money and so uh you may work you
know
wait for a while you know until new uh
hash has been ended
you know to do a new blocks will be
extended to the uh blockchain
and you know once you have five or six
uh as the paper does some calculations
you're gonna be pretty confident that
you'll be very confident that
um uh that it's unlikely
you know for attacker to basically uh
compute a new chain
and sort of overtake you know the the
longer chain
right let's say this is the attacker the
attacker has less computational power
you know presumably or this is
the assumption behind this whole paper
has less computational power than all
the good people
and so if the good people have more
computational power
it's going to be impossible for the
attacker or you know
unlikely or if it's intellectually uh
impossible or unlikely
for the attacker to basically compute
faster and actually make a chain that's
longer than the good chain
and so that's sort of the key assumption
that's behind
all this uh about among this among this
reasoner
reasoning and so basically c
you know just has to wait for a while
until the good guys have extended the
chain uh long enough that you know the z
is completely convinced that you know
you know it's impossible for a set of
attackers uh to actually
out compute you know the the good people
and and at that point you know z can
just accept the transaction
and say like oh this is a legit
transaction and if everything else
checks out
and uh hand over the latte or the car
you know to
uh to z or yeah to y i guess
sorry quick question uh who distributes
the puzzles
uh there's no distribution deposits
necessary
right the uh
the puzzle is you know predetermined you
know the puzzle is you have to compute a
hash of a block
that has enough leading zeros
so there's no distribution of the puzzle
the only thing that's distributed maybe
is the difficulty but as we talked a
little bit earlier that sort of adjusted
over time
in a deterministic way thank you
so there's all these transactions that
are happening and then
through some gossip protocol or
something the transaction is distributed
to all the nodes
and then somehow
there's agreement on what set of
transactions are packaged into a block
so everyone has
agreement on what the block is
no no no the miner receives transactions
right
uh we go here where was it
uh new block there was some slide on
i think the next one
yeah blocks in transactions so the miner
maybe like miner i
you know just receives transactions over
the network and it just decides which
transactions go in that block
and it starts computing and if it wins
that is the transactions that go in that
block
i see okay so that determines that the
total order correct
you know the total order is determined
by all the previous blocks you know plus
this new block and within the block you
know basically a minor i has decided
what goes in
and there's some complicated rules that
the reminders are supposed to follow
but you know basically the miner gets to
this side
thank you
and there's sort of incentive systems
for the miners to do the right thing
uh so let me talk a little bit about
this um
uh so uh so far you know we've seen you
know the
this puzzle that's sort of the core of
this proof of work idea to that's at the
core of actually
achieving consensus uh
and uh but you know this requires the
miners actually do quite a bit of work
you know like they have to hash hash
hash you have to have a serious computer
uh you know it's a month one roughly a
month work right
and so why would a minor do that and so
there's an incentive system
for to encourage miners to actually play
this role
and you know there's a rule that
basically the
uh there's a bunch of sort of bitcoins
reserved in the pool like when the
first bit you know bitcoin transaction
was created
and miners get paid or rewarded out of
that pool
and so basically the first transaction
transaction in the blog is basically a
reward for the miner
and so basically the miner can insert a
transaction in in the
first generation conservation
interaction the first slot uh
where that basically is you know the
miner's public key
and uh transferring money out of the
pool to himself
or herself and uh and as the way the
miners get actually
uh uh uh uh getting
really sort of a return or reward for
actually the work they do
uh that reward changes over time um
currently i think you're for you know
today is i think it's 6.25
you know bitcoin uh
to actually mine a block um but this
changes over time it actually has sort
of a halfing rule uh
that reduces you know half the like a
couple years ago it was
a 12-bit 12.5 bitcoin uh you know in a
couple
in the wild will be whatever free point
you know whatever they have for 6.25 and
i think
uh i remember correctly every like every
two and every two
under 10 000 blocks uh that number
halves
it's until it runs into the most finest
uh you know the the finest uh
bitcoin uh denominator and then it
basically stops
but we're a while away before that
actually is the case
if that happens then uh the idea is that
you know to mine actually block every
transaction pays a little fee
and the miner collects the fees you know
from all the
transactions in the block and use and
reward
the miner with those feeds even now
there are some fees
but to basically ensure that basically
the transactions are not frivolous
and so really the miner actually earns
not only the
uh 6.25 but also like the
the the fees that actually uh and the
fees that actually go along with the
transactions
okay so that's the minor incentive uh
in uh you know bitcoin has gotten so
successful
that basically there's sort of an arms
range in minors
and this is like for example why you
know if i would want to participate
and actually win and make some money i'm
going to lose
because the serious miners
are much better at computing hashes at a
very high rate
than you know your standard laptop can
and so there's a couple of things that
are actually going on in this arms race
first of all the miners for pools
so the basic idea is that the miners
collaborate with each other
and they share the revenue with each
other and so like you know if you've
pulled
many many many notes uh you know maybe
from different people many computers
from different people the uh you know
the people can share
the revenue stream out of mining and uh
because they do it as a pool
you know they're more likely to actually
win and once in a while
and you know of course probabilistically
they have some chance to win
and basically you know spread sort of
the income stream
in a more stable form across all the
miners in the single pool
if you think if you look online today
there are some really large pools and i
think like
the three biggest pools uh continue
to contribute more than fifty percent
you know sort of the mining power
oh sorry why is this why you said that
each block takes like around 10 minutes
to mine even though it takes a month of
cpu power
oh yeah on average is a month
uh but you know you're gonna have some
lucky you know you pick the noms you
know
uh you can get lucky and actually uh uh
pick a nonce that actually allows you to
solve the problem much quicker right
there's always some probability the
nonsense of some big number
or and if you pick the right number you
know you get a good lucky and many many
many
minors do that there's actually a chance
that
it's going to take much less than uh a
month and in fact that's why
where the 10 minute comes from um wait
so is
is the month more important or 10
minutes more important because
like if there was only one minor right
and the expected is one month
you on average it would take one month
right yeah but the the assumption is
there are many many miners
um but what wouldn't it like vary like
if there's a lot more minor
miners there's a lot of variation but on
average is 10 minutes
so it's picked that his own averages
comes out to be 10 minutes
okay is it ever possible that like a
puzzle is
impossible
uh no i don't think so
it may take a long time there is going
to be a
there's going to be you get to pick the
nonce correct and
you know there's going to be a case
where the hash is going to fall
you know within the in leading zeros
i'm so like how so since the value of
bitcoin is actually very
let's say volatile yes
and so then like how can we actually
ensure that the incentive system for the
miners is
uh still adequate to keep this thing
going for the future
i mean since the number of like since
like the reward is predetermined let's
say to be 6.25 bitcoins
what if for some reason the bitcoin
value just dropped and then the
incentive is not good enough for the
miners and so
just there yeah you know like there's
absolutely no value for miners to do
this
then you know the bitcoin network will
collapse and presumably the way this is
going to work out is that the
transaction fee is going to go up
but then if the transaction fees go up
then it will
it will be a counter incentive for
people who
yeah but like you know if everybody's on
the bitcoin network you know if you want
to trade you know goods you know
you have to deal with somebody on the
bitcoin network so there's all kinds of
you know sort of compensated analysis
that i'm not going to like you know
predict on like what is going to be the
outcome that's
okay well i guess we've seen two 21.40
and that's sort of the point where i
think the reward system runs out and
it's going to be all based on
transaction fees
and with the current rate i think
um okay so the other thing that's going
on is
you know people build special hardware
you know there are companies that you
know will deliver you boards you know
that are really good at fast and hashing
and uh these are used by the minor poles
uh people try to maybe they have high
speed links too many peers
so that if they find a block they can
actually you know get it out first
and so they win etcetera etcetera so
this is a you know if you're interested
in this you can read lots and lots of
information about it online
uh but you know still the system seems
to be sort of hanging together
okay uh let me talk a little bit about a
whole bunch of sort of
practical issues that i sort of ignored
although we touched on it a bit
um so first ten minutes
i think the ten minutes is basically
you're sort of the tying
you know the sort of an upper bound or
like if you will like sort of 10 times
the time roughly to flood the network
so bitcoin wants to try to avoid you
know these uh sort of
privileged uh you know frivolous uh
forks you know we're basically you know
two nodes at the same time roughly
compute
and therefore extend you know the uh
chain
roughly at the same time and want to try
to avoid that
and so one way to avoid that is to
basically give enough time to the nodes
to sort of get the
uh the block out you know to many many
many peers
so that most peers actually know about
it
and then you know so that's where this
sort of the 10 minutes comes from
um of course the block size
determines the uh the newer transactions
per second
the block size is roughly a megabyte and
so uh
you know you're gonna do one block you
know per you know roughly 10 minutes
then you know the number of transactions
uh
is limited to uh
the number of uh you know the number of
introductions that fit in a single walk
and that is the only number of
transactions you can do
and it turns out that uh for uh
today you know the uh the number
transactions is like in
the thousands per second you should work
out the numbers and that's sufficient
for example there's probably you know
the analogy that people always make you
know sort of bigger than the sort of the
visa network
uh the more transaction the visa can
process by presumably is not big enough
to actually
uh uh you know basically run all
transactions you know uh money
transactions in the world
across
another big you know this i'll come back
to this in a second
another big issue is that changes you
know to the protocol
change required consensus
and in some cases this is easy right
some changes are easy
there's one easy changes for example the
number of leading zeros
you know there's basically a
deterministic algorithm
to compute from the past log entries
uh what the difficulty is going to be
for future uh
puzzles and since that is deterministic
uh function of the log you know there's
nothing
that changes basically uh and easy and
there's a bunch of
other parameters in the protocol that
have that kind of flavor
some changes however resolved in a soft
fork
let me talk just a little bit about well
let's say when uh you know the
main software the main distribution the
core distribution for bitcoin uh wants
to make a change that they're already
sort of incompatible
uh then you're gonna have old clients uh
clients running with the old software or
appears running with the old server and
new gears with the new software
and that will you know temporarily you
know may create some forms
uh and of course you know there's some
communication going on and
uh in the long run you know probably the
people will settle on the new fork
with the new software
some changes actually result in a hard
fork
oops work for it
uh so for example there was a you know a
couple years ago there was a lot of
discussion about this block size
uh because some uh people in the
community community want to increase the
block size some other people don't want
to increase the block size
and basically you know uh they split and
immediately there's corresponds with
two bitcoin or two bitcoin
forks running
in fact there's probably more than two
uh but like that one resulted in a
hardware and a hard fork split
um and so sort of an interesting you
know aspect of this consensus you know
that kind of systems that you know
you're gonna have have
these kinds of practical problems that
actually can relate either
into software or in hard work so people
just don't want to collaborate on a
particular form
any questions about this
um what happens in hard forks
like you have two good two different
blockchains
and clients have to choose from which
for they want to be
interesting um or publish their
transactions in both
i don't know i mean but you have like
i mean say i have like a couple bitcoin
i'll have a couple like bitcoin in both
forks right
but i can start spending them in either
like well you have you have bitcoins in
the prefix
of those yeah right so and both both
forks have to prefix
so you can you can't double spend your
money
huh well so actually in in the case of
like when
bitcoin for there was a hard fork and
they in the one of the new
forks was called bitcoin cash all the
tokens were duplicated
but then the the value of the tokens
um it wasn't like you doubled your
values like the price of bitcoin
decreased
and then the difference in that decrease
was the value of the bitcoin cash
so is think of it like a stock split
like you get
more tokens but the actual value would
stay the same
because you're just increasing the
supply of tokens okay
great thank you
any other questions
okay good let me summarize that
um so uh basically what we're seeing
here
is you know distributed consensus
with uh in an open distributed systems
with you know
potentially a byzantine participants
oops
let's see my program crashed hold on a
second
um
so these are the consensus with visiting
potentially byzantine participants
um and you know the you know the the
thing that actually is being reached
consensus on is this public ledger
or public log if you will
that basically orders all the
transactions ever since the beginning of
time
and allow people to
check you know what the balances are of
every
public key and avoid
double spending and you know the
particular cool sort of idea here is to
you know
basically just prove a work uh idea to
uh determine actually who uh
is allowed to extend the blockchain
okay so that's basically uh all i wanted
to say
uh and so if you need to run
and leave uh feel free to leave this is
basically the end of this lecture
and anybody who wants to stay and ask
more questions please feel free to stay
on thursday there's no lecture it's a
hacking day
as you know the friday is the deadline
for
the final project or lap for whatever
you'll be doing so good luck you know
trying to
get that work finished uh and uh we'll
talk in the next class meetings next
tuesday
okay thank you
oh could you talk a little bit more
about the proof of stake
um there's a sure i'm not sure i have a
ton to say about it
um
you know if you want to know any more
details you know just google
proof-of-stake
you'll find all the different bitcoin
currencies that use it and
uh and i'll tell you in more detail
but basically you know the power
in the network is proportional to your
stake in the network
and the basic idea is that like if you
uh own like whatever three percent or
ten percent of all the bitcoins you know
you get sort of to decide ten percent of
the
uh the new blocks um and you're gonna
have incentive you know the higher your
stake you know the higher incentives
actually is to
uh play the game correctly
so becomes more deterministic in that
case right
uh it all depends on the details of the
protocol
uh like in el grant you know basically
there's a periodic leader
and there's a committee election and
then the committee decides on like you
know what the next you know block is and
then you know there's a new leader in
the new
committee election et cetera
and many aspects of that are uh you know
probabilistic
and randomized so that the attacker can
like win the game
these particles are quite sophisticated
um also to be able to mine you have to
have of the log to verify
the transactions right yes
yeah so the miners have a complete copy
of the uh which is gigabytes
isn't that a lot well i think it turned
out to be
totally doable for a reasonable computer
okay
thank you
this is unrelated to the lecture but do
you think it'd be possible to
to talk about during the class sometime
like the design that
tas and that you had for labs three and
four
like because it was more open-ended so
certainly yeah certainly that floor is
more open-ended
um i was not planning to
uh i don't know we have time left to do
so
uh first of all not everybody has done
lap four
and so i currently have no intention to
do so but
of course you can reach out to office
hours and talk to the tas
or reach out later to me and we can talk
about a lot three and left four
sounds good thank you
um so i i had a question about um
like it says it says on the paper like
uh
or rather sorry um
yeah once once the latest transaction
the coin is buried under enough block uh
to spend transaction before it can be
discarded to save disk space
yeah yeah um like
i i i understood though that you know
blockchain um never really like
like uh discards transactions
it keeps like a whole log of all the
transactions
um why is this like why was this done in
practice
ah because to save space on the
say stays on the allow
space compaction on the you know on the
nodes and the miners
and so they don't have to keep track of
every transaction
in the log you know for every basically
bitcoin they have to just keep track of
the last one
um and efficient and so
one way to think about it is sort of
like you know you could compute the
snapshot in time
of all the values of all the uh
points and then you don't really have to
remember the whole past
who does keep the whole past then
uh there's two things so the one is like
you know
when you check whether a transaction is
valid you know go you scan the whole log
people don't do that you know they take
forever they basically build a data
structure that is
quite compact and has the last
transaction for
uh every uh unspent
uh coin um the
you know you can totally download the
whole log you know from
you want to from the internet uh and it
is maintained and
no notes store it you know to basically
they
lose all their data they can compute all
the balances you know basically from
running all the trajectory from the
beginning of time
um but so so like if people are
are like who maintains a whole block
like the whole
transactions i just replicated
everywhere right like everybody
wants to can have a copy of the log
right
but but if most people are doing this
and discarding like transactions
like why would someone keep like the the
whole like
well this is not good enough to actually
keep track of
this allows you to decide where a
transaction was actually
uh happened in the past but it doesn't
allow you to validate transactions so
you want to validate instruction you
have to keep the pass
okay okay
thanks welcome
any more questions