okay
good afternoon or good morning or good
evening wherever you are
uh i want to talk today about the
perma-backup replication
and really sort of an introduction to
primary backup application
uh we'll come back to this in multiple
lectures during the semester
but this is a the the fmt default the
virtual memory or for
vmware fault tolerant paper is sort of a
really nice introduction
that brings out a lot of issues that are
going to come up
throughout the semester so the plan for
lecture today is as follows
i'm first going to talk about failures
that you might hope
to tolerate using primary backup
replication and some that you might not
be able to
then i want to talk a little bit about
the main challenges in sort of any
backup scheme uh sort of rotating
speaking
then talk about two you know dominant
approaches
uh to replication uh
one is you know what's typically called
state transfer
replication
and the second is typically called
replicated state machines
and today's paper is an example of a
replicated state machine
approach and in fact you know lab two of
the lab three and lot four
you know also we'll be using replicated
state machine approach and in fact you
know the
gfs paper uh or replicating chunks and
was using a replicated state machine
approach
uh so it's a quite a common approach and
then you know i want to
make everything a little bit concrete by
looking at this case the case study
of the vm vmware fall tolerance
scheme or implementation or system
so any questions before i get started
just to
put up i have tried to answer all your
questions that you sent by email
uh uh the ones you know they're coming
before midnight that generally all
answer that wants to come in after
midnight you know i try to answer
as many as i can uh but if i didn't
answer your question then
you and the topic comes up in lecture or
at any point by that time you'll feel
free to
interrupt and ask it okay any questions
before we dive in
okay um so let's talk about failures
in a very broad sense you get a sense of
like what we might hope for
that a replication scheme can handle
so first of all typically the papers
that were in the system there were going
to be a
building will only deal with what
sometimes called or typically called
fail stop
failures
and the basic idea is that there if
there's a failure or a component of the
computer doesn't really work well
that actually stops the computer
so the assumption is that basically the
computer goes from working
to not working sort of instantaneously
it doesn't produce like weird results
because the computer's not working
uh correctly so it just follows the
protocols uh
you know when it you know does to add it
adds it to register values you know that
producers are correct you know add value
uh
and so we're just assuming that when the
computer works you know it works
correctly
and when there's a failure it just stops
um and this covers it in many scenarios
you know for example like whenever you
fan of the computer
uh fails you know the computer overheats
and then the computer shuts down itself
um
the other cases are where like you know
somebody steps over the power cord
and boom you know the whole computer
disappears or you know
you know cuts the network link and you
know that point you know the
computer might keep you running uh but
uh it is completely disconnected
sometimes you know systems or software
on the computer itself
does it best you know to turn these
partial failures into uh stop till stop
failures
so example you might you know the
software might compute checksums on data
and then
if it sees that the checksum is
incorrect you know just stop you know
the computer
um uh and so that's a quite common
uh and to do so the basic model of the
world is
computer work correctly then the
computer starts
so what does this exclude you know
there's a whole bunch of sort of
failures that it excludes for example
uh it doesn't really deal well with
logic bugs
like if you have an error in your
software you know whatever you divide by
zero
and then uh incorrectly or in the where
you shouldn't have
then though it is very likely that the
backup will do exactly the same thing
because when the software is broken and
so it's broken on the primary it's
broken on the backup
and so nothing you know basically
replication really not
does not solve that problem for you
similar
you know if you have configuration
errors
memory backup is not going to assault
you no problem for you if you know the
uh the files that you know specify the
replicas that are just incorrect
then the system will not work correctly
uh similarly we're not really in this
class
we'll talk a little bit at the end of
the semester but we're not
dealing with malicious errors
so we're not dealing with attackers that
you know try to fake the protocol
uh you know have run servers that send
incorrect messages
and try to sort of spoof the whole
system uh which is not in consideration
so in uh
for most of the semester presume that
the software works correctly
does not have logic bugs there are no
configuration errors
and the thing that we're focusing on is
actually handling stop failures
there's some failures that sort of fall
you know that could be handled
or maybe handled with uh primary backup
replication
or not and as an example you might think
about like
an earthquake
you know if the primary and back are
physically you know separated
uh in completely different parts you
know on different continents or maybe
parts of the same continent i know you
might hope that
you might have some hope that the uh the
backer could take over if the failure
if the primary fails due to an
earthquake but
um you know some other primary
replication schemes you know this is not
going to be the case you know where for
example at the primary and the backup on
the same data center and the whole data
center uh disappears
then you know sort of end of story okay
so hopefully that gives you a little bit
of context of sort of the type of
failures that
we're trying to shoot for now even with
this sort of
just focusing on stop uh till stop
failure
it turns out to be difficult to build
you know fault along systems
and we're going to talk a little bit
about the general issues that will show
up
you know if we're going to build
a primary backup system
and you know we'll see concrete exam
instances of these problems in the
vm ft paper so you know one challenge is
you know if a failure happens you know
has the primary actually failed
uh an issue here you know that makes
this challenging is that in intercepted
systems you can't tell the difference
between a network petition and a machine
failed so it might be perfectly possible
that the
network uh that the primary is still up
but you know that some computers cannot
talk to the primary because
the network has petitioned and so for
example the backup may decide that you
know the primary is dead because
network's petitioned but in fact the
primary is not that
and maybe some of the clients are still
able to talk to the primary and so you
have to have some story
of making sure that you don't end up in
a situation
where you have two primaries and again
you know
we talked a little bit about last time
it shows up in this paper again we'll
show up
next week too which is like you know we
want to avoid that we get into situation
where there's sort of a split brain
system
where we basically have two primaries
and like one subset of the klein
to one primary and the other subset of
the client talks to the other parent
and clearly that's going to diverge you
know the state of the system
and when the the network heals
we are in an incorrect state so we have
to avoid this
at all costs the second uh
general challenge is you know how do we
keep
the you know how do we keep the primary
and the backup in sync
and our goal is going to be that uh if
the primary fails then we can just
gracefully fail over to the backup and
the backup just
picks up right where the primary left
off and that requires that the backup
actually is up to date
we have like the latest things that the
primary action has written
uh to its state so that action can pick
up
seamlessly and the return errors or uh
responses to the client that are
completely unexpected
you know from the client's perspective
it really should look like you know the
whole thing even though it's replicated
it's like a single computer it just
happens to be a little bit more
fault-tolerant than a single computer
and that turns out to be uh difficult
you know first of all we
have to make sure that we apply all
changes we have to apply the changes in
the right order
and you know in continuous uh issue and
that is that
we have to sort of avoid non-determinism
or
we have to deal with non-determinism
i mean if the same change on the primary
behavior is different than on the backup
because you know for some reason
that would be not good you know we got
to make sure that we make a change in
the primary backup very identical
effects
uh to the primary and the backup
uh a similar you know sort of issue that
overwhelming shows up
you know as a challenge is failover
you have actually the primary fails and
we need to fail over to
the backup and we've cursed all they've
got to make sure that the
their other primary is definitely dead
but for example the primary might have
was in the middle of an operation
and uh it was about to send a packet out
to the response to the client
or maybe not and so we got to figure out
whether that response if you send or not
being sent
or is it okay for us to send it again
um there's a question here in the chat
like when
would failover need to be happen no
fails need to happen when the primary's
gone
right because then we want to fail over
to the backup that's sort of the
terminology
used and then often
another issue we fail over is like who
actually has you know we have multiple
backups which is not the case in today's
paper
uh you know we actually have the latest
stage like for example maybe they all
crash
after a few operations they come back up
and
uh and and uh and we are going to make
sure that we're actually talking to the
one that acts in the most recent states
you know this is going to be not an
issue today tomorrow so much
as we'll see in a second why but it will
come up later in other replication
protocols
yeah so basically failover means you
know the backup takes over
um okay so that's sort of the main you
know fail
the type of failures that we hope to
handle the main challenges
uh and we'll deepen those challenges out
as we go
um and you know i want to talk about
sort of two the two main approaches that
we'll see in the semester
uh for dealing with primary backup
replication
one is as i mentioned earlier that is
state transfer
now there's been a reasonable at a high
level very straightforward you know we
got a primary
uh you know it's you know the clients
talk to the primary
the primary you know updated state once
update to state in response to
client request and once a while it sort
of makes a checkpoint
once a while basically checkpoints state
it stayed to the backup
and of course if you want to the backup
in the primary to be in sync you know
that means that every time the primary
actually performs an operation
i before it responds to the client it
basically has to transfer whatever state
changes that were made by that operation
to the backup
so that's one scheme one of
high level approach the second approach
is what uh
it's called replicated state machine
state machine replication
often shortened to rsm
and here you know the uh you know the
picture
is you know we got the primary we got
the clients they're talking to the
primary
and of course you know we have the
primary talking to the backup to keep
the backup in sync
but instead it was sending the state
changes or the modifications to the
state from the prime to the backup what
we do actually we sent the operations
to the background so before the primary
response to the client you know
executing its operation
you know we sent the operation that the
client sent to us you know to the backup
so the backup can execute the operation
to uh updates its state you know
acknowledge it to the primary primary
actually updates it's state two
you know executes the operation and then
sends the response back to the pre
to the client and
sort of in all these sort of in in all
these
in both approaches you know the sort of
the scheme is like the primaries of some
particular state
uh we apply changes to the state um
and we do exactly the same thing at the
back so the backup
starts out in the same state as the
primary we apply the same changes to the
state whether it's through an operation
or state transfer
we end up in a new state and that state
has to be identical to the state that
the primary
has so if then ever there's a failure
uh you know we know that when we fail
over to the backup and it's exactly in
the same state as the primary and so
it can take over um
and we'll see you know this is actually
challenging to actually make happen but
that's what the basic point
um the primary
goal approach is actually reasonably
popular the primary disadvantage
of the state transfer approach is that
like if an operation generates a lot of
state
uh then it's going to be expensive right
like if a single operation writes a
gigabyte of data then that gigabyte of
data needs to be transferred to a
primary or due to backup and it might be
much more expensive and much more
less expensive to basically just send
over the operation to the backup to the
backup connection to the operation so
many of the systems that were
talking about actually therefore follow
the second approach you know where
they send the operation but not the
state transfer
and uh in fact you know if you think
about
uh gfs uh the discussion from last week
when we saw that basically the primary
since the
append operations or the right
operations to the backups
it doesn't do the append and then send
the result you know to the backups that
actually sends the operations so that's
an example
of a replicated state machine approach
where we'll be sending operations
and the paper of today also follows this
replicated state machine approach where
the operations are not
you know append and right uh file system
append to file system right
but the operations are actually x86
instructions you know um
that's what we'll see later but they uh
both you know send operations
in labs as i mentioned earlier labs
three and four
uh are also replicated state machine uh
approaches where you know we're gonna be
sending operations from the primary to
the backup
as a
because there's a question to chad why
does the client do not send
not need to send the data to the backup
in our replicated state machine because
the the idea is that these operations
are deterministic
and so the primary and this you know
remember the we'll talk about this in
much more detail but the primary and
backup are in the same state same state
as
the uh if the operation is deterministic
and you apply it to the same state you
know they will end up in the same state
as prime
and so there's no reason for the
application the client to send the data
in this case because by just sending
this deterministic operation
it is guaranteed that that operation
will generate the same data
so subsequent question is how do you
know for all programs and their
operations whether they are just
stimulus
or non-deterministic to know what
information need to be sent
so the typical approach is to in
replicated state machine approach is to
make all operations deterministic
non-deterministic operations are not
allowed and we'll see in a second how
you do that
okay so before you know going to a
little bit more specific
uh under hybrid approaches
uh yes you know there are hardbacker
approaches you know for example you can
run sort of by default in a replicated
state machine approach
uh uh in effect in some ways the paper
uh does this then if uh uh
if the backup fails or primary fails and
you go back to a single machine
then you need to create a new replica
and often for the new replica the way
you do it is actually by
transferring the state from the existing
replica or a copy of the state of the
existing replica to a new replica
but that's like hopefully a less
frequent operation
and then actually you know doing the uh
uh
then replicating the operations that
they're doing much more frequently
um also three uh feel free to ask the
questions you know in real time as
opposed to chatting uh typing them in
the chat either way he's fine
but um okay so
as i hinted you know with this
replication state machine approach you
know there's a question about
what level
of replication are due what level of
operations
to replicate
um so in one
uh one possibility sort of application
level operations
so what i mean is you know think i think
back at the
gfs like whether it's append file append
or right
another and the the okay and
if you play the game sort of replicate
state machine game at the level of the
sort of application level operations
that means that the application has to
be involved
you know because it knows what the
semantics of these operations are
and then it knows what an independent
actually supposed to do
uh or what a ride is supposed to do and
so uh if you're
playing a replicated state machine
approach at the that kind of
application level then the application
itself needs to be modified
you know to actually uh perform or play
part of the replicated state machine
approach
one thing that's cool about the paper
today that we're looking at too
and we're looking at today is
it you know does the operations at the
machine level
or the processor level or the computer
level uh
and so the state uh is registers
you know the x86 registers the memory
state
and the operations are just ordinary
computer instructions
and by replicating at that level
then you can basically um
make your replication completely
transparent because you can take one
computer
run the application or an operating
system on top of it that just runs
x86 instructions and this replicated
state machine approach
uh automatically uh creates a backup
of that of that particular execution so
the application doesn't have to be
modified at all in fact in this paper
the uh operating system is not modified
the application is not modified you can
take an ordinary application not even
written with fault tolerance in mind and
using this sort of
uh machine level uh or instruction level
replication
it can be transparently replicated so
one of the things that is very cool
about you know the paper of today
is it's just completely transparent
now um that makes you wonder like you
know
you know how to do that because like
what happens if like you have a machine
and an interrupt happens you know that
interrupt needs to
be propagated in some way directly to
the backup because like if you think
about the x86 machine
you know of course the regular
instructions that the applications
execute like add
you know whatever divide you know
conditional branch branching
uh procedure calls but there are also
other events like you know interrupts
and they need to be you know handled
with and so how do you do that
and so um the traditional uh
way of doing sort of machine level
replication
uh used to be sort of quite expensive in
the sense that
uh the you could buy computers or where
the processors like maybe replicate it
twice or three times
and the hardware itself would organize
you know that these processors
ran exactly in lockstep um
and you know that there's a lot of
hardware machinery to actually make this
happen and
this paper has a cool observation that
uh
you don't really need to do really
hardware replication
instead you can actually use virtual
machines
and that's the way they do it now pure
hardware replication happens too
uh you know for example in uh
in aeronautics or
uh you know whatever mars rover uh you
know often
the hardware modules are just like you
know double
duplex replicated or triple replicated
and have a hardware voting scheme
you know to keep the processors in sync
and to detect failures
but a sort of a level of you know
tolerance that you know that's not what
the
this this uh the level of autonomous
that the
this vmft paper is not actually shooting
for it's really thinking about like you
know you got a
business application uh running on on
the computer and now you want to make
that business application more fall
tolerant
and the approach to take is to you know
exploit fertilization
so the piston to vmft
and exploit virtualization that's the
main
big idea that they uh bring along to
this problem and you know by doing so
they can make this
replication transparent to the
application
of course you don't have to design as an
application design and then a
replication scheme like you know for
example the way it's done in uh
in gfs uh it appears you know
using the scheme there's replication
scheme that the vmct
uses it appears basically that the
severe client but the service is a
single machine
meaning just you know we'll see in a
second how but you know basically
they're going to provide very strong
consistency you know the the the
client on the outside can't even tell um
and uh it actually you know the paper
sort of cool paper because it actually
is it's a real product
and it's still in use you can uh
you know get this uh this is the support
uh if you want to uh the current product
i think is quite different from the one
that we actually read about in the paper
uh but you know at the very high level
you know the
the issues are very similar in fact you
know the
one of the big uh shortcomings as many
of you noted in the questions
uh of the the the one that's scrapped in
the paper it's
like it's a single core solution so
there's no multi-core support and so
multiple application
multiple threads on one computer cannot
run in parallel
and we'll talk about in a second why the
solution doesn't really support that
uh in i think later later versions of
ft this actually works and uh
i think you know there's no pay real
detailed paper that describes it
but i actually think that instead of
using actual replicated state machine
approach to actually using a state
transfer approach
but i really don't know any really the
details
i'm going to focus on the replicated
state machine approach because one
reason i like this paper is because it
sort of illustrates replicated state
machining approach in a very clean
manner
and all the you know a lot of the
subsequent uh
replication schemes that we're going to
be looking at are replicated state
machine approaches
okay so
so let us sketch out the overview
of this system and so the first thing
uh you sort of need to realize is that
there is a virtual there's a virtual
machine monitor
involved so what is a virtual machine
monitor well virtual machine monitor
basically takes a piece of hardware
and uh it makes it appear you know
basically
makes end pieces of hardware out of it
uh
so if we like have a you know an x86 box
you know we can take a virtual machine
monitor and run it on top of it
and you know on top of it we can have
virtual machines and a virtual machine
uh we're gonna have multiple virtual
machines although in most of this paper
we're gonna be talking about running one
virtual machine on top of the virtual
machine monitor
um and so for example we might actually
have a linux you know operating system
running
on top of the virtual machine you know
with its you know applications
and you know here's actually the actual
hardware
and why you know so and so the vm
uh the terminology used here is
sometimes called the hypervisor it's
called the virtual machine monitor
um and so in our case you know really
with the the hypervisor here
this is actually you know vmft
so it's a hypervisor modified you know
to include you know the ideas that
vmft has
and why is this cool well the reason
this is cool because or useful
uh for replicated state machines is
because even hardware you know interrupt
actually happens
that hardware interrupt doesn't really
go straight you know to linux in fact
the hardware interrupt goes first
through the vm monitor
the vm monitor actually this site's
going to win to deliver you know that
interrupt you know to linux
and so any external events you know
before they actually sort of observed
you know by the virtual machine
are actually captured by or can be
captured by the
hypervisor and so this gets us about
this mess
you know of like what i mentioned a
little bit earlier where you know
what happens if there's an external
interrupt you know how can we sort of
replicate that
and the way we're going to replicate it
here is because the virtual machine
monitor just gets control over it
and we'll see you know this is going to
be an extremely powerful tool uh
to actually uh make instruction
deterministic you know handle external
operations et cetera et cetera
so the basic plan is like if uh an
interrupt comes in
you know whether there's an interrupt
from the network or from
uh uh from the hardware itself like a
timer interrupt
you know basically the timer interrupt
is delivered you know to the
virtual machine monitor uh the virtual
machine monitor
then in the case of fmnt it does two
things you know
not only delivers it at some point to
the application it also sends
over a logging channel to a backup
computer
and that computer is restructured in the
same way you know it has hardware
uh it has uh the virtual machine monitor
sitting on top of it so here's another
copy of
fmft and you know on top of this virtual
machine
you know where identical software
running on it like linux
same version of linux you know with you
know whatever some set of applications
all right okay and so like you know
these
machines both on you know some networks
so here's the logging channel
and maybe years of clients you know
talking basically to
the hardware uh do the sensor packet
over the network
uh the actual hardware you know receives
that packet
uh and then uh they will uh and
deliver it you know and the virtual
machine monitor just gets control and
delivers it and the hardware delivers it
to the virtual machine monitor or the
virtual machine monitor if you will
picks it
up and so um
if you think about it you know this this
packet you know results
in an in an interrupt that's delivered
to the virtual machine monitor
the virtual machine monitor will send
that interrupt
as we'll see in a second you know
forward it to the backup
uh deliver it it delivers it also to the
local virtual machine the local virtual
machine you know was just linux running
she saw i got an interrupt and so it
does it's normal processing it always
we're doing an interrupt and so at some
point you know maybe it will
generate a response and also for example
write
you know to the network card or at least
it will think it's writing to the
network interface card but really what
it is
is a virtual network interface card that
is like
emulated you know by the virtual machine
monitor so when it writes actually you
know
a bunch of instructions uh to this you
virtual cart really what it is it's
actually writing to the virtual machine
monitor and so the future museum is like
ah you know here's
uh an operating system trying to
actually send the packet
and then you know the virtual machine
monitor you know can actually send the
packet on behalf of the operating system
by
programming the real hardware and then
the real hardware you know sends off
you know response to the client right
now just the sort of normal execution
for what here's the
the primary and here's our backup
and basically the backup the same thing
happens you know if you know the machine
started exactly in the same
state you know they take the interrupt
you know at the same time and the
virtual machine monitor can control
when to deliver the interrupt so you can
arrange you know to make sure that the
interrupt is actually delivered exactly
at the same time and exactly the same
instruction
that the primary got it so we'll deliver
the interrupt you know to the
you know we'll receive the interrupt
from the primary maybe buffer for a
little while until the
back of us was seen second hits near
sort of the same instruction that the
primary dot
then delivers the interrupt you know to
linux linux just as usual way it will be
you know since it's exactly in the same
state as in the primary it will do
exactly the same thing as the primary
dos
so at some point you know it will you
know program the
virtual network card to actually send a
response packet
you know all that stuff will happen and
at some point says like you know sent
that packet
you know the virtual machine uh monitor
will get control
it knows it's a backup and so it doesn't
doesn't do anything it actually doesn't
send the packet on the network
because it's the background okay that's
the
basic plan then there's uh
one more component in this story that is
important to realize which is that there
is on the
side on the side on the same network
there is a storage server
you can think about this as the the hard
disk you know for these
uh for these two virtual machines or for
the
and so when an application you know here
writes to a file really what it turns
into
is you know the kernel will you know
that file system is maybe mounted
uh on there on the the local linux
operating system the linux operating
system sees ah this is like a remote
disk
and we'll format the packet and then
we'll send that packet you know to
you know let me throttle maybe in a
slightly different we'll send a packet
you know to the virtual machine monitor
the same place in a virtual machine
monitor like send it off the virtual
machine monitor you know we'll go off
and send it over the network you know to
the storage server the storage server
will respond at some point and in some
ways this communication looks identical
as if there's like
a client sitting on the other side of
the network you know the only difference
is being that in the
uh storage server case the linux sort of
inner
starts the communication while in the
other case the client starts the
communication
green errors represent communication to
the storage server so a network packet's
being sent from
through linux through the virtual
machine monitor to the storage server
and so when uh so i'm right by an
application through a file basically
results in these messages
and then you know it will whatever
update any state you know
persistent state that you know on the on
the storage server
now as we saw in the paper uh the
storage server place
an additional role on top of uh
on top of a basically being stored
server namely there's sort of a special
flag
that sits on the site where there's a
block in the storage server
that's being used to arbitrate who
becomes the primary after a failure
so so and this all comes down to
this is the part of the failover plan so
let's say
you know the uh logins general breaks or
and
in the way you know this manifests you
know through the virtual machine monitor
is that it
sends periodically packets you know over
this logging channel
and it doesn't get any responses uh uh
from the other side then it assumes that
the
other side there's a problem and of
course it can't decide
whether you know just the network is not
working or
whether actually the virtual machine
monitor you know the computers really
crashed
and if it's really crashed of course it
should you know take over
and if it's really not crashed then you
know we have to arbitrate in some way
we'll make sure that only one of them
actually proceeds so let's say the
network partitions
and so this is the harder case when the
network petitions uh instead of like
one of them two crashes so yeah network
partitions
uh but you know notice that the two can
still communicate both the
frame and the backup can communicate to
the storage server
and so in this particular case you know
what will happen is they will notice you
know both sites will notice
the primary and backup will notice oh
there's some problem because i can't
talk to their
primary anymore or use it and so they at
some point decide well the other guy
must probably
could be dead and i want to promote
myself to primary so the backup says
like i want to promote myself the
primary
or the primary says like well i just
want to really continue uh
serving client requests and i just want
to ignore the backup for now
so basically this says this is what they
call they want to go live
basically go back into single mode and
we want to do
and with one primer and so the way that
this happens is that
you know both of them you know send try
to read
they call this a testis set operation
and i'll talk a little bit about it in
more detail but basically both reach out
to the storage server
and try to write the flag saying you
know instead of do one
and if the flight was already set to one
set to one
then it ended like that the other guy
won earlier
okay so it goes from zero to one uh they
both try to do this atomically
one of them is going to go first you
know that will succeed you know sitting
to one and look at return the old valley
zero so it knows that you know nobody
else succeeded actually in writing the
flag to one yet
and therefore you know i should become
the primaries to keep it running
and the second guy you know what's the
primary the backup you know that
uh comes in second you know we'll see
you will try to set the flag to one it's
already set to one the return value
would be one because that was the old
value
by the time it you know did this test
operation and therefore it will decide
well i'm just going to give up
uh because you know there's already
somebody else who took over from me
and basically you know as the paper
calls up you know it terminates itself
okay
so that's sort of the high level uh
operation
uh uh uh the high level operation for
failure there's a
question in the uh chat which is a good
question and when does the flag reset to
zero
well there's sort of basically a whole
separate story that i haven't talked
about yet
and you know so you'll get through uh is
that in once you know the primary runs
on
like one we have one server running now
i would like to make a second backup you
know
and so get in the position that we
basically have to back up again you know
we have to do what's called repair
because if we don't do repair then you
know the we start every two computers
one fails then we have one computer and
a little bit later that one computer may
fail then we have no computers anymore
and so it has to be the case there has
to be some repair plan
and in you know dmvt this repair plan is
executed manually you know so somebody
you know monitors where the the monitor
software uh sort of notice this and
basically creates then a new replica
or based on the vm image of the the
first one
uh ensures that it's in sync and then
you know
it uh resets that flag and you know and
it's the logging starts again and then
you know the flag is reset so
once that second primary is completely
back up
and following the protocol then the flag
can be reset
okay
okay uh
okay good that's a great question like
you know why maybe the logging channel
broke but maybe
the the the the
the channel to the server broke too and
uh
and so you know we're not going to get
the response and that
basically that point the system just
stops if you will until something
repairs
uh because nothing can be done so at
that point from then on no clients
requests are actually processed
uh because we just don't know what state
we are
and maybe at some point network link
will get uh
repaired and then point you know things
get started moving forward again
so that's sort of the disaster case
right where the you know disaster cases
actually the primary backup are
both actually up and running by all the
network tables of broken and which is
sort of similar basically to the case
where both the primary and backup failed
at the same time
okay question yeah could you explain
again real quick
when the client is reading from the
storage server
the client never reaches really from the
store server that's the
uh linux that might or the application
running on top of linux might be running
from the storage server
and that's the one case in the second
case the mft might be running from the
storage server to read that slack or
test and set that flag so that like
green arrow at the bottom from the
storage server to
see is uh
oh ah sorry not green that's a bad green
arrow that should have gone like all the
way
oh okay thank you it's just going over
the network and not intended to go to
see it was intended to go over the
network
thanks for clarifying that i hadn't
realized that
okay so um
so what i'd like so i want to maybe take
a
quick uh break at this point or do a
breakout room
uh in particular i would like you to do
is talk a little bit about the homework
question
uh which we sort of you know covered uh
at this instance
uh but i want you to think about
understand or argue with each other and
you know convince yourself that the
scheme actually
provides uh avoids this sort of um
range you know split brain syndrome in
the sense that there's never
going to be two primaries and the second
thing you know maybe to debate
is is this a reasonable design because
it looks like you know what we've done
is like we pushed all the sort of real
hard part of default towels into the
storage server and it's not really the
case or is that not the case
uh so that seems like a two things that
i would like you to discuss
uh in these breakout rooms so i'm gonna
stop the sharing
and i'm going to
participants and i'm going to make lily
post
so that you can set up the breakout
rooms
and enjoy you know talking to each other
lately you got this under control
testing to see if i can uh join a
different room this time not looking
good though
uh
well yes i'm stuck here
good
the screen again
okay everybody from the screen
yes okay good um
so i hope you had a good discussion and
hopefully met some more
uh new students in the class uh than uh
than you knew before
and uh let's sort of proceed uh talking
a little bit about
uh the the design of uh
uh off at the mpt and just like
summarize quickly you know this could
you repeat like
when the flag is reset to zero i feel
like some of us might have missed the
explanation
okay uh okay so okay good good good good
okay so
okay so here let's draw the picture
again uh in a sort of simpler way
here's our primary with the vm
everything in it here's the backup
with the everything in it you know and
there's the login channel in between
they're connected you know to a storage
server and
you know one thing to think about is
that the storage server is doing playing
tool roles so let's
separate the two roles one is given the
storage you know for
you know a disk basically for you know
the primary and the backup
and then look we could just split that
and just attach the disk to the primary
backup
and then we basically have the role here
is really the arbitration server
and it has a flag
and the flag is initially zero right and
so now let's say there's a
partition of primary backup can actually
not uh talk to the
to each other anymore so they're going
to talk to the arbitration server
basically to try to promote themselves
through the single
uh to go live and sort of be the single
server that serves the client request
so they both sent the packet to do a
test to set operation
one gets a zero back the other one gets
a one back the one that gets one back
knows that it was actually the second
who tried
and then uh and so the first one will
succeed
and will go live so let's say this guy
goes live and this guy just you know
disappears
this virtual machine is terminates
itself and
is done and so now the flag is set to
one
and of course now at this point there's
no arbitration in necessary anymore
because there's no secondary replica
there's no backup at all so really the
question is like you know what happens
next
and in terms of repair that has to be
the case that the second backup the new
backup is brought up to the light
correct and
this section 31 of the paper talks about
this in quite a bit of detail
and the way it works is that you know on
the user interface you know through the
system you know vmware motion
uh you're basically saying like hey i
want to clone this primary
and uh the cloning operation uh
basically will we'll basically stop
processing pioneering during cloning the
the
the primary won't actually work the one
system still running won't actually
serve any client requests
the uh the the emotion thing
makes a vm clone and basically copies
you know the state of this vm up to the
backup and so here we have an identical
uh copy of the backup of the primary
that becomes the backup
and so this state of the virtual machine
is identical
once you know the sort of this cloning
operation has happened
then again it's free you know the the
the user interface is free to set that
this guy back to zero two client
requests are still not being processed
when that has actually happened then the
system can go sort of live again
but now with two machines with a primary
and a backup
and the client requests are being
processed you know they're send over the
channel
etc etc so we're back in business does
that answer the question
i hope it does if not i'm happy to
uh revisit this actually maybe at the
end of the lecture if they're still
confusing
okay good um okay well i want to go back
now to sort of this sort of like the
overall architecture of the system i now
want to
dive in a little bit more and uh talk uh
you know we have decided i think you
know that you know this arbitration
scheme allows you to at least avoid a
split brainstorm
uh but you know the surge is still this
larger issue that if you know two
machines are running
uh you know our goal is going to be
you know basically behave like a single
machine
so from the client perspective it should
not be possible to really
discern or at least you know sort of
demonstrate a bad way
that you know we're actually having two
machines right
and so there's usually take a step back
you know we can get at a very high level
you know we have here our primary in the
house you know like machine registers
the virtual machine
uh you know some registers there's
memory
and our basic plan is to you know sort
of forward you know make sure that
basically it executes exactly the same
instructions
uh boom boom boom here's our own
here's our backup here's a primary
and you know basically you know when the
uh
uh you know when the primary so we start
the map in the same state
and they start executing instructions
you know so like maybe the first
instructor is an ink
the second instructions in deck you know
through the structure is a branch
and if they you know start all in the
same state correct then at the first
destruction just branch they will branch
in the same direction
and so maybe the brands do some
instruction and and you know whatever
the next instructions in the divide
et cetera et cetera now all these
instructions are
deterministic so that's they're pretty
straightforward right like if you know
we both start at the same style
state they execute exactly these you
know the same set of instructions in the
same order
then we're going to end up in a state s
prime
and those two states are going to be
identical
right now the thing that is sort of the
challenge
in uh this design or like any sort of
replication scheme is
there might be sources of divergence you
know so our goal is to actually get them
exactly to the same
uh state as prime but you know they're
sort of
sources of divergence
and it's pretty good obviously what
those are you know for example
instructions
that are non-deterministic our problem
and so what are what is an example of a
non-deterministic instruction
getting the time yeah getting the time
why is that non-dehumanistic
because and
the machines are not like the backup is
not executing
the issue here correct is that if you
know the primary and the backup you know
at some point they'll execute this you
know
get time of day instruction if you will
and they might not execute it exactly at
the same time so the values returned
you know by that instruction is going to
be different right so
that's an uh source of potential source
of the
divergence that we need to control in
fact we basically have to turn every
non-deterministic instruction into the
deterministic instruction now we'll see
a second here and how does
how could that be done similarly uh
inputs right or packet inputs like when
a packet arrives over the network
you know at the primary uh you know we
got to make sure the you know the
that the package is executed or
processed or
the the interrupt that goes along with
that packet is exactly delivered at
exactly the same point in the
instructions team
right so we go back our previous paper
the day page
and like you know the backup's also
executing these instructions
and deck blah blah blah blah and exactly
in the same order
so if the primary for example you know
we get the you know the interrupt is
delivered between instruction one and
two we got to make sure that at the
backup it
also is delivered between one and two
because if it's delivered exactly in the
same
uh point in the instruction stream the
interrupt handler will run and it will
you know
they both will execute the same
instructions again however if you know
example the backup
you know would process you know this
timer interrupt you know where this
impacted arrival interrupted a little
bit later
in a different side of the stream then
the state of the system might be
different
and therefore the result of that you
know computation might be different and
so we can't have that so it has to be
the case
that in interrupts whether it's packets
or timers
all get delivered exactly at the same
time and the same put in the instruction
stream
so input packets
or timer interrupts
need to basically be delivered at the
same point in the instruction stream
um and so those are the sources
of divergence uh that we need to handle
any other source of diversions that
um so i can like i think it was
mentioned in the paper that
concurrency also can produce
non-determinism but uh
from my understanding here since the
hypervisor actually controls the
interrupts
and since we have a uni processor
wouldn't the thread
switch be conducted through the
hypervisor by by
interrupts so if we control the
interrupts and we can transmit them
exactly
at the right location wouldn't we also
uh control the non-determinism from
concurrency
yeah so i think there's a great
observation so let me it's a
potential divorce okay so first of all
let's first agree that it's a potential
source of the uh
uh divergence so multi-core
and let's say you know basically the way
the solution
in this particular paper to avoid this
problem is to say like well
just disallow
we're not allowed to have that and so
just only unit processors
but let's say we had multi-core and you
know what
just to make sure that we understand
what the issue is the issue here is
correct we have
two threads running on the same
processor
with them different cores and they erase
for example to
grab a walk and one of them is going to
win
and so that that's the threat that's
going to run next and the other one is
going to be stopped for a little while
if we want to do this replicated state
machine approach at the back up the same
thing would have to have
happened right where if the two threads
run you know
race for that lock at the same time then
we got to be arranged that the
whatever winner on the primary is also
the winner on the backup
and so that requires a whole bunch of
machinery uh
that you know additional machinery or
complexities that the you know the paper
clearly didn't want to address or didn't
know how to address and basically
said like okay we're just gonna exclude
that uh possibility of divergence by
just declaring
that the process is a unique processing
and so then thread switching and all
that kind of stuff doesn't matter
anymore there's always one you know
computation running on the computer on
the processor
and it will switch you know if the
primary switches to a different thread
the backup will switch also to the same
different thread because it's like a
single instruction screen
and they get their external inputs
exactly at the same time
that make sense so in some ways and it's
a little bit lame you know they're just
give up on multi-core
and as i mentioned later systems uh
the more recent systems of this uh
product do handle multi-core
and you know and i don't have time to i
don't actually
understand exactly how they do it
there's a potential difference uh
potentially different schemes that you
could think of doing uh
people have done uh multi-core replay
which is really what's
the thing that is necessary so uh but i
don't really know exactly so i'm not
going to talk about that at all
i'm just going to talk about that
focusing on the first three items
and see how they handle it in this case
okay any questions
oh sorry just to make sure it only
transmits the
um instructions that the that the
application makes
right it doesn't transmit the
instructions that linux
makes uh yeah exactly so here's an
interesting
uh thing but we'll see in a second uh
but let me make that more clear
uh right away the
in fact these instructors ink and deck
and branch are not sent to the primary
backer at all they basically have their
own copy correct and we're just starting
them at the same
point in the program and so therefore
they run exactly in a sort of lock step
almost
they're no longer running lockstep but
they execute them in the same order
only something special has to happen in
at these points of diverge
possible divergence and you know the
assumption that sort of paper makes is
that you know most instructors are
deterministic so we don't really have to
do anything
it's only at the instructions where
things are going to potentially go wrong
we have to do something and so
one of those sources where something
could go wrong is interrupts
so let's talk a little bit about
interruption
and so here like basically the the
virtual machine
sort of comes to rescue and really helps
you know us solve this problem so let's
say
here we have our hypervisor
an interrupt happens then the interrupt
will show up at the hypervisor
and the hypervisor knows exactly at what
instruction
the application was or where the vm was
at this level
so your linux is running inside of this
vm uh the interrupt happens
uh of course via the the the
photo the hyperfix already has taken
over control and it knows
where it stopped you know linux to
actually take the interrupt so maybe you
know whatever it took at it
you know it has executed 100
instructions so far
and then you know this interrupt comes
in and the hypervisor now wants to
deliver that uh interrupt basically
after instruction hundred
and before doing that actually it just
sends over the logging channel
the message you know to the backup okay
so
here's the backup ft and in that message
it basically says like okay
add instruction hundred you know when
you get to instruction hundred
you know deliver this interrupt and you
know maybe some data associated with the
interrupt
right so this does two things and the
inner comes in sees what the instruction
number was and then it sends to the
backup this message saying like hey
you know at some point you know when you
get to instruct
and you know some point later you know
there's interrupt one and interrupt two
comes in
uh and so you know the hypervisor does
exactly the same thing
you know again you know we'll send out
say this is instruction 200 you know we
send the message 200 interrupt you know
perhaps any data associative the
interrupt you know to the ft
so when you know the backup
gets the first message it just buffers
the message
because it doesn't know how long it can
run after that message
until it knows what the next point is
that it has to deliver something
so at the point that the second message
comes in you know for the second
interrupt
it knows you know it's perfectly fine to
start the computer
at instruction hunter deliver the
interrupt and basically keep running
until instruction 200
and the way it does it is that basically
most processors have this but the x86
has this too
where you can basically program the x86
and to say like well
you should stop after executing 100
instructions and so
the processor will stop executing it
after 100 instructions and just give
back
control to the operating system in this
case the virtual machine monitor
and so you know so this is the scheme
this is the scheme that the
uh the mft uses to basically you know
deliver interrupts
both at the primary and the backup
exactly at the same instruction
so that they sort of stay in this and
exactly execute the instructions in
exactly the same order
to arrange this of course you know the
backup needs to lag lex behind one
that's behind one message
okay
um so just to be clear so the
deterministic operations don't
don't get communicated through the
logging channel it's only the operations
that
perhaps might diverge exactly if you got
it
that's exactly what it does so let's
look at one more you know just to get
the
flavor and then we'll talk about it yeah
go ahead
sorry so deterministic operations you
said
don't get communicated through the
logging channel no
there's no need for them because both of
them of course have
a copy of all the instructions of like
the binary that like whatever linux runs
correct
uh but you know the instructions are not
communicated over the logging channel
it's only the non-deterministic watch
so like in this interrupt and we'll see
in a second you know let's talk about
the second one
non-deterministic instructions
like you know get the timer time of day
so the way that works is
uh so years we got our linux running in
the vm
you know we got our ft running and
basically when you know this linux uh
you know
usually the image you know the program
image that linux runs
and maybe you know here's our
non-deterministic instruction
and basically what ft has done uh before
it started linux
is sort of gone through like the linux
binary and
found all the instructions that are
non-deterministic like you know get time
of day
and basically ensure you know turn them
in sort of an invalid instruction
and so when linux execute executes that
non-deterministic instruction
it actually controls transfers control
to the hypervisor
this is the trap and now the hypervisor
knows okay well this was you know
whatever instruction 341
i know that is a non-deterministic
instruction because i wrote you know
those bits you know that caused the trap
and
it will emulate you know that
instruction and so it will do all the
effects that that instruction has
but record what the results of those
effects are so for example
you know whenever we record what the
result you know executes instruction
the result says goes into a0 uh it
records the value of the a0
and then basically sends to the backup
you know the outcome you know of that
instruction so whatever is like
the value in a0 is you know whatever 221
then it will you know send back you know
saying you know there's none
deterministic construction
uh the result of it is 221.
and at some point correct you know the
backup legs behind
uh it will you know execute because it's
actually keeping the instructions in the
same order in the
same way it will also execute the
numbers to deterministic instruction
that will trap into the kernel uh and
the usual wait until
you know since it lags behind it already
has received probably the message
and basically you make sure that you
know it sticks the same value
you know or returns the same value as it
did on the primary
right so this is how non-deterministic
instructions are handled
sorry so that happens um like the
modification of the binary it happens
when
um it creates the virtual
machine yeah we think about it when it
boots the vm okay
right so the um the backup re-executes
the
the non-deterministic instruction and
then just verifies the
result no what it actually does is if
the virtual machine monitor executes the
instruction
and then you know uh or actually the
virtual machine model doesn't execute
the instruction at all
uh it knows that this instruction needs
to be executed
and it knows what things will be changed
like what registers need to be updated
as a result of this uh
instruction and it sticks the value from
the message
into the red register so that the uh you
know the linux running on the backup
sees exactly the same effect as
the the linux running on the primary
and so like this assumes that the
hypervisor will do some work before even
uh or while putting up the vm just
because of where the locations of these
non-determinations oh yeah yeah i'm
wishing any hypervisor does to these
days
so this is our standard hypervisor stuff
this is nothing new to uh
ft uh other than you know these guys are
the tone and experience doing
hypervisors right because of vmware
and so they understand like what what a
neat what it takes
and which instructions are
non-deterministic thank you
okay so i i had one more
uh one more question so if
you know it's a program of fully like
deterministic instructions
uh could could the backup run
faster than the primary um
okay so you know there's a whole
discussion in the paper about like the
speed of the primary in the backup and
making sure that they're
running roughly at the same speed
because you don't want to get one far
behind ahead and the one not far behind
um i think you should think about them
they're running on sort of identical
hardware and so they run roughly at the
same speed
uh it's also the case that uh there's
gonna be always some communication over
this uh channel
uh because interrupts are happening
periodically right like
every you know whatever you know a
couple milliseconds
or maybe 100 milliseconds or 10
milliseconds depending on like what how
linux
and what rate linux programmed the
hardware timer there will be a timer
interrupt
and the timer interrupt will be
propagated you know to the backup and
sort of be your sync points if you will
right but um my question is like for
example
say you you have a bunch of like
deterministic instructions right
instructions that aren't sent through
the logging channel
um which means you know the primary and
backup
can run those instructions and at their
own pace correct
yes so say i mean i don't know if this
could happen but say like
um it's you know a hundred instructions
and the primary goes to like instruction
and gets gets a timer interrupt
uh but the backup is already a timer
like 60 or something
could that like that could not happen
great because remember the backup
likes behind one of these messages
so the back of both start executing the
next block until the
primary has finished it okay now this is
why
this is why it lacks behind one um
like to ensure that the backup is like
lagging behind one instruction that does
that mean
no no not one instruction one message on
the channel
but the interrupt is unexpected right so
if we have as you said if you have 100
lines of instructions and uh running on
the backup
as well as on the primary then the
department would the backup would not
have started yet
right so the primary runs the 400
instructions the backup actually waits
until
uh the priming actually has completed
you know whatever those hundreds
instructions
before it starts running those hundred
so just again one way to think about is
like always runs like one epoch behind
oh so it's kind of a batching kind of
scheme yep
all right thank you okay so i want to
talk a little bit about failover because
there's a couple of interesting there's
one more rule that needs to be ensured
that we actually
uh get the right behavior and so
uh so let's uh walk through some
scenarios here's the primary
here's our hypervisor correct ft uh
here's our logging channel
it's ft the bose is on the network
here's a client
and here's our backup
and i'm going to talk about a couple of
scenarios so
um the first scenarios or the normal
case or
the client sends a message
you know to the primary or like the
server is running on the primary you
know that's delivered of course
you know to the primary it's also sent
you know to on the channel
and uh let's assume for a second that
actually the message you know
arrives you know at the hypervisor so it
actually knows that this was an
interrupt and some packet
arrived and so now let's say the
primary sensor responds back
and at that point the computer crashes
so the primary fails the client has not
gotten response yet
now this turns out to work out perfectly
fine right because before
you know the backup actually takes over
it first processes all
its uh messages that hasn't received yet
because lag's one behind
you know as we talked before so you know
this thing will be
delivered so it will sorry
um uh
ah okay let me be a little bit more
careful uh okay so that gets delivered
the prime backup does it you know but it
actually won't send in the response
because it's still sort of you know
doing exactly what the primary
has done you know gets to that
particular point and stops
then point you know the erase you know
or like the backup actually comes to
primary you know from the arbitration
server
and the client will just time out and
retry right because like tcp packet then
get a response and
retracts everything works right perfect
the interesting case is what happens
in the following scenario where
the client sends the request it can
arrive at the primary
primary uh does the operation or
whatever process the client requests
sends the message to default talent
server
in the meantime okay it was also sent on
the logging channel
but let's say we got unlucky the message
actually never made it over the logging
channel
and um uh
but the primary actually you know sends
a response
before and just sends a response
and then it fails right and so for
example like maybe
you know this request was like increase
you know the variable from 10 you know
to 11. so
inc you know the old state was 10 and
now the new state is 11.
right and is this problematic
the scenario um yeah because
when the backup takes over it won't
uh know about that increase
um and so it'll just continue execution
as if it didn't happen
and this provides um like
inconsistent uh output to the external
um like facing world i guess yeah
exactly
right because the primary will take the
backup will take over the value will
still be 10
uh and now if the client doesn't inc it
can actually
uh gets 11 back instead of 10 over
instead of 12
right so this is no good and so how is
this avoided this problem
um the primary will send
things to the backup and then wait for
acknowledgement and once that
ah once that acknowledgement is received
it can uh send
output and it doesn't matter whether the
backup actually
runs the command it just has to like
have it so that
if it ever needs to take over as primary
it has that in its logs and it will
catch up
before actually like becoming the
primary this is exactly right
so this is what's called the output rule
right
and the rule is that you know before you
can output you got to make sure
that the preceding messages that you
were sent to the backup actually have
been received by the backup
so the scenario that just drew out you
know can actually never happen
because you know at the point you know
the primary wants to send the response
out on the network
the ft the primary ft will wait until
this message actually has
has been received by the pr by the
backup and
only when it receives an acknowledgement
from the
backup ft uh and now it knows you know
that basically the
backup has uh a copy of this input
uh and so whatever you know whenever it
fails you know the
backup will you know process that input
and basically get you know the computer
in the same state as in
the primary so at that point it actually
save
you know to send out the reply and so
this is the output rule
is that you don't output until
all proceeding messages that you send
over the log channel
actually have been received by the
backup and so just to clarify
it seems that the output rule is here to
uh
to solve the inconsistency that could
happen if we have some non-determinism
so like let's say that we have the
output operation
to be instruction 60 and uh we did not
have the
uh the output rule and so the backup
actually
did not let's say for some reason did
not receive the
output operation um or it did not
receive up until the output operation
if the instructions are deterministic
between the point
where the backup did not receive
messages
until the point where we have an output
operation
do we still run into the problem of the
inconsistency
yeah because the client might have
observed it right the client might have
observed that actually the value is now
11.
and so when it actually talks to the
backup after
the primary has failed you know then the
values certainly
10. and this is that can't be true
so that you know that reveals that it's
not behaving like a single system
it's really the external it's the
external thing you know the external
client that will observe something right
and this is why the output role exists
and any replication system that we'll
see this semester has something like the
output rule
it turns out to be you know for example
we'll see in the uh
even in the rav paper but also in
zookeeper there's sort of this notion
that you know sometimes you want to like
uh respond to reads immediately but you
can't really do that because
you run this risk and there's sort of a
sort of an equivalent of an output rule
that tries to avoid you know problems
like like that
so does the client um re-execute the
command
like do they get some sort of signal
that because the
command okay
okay so let's say uh we did not get the
ack right
so it got to the back up but not to the
ack then
uh the client will have not you know
this response would have not been sent
to the client yet correct
the backup will take over the client
presumably will time out
and do whatever it needs to do you know
either you know does nothing
you know if you know the that's part of
the their that's part of the protocol
between the servers and the client
most likely the client will reset like
it's a tcp connection
uh the response packet didn't get
whatever received and so it will
you know try to uh resend and so it will
resent to the backup and then finish the
operation
but it won't observe an old value
okay
okay um now i want to
talk one thing a little bit uh so this
system
i think is actually very cool it's a
very clean uh
version of uh sort of statements of
state machine replication
uh it brings out these issues of
non-determinism uh the issues like
the output rule that we'll see in the
versions of that we'll see in
similar uh in in other
systems but i want to talk a little bit
about performance
because like one downside of this system
is you know because you're doing things
at the level of the
machine instructions or like at the
level of interrupts uh there
you pay uh a performance a hit
um so i want to point to the two tables
that are in the paper uh
and one you know the first thing to
observe is that actually the left table
is actually extremely good
uh so the backup and the primary if you
run the backup on primary the
performance is very close to as if you
were not running with a
backup which is very very impressive
including the fact that you're running a
virtual machine
uh the more uh the more
uh troublesome part is this
side of the things where um if you don't
run
in in a primary backup mode you know
like your bandwidth and receiving
ascending actually is pretty high you
know
at least in the particular experiment
they did but you know when you're
running the backup mode
things are actually not so good right
you know these numbers are quite
different
in fact there's sort of like a 30
reduction in performance
and where is that 30 coming from like
why why is that the case
um is it because the primary is actually
the one receiving inputs from outside
yeah well i think there's two cases in
on the receiving
case right the primer is receiving input
from the outside and where does that
need to go it receives a packet from the
from the client and so the packet has to
be sent you know to
the uh
to the backup and furthermore but the
primary is also the one
sending output uh to back to the clients
so is that what's using the bandwidth
uh well there's the that's one reason
that's what the bandwidth
that's part of the band revision but the
real thing i think was going on here is
that the
uh primary has to wait until it can send
the response to the
client until the backup actually has
acknowledged it
and so it just can't like process
packets at the same speed
as it could without actually a backup
and therefore you know we should see a
reduction in performance
nevertheless this performance is pretty
impressive but you know
there is a performance cost and this is
one reason that people
uh play you know this game of replicated
state machines not at the
instruction level but at like the
application level and
you'll basically be able to get higher
performance but that requires
modifications to the applications as we
saw in gfs
okay i think i'm running a little bit
over time so i'm going to stop right now
uh so that
and i hope people that actually uh
needed to leave already
left uh but i will stick around and so
if people have more questions
uh i'd be happy uh uh
to answer those and i'll talk to you on
tuesday
thank you
um i had a question about the previous
image that you drew
with with the uh yeah yeah that one
um i was confused because wasn't it
the case that if that number 10
it just sits in the memory then when we
do an increment
we don't need to send anything to the
backup right
there okay so there's two things going
on here so we do
at the at the point that the message
comes in like this increment comes in
from the client arrives at the
ft at the uh the hype the primary
hypervisor
it needs to forward that message to the
backup ft so that it can you know
process it if it
needs to be processed when it needs to
be processed you know when it you know
it
processes exactly at the same point in
this instruction stream
right so it sends it off and then you
know delivers it to the primer
and then the primary goes up and does
its thing primary you may
respond with a message and so the if the
prime response is a message
the output you know of that message is
stopped or hold
hel on hold into all uh the backup
has acknowledged the reception of this
increment
which will ensure that if the backup has
to take over you know whatever
it will process that increment first and
it also will be 11
before response is sent
okay okay thank you
welcome one thing i was kind of confused
about is a
goal of the system to uh
to help with like bucking up an actual
server where
because it's not easy to handle the
interrupts uh without a hypervisor or
is it actually to help distribute uh
virtual machines themselves it is purely
to make an apnea like so you have a
business application that runs on a
single machine
and you want to make it more fault
tolerant and uh
the what this scheme does is it makes it
fall down for you
transparently you know you run the
business applications and both machines
on the
on the ft hypervisor and the ft high vr
exerciser will assure that you know
basically these applications more or
less you know not literally
running lockstep but basically you know
you know
are fault tolerantly replicated so the
vm using the vm itself is kind of a
design decision
yes and that is a good design decision
because
it allows you to do this sort of
replication at a transparent level
got it thank you so much you're welcome
yeah there's a question in the chat
about can the uh
the output rule is it possible that the
client sees the same response twice and
the answer is yes
uh it's absolutely possible that the
client will see you get the
response twice uh and basically what
they argue
uh that's okay uh because in sort of the
fault model of the network
it is always assumed that the network
can actually duplicate messages anyway
and so protocols like tcp are totally
designed to deal with duplicate messages
so yes it's okay because of tcp
or whatever replication duplication
scheme the application uses or the
client uses
i was curious about uh cat's question
which is uh
if the primary like sort of like goes
down for a few minutes
back up goes live then sets up
it's uh it's its own backup you know
switches the bit back to like uh to zero
and then suddenly somehow the the
first primary goes back like
goes back oh yeah it has to be the case
that first crime is definitely
terminated it's cleaned up
and gone nice
yep thanks
i was gonna ask um actually something
similar this may be too broad of a
question but like will you ever need to
store
more things besides like an arbitration
flag in the server
and decide to flag an arbitration server
um if you have like multiple like
uh backups oh yeah like
this is a scheme tailor two and one
backup and not more than one backup so
if you had more backups you know the you
know
there's other issues that we need to
resolve and in fact you know we'll come
back to this on tuesday you know with
more sophisticated protocols that you
know handle
those cases much cleaner okay
i have one question about the
performance yeah
um so can you go back to that table
yeah so my question is is it the delay
only be
viewed on the first pack here like after
the first packet it will just flow
through
the channel and there is no extra delay
on
the link so the bandwidth should be
roughly the same
but no no okay for every packet received
correct by the primary you know that
packet has to be forwarded to the backup
yeah and for every response you know the
backup will have to wait on the primary
has to wait until the output
rule is satisfied and then it can send
the response
so there's some like processing on the
backups
backup server too before getting back to
the primer
yeah so again they talk a little bit
about that correct like the particular
crossing that needs to be done is
actually acknowledging the
uh perception of the packet on the
logging channel
and they talk a little bit about like
how to reduce the delay
to make sure that that sort of the
acknowledgement is very quick
i see i see okay thank you you're
welcome
i have a question about the the logging
channel so they they mentioned that they
they use udp um and i assume that's
mostly for performance
but then so basically if a single
failure happens
the primary like if a single packet is
unacknowledged then it assumes that the
backup failed
without any like re-transmission no no
no no uh
because of there's a timer interrupt uh
and the timer interrupt goes off
like every 10 milliseconds or something
uh the
there's always sort of multiple you know
one package is sent if that packet
doesn't get uh
there's no heartbeat coming back then it
will do a couple
of these time interrupts before it gives
up okay
and the the the heartbeats are they
saving from the primary or
it was like sort of implied it was like
from somewhere else in the system well
they sort of come from the time you're
in the heartbeat basically have an
indirect side effect
because every 10 milliseconds you're
going to send an interrupt message to
the overlogging channel anyway
i see okay
all right thank you thank you welcome
actually i wanted to follow up on that i
think it said that
it's gonna wait a couple a few seconds
to go yeah we'll wait a while you know
we'll do a couple heartbeats and wait a
while and if there's really none of them
to go through
then it will stop okay and
is there is a few seconds that's that's
a lot right
yeah i don't remember exactly all the
numbers uh so you could be right in a
few seconds i would imagine it's a
little bit shorter but maybe it's not
clear i think is that like something in
the order of a few seconds but
is it bad that was for the cloning
but you know i can remember the right