be talking about uh is spark
and so this goes back to sort of almost
through the beginning of the semester
uh where you know we talked a lot quite
a bit about mapreduce in fact you know
lab one
you implemented mapreduce
so and really what's you know one sort
of informally you know
the spark is basically the successor
you know to hadoop
and hadoop is the sort of open source
version
of uh of mapreduce
so i think today uh you know people
typically will use
spark instead of hadoop
and so it's really widely used
and it's widely used for data science
computation so people that you know have
lots and lots of data that need to run
some computation over it
require a ton of machines uh you know
spark
is designed for that particular case
it is commercialized by a company called
databricks
who's the offer or the main offer of
this paper in his it's his
phd phases started with a number of
other people this company databricks
uh which you know commercializes spark
but it also supports the apache open
source
smart version this is a
pretty popular open source project or
very popular open source project
it is one reason has sort of replaced
you know the use of
hadoop is because it actually supports a
wider range
uh wider range of applications than
mapreduce can
in particular they're very good at this
iterative
what happened there
let me see something maybe external
crash
hold on a second
uh
story
okay um fortunately i think we're in
good shape uh okay so it supports a
wider range of applications
um and in particular is good at these
iterative applications so applications
where
there are multiple rounds of mapreduce
operations so if you have an application
that requires sort of one
set of mapreduce followed by another set
of mapreduce followed by another mapper
series
computation you know spark is really
good at it and the reason it's good at
it is because basically it keeps the
intermediate results in memory and
that's really good support programming
support for
uh doing so
in some ways uh you know the sort of if
there's any
connection at all between the previous
paper and this paper which basically is
not
uh but you know they're all both
targeted
to sort of in memory computations
you know for data sets that basically
fit in memory in the previous paper and
farm paper is all about you know the
database fitting in memory
here is the data set of the data science
computation for the data science
computation that you want to do
of course you know since 2012 whenever
this paper was published a lot of things
have happened
uh the
spark is not really tied to uh scala as
i sort of described in this paper but
there are other language front ends for
example
but probably more importantly you know
the
rdds as defined in this paper slightly
deprecated
and replaced by
data frames but data frames the way to
think about it or
the way i think about it this is
basically column is an rdd with
explicit columns and all the good ideas
of rdds are also true for
data frames and so from the rest of the
lecture i'm just going to talk about
rdds
and think about them as equivalently as
to
data frames any questions
before i proceed
uh and then a quick other point maybe
this is this research is really uh quite
successful and except you know
it's a white reuse also uh mate
uh you know received the uh acm doctoral
thesis
uh award for it is for the for his uh
thesis that basically
is all about spark so it's quite unusual
actually for uh
you know doctoral thesis that to have
that kind of impact
okay so the way
i want to talk about spark is by just
looking at the some of the examples
because i think you you get the best
you understand the programming model and
that is based on rdds
best by just i think looking at examples
and you get the best idea of what
actually an rdg is
and so let me pull up some of the
examples that are in the paper
and then we'll walk through those
um pick this one so let's start here
a very simple uh example and so
you know the idea is that
uh in this example is you know first of
all you can
sort of use uh spark interactively
you consider your startup spark on your
workstation or your laptop
and start interacting uh with spark
um and you know the way you know you
could type in commands like this
and so now what does this command do you
know this basically
uh creates an rdd you know called this
is rdds
lines is an rdd and it just represents
the an rdd that actually stored in hdfs
and you know the hdfs you know might be
have money partitions you know for this
particular file so for example
the first you know thousands or a
million records list on like partition
one there's next
million live in partition two and the
next mill lift to impetus free
and this rdd uh lines basically
represents
you know that uh that set of partitions
uh when you uh run this line or you type
in this line and you return
hit return basically nothing really
happens uh uh and so this is what the
the paper refers to as lazy computations
in fact the computation is executed some
point later and we'll see
in a second when uh but at this
particular point the only thing that
actually happened is that there is a
line a lens object uh that happens to be
an rdd
and uh an rdd you know supports
sort of a wide range of operations we
can actually look at a little bit of
some of the operations that it supports
uh yeah
so it's used as a an rdd has an api
uh and it turns out that the methods on
the api
or the methods on an rdd fall into two
classes
one are the our actions and actions are
really
the operations that will actually cause
computation to happen
and so all the lazily sort of build up
computation really happens at the point
that you run an action
as an example you run count or collect
then
the the spark computation actually is
executed
all the other api or methods
are transformations and they basically
take one rdd
and turn it into another rdd it turns
out that every rdd
is actually read-only or immutable so
you can't modify
an rdd you can only basically
generate new rdds from an existing one
and so if we look at the second line
this basically creates a second rdd
there are the rdd errors
and that one is created by uh running a
filter
on the lines rde so the lines are
deducing
read only is read only
you can run this method to filter on it
which in this case basically filters out
all the records there that start with or
all the lines that start with the
message error or the string error and
that represents a new rdd
and again at this point nothing actually
is really being computed it's just like
a recipe
or you know it builds up like almost
like a data flow uh
or what the people call the lineage
graph of the computation
um
also when the computation actually
starts running
it hasn't run yet but you know when it
will start running uh these operations
are pipelined
uh and with that they mean that uh so
for example
in stage one you know the this
computation of the lines
the stage one will read some set of
records you know from
uh for example this first partition um
and then uh do its processing on it if
there's anything and then hand handed
off to stage two
you know which is stage two is basically
you know doing this filter
and so in stage two you know the uh
uh the uh this filter will run
and sort of grab out you know the lines
that actually are
that match and you know basically
produce with that a new rdd
that just all contains you know the
lines you know strings with that start
with
lines that start with the string air
and while uh this sort of second rdd or
the second stage runs you know the first
stage you know grabs the next set of
uh records from the file system and then
you know feeds them again to stage two
and so as you go further further you
have more and more stages in your
pipeline or your your
lineage graph you know all those stages
are going to be running in sort of
parallel and that's what i mean with
like sort of pipelining
the transformations okay so
um so here this so this you know
this line basically describes how to
create the rdd error
uh the rdd errors rdd and then this line
basically says like
uh tell spark to basically keep a copy
of this rdd in memory
so a subsequent
computation run that you know do more
stuff with errors
spark will actually keep the original
rdd actually in memory
uh so that uh it can be shared with
later computation so for example if you
wanted to reuse the error file
then you know that error file will be in
memory it doesn't have to be
reconstructed from the files in the
vector we represented
hdfs and allows you to run the second
computation
and here for example one already you
know even in this simple example you'll
see there's a bit sort of a big
difference between this
and mapreduce where can the mapreduce
job you know you run the computation it
ends
and then if you want to read you know
redo something with the data
you have to re-read it in from the file
system and
using the sort of precious method
spark can avoid you know having to
re-read
that data from the disk and you know
save a lot of time
any questions so far um so when the air
file
gets extracted from p1 let's say and
then there's
another error file that gets extracted
from p2 so my understanding is that
these happen in parallel
yes so you can think about it like you
know they're going to be mini worker
like in the mapreduce and the workers
work on each petition
so basically you know the scheduler will
send a job you know to each of the
workers
and a job is or task you know pertains
to a particular petition
and the workers start working on
get one of these tasks and basically
start running so you get parallelism
between the
partitions and you get parallelism
between the stages in the pipeline
i see thank you
what's the sorry can you hear me uh
what's the difference between um
the lineage and the like just the log of
transactions that we've seen before like
is it just the
granularity of the operations
as we'll see lineage uh the log is
strictly linear
right and the examples that we've seen
so far the the
the lineage is also linear but we'll see
in later examples where
you know we have forks where one stage
depends on multiple
uh different rdds and you know that's
just not representative in the log
right you know there share some
similarities in the sense that like you
start in the
beginning state all the operations are
deterministic and then you will end up
in some
and if you apply all those operations
you will end in some you know
deterministic end state uh so in that
sense you know there's some similarity
but you know i think
they're quite different
uh i also have a question in this case
filter
um it just so it works by just applying
filter on each partition but sometimes
like i see the transformations also
contain join
or sort yeah yeah let's talk about these
a little bit i will talk about sword and
join in a second okay
they're clearly much more uh complicated
so is uh do we like does persist
is when we start like computing no
no nothing has been completed yet so
still all descriptions so let's talk a
little bit further
um so let's look at actually something
that actually generates
a computation so
so here are two commands that actually
result in computation so this command
will result in computation because it
contains counts which is an action
and this command will result in a
computation collect
is an action and so
uh yeah yeah and so you can
and so we look it looks like that's a
reason that they show two commands is
because to demonstrate that basically
you can reuse errors
uh and so if you look at you know this
uh
computation yeah then you can draw the
lineage graph
right so it starts with lines
uh there was a filter that we ran
uh oops sorry let me write this slightly
differently there was a filter and lines
that we just saw that produces errors
or that's the description how to get
errors uh then there's an
in this case there's another filter it's
the filter on hdfs
and that basically produces another rdd
you know that rdd is not explicitly
named here
but you know it does produce another rdd
so i'm just going to call it
hdfs because it filters on hdfs
and then we see there's a map and that
produces yet another rdd
uh again this rdd doesn't really have a
name here uh but
uh so it's anonymous uh but i'm just
gonna give it a name
that's time because basically
uh splits the one in your line into
three pieces and
grabs the third piece out of that line
and that happens to be the time
and then uh there's a final you know
operation and that's collect
uh which then actually counts up all the
the number times that time actually
appears or the number entries basically
the result of the
in the rdd produced uh in the time rdd
okay so this so this is actually
at this point when you know the the
return you hit return here in the user
interface or in the uh
interactive uh user interface uh it is
and
at that point basically uh spark you
know we'll
collect you know the a lot of a set of
workers
uh split you know send them the jobs or
basically inform the scheduler that the
job needs to be executed
uh and the description of the task that
needs to be
executed is this lineage graph
and so we can sort of think a little bit
about exactly how the execution happens
so let me draw a picture
so the picture just as follows we got
this what is called the driver that's
the usual thing
you know that's where the program that
the user typed into
uh it uh
starts off collecting a bunch of workers
you know a bunch of machines
almost the same way like as in uh
mapreduce
and you know there's going to be an hd
vest there's this
lines file that actually has partitions
p1
p2 whatever
and typically the number of partitions
is larger than the number of workers
uh sorry the number of yes the numerous
partitions is larger than the number of
workers you know you go to you know get
some load balance
uh if like one petition is small and the
other one is big and
you don't want to have workers relying
sitting around idle
and basically the scheduler you know the
there's a scheduler that runs
you know basically the computation and
exa has the you know the information
that has the lineage graph
and so workers basically check in you
know the driver exercise and the code
the spark program and that would just
construct it
and then the work actually go basically
to the schedule and say please you know
which partition should i work
and uh and then they run uh basically
uh a part of the pipeline
and so we look at this let me actually
draw this slightly differently so i have
a little bit more space here
um so we saw there's a whole bunch of
stages
and then the last stage was the the
last upgrade was to collect stage
so uh in this in this
scenario that we just looked at the
collect stage of course needs to collect
data from uh all the partitions
right so we in principle you know let's
just draw a green line
you know basically everything of this
you know sort of executed on an
independent partition
so every worker you know gets one of
these tasks from the
scheduler runs you know the uh that
thing and produces in in the end
on uh time
rdd and when the sky scanner you know
determines that basically all the time
you know like all these stages this is
called the stage
if all the stages have completed and so
all the time
partitions have been produced then it
actually will run
you know the collect action uh to
basically do the addition
and you know retrieve information from
every partition
uh to actually compute the collect or
the
actually this does not collect it was a
count
sorry about that
and so uh one sort of thing way to think
about this is that this is sort of like
uh almost like a mapreduce right where
you have the map phase and then
you have sort of a shuffle and then you
run the reduced phase
and uh the count is almost or similar
in that fashion and in in the paper the
way they refer to this is
to this dependency if although there's a
white dependency
because the action or the transformation
is dependent on a number of partitions
and these are called narrow narrow
dependencies
because this
uh rdd to make that rdd is only
dependent on one
other uh only at the only dependent on
the parent
partition only one parent partition to
actually be able to compute it
and so in general you you would prefer a
computation that can have narrow
dependencies because they can just run
locally without any communication
uh but for a white dependency you might
have to collect uh
uh you might have to collect um
petitions from the parent or you may
have to collect
petitions from the parent rdd from all
the machines
um professor i had i had a question so
um in the paper it says
narrow dependencies um where each
partition
of the parent rdd is used by at most one
partition of the child
rdd yep um but but it doesn't say
anything about the
the country like the river is like like
it doesn't say like a child partition
needs to use it most
one um one
parent um yeah that's correct because
then
and then yeah if if a child uses
multiple parent partitions then it's a
white dependency
if apparent sorry if if
if the child meets the uh predictions of
if the petition for mult multiple parent
petitions
then it's a white dependency um
so for example in the count case correct
you know you have
you know time time partitions
right and the count operation
is going to collect in the data from all
of them right
and so if count were in rdd it isn't but
like it's just an action
but even we're in rdd then basically you
know that would require
uh interaction with all the parents um
what i'm saying is i think
i think it says the opposite right
i i think this might like
i mean i i i i was actually confused
uh like with the paper
on this very specific issue but like it
says
like each partition of the parent rdd is
used by at most one partition of the
child
but it doesn't say one partition of the
child uses it most
okay i'm not who accenture you know
exactly
why you're confused with this so let me
can we explain this and come back to it
sure i think the key thing to observe is
basically two types of dependency white
ones the narrow ones
and white ones basically you know
basically involve communication because
they have to
talk to the
collecting the information from the data
from the parent petitions
okay thanks i actually have a question
on the interface
um in like the previous like one or two
slides what happens if you don't call
error stop
persist ah uh
if you do not then uh the
you would the second computation like
this computation
would recompute errors from the
beginning
so if you run this workflow
uh this spark you know computation it
would recompute uh
errors you know from uh the starting
file
got it thank you um so i actually have a
question about
this point so for the partitions that we
don't
call persist on in the mapreduce
case we basically uh stored them in
intermediate files
but we nonetheless stored them uh in
a local file system let's say in the
case of mapreduce
do we actually store uh intermediate
files here that we don't persist in some
persistent storage or we
just keep the whole flow uh in memory
throughout the time
by default the whole flow is in memory
except
uh you can provide to uh let me
there's one exception i will talk about
a little bit more in detail in a second
hopefully
which is um
you see this persist here this persists
can take another
flag i think it's called reliable and
then
that set is actually stored in hdfs
basically they call this a checkpoint i
see thank you
i have a quick question about the
partitioning that um
with uh partitioning the rdds initially
uh is it initially hdfs who
partitions them for each worker to
operate on or is
is spark handling all that the the the
the
this aligns rdfs you know the petition
is defined basically by
uh the files that are actually in hdfs
okay you can repartition and we'll see
in a second that actually uh might be
advantageous to do so
uh for example using this hash partition
trick uh
and uh and you can define also your own
partitioner there's a
partition or object or extraction that
you can supply
okay so it's so it's already handled by
by hdfs but if you want to do it again
through spark then you can
yeah and in some sense of course these
files are also created by
this this file is presumably you're
created by
some logging system that sits on the
side and just produces different
partitions
or you know you can reshuffle if you
want to make sense thank you
okay uh
so um and so let me uh so so that's the
execution model
uh and i want to talk a little bit about
fault tolerance um
and so let's uh go back to uh this so
this is sort of fault tolerance and
the thing that we worry about in photons
is that maybe one of these workers
uh you know might crash right
and you know the worker is computing
some petition
and so we need to re-execute that uh
and now basically this plan is sort of
the same as a mapreduce
right uh where if a worker crashes
uh we need to uh in mapreduce and then
the map test need to be re-executed and
perhaps maybe a reduced task has to be
re-executed
now in here the tasks are slightly more
complicated because they're basically
like these stages
and so it means that if one worker fails
we may have to recompute the stage
so let's talk a little bit more about
that so that's sort of just perspective
from fault tolerance right that's what
we're trying to achieve
this is really different than like the
fall columns that were you know you
implemented in lab
and two and three were taxes and you
know stable storage and all that kind of
stuff
and you're really what we're we're
worried about
is a crash of a worker
the worker loses its memory
lost memory and the means of losses
partition
and uh you know the later parts of the
computation are probably dependent on
that partition
and so we need to re-uh
re-read or re-compute this partition and
so the solution is like exactly like in
mapreduce
you know basically the scanner you
notice at some point that doesn't get an
answer
and then re-runs the stage
for the petition
and you know and what is the cool part
like exactly as in mapreduce
all if you look at all these
transformations that are sitting here in
the api
all these transformations are functional
and so they basically take one input
they take an rdd as an input they
produce another rdd as output
uh and it's just completely
deterministic and so
like you know with mapreduce you know
these uh the maps and the reducer
functional operations if you restart a
stage or a sequence of transformations
from the same input then you'll produce
the same output
and so you recreate you know the same
partition
recreates petition facebook
okay
sorry is this why they they're immutable
there's also the reason i think they're
ideally immutable yes
okay there's one tricky case though uh
which i want to talk about
so this is the the the fault tolerance
basically for the narrow case
is the same as sort of as we saw before
in mapreduce but you know the tricky
case is actually the
white dependencies
so let's say you know we have you know
some transformations
and one of these transformations
uh is dependent on a you know this is
like sort of here we have one worker we
have another worker we have another
worker
and one of these stages um
is actually dependent on
a number of uh parent uh partitions
so uh let's say whatever maybe this is a
join or we'll see later other operations
uh we're you know we are actually
collecting information for lots of
partitions
and uh and you know create a new rdd
from that and from that rbd that might
be used again by a map
or whatever keep it going and so now
let's say
you know we're you know we're a worker
and you know we crash here
right then we need to reconstruct you
know this rdd
and you know we sort of followed uh that
means that we have to you know we could
also recompute this rdd
to review this rdd on this worker that
means we also need
the partitions on the other workers and
uh so uh the
uh the reconstruction the re-execution
of
uh a computation on a particular
uh worker or a particular partition may
actually result
that actually these ones also need to be
recomputed
now of course you can do this partially
in uh parallel you can just ask you know
please you know start
you know re-compute this guy we could
see that guy uh and
you know produce then the final uh rdd
again
uh but you know certainly you know an uh
failure one worker might result in the
recompensation
of many many uh petitions
and that's sort of slightly uh uh
that could be slightly costly and so the
solution is
that as a programmer you can say you can
actually
checkpoint or persist
rdds on stable storage
and so you might decide you know for
example this is an rdd that
uh that you don't want to recompute in
the case of a failure
because it requires you know recomputing
all the different partitions
you know you may want to checkpoint this
rdd
and then you know this you know stage
when it actually when this
computation needs to be re-executed now
we can actually read
you know the results of the partitions
from the
checkpoint instead of actually having to
recompute them from
scratch and so this is why uh spark
supports
checkpoints and that is sort of their uh
uh fall down the story for white
dependencies
any questions about this
um i i had one question
so there was um
so you can persist right just in in
general
but the they also mentioned the reliable
flag
um so i was wondering like what's the
difference between just persisting and
using a reliable flag
persist just means you're going to keep
that rdd in memory and you're not going
to throw it away
so that you can reuse it in later
computations in and this is in memory
the checkpoint or the liability flag
basically means
you actually write a copy of the whole
rdd
to hdfs
and ac has a persistent or a stable
storage file system
okay is there a way to tell spark to
unpersist something
because otherwise like for example if
you persist an rdd um and you do a lot
of computations
but like those later computations never
use the rdd
you might just have it sticking around
in memory forever
yeah so i i i presume you can
uh there's a general strategy that
spark uses so they talk a little bit
about this is that they
if there's really no space anymore they
might
spill some rdds to hdfs or remove them
the paper slightly vague on exactly you
know what their plan for that is
thank you of course when the competition
ends and
uh as a user you log out
where you stop your driver then i think
you know those rdds are definitely gone
from memory
okay okay so
that is almost you know the story of
spark um
uh the you know we've seen what an rdd
is
uh we've seen how uh so the execution
works
and we've seen how the paul thomas plan
the thing that i want to really want to
talk about is another example
to really show off where park sparks
shines and that is an iterative example
so in computation that has an iterative
structure
and the particular one i want to talk
about is page rank
uh i assume that most of you are
familiar with pagerank in
some form uh basically you know it's a
plan to
uh an algorithm to give weight or
importance
to web pages and it's dependent on the
number of uh
links that point to a particular webpage
so for example if you have a you know
webpage u1
uh main points to itself uh you have
maybe a
web page you free so i'll use an example
and my page youtube
you know you too has a link you know to
itself
and to you free and maybe you know your
free has a link to u1
and basically page rank is an algorithm
that you know based on these
connectivities computes you know the
importance of a web page
and patreon was sort of the early one of
the
algorithms that really drove the google
search machine
uh in the sense that if you had a search
result the way you rank search results
is that if the search result
appears on a more important web page you
know that results you know it gets
promoted to higher in the list
uh and uh number one the reason that in
the early days of google the google
search machine actually produced
a better search results where i mean the
more important information actually or
the more important web pages where on
top
and so the paper uh talks about
uh shows off the uh
an implementation of page rank in spark
so here's the implementation of
the spark implementation of page rank
and as before you know this is just a
description so we look at the individual
lines
um you know these are just the sort of
the recipe to actually how to
uh compute page rank and only when like
you know in this particular case if you
do say ranks collect
at the very end uh then actually the
computation would run
uh on you know the cluster of machines
and you know using sort of the execution
uh pattern that we have seen so far
and so i want to walk through uh this uh
example a little bit more detail
to get a sense you know what uh you know
get a better sense why sparks or
shines in the iterative case
so uh so there are two rdds here
uh i'm also going to talk about some
optimizations that are cool in uh spark
one is this linx rpgs and lynx is
basically you know represents the
uh the connection of the graphs and so
precisely
it probably has a line uh i'm just going
to write it like that has a line
uh per uh url so here you one
and it has two outgoing links uh u1
u3 yeah
uh
actually i missed one link here and then
uh there's a u2
entry for youtube which has now gone
linked to u2 and u3
and there is an entry you know q3
uh going to u1
so this is basically a description of
you will the you know the world wide web
and so of course you know in our my tiny
little example i have free web pages
uh but if you know we're running this at
the scale of you know google you would
have a billion web pages correct
and so this file is gigantic and it's
partitioned
uh in predictions
uh so that's links uh and then ranks
uh is a sort of similar file uh that
contains the current ranks for these web
pages
and so you can think about this as a new
one
you know comma you know it's rank uh and
let's assume that the ranks are
initialized at 1.0
uh then you know here's 1.0
and you know u 2 1.0
u u3 1.0
uh and we see actually that the links
that the links rdds is actually
persistent in memory
uh that's presumably like in the same
way as the error file that we saw before
or the error
rdd um and then
uh ranks uh you know it's initialized
you know to something and then basically
there's this sort of
uh description of number of iterations
uh to produce a new ranks uh
rdd and then you can see a little bit
you know how this actually
plays out uh and one of the things to
notice is that
links gets reused in every iteration
and length actually gets joined with
ranks what means what does it mean to
actually do this join up this
this operation this operation basically
creates an rdd
right and what how does that rdd look
like well that rdv is going to look like
u1 you know the and then the join of
the ranks and the and the links file so
it's going to be u1 u1 u2 because
there's a d or
u3 the outgoing links plus the rank for
u1 which i'm just going to write as rank
one and that's sort of the idd that's
being produced here and so
same thing for you know whatever you do
and the one for you free
is whatever you want and
you know uh are free rank for free
basically merges these two it literally
joins the two files
based on key okay
and then you know it runs a computation
of flatmap on this and that flatmap
itself internally has
a map over links and so basically it's
going to run
over like the screen it's going to run
over these lists
and basically partition or divide up
the rank you know to the outgoing urls
and so it will you know create uh
triples
uh of the form uh you know let me write
this in green then you know u1
uh r1 divided by two
and you know u1 or dual three
over the outgoing link so it gave one to
u1 one to u3 here's u3
r1 divided over two et cetera so it
creates triples of this kind of form so
basically you know it computes the
weight you know it divides the rank
across the outgoing edges
and gives you know the values of these
uh
rings you know to the outgoing edges so
the outgoing edges so we're going to get
a big you know rdd
that has you know disc four
and that's produced basically that is
the contributions
rdd then there's a final step
in the uh i think at first it doesn't
reduce by key
so basically grabs all the u1's you know
together
and then sums them up so basically this
will result is that you know all the
uh weights or the the fractional weights
you know that
you want is going to receive are being
added up so
u1 of course is going to receive weights
from
itself this one is going to relate from
u3
and so we'll sum them up it's going to
be r1
divided by two and r3 divided by one
and that is basically the sum that's
being computed
and so that gives us a list of sums and
then actually they are added up
and computed into a final value
and that produces the new ranks rdd
which has the same shape
as the one that we saw before namely
this shape
for every web page there is a number
does that make sense
and so uh it's interesting to you know
that's sort of the description so first
of all you can see that
actually the description of patreon is
quite precise
and this is one of the examples this is
like if you had to run this in a
mapreduce style then
that would mean that every iteration you
know of this loop
at the end of the iteration you would
store the results in the file system
and then you re-read you know the
iteration from the result for the next
iteration and
in uh in this
spark system you just every iteration
just runs straight out of memory it
leaves
results in memory so that the next
iteration can pick it up right there
and furthermore you know this links file
is shared among all the iterations
okay so to get a little bit more sense
of like you know why is also very cool
uh the way to look at it is to actually
look at the
lineage graph for this particular
computation
so let's look at the lineage graph for
uh
so here's the manage graph for
um the the
um for patrick
and so the couple things i want to uh
point out but first of all so the
lineage graph is like dynamic almost
looks uh
you know just keeps growing you know
with the number iterations
uh and so as the scheduler you know
basically computes and does new
uh stages then uh it uh keeps going and
you know we can see what the stages are
going to be correct because uh
you know sort of you know every
iteration uh
of a loop uh is uh one stage and will
basically append you know
uh uh parts uh transformations to the
to the lineage graph so we see here's
the input file
uh here's the links and as we saw like
links is actually created once
then persisted in memory right now not
on this persistent memory
and it's being reused many many times
like in every loop iteration
basically ranks is being reused and so
again you know compared to a mapreduce
if you have to write this in the
mapreduce style you don't get that reuse
and so that's of course going to like
tremendously perform performance because
links you know as we said before it's
like this gigantic file that basically
corresponds to
one line for every webpage in the
universe
another interesting thing to observe
here is that
we see a white dependencies here right
this is a white dependency
who could be a white dependency i will
be a little bit more sophisticated about
this in a second
um because basically these contributions
you know when we contribute
the intermediate result it is a join
across
ranks and links and so it needs the
partitions uh from links
and it needs partitions from ranks to
basically compute
a contribute a partition for contribute
for the
contrib contrap rdd sorry
so that might require you know some
never communication
but it turns out they have sort of a
clever optimization
this is in response to an earlier
question about like uh partitioning
uh the uh you can specify that you want
to
partition uh an rdd
using a hash partition
and what does what does that mean is
that the
links and ranks file these two rdds
are going to be petitioned in the same
way they're going to actually partition
by key
or by the hash of a key so if we go look
back you know
in our previous picture yeah the keys
for uh ranks you know are
you on youtube the keys for
um the uh links okay sorry the keys for
ranks are you want youtube free
the keys for uh links are also you want
youtube really free
and basically uh the client for
optimization this is a standard
optimization
from the database literature is that if
you partition
links and ranks by key then you know
this one is going to have u1 on one
machine
now maybe this is u2 and one machine
then ranks is going to have the same
thing it's going to have u1
on one machine and in fact you know it's
going to have u1 on the same machine
as the lynx one saying for u2 and u3
so even though this join
is exceptionally white dependency it can
be executed like a narrow dependency
because basically
to compute you know the join of these
two for the u1
you know for the first partition for pt
p1 you only have to look at the
partition p1 of links and p1
p1 of ranks uh because you know the keys
are hacked in the same way
to the same machine uh and so the
scheduler
uh or the programmer can actually
specify these hash petitions
the scheduler sees ah you know the join
actually
uses these hashtags the hash partitions
that are the same
and therefore and actually don't have to
do this white dependency i don't have to
do sort of a complete
barrier as the map reduce but i can just
treat this as a narrow dependency
so that's pretty cool
um then you know again uh
if a machine fails correct we talked a
little bit about this earlier
that might be uh painful because
you may have to re-execute many loops or
one iterations
and so uh you know if you would probably
write this for real then
uh the programmer would probably say
like maybe every you know 10 iterations
you know basically checkpoint
so then you don't have to re-compute the
computation all the way from uh
from the beginning oh so we don't
actually recompute links or anything
each time right like we don't persist it
sorry
we don't persist it no not at all the
only thing that was existed
was only once was links correct this is
the only thing that was had a persist
call
oh we do persist it links we do okay
but not the intermediate rdds because
they're basically new rdds every time
like range one is a new rdd ranks two is
a new rdd correct
uh but you may want to persist them you
know occasionally
and store them in hdfs so that uh if you
have to
a failure you don't have to go back to
the iteration loop iteration zero to
re-compute everything
okay does this make sense i'm sorry the
different
contribs can they be computed in
parallel
on different partitions yes um
because there there's like this line
that goes vertically down
down uh it's pipelined correct and then
there's
so there's two types of parallelism
there's stage parallelism and there is
sort of
panelism between different partitions
and we can think about this thing
you know this whole thing like running
many many times
on different partitions
so in this case the collect at the very
end will be the only place where we have
a wide
yeah exactly exactly the collect is the
only one that's gonna
you know whatever year we have no
repetitions correct
i'll make a mess of this picture but
that is gonna has to
get them from everyone
okay i hope the driver's overseas this
is actually pretty cool
right uh you know just by expressing
these computations
uh sort of a lineage graph or a data
flow computation
uh the scheduler has a bit of room for
optimizations uh like these uh
it's exploding hash partitions uh
the you know we get a lot of parallelism
uh we get also a lot of reuse
you know we can keep the results of one
rdd in memory so that we can reuse it
for the next iteration
and you can sort of see that you know
these techniques combined you know are
going to give you a
significant performance optimization
and allows you to expand and express
more uh powerful or more
interesting computations
so maybe with that i will like summarize
this lecture
um so a couple things uh
you know so rdds are made by
functional transformations
uh they're grouped together in sort of a
lineage graph
which you can think about as a data flow
graph
and this gives the you know this allows
reuse
uh it also allows some clever
optimizations by the scheduler
uh and basically allows also more extra
there's more expressiveness
yes then you know mapreduce by itself
and which results basically in good
performance because like a lot of the
data just stays in memory
and so if you actually if you're excited
about this uh you can try it out
uh you should download you know spark
play around and write some programs or
you know go to databricks.com and you
know create an account and then you can
run
spark computations on there on their
clusters
so if you're excited about this and want
to try it out you know it's pretty easy
to do so
like unlike farm you can just like not
play with
but this actually you can actually go
out and try out okay with that i want to
stop
uh for today and uh and
the people that want to hang around and
ask more questions please feel free to
do so
the other thing i want to remind people
of is that you know the
deadline of for 4b uh is a little bit
away but
i just want to remind people that 4b is
pretty tricky uh requires a bit of
design
so don't don't start too late and uh
with that
i'll see you on tuesday
and again questions i'm happy to answer
that
thank you uh i had a question about
the checkpoints i think they mentioned
automatic checkpoints um using
data about how long each computation
took
um and i wasn't really sure what
they mean by this like what what are
they going to be
optimizing for i think you know the
whole checkpoint is correct is an
optimization between
uh you know taking checkpoint is
expensive
uh and so that you know takes time uh
and but you know re-execution if there's
a machine failure
also takes a lot of time uh and so for
example if you take never
checkpoint then you basically have to
re-execute the computation from the
beginning right
but if you take periodically checkpoints
you know you don't have to repeat
you know the computation that you did
before the checkpoint but the check
taking the checkpoint takes time
so if you take very frequent checkpoints
you don't have to recompute a lot but
you spend all your time taking
checkpoints
and so there's sort of a you know an
optimization problem here
you know you want to take the
checkpoints and some regular interval
uh that you're willing to take to
recompute
okay so maybe like compute checkpoints
only for very large computations
yeah or like for example in the cases
pagerank you know maybe you know
do it every 10 iterations
thank you it depends of course if the
size of your checkpoints
decides to check when you're small you
can checkpoint more frequently
but in the case of this pagerank you
know that checkpoint is going to be
pretty big
there's going to be a line or a record
you know per
uh webpage
that makes sense thank you
i have a question about the driver
because the application
is like does the driver is the driver on
the client side
or is it yes okay yeah the driver is on
the car
if it crashes we lose like the the whole
graph and that's fine because that's the
application right yeah i don't exactly
know what happens because the
the uh the scanner has a tube
and uh and the scanner is full tolerant
so i don't know exactly when you know
what happens maybe you can reconnect i i
don't know
i had a question about the why
dependency optimization
you mentioned that they do like the hash
partitioning um
how does that work okay i can say a
little bit more so this is not a
hashtag is not something that they
invented i mean this is actually
something that is
uh uh is a standard database
uh partitioning scheme and it is cool
because if you need to compute a join
you don't have to do a lot of
communication so let me actually i can
maybe
start a new slide because it's a little
bit hard to
read so hash partitioning
so if you have two data sets and here's
data set one
your data set two they have keys right
like you know e1
p2 so they have the same
set of keys then what you do
by hash partitioning you partition the
data set in number of partitions
so boom boom boom and
uh you has the key
so you have k1 you has k2 and that
actually determines the partition it
ends up in and so all the
keys that actually have the same hash
will end up in the same place so like
this is machine one
this is machine two it's machine three
so you take you know whatever
you hash k1 that goes in here you know
you hash you know whatever k2 maybe
somewhere else in the file who knows
where it is
and you hash it to that partition you do
the same thing here
for the other data set so here's data
set one
this data set too
like links and ranks and you know what
will happen
is that all the records in this data set
that have
the same keys as records in the other
data set those keys or those records
will end up in the same machine
right so here you're going to partition
this guy and basically k1 will end up
here too
on the same machine
correct and same for you know the other
lp's because you basically use the same
hash function and you have the same set
of keys
and so this allows you to take a data
set you know partition them both in the
same way
uh using this uh hashing trick and this
is cool because now if you need to do a
join
over these two data sets like if you
need to do a join of these two data sets
then basically you can just join the
partitions
and you don't have to communicate you
know each of these machines doesn't have
to communicate with any other
machine because it knows it has all the
keys that you know
uh that the other data set has and
they're all on the same machine
gotcha so basically it's just trying to
uh sort
not sort but like bucket the different
yeah in the same machine
okay great thank you so much
so this means the hash function has to
make sure that
there are no links that would have to be
like
using the computation on another machine
right like for instance yeah well
since they use the same hash function
and they have the same keys you know
that will happen
um i oh i had a question i
actually wanted to come back to the
question i asked before yeah yeah yeah
good good good
um so let me open up yeah let me also
open the paper i guess
is there any other people that have
questions because maybe this will take a
little bit
of time yeah actually i had a quick
question on the uh
thought holler thought tolerance of farm
um so so just to clarify
what happens so if a failure occurs
before the decision point um
then the entire thing is aborted but if
it occurs after the decision point then
after
the failed computers come back up they
have to
re-ask the coordinator for whether or
not they should come in
uh they don't really re-ask correct like
the what what happens is they're
after failure there's a recovery process
runs and the repulsion process
looks uh basically and all the logs are
drained
and and then the recovery process looks
at the state of the system
and based on the state of the system it
decides what to do with the transaction
either it aborted or commits it and
the key uh aspect here in this protocol
is to ensure
that at the point when the
uh transaction coordinator actually has
reported to the application that the
transaction succeeded
uh committed uh it has to be the case
that there are enough pieces of evidence
left around
in the system so that during the
recovery process that transaction is
definitely committed
and uh and that's not sort of the plan
and the reason that there's enough
evidence is because there's these
log records lying around uh there's this
command backup records
lying around and there's this this one
commit record
i see so if something for example if a
failure
occurs on a primary before it gets a
commit primary
um what happens there ah so that's
interesting so there's enough backup
records correct
to basically decide you know that every
backup that every shard actually has
committed
and uh and so that's enough information
for the recovery process to say oh yeah
i'm gonna run for that transaction
because it could have committed
got it so it doesn't need the primary in
that case it can use the backups because
the backups have
exactly got it thank you
and what happens if the backup fails
uh well if one of the backup fails and
presumably that means that the commit
record is still there and then again
that is enough information to decide
that actually the transaction needs to
commit
and there's enough backups around to
actually know what the new values or
there's also the log
entries which actually contain so if a
primary is up
it will have a log entry it will be a
commit entry plus and there's enough
backups to actually uh finish the
transaction
thank you i'm sorry to follow up on that
if you said that
if the primary failed then you could use
the backups to
complete the production if there's
enough of them
you need need to elect a new primary
i think this has all happened during the
uh
basically you can think of the recovery
process as a primary
and that just finishes everything off
oh so whoever does the recovery is the
primary
yeah yeah okay makes sense
thank you i don't think explicitly they
you know promote a primary you just like
go ahead and do it
and what is like enough backups well
we have f plus one right
uh and so it means that you know as long
as one is left
you know we we're good so we can't have
more than f plus one failures
and we can only have f failures in this
particular drawing
f is one
so there has to be per shard you know
one machine left
okay that makes sense thank you you're
welcome
okay philippians just me and you
well unless anyone else has questions i
think
so it's it's page they explain it in
page six
yeah right below
table three yep
um so the bear got it starts the most
interesting question right
it goes on to define yeah we found the
most sufficient usual to classify
dependencies in two types narrow
where parent petition the parent id is
used by most one partition of the child
rt correct so this is
right so let me so let's let's draw this
correct so here we have
a parent petition
right and let's say there's a map
and here we have the child petition
okay right okay so that's the narrow
this is the narrow case
right but um
i think like the the the example i was
thinking of is
you know each um
parent is used by at most
um one partition of the child but the
child
right that doesn't say anything about
like it says
right like it doesn't necessarily mean
it's a one-to-one relationship
right well because more or less have to
correctly just let me
uh let's say we have a white one correct
so then
here we have parent
partition one
here we have you know maybe it has end
of them correct you know here we're
right here
and here's n and in the white one
the child is
right um what what what i was saying is
i i think you know based on the
definition given the paper
this could be a narrow partition
and in fact i mean like if you look at
um like a join with inputs
co-partitioned like you have yeah the
hash partition that actually the white
one turns into a narrow one
right right but but you still have like
a partition a child partition getting
like
and like being completed from several
yeah parent partitions yeah right i
think
explicitly mentioned that correct i
think that's the only example
yeah but like i think there's a typo in
that sentence correct
i i mean i'm not i'm not sure if it's
yeah i i'm not sure like if it's
what they meant to like write or
what we know we conclude this is the two
cases like i got it yeah
okay so there are no other cases well
we can go for every operation correct
and then we can see whether it's an
error or a white one right right
and the ones that are and it's the job
of the programmer
that defines these operations to
actually indicate whether it's a
white partition or an arrow but a white
dependency or a narrow dependency
correct
that's what the figure table three is
about
uh-huh yeah uh like what i'm saying is
like usually like
like the way like i saw it through the
paper like uh like
your example on the right would be a
could would be a narrow dependency
unless
right like you have several child and
the parent partitions
are like ah okay so in general okay it
is the case support correct if there's
another child petition here okay so
maybe this is why we're trying to get it
so let's separate
the real picture that i should draw is
this okay that's another channel
partition
and basically operations uh
the transformations are
exactly yeah and that's narrow for sure
right like this on the right side this
is why
sorry that's why yeah yeah that's what i
meant that that for sure is white
okay and the other one is white you know
the one i drew is also white i believe
like okay do you join if you do an
action like
uh collect at the very end yeah it's a
white dependency yeah
okay there's a does it say that it
doesn't say it has to come for different
rdds it just says like it has to come
from
different partitions and so this is
narrow so i think narrow
is only the case where there's one to
one okay
there is like narrow means no
communication
right okay
yeah i think i think the case where i
was like confused was like the
like men many the one
like i think based on the definition of
the like of the of the
paper like the many-to-one relation is
still um
it's still narrow no i think they i
think they
mean it to be uh i mean yeah yeah yeah
but like strictly
like if you re like yeah i i think maybe
like an implementation you'll see like
yeah what what are you saying right like
it's white i was just like i think if
you read like the
the yeah you could be confusing paper
textually yeah like you
you can get confused so like the menu
one relationship but the one too many
is clearly wide yeah but yeah okay
sounds good okay yeah that'll just makes
i can't make the paper easier to
understand in general
okay good good okay yeah there's
an easier to understand paper than the
form oh yeah
yeah for sure yeah i think
well i think those were probably the
most too heavy-duty papers that will uh
that we'll see in this term
okay nice environment yeah farmer's
banner i think the remaining ones are
a little bit more you know more uh i
wouldn't say straightforward but
perhaps fewer moving pieces nice
okay awesome thanks professor can i ask
one
last question i just realized that i
have um
it was about the computation you can
paralyze it if
if it's on different partitions but if
it's also
um you said if it's in yeah there's a
stage the stages correct you know
they're sort of uh like streaming
parallelism if you will or
pipeline parallelism uh let me see if i
can find a picture
that's one of them
[Music]
i gotta find a lineage graph uh
no no
right here it's really in this graph
great now maybe here's a
picture that we can modify uh do you see
it
yes okay so basically
this is the lineage graph and he was to
collect and
so this is like one stage right
and the schedule runs one of these
stages on each worker
for each partition right so each
worker
runs a stage on a partition
so basically all these partitions are
all these uh
stages running parallel on different
workers
then within a stage there's also
parallelism
uh because you know every filter uh
is pipelined uh with that you know they
mean
like you read maybe like the first n
records
and then you apply the filter operation
and then uh you know that produces you
know whatever
few m records
and you know then the next you know
filter you know process those
and records but while it's processing
those m records
the first filter reads the next end
and you know produces them and then
passes them on and then you know maybe
that results in some number of records
and again and you know it goes on and on
and so basically all these you know all
these oops not these
all these uh transformations are
pipelined
and so they're almost running
concurrently or they're running not
truly concurrently but they're running
in a pipeline fashion
oh i just said this is the batch thing
that they were talking about yeah
exactly so things are passed in veggies
and basically every stage of the bike
will improve
uh processes batch okay okay yeah
that makes it very clear yeah thank you
so much that was that was an interesting
lecture thank you
okay you're welcome glad you enjoyed it
it's a cool system okay
sorry sorry can you hear me now yeah
yeah i didn't hear
i'm sorry about that i yeah sorry i was
listening i um
um i i realized we'd be going light i'm
going to try to make this question very
quick
um i've gotten to smart because you're
addressing my schedule
thank you thank you so much
so yeah uh yeah i really really
appreciate this lecture
uh spark is actually something that i'm
gonna use in my future job so i
appreciate you teaching this to me um
just one problem i'm not sure this
lecture will
really help you writing spark programs
no i i mean i did it as an intern really
not knowing what i was doing
but like this has helped me give like
get more context with it
so uh i guess the the quick question
with uh spark programs that i
um the way that i've understood spark
jobs is
how spark constructs a directed a
directed acyclic graph of all the tasks
yeah yep and this is what you talked
about with the wide partitions and
narrow partitions how like
yeah so i guess they're called
dependencies not partitions but
oh yep yep sorry okay okay
uh okay sorry um that
with rdds then i guess like okay this is
different terminology between
the dependencies are like these tasks in
the directed acyclic graph
of all the tasks but the rdds that
like each task in this graph is not
represented by this
rdd let me actually go back so maybe
this picture is the right and oh gosh i
appreciate you staying here please let
me know if you have to go
no no no no no no that's fine i got some
more time oh yeah yeah all right so
um uh so okay
so this is sort of an rdd correct let me
draw another color so that we can agree
this is an rdd okay an rdd has a bunch
of partitions
and here's another rdd
all right okay yep and
uh the arrows are basically sort of like
here's the same story
let me actually uh finish this picture
too on the side here's some more
partitions
here's the rdds boom boom
rdd boom boom rdd and then there are
transformations basically between
rdds correct and so in the arrows
when you pick another color you know
these errors
there's our transformations
got you and this is this is like part of
the directed acyclic graph of the spark
job
every single transformation leads to
like creating another rdd
that makes sense that that makes sense
okay and then the only thing is like
some of these arrows
are white and some of them are narrow
and the graph
from the graph you can't really tell
whether which ones are narrower or which
ones are
uh which transformations are sort of
narrow transformations and
white transformations you're talking
about the graph that's the spark program
actually like shows you
in there uh yeah this lineage graph you
can't tell
she got you okay okay that's uh here so
here
if you look at this lineage graph uh
like
this transformation that transformation
that transformation all that
transformation they're all looking like
narrow because it's a single arrow
but it's not really true right like the
last one for example must be uh
white one because it will collect
information from all
right okay
uh then i i guess i was wondering like
do you have
uh recommendations on resources for
things that can show me how spark
figures out how to construct the
directed acyclic graph to
to do all these tasks yeah look at the
excess is really the scanner that does
all this right and
yeah reading the paper like i i you know
i was trying to comprehend the paper as
best as i could but it's you know it's
it it's difficult but
yeah i know all these papers are
difficult to read so the scheduler uh
i think i would go back first to uh
mate's visas these doctoral thesis i'm
sure he has a capital on the
schedule gotcha gotcha all right i'll
okay and that'll show me just how spark
figures out how to make this graph