yes okay good
uh okay so the topic for today is uh
threats in rpc
uh this is our second lecture in uh 6824
uh and we're going to mostly look at
threats and rpc in the context of go
programming language that we're using in
the labs and in fact
most of this lecture is really tailored
uh towards
helping you do go programming for
the labs that's all you've done
uh hopefully the tutorial and uh did the
crawler exercise which we'll uh discuss
in quite a bit of detail uh later in the
lecture
but before jumping into the details let
me you know do a little bit more of cold
calling
to break the ice and get people to ask
questions
uh so maybe you can answer the question
you know where are you
and how did you enjoy the tutorial what
is your first impressions of
go maybe i'll uh how about
even development
i'm batman i'm in newton which is uh on
the outskirts of greater boston
um tutorial was interesting it was my
first exposure to
you know a non-object
non-object-oriented language um so it's
uh it's kind of a change a
change in framework that that was
interesting to adapt to
how about uh brandon wall
brandon are you there yeah i'm sorry i
was just finding
the mute button sorry what was the
question i just joined oh yeah
where are you and what is your first
impressions of go um
yeah it's i had used go before for an
internship but it's my first time
actually
dealing with the concurrency stuff i
like like really working with go routine
so
um kind of initially was like tricky to
think through like
um like as soon as the main thread ends
all to go routines are ended so kind of
working through those early kind of
conceptual issues but it's it's
interesting
to kind of think through okay how about
the conor prisby
connor are you there
oh yeah maybe try somebody else uh dory
shin
hi uh i'm in cambridge right now and
i found go to be real uh pretty
interesting i thought like
go through like the first part of the
tutorial i like
like learning about the for loops and
the way they do for loops i thought that
was pretty interesting and like
the way it's kind of structured i think
that i like
the threads and um i found to be
a little bit like more difficult about
like when it ended and like
when um like sometimes like the function
would end before all the routines like
ended so
that was like interesting to think about
and like i learned more about that so
it's pretty cool i liked it
well i hope all of you going to have a
very positive experience
with go uh in the semester
um and uh so let me say a little bit
like you know
why go um in principle you know there
are a lot of
programming languages that you could
have used for doing distributed
programming and goals are absolutely not
the only one
but some reasons why we uh why we chose
go in a24
uh you know first of all it has good
support
for frets and rpc
and those two are very important for
distributed programming
so it makes sense to you know ghost is a
good match for that
second reason that we like it a lot is
you know they have a garbage collector
and if you do a shared memory style
parallelism where multiple threads share
a structure or a variable then having a
garbage collector
is nice because then the frets don't
have to decide who's the last
fret that actually has a reference to
this memory and should therefore be
allocated
the guards collector just takes care of
all those problems
so that's convenient let's type safe
uh it is simple it's a
reasonable simple programming language
quite easy to learn
and in fact you know ideas hopefully you
got that experience with doing the go
tutorial that you know once you do the
go tutorial you mostly you know you got
most of go
um and then finally it actually has a
compiler so it's compiled
unlike python or uh
you know actually the compiler produces
actually youtube code and so the runtime
overhead is not as
large um i guess sort of the final
reason why
you're from e24 is in uh it goes because
i enjoy
writing go programs and so that may be
also an important reason
um so what i'm going to do is i'm going
to talk a little bit about
threads in general rpc in general and
you know talk a little bit about
uh different aspects of programming with
threads
some of this is pretty tutorial uh if
you have seen this before uh
you know my apologies i'm going to go
reasonably quickly through it
it's definitely not a comprehensive
introduction to concurrent programming
but just hopefully enough to remind you
what the issues are
and what you should look out for and
we'll hopefully spend some time
uh quite a bit of time on the crawler
and so
i'll share you uh the solution that i
have two solutions one using channels
and one's using
new texas and we'll go through both of
them
any questions so far before i dive in
okay let me get started with frets
so fred is basically short hands off the
threat of execution
uh in uh go a friend is called the go
routine
uh but everybody else basically in the
world goes uh calls a threat of threat
and so the way you think about it is
that like when you uh
do go run now the go will create a
process
you know on your operating system and
inside of that process is you know the
goal runtime system
when go starts it actually has one
thread of execution in the main fret
and but then it has primitives to create
new threads and so you can think about
this those are many many threads of
execution
you know running in parallel and you can
think about a single thread as basically
sort of a
sequential program running so the
program has a
program counter has its own stack
it has its own set of registers
and so this behaves like a sequential
program like you can
execute structure one then extrusion two
then structure three and four you're
gonna
make a procedure call allocate memory on
the stack i don't know
return from a procedure call do a
recursive call
all sorts of standards if you want to
tell your programming it's just like
happens about a as a sequential thread
basically
um the interesting thing is that you
know the threads may actually share
memory
uh with other threads
since uh all the threads are running in
the same address space
uh the same operating system address
space or the same process address space
uh they can actually share uh memory so
one thread can write
to location say you know 10 and then
another thread can actually read that
location 10.
and so that way they can actually
communicate information
one way to think about a fret 2 is to
think about it as a sort of an
abstraction that you know supported by
the run time and the runtime has a
number of operations on a threat so one
operation
uh you know what i've seen many times if
you've seen that many times is to
actually start a fraction of a creative
threat you know this is the goal
uh synthetic you know the go uh keyword
uh a thread can exit and generally this
means the axis is actually sort of
implicit like when the threat returns
uh uh from its
if uh you create a function using go uh
the go
uh keyword and you know you return out
of the function then implicitly the
thread actually exits
um the go runtime also has a couple
other uh sort of under the hoods
operations if you will
one it can actually stop a threat for
example if a threat writes to
a channel and there's no reader on the
channel yet then
the threat might get blocked and so the
go runtime sort of stops the threat you
know puts it aside
so that it can actually run another
thread on that on the processor
uh and then maybe later on resumes that
thread so
there's a third you know final primitive
that actually is resumed for this
and really what it means to stop resume
thread is basically taking the state of
the thread like the program counter
the stack pointer in the registration
put it inside
run another you know thread on the
processor and then at some point you
know decided to resume the processor
which means basically loading the
program count at the stack pointer and
the registers back into the process so
that
we started running so that's sort of a
very mechanical view
of what a thread is
so why you have threads in the first
place that seems like an important point
to
discuss
because in some ways the only thing the
threads do is make your life more
complicated as a programmer
like writing sequential code is actually
just easier than writing parallel code
and the main reason to have it and the
main reason we care a lot about it in
684 is to express a concurrency
and sort of three different you know
sort of two or two or three different
types of
currency that we actually care about so
you know think about our you know
process we've got our run time
with our threads running uh you know one
type of concurrency that we care a lot
about is io concurrency
so one of these threads you know that is
running here it might actually make a
network call
you know connect to another machine on
the network
uh you know to implement a distributed
application not like mapreduce
uh and you know as it makes the uh
call you know it's gonna be blocked you
know waiting for a response and while
it's blocked and they're waiting for a
response
everything will be nice to actually run
some other threads uh so that way you
know they're
sort of more we're done for example we
want to issue multiple requests to
multiple machines
uh sort of roughly in parallel you know
we can just do that we fire her off one
bill routine and fire another coaching
another go routine that all
kind of send and make connections to
other remote machines
that's one reason that we care a lot
about it io concurrency the second
reason that we care about it is you know
it allows for multi-core parallelism
so we have you know multiple cores in
our you know
computer or a processor then you know we
can have
one fret running on the one go routine
running on one core and another thread
or another go routine running on another
course just
straight in parallel and as for example
we implemented like a key value servers
then we could process
requests for different keys and the key
value servers used on different course
completely parallel you know increasing
our uh throughput so those are the two
main reasons that we care a lot about
uh precursory uh by threats there's a
sort of a third reason
you know there's a little bit of
convenience
there's going to be numerous cases in
the lab for example where we want to
uh have something happen periodically
maybe every second or every 200
milliseconds
and we can just launch a thread for that
or a go routine for that you just sleep
for 200 milliseconds you know does what
it needs to do and then
it goes back to sleep for 200
milliseconds and so it's convenient to
sort of have these
uh sort of background activities that
need to be done periodically and you can
express that using uh threats of course
you can express them in other ways the
threads are actually uh
convenient another question that comes
up
uh often and i think came up in some of
the lecture questions so today like how
many threads did you create
and i think the go designers the way
they want you to think about it is that
you should create as many threads as you
need
they're definitely not free they tie up
some memory because you know you have to
have a stack
uh there's a performance overhead we're
starting them
but you should think about them as very
lightweight
and so you should be encouraging or
you're encouraged to create
threads as you go any
questions about sort of this basic
reason for why to have friends
okay let me uh then you know as i said i
mentioned earlier
uh frets actually have challenges
for programming refresh has challenges
so let me talk a little bit about the
challenges
i'm not going to go in great amount of
depth here uh
i assume that you know there's a they
all make sense and they'll become more
clear if we
look at some of the examples and
probably the the main reason
uh that you know fred's actually are
challenging is that you can have race
conditions
and just like a basic example of a race
condition let's say you have two frets
you know here's t1
is t2 and they share
variable n let's say the initial value
is zero
and they both execute you know both
frets execute the statement
the form you know adds you know the
increment and by one
now of course you know you might think
that statement is an atomic operation or
like something that is indivisible but
it isn't right i mean there's a go
statement that gets compiled you know to
whatever instructions the processor is
executing
and so we cannot assume that that's an
atomic instruction and in fact
you know uh it's uh it could consist of
basically like a load
you know to which stores the end the
content of end into
a register then increment register and
then you know sort of register back into
memory
and so if you're very unlucky you know
if the two threads basically try to
both execute this particular instruction
then we can have a very
you know unfortunate sequence of events
where like both frets
you perform the load instruction
you load the variable in you know
registered let's say r0
you know here also in r0
now they increment it so r0 becomes one
and then they write it back you know to
you know
they do restore instruction that
actually results you know stores results
back into the variable n
in memory and uh so if this happens at
this particular
uh in this scenario where you know this
happens to be like truly concurrently
you know what is the value of n after
these two threads that both in increment
just one yeah it's one and what what is
this
value supposed to be or what would you
expect it to be
two yeah expect it to be two right and
so one is definitely not equal to two
and
uh there's a bug uh and so
and this is like you know the sort of
the heart of race conditions uh
which uh is not you know if in an
unforced uh
an unfortunate sequence of events where
threats share you know state
uh the updates actually might not be
reflected correctly
and of course most of the time this will
work out fine because you just have to
be in the sort of very
uh sort of this very specific case
before it shows up
so for example i think one uh one of you
reported like oh i
didn't have my walks or my race you know
my walks in order
and oh my program just worked fine and
that's actually the the real
issue with race conditions they
typically just work fine but sometimes
it goes wrong
so the two ways to address race
conditions
the first way is to avoid sharing
don't share variables and
this is one style of programming that
you know go encourages
by using channels you know channels you
just communicate values but you don't
really directly share memory
so that's one way of doing it another so
avoid sharing is one big approach the
other approach is actually to use locks
you know to maybe make a sequence of
instructions an atomic operation
now we'll talk a lot more about that in
a second uh one of the things that i
want to point out that is really cool
about
what is usual tool is go actually have a
race detector
and you know most of the labs that you
you were doing would encourage you to
basically run go
using the dash race flag and
that will actually not catch every
possible race but it does an extremely
good job of actually identifying races
and so you should by default run go with
the race detector enabled
okay so that's one challenge with reds
the second challenge with threats is
actually coordination
so it's often the case that one has to
you know one friend must wait on another
fret before something is accomplished
uh you know the number of the go
exercises in the tutorial you know have
that kind of
form and there's two ways you know go
actually through primitives for
dealing with that one again channels you
know channels basically
allow you to communicate and to
coordinate at the same time
or uh you know which i'll talk a little
bit later about you know
condition variables
and both can be useful i'll talk a
little bit more about that uh and then
finally you know so the
final challenge uh big sort of
conceptual challenge is uh you can
get that lock so if one thread waits in
the
uh like t1 waits on t2 and t2 waits from
t1 you know
for example to release your lock or
before some other sequencing you can
basically sort what i call deadly
embrace
you know where both were waiting on the
other and as a result nothing makes for
progress uh the trivial way of getting
you know say deadlock
in a go would be you know you have a
single thread there's no other threads
at all
and you're right now to your channel
and that will block now that one thread
until somebody else
you know reads some other friend reads
from the channel but if there's no other
thread at all you know that will result
in a deadlock
this is like the simplest possible
deadlock possible
um and you know go actually will catch
this case and we'll run
a razor runtime error saying like no
frets can run you know you have a
deadlock
uh but there can be more complicated
deadlocks you know we're both involved
in multiple threads and
as you're going through the labs and in
the semester you i'm sure you'll run
into some
so take a little bit of a step back here
and think about
you know go for you know these
challenges
uh that i just talked about
roughly speaking uh goes sort of two
plans
to handle these concurrency challenges
and one plan is you know basically
around channels
and there's another plan basically
around locks
and condition variables
and the way i think about it uh you know
some people are quite dogmatic about
this i think one plan is better than the
other plan
uh my general approach here is like i
use what the plan that is most suitable
for the case that i'm looking at
uh or that i'm running into and
generally you know
i have no sharing uh and basically i
need two frets basically to communicate
but i don't really share any memory i
tend to use the channels
uh if there are two threads actually do
share memory uh because it's convenient
to share memory for example i write a
key value servers and i want to share
the key value table
then i use locks
and condition variables
uh and so uh you know my general
approach is not so to be dramatic and
you know take whatever approach you know
that actually is most convenient for
for the problem at hand um
the tutorial does a pretty good job of
actually uh
teaching you about uh channels mentioned
logs doesn't say much about condition
variables
uh so i i think it's worthwhile uh to
talk a little bit about condition
variables to
make sure that you're aware that they
exist
and i'm going to do that using a tiny
little example
to sort of illustrate the issues and
attending a little example is
we have a you know sort of a little bit
inspired uh as well
you know inspired by the labs you know
have a friend t1
uh and uh t1 needs to collect some
number of votes you know from remote
machines
and uh for example needs to decide that
it has a majority
uh so that it actually proceeds to
commit you know some value
and you'll see that later in like this
shows up in the raft lab uh
as one of the primitives that you need
uh and so
to do that you know the t1 will fork you
know other threats
you know let's say t2 and t2 amazingly
does something expensive like you know
talk to some remote machine to actually
get its vote
and then you know report back you know
that vote to t1 and t1 basically i need
to collect all the votes head them up
and then assume that their majority then
you know declare sort of victory
so this is a pretty straightforward
simple program but it gives you a little
bit of
allows me to illustrate you a couple of
issues so i'm going to switch
to another screen
can everybody see this
so here i have a very simple
uh implementation of this program uh the
vogue thing uh and again it's a little
bit of a toy example but just hopefully
gets the
points across uh the two variables
shared here
uh count and danish count accounts
number three
finish you know accounts when we're done
um
uh so you know there's a loop you know
going for 10
uh creating a go creating a
you know launching on
an anonymous function and an anonymous
function you know concurrently
you know calls this function request
vote the request basically you know
simulates you know doing a long
expensive operation on some remote
machine and the way it simulates it is
by just going to sleep
it walks for a little while then it
returns and then
you know the returns voted yes then you
know the count goes up
and we count the fact that actually we
had one more uh fred voting
and then we're done and so that's uh so
we fork off ten threads you know the
interview and request vote
and report the results and then at the
end we'll check if the
count is small revive you know we know
that we failed
uh we lost the election uh and if we uh
have votes equally larger than five you
know we basically
won the election right so this is sort
of the simple uh it's a very simple
program
uh does it all make sense let me run it
just for the
kicks
and you know we run it a couple times
sometimes we lose sometimes win you know
makes sense
um and so this program looks you know
working
and correct is it actually correct
sorry was the question uh whether this
program is actually correct
yeah it seems to produce results um
i i think there's a race condition isn't
there like you have
all of these different threads um
incrementing the count and finished
variables
yeah um and it's also um
it's not clear to me that finished
necessarily always reaches 10.
um is it possible that it doesn't
uh let me let me take this one one by
one and just go over to your first point
this is the one one hours after
uh you know clear house uh this is again
the fact you know we have two variables
here correct uh
you know uh count divinist they're
actually by different go routines so
this is immediately a red flag
it could be a serious problem here like
as soon as you have you know a variable
that has access to or modified
and by two different goal routines you
know there's got to be a problem
and so you know it's interesting to run
the race detector and see if it actually
catches it right
and as you expected you know to go the
race detector tells you exactly you know
there is indeed you know some problems
here with this uh program
and you know list the line numbers you
know where things actually can go wrong
uh so that gives you actually a pretty
good clue that something is not
up to snuff this program and so we're
gonna like repair it in small steps
and uh you know that will uh hopefully
shed some more light on
concurrent programming so let me you
know here's my second solution to this
program
uh and in this case um i'll talk about
channels in a little bit later because i
wanted to illustrate the
uh locks and condition variables first
because i've got less emphasis in the
tutorial
um so you know simple solution you know
you go
correct you introduce a lock uh the lock
is completely independent of the
variables
uh and uh and you follow some convention
which says like well this lock mu
protects counted finish and so whenever
you know you access and count the finish
and basically you have to wrap that into
a lock and an unlock statement and so
here we see two
like this is the go function because it
runs concurrently uh
and after you know the request code it's
about to update the vote and finish so
we take a lock out
and then go has this nice feature you
know uh called the defer statement
but if you exit the basic block you know
we'll
run the function that is uh declared by
the defer or that
after the key word deferred and so this
means like when we execute
we leave the go function here will
automatically unlock
this is convenient because then you
won't forget to unlock and so it's nice
to do that write a point where you do
the lock
and so you can write immediately before
it lock and then you don't have to worry
about
if there are multiple exit pass out of
the go routine or at a function
uh that you forget to unlock so now
you know we're basically in a critical
section where we hold the lock
we update vote and count and then of
course the function returns and unlocks
automatically and similarly at the
uh at the you know at the end you know
we gotta
uh every time we access you know count
to finish
uh since they share it you know we need
to surround it with locks and then you
know a simple way of doing it we could
have written d for unlocking or two in
the body
but we've been fine all right so we can
actually run this program
let's see yeah and so
we run it you know the race detector
seems to be happy uh so
hopefully we'll have a better program
all right
um so i just have a question here about
scoping
yeah so it seems that when we have the
anonymous function then we have this mu
and we have uh the count and we have the
finished and it seems that the anonymous
function has access to
that we're defined outside of the
function so how do looping rules work
yeah uh you're building any an anonymous
function
any variable that's you know used inside
of the function that's not declared
inside of the function
basically result uh points to variables
outside of the outer scope
so statically scoped what about the
scope
of uh like the mutex
how many times you have to declare that
or and what's the scope of it
i guess the scope of the the first
statement is this this block
one basic block you know i mean like
when you actually declare like the mutex
data structure i guess it's like any
other variable
it has the same scope as finish or count
so it applies to any variable declared
in the rest of the
yeah the way to think about it is that
uh the
the mutex is not directly associated
with any variable it's just a lock
you know it's like a name and it's up to
you as a programmer to decide like what
that lock protects
so they're two independent concepts
what happens what happens if you use i
in the um
go routine that won't work right you
need to pass that in
yeah so whatever yeah that's a good
question and then the number of number
of you asked that uh for email too so
what are you what happens to like if we
use i here
you know what you know do something with
it like whatever
count is i uh is this a good plan or not
what value of i will be using when this
fret actually happens to run
if the gold starts to function function
that will run at some point
what value of i will using whatever
i happens to be at the time which is
being
uh changed by the for loop outside yeah
correct so
you know so this is not so great that's
probably not what we intended right we
probably intended the eye that we
whatever for that particular loop
iteration right
so how do we want to if we don't have to
solve that how what would we do
you could um add it as a parameter to
that
function and pass it in so it gets
evaluated when you create to go
go routine yeah okay so we could write
this
and then pass it actually in right and
then a point what happens then at the
point we have to create
the go routine i is being captured and
then passed in
okay okay
um how are the local variables allocated
like if if captain finished are like
local variables wouldn't they like
be destroyed after the main function
exits or like if this wasn't made by
like another function what it's like
that hitting function exit before the
corrugation yeah
they're in principle allocated in stack
uh and
you know the room with the other
functions have just memory addresses
references to them
and so it's indeed the case it's main
returns then these
you know these stack allocated variables
are gone
so typically what you'll see is that in
a go program you would allocate them in
you know on the heap you know using new
like if you make a new truck
or whatever so would you get a
segmentation fault then or would it just
you would get air okay
i have a question i actually remember
this is the correct
uh like way to do it or not but instead
of passing it in would it be possible to
as the first line in the for loop do i
colon equals i
um and then you're like you have a i
don't know how the scoping works within
the like block of the for loop because i
think that should create
a new variable i that the go routine can
access that isn't being updated again
right you can do that
that can help instead of passing it in
it kind of makes it look ugly to me
okay well i i like the passing in but
that's another way of doing it i'll
show you an example later
uh so this summer somebody asked
actually you know do we get a
a segmentation fault we're not
immediately going to get a segmentation
fault i should take that back
because basically one thread will hold
still hold a reference and so the
garbage collector will not delete the
object yet
right only when the last thread actually
uh only when no fret holds a reference
you know the will the garbage collector
delete the object
and this is one of the cool things about
having garbage collected language and
shared memory programming
you don't have to worry about that
scenario
okay uh there's a
yeah uh would could this code like
deadlock
because like if we if like the go
routines
like the first four loop will exit and
then the second one will like
oh yeah no never mind okay
uh there are definitely some issues that
are not ideal yet so let me
actually talk about them uh one of them
is that like this particular loop
it's a little bit annoying right like
this this forward loop is there's
nothing else than waiting until count
reaches
five for finished and the way it does is
by just spinning
right so it just locks it locks it looks
at the value quickly unlocks it and
spins around again so it basically is
spinning on the processor doing really
nothing it'd be nice to express that in
a little bit better way so that like
basically the go can sort of give up the
core
again so that another threat can run and
so the way you can do that is using
condition variables
and so this is my the next
implementation
um uh or actually i'll show you one
other implementation well one way to do
that is a little bit not
you know not so nice as for example and
what somebody suggested this
um is to actually sleep for a little
while so instead of like
uh giving up the spinning like crazy
just sleep one and period
sleep for a period and then come back of
course the solution will work but the
downside of it is that you know how
how long should you sleep right you
really would like to be the case that
you know soon for example as this guy
reaches five uh
then you know you wake you know you
could wake up the this particular you
know the main thread
and so i was jumping ahead a little bit
but uh
so that's what condition variables are
for um
and you know here's a solution with
condition variables
uh so uh we allocated a new
condition here as a condition variable
is allocated it's associated with this
particular lock
we'll see in a second why this is
important and
you know basically the main thread what
it does now uh
it you know grabs the log because it
needs to grab the lock to look at count
and finished otherwise that could be
race conditions
and then if you know the condition is
still not true
it just calls weight on this condition
variable
and what that does is actually that
atomically goes to sleep
as well as releasing the lock that is
associated with the condition variable
you know since you know mu is actually
really associated with the condition
variable
can't wait basically unlocks the
lock and goes to sleep in an atomic
operation
and when it returns you know from count
weight it will actually hold the lock
again
so the caller knows we're absolutely
sure that if conjugate returns it will
actually held the lock again
and so it's safe again to look at count
and finish and then call wait again
okay so basically you know this friend
will go to sleep
um and then the go routines that you
know
are collecting the votes you know the
same code as before
my lock and unlock or defer to unlock
and then when you're done
you know updating count to finish uh
there are two primitives on the
condition variable one is signal and one
is broadcast
and broadcast basically uh sigma wakes
up one waiter and broadcast weights of
all waiters
you know there's only one waiter here so
we could have used either one of them
and so basically when it reaches you
know five you know at some point or ten
then you know the so every time finish
is incremented you know the
main thread will be woken up you can
check the condition
and then keep going okay
so this is convenient sort of you can
think about condition variables as a
coordination primitive you know between
uh two different threads and they're
particularly convenient when you're
actually using locks
you know for to protect your shared
state
so here's the same uh implementation
uh of this program using channels uh
and more or less works the same way
except of course no locks
uh but the main thread creates a channel
passes the the go routine the anonymous
function
that's being created as a separate
thread and writes basically the request
vote to the channel and then the main
thread basically blocks here correct
when it starts reading from the channel
once it actually get something where
something is written to the channel will
unblock
you know look at the value and if it's
true and add up
and uh ottawa and always increments
finish
and what's going on here correct is we
don't need locks because count and
finish are not shared there's only one
thread that actually updates
uh count and finish and that's the main
thread
okay um the
uh and this this you know the the name
the the sort of request that threats you
know all basically just write to this uh
channel they write concurrently perhaps
to the channel but the channels are one
of the things that go that actually
frets save so multiple threads can
actually write to the channel
um any questions about this
about the solution
what was the thing about like having a
buffer
for the channel yeah so uh normally when
you write into the channel and nobody's
reading from the channel or no thread is
reading from the channel then the center
will immediately be blocked
you can specify that the channel has a
buffer of a of 10 or 20
and uh that allows the channel to have
multiple values
in in eight to four labs i've never used
uh buffered channels and one of two
three times i did it you know i
regretted it
so in general i i don't use it
but this is a really important point uh
this but this program is actually still
not very good
um so for example when uh
you know it doesn't matter in practice
in this particular example but it's not
in in in some collapse if we could bite
you
uh as soon as it reaches count five what
will happen
it stops listening for um this new
channel
so any other threads um are just going
to be blocked yeah so basically this
means like if the first five
threads voted uh yes then the next five
threads will be
blocked in this channel correct you know
they'll be hanging around
uh and uh in this case it won't be a
problem because as most of you guys
have most observed like that if the main
thread exits it actually cleans up all
the other threads too
uh but for example if this would be a
long running surface
uh this would be not good basically
we're leaking threats here you know
they're sitting blocked on the side
uh doing nothing uh in that channel and
so that's quite inconvenient
and uh this is something to watch out
for uh and this showed up in the crawler
i think for many uh people in uh and
[Music]
there's the flip side of this is that if
the main threat
enters too early before any of the
request votes are done uh then you also
have a problem
and so there's this management of
threats that actually is
often a tricky issue
is there a way to kill the thread
without um exiting from me
uh well you can send it a variable or a
value on some
channels saying like please exit but you
have to coordinate it yourself
i want to go back to one of the things
that actually is cool about
condition variables is that um
in principle you might think that the
same issue exists here uh
where like this fred actually runs and
uh
in this thread and
it might get blocked like example if you
know we reached you know five
you know this main thread will you know
perceive doing its thing
uh while the other guys are still maybe
actually sitting in here
uh but notice these in this case they
won't be blocked uh
because you know well grab the lock then
you know does the thing does a broadcast
and the broadcast is actually not a
blocking operation so
unlike you know writing to a channel
that is a blocking operation if nobody
is listening
the con broadcast is not a blocking
operation so this actually works out in
this particular program you know by
itself
correctly okay
okay good any further questions about
you know these
two examples just to do
okay then let's talk about the crawler
and so the crawler is also a more
realistic example of concurrent
programming
yeah and just to remind you um uh
you know basically the idea is that you
know you start out with a url for some
web page
uh you fetch you know that just defects
the webpage so it might have more urls
and you basically proceed you know then
fetching those web pages
you know looking at those urls and you
keep going
the idea is to crawl basically the whole
internet you know for all the web pages
that are
exist and of course you know some urls
might point back
to a web page that you already visited
and so the goal is to actually not visit
the
same webpage twice
and so the goal of the exercise is a
couple of goals that you want to achieve
one is io concurrency
the defense operation is uh may take a
long time you know maybe it's a
web page that sits on the other side of
the world your uh maybe goes over slow
networks
and while your one thread is sort of
fetching that page you know you would
like to be able to fetch other
uh other uh other pages
another goal is this correctness goal or
you know performance goal
namely you know if that's one affect
your url once
and you know presumably you'd also like
to exploit multiple cores
you know if you have multiple course you
can do more comparable
okay so uh what i'd like to
do uh before actually uh
talking about the current solutions
first let me show you
uh a simple serial solution uh so that
we uh
have something to talk about as a
baseline
so uh something i have free solutions in
here
so you just
run them go run a serial solution
one with mutexes and one with channels
uh you know you see that
more or less they produce the same
result you know two found one missing
two found
the only difference is that the order of
the output is slightly different once in
a while and of course it has to do with
concurrency
okay so the main function
calls in serial with the starting url
the fetcher
and then an empty map and then
the serial solution is basically a sort
of standard
sequential recursive solution we'll
first check
if we already visited the url that's
passed into us
if we did then we returned immediately
otherwise we mark it as visit
we'll fetch the url that gives us a
bunch of new urls
uh we look through all the urls and call
basically zero
again right and this is your sequential
solution actually what i expected
and you know your goal was to basically
write a current version of this
um and so uh uh
what i like to do is actually to make
the class a little bit interactive uh i
want to go switch over to breakout rooms
and what we're going to do is basically
put
four to five of you in a single breakout
room
for about 10 minutes and i would like
you to do is
share your solution with each other and
discuss it so maybe
the best way to go about it is that one
of you
you know you get into the room one of
the persons in the room
you know basically screen shares their
solution and discusses you know one the
issues that he or she ran into
and other people can comment or share
other solutions and just to get into the
discussion and meet some other students
in the class
any questions about that
okay good uh let me go back to
sharing my screen again can everybody
see my screen again
yep looks good good good thank you
okay so hopefully that was interesting
um
and let me you know talk about you know
the
solutions that i have uh they're posted
on the schedule page
if you haven't uh uh you can look
uh concurrently with me if you want to
um
there should you know let me walk
through the
new text version first and then i'll
walk through the
channel one second uh so here's the
the mutex one the mutex one uh
declaration struct
you know with that has both the map and
the mutex and
the map needs to be protected by mutex
because there's gonna be concurrent
access to the map
so map by itself is not fred say it's up
to the programmer to actually make the
map fret safe and the control mutex one
works sort of similar to the serial one
except for whenever their start stage
basically takes a walk out now so we'll
take the lock you know we look at the
if the url already has been fetched if
it hasn't been fed
the market has now been fetched or
hasn't been fetched and we're in lock
and we kept this already valued to
decide whether we should return or not
and then uh you know we this go routine
starts fetching uh a page it gets a
bunch of urls back
and then for every uh url back uh
it creates a new go routine here on this
side
uh passes in the url that that go
routine is supposed to
fetch and crawl uh
the only sort of other interesting thing
here uh
is that it uses something called weight
group and weight group is a very
convenient primitive to keep track how
many
threads you still have active and when
you can terminate
and this was a really sort of a big
issue in this particular assignment that
if you terminated too early then you
didn't crawl
the web pages and so you need to keep
track of whether you're
whether there's still outstanding web
pages to be crawled uh saying weight
group does it very easily
uh basically every time you call a
friend you call uh ad
and then when the threat terminates uh
you call
done and you know you could conveniently
do that in the defer statement
and then the main thread that is waiting
for all the frequency terminal just
cause weight and weight will return
until every fret that was started for
every every add one
if all those threads actually have been
uh exited
so that's the mutex
version
and you can think about sync weight as
sort of being internally implemented
using
a condition variable
okay let me look at the uh
the channel version uh so here's the
channel version is basically sort of
working organized as the mapreduce
uh lab where there's a coordinator and
workers
and so uh we start off you know we start
off creating a coordinated thread
and the way we do that actually is we
make a channel
and then we pass the channel into the
coordinator uh the coordinator of course
has to start with a url the beginning
url so we need to
supply that on the channel that's the
most convenient thing to do as we'll see
in a second
uh but you know to send it on the
channel we basically have to create a go
routine because otherwise
you know we deadlock here so we and this
is our typical thing we
could go to just to send that value on
the channel
so let's look at the coordinator
here's the coordinator it doesn't use
any locks at all
because you know the the data structures
that uh
uh there's no data structures actually
being shared like fetched
you know the map that actually keeps
track of which uh urls has manufactured
is actually only accessed within the
coordinator
so the coordinator got a you know when
we called it initially
uh we got a it has a one url
it checks the fetch map and then for
every url
then it goes basically you know cycles
through reach the
channel using a range statement and
basically what this does is it just
keeps reading the channel and just grabs
the next value it gives an x value grabs
the next value so basically it grabs the
url we know there's one in it because
you know we put it on
when we created it and then for that url
we sort of roughly do the same thing
as the uh
concurrent as the mutex one uh
you know we see if the url has already
been fetched
if it hasn't been such then we're done
otherwise we'll create
a go worker to actually fetch that url
and we keep track of how many
outstanding workers we have so n is
counting the number of workers and only
when n is zero
uh do we terminate the coordinator
uh to make sure that basically we have
fetched all the
web pages that we're supposed to be
affecting so let's look at the worker
worker basically calls fetch you know
this of course not happens completely in
parallel with any other workers
if it actually fetches some url from
that
webpage it basically writes all those
urls to the channel
and so the coordinator will get all
those channels through its range
statement
and then when it's done you know writing
all the urls through the channel
then the coordinator uh the worker exits
and that will
you know at some point uh decrease
you know and and then at the end
and that's it basically okay
so those are the two solutions uh any
questions about these
is it all clear
there is a question in chat ah okay uh
let me
get my chat list back backup
okay so the question is when ch has a
value in it and all other threads be
idle uh it is the case that
the since this is not a buffer channel
that you know there's going to be only
one request in the channel at the time
and so all the frets you know will be
appending to the channel one by one
but doesn't that make the program
sequential because no two threads are
running in parallel
except the main thread and one well the
the fetchish
will still happen in parallel and those
are presumably the expensive operation
right those go out across the internet
got it thank you
okay let me switch back to my other
screen and
talk a little bit about rpc since that's
the other thing tool that you need
for the labs
i'm not going to say a ton about it but
there's a
rpc which stands for remote procedure
call
and basically the goal you know the goal
of an
ipc system uh like the one that go has
is to make sort of rpcs
behave roughly similar to procedural
calls
local procedure calls that you execute
on the stack right and so
the goal is that for example if you have
a client in rpc
terminology the caller is typically
called the client and the
the callee is called the server saying
you have a function in
you know fn you know we're calling with
x and y
and then at the server there's the
implementation of this function
and so there's a function n whatever x
comma y
int and you know it returns
you know whatever does some computation
but maybe use this returns
uh x plus y
right and so uh what we like to like to
have happen or like the model that we
would like to
sort ourselves to think about is that
when the client calls this function
uh fn uh the rpc system will
make sure that there's an infra
corresponding amount of information
happening on the server side
uh passes the arguments x and y you know
to the server
the code runs on the server uh it you
know
returns a result you know you see and
that result is then
communicated back to the client and you
know and and then
fn will resume and will return and the
client will return uh
we'll resume with you know the x plus y
in
the value of x plus y and z right so
this looks like you know even though the
programs are running on different
computers
you know they're not sort of a hard
boundary here uh it looks like you know
they they uh make sort of regular
procedure calls
um and we'll see in a second that
actually uh
we can make a lot of similarities but
it's possible to make them very behave
very similar
but we'll see there's also a sort of a
fundamental difference that actually has
to really do with distributed computing
but before getting there let me first
sort of
uh sketch out how you can make this work
and this is sort of roughly you know
what go does too so
so the way you know to think about it is
that when the client
near our program and when the client
calls the function f
n with x and y in it uh what it does is
actually calls something what's called a
stop
and the stop is basically a local
function you know called f n
and with the two arguments declared with
x and y
and basically what the stop does
you think this is a stop procedure and
what the stop procedure basically does
it
builds a message uh you know saying you
know which function needs to be called
you know the arguments of the function
you know the types of the fun
of those arguments the values of these
arguments
et cetera et cetera and then uh
what the uh stuff does actually it sends
it over to network
you know to a corresponding stub at the
server
so the server receives this message
and basically you know takes this
message
and then marshall or marshall this is a
the
term that's being used to basically
convert uh
values uh from sort of to bite arrays
and from by the rays back
to values and then calls you know this
function
fn at the server here's our fnx
blah blah blah
all right so the stub basically calls
the function the function returns back
into this stuff this stuff marshalls you
know the response value
like the z x plus y
um and since the back you know to the
climb stop and the client stop is still
waiting so basically the client stuff
the way it actually works it sends out
the request and then waits for the
response and so when the response comes
back in
you know it unmarshals
and then you know returns the value to
the clients right so basically
these two stops uh sort of make a
remote procedure called look like a
regular procedure called you know for
almost you can't tell
and the key uh and
these stops are generally you know
automatically generated and so the
compiler and like
in case of the cocoa powder that will
generate these stuff for you uh
and uh do the uh marshalling and then
marshall your arguments for you
um and um and that's how it goes
also so when you're doing it from the
server to the client there's also
another stub again
you basically return back to that first
stop so
this stop this makes a procedure call to
basically calls the procedure fm
that procedure returns right into the
stop because the stop
called it oh it's the same stuff that it
goes in
exactly got it okay
okay so uh let me show you sort of how
this plays out inside of go
and by showing you a very simple
key value server
and you'll see you know it doesn't look
exactly what our procedure calls but it
is
pretty close uh so the typical thing is
that you know you actually declare
a typical convention for the main goal
is that you declare
the arguments as trucks and so we're
going to implement two procedures
two remote procedures one is put and one
is get and put is basically
fruit rx is the arguments to the put
input replies the response
similarly and there's a get rx with the
request or the arguments to the request
get procedure and then reply and so let
me first look at the server
so here's our two functions you know
actually the
two functions that we're going to be
calling on the server
um i think i'll skip down for that for a
second
so maybe actually you know
let me talk about them a little bit so
this is the client site
so the client calls a function get and
uh what
inside of get you know you this function
actually connects to the server i'll see
in a second what that means
um it fills in the arguments it
allocates a response and then calls this
procedure client
it calls call you can think about this
as a generic stun
that basically takes the method that
needs to be called on the server and the
arguments and the reply and so call
always has three arguments
the method the argument and the response
and then call internally we'll send
marshall the arguments
send the message to the server over the
connection
and wait for the response the reply when
the replies comes in the reply structure
will be filled in
by the call stub and then when that's
done then return out of the call
call and basically put looks exactly the
same way
great and so on the server side let's
see how that is implemented
the server has a key value map this is
nothing else than a regular go map
and
let me see actually the key values
trucked
i declared it somewhere
oh sorry it's right above it so there's
a structure called kv
that actually has a mutex and a map in
it and the map is like where we're going
to do the put and get operations on
and there's another little preamble that
you need to sort of write you know to
sort of set up a server uh but here it
is uh
you know you basically uh allocate a new
server
object and then this is sort of the key
operation
rpc register kv will register basically
all the methods that are implemented on
the key fee struct
with the rpc server with one twist
the method only the capital named
uh only the
the methods with the capital uh will
actually be reported
and so basically go uses capital names
to indicate
public you know methods and uh a method
with a small
small caps is in private method so only
you know basically rpc register
exports only capitalized methods so for
example here's a method below here's our
get method
you know it has a capital letter and by
calling register that method is now
callable by a client that connects to
this server
so the server internally you know
basically uh it creates a tcp connection
uh and waits on the tcp connection to to
get a request or a new
connection request for the tcp
connection and then calls rpc
servcom to serve that tcp connection and
basically
every message that comes in over that
you know connection
it will automatically find the right
method you know that is associated with
the message
and called that method with the
unmarshaled arguments and
marshall's reply so for example if the
client calls get you know connects to it
double call
makes this connection into existence and
then if the client calls
call with a get then this get function
will be run
and as you can see in the get function
first thing it does it actually takes a
walk out because
multiple clients could be calling the
server and so there will be multiple go
routines running at the same time
perhaps invoking get and put and so they
will manipulating the
the map concurrently and so we need to
make sure that you know those
uh that is done in an atomic way
and so therefore use locks so the get
function
looks up the key into the map it looks
the key
looks of the key in the map and returns
basically the value
if there's no entry in the map it will
return error
no key otherwise it will return the
appropriate
value and that's it and so on the server
side when this get function returns
it will marshal its response sends
response back to the client the client
will
cite of it will unmarshal it and
actually return it to the caller
okay since that makes sense so that's
sort of a
dirt simple key value server in action
okay i want to make one more point which
is an important point
and in the end
what's important to think about is what
the rfpc semantics are
under failures
um and so the different types of
semantics possible
something is called at least once
and this all has to do with like what
does the client do if the server fails
so let's say the client sends the
request the server crashes
and uh of course now at some point the
client will time out
and just doesn't know whether the
operation actually happened or not
happened
and at least once rpc semantics it means
that the client will automatically retry
and will keep going until the next has
executed at least once
uh the downside of course of at least
once is that you know the same operation
might be executed multiple times so
example if you do a put you know the put
might be actually executed multiple
times in at least one rpc system
so that's not appropriate for many
applications so another
type of semantics that's common in rpc
systems is it most wants
so the corresponding survey request
actually executed either
uh zero times or once
but no more than once and the way you
know that is typically implemented is by
filtering duplicates and you will
actually be doing that
in uh in later labs
that could could be the case that
actually both requests actually come
through
uh maybe the network is like a temporary
petition then the server actually gets
both requests and the server has to
arrange that
it detects a recent request and doesn't
execute it twice
now of course ideally you might actually
want exactly once
because that's actually what your normal
procedure call would be due right like
if you call a procedure in uh
your server in a normal sequential
program it actually executes exactly
once it's never possible to be at least
once
at most once this turns out to be
actually very hard to arrange
uh this requires you know uh you
basically have to maintain state on disk
uh and so the tent tends to be expensive
and in fact you know in practice very
few rpc systems are exactly once
although in the labs you're going to
build actually one in lab three
you're gonna actually build an rpc
system that's basically exactly once
okay in practice
goes rpc system is at most wants so if
you do a call
and you do the call across the tcp
channel the tcp channel will make sure
that there are no duplicates
uh and so and the rfpc system
uh will either execute once or none at
all
and then in the case and return an error
uh and then of course the application
may retry but now it's the application's
responsibility to
uh deal with the problems with
duplication and failed messages
okay so here's the sort of the key point
correct the fact that there are failures
basically makes you know rpcs
not identical to procedure calls so even
though the goal is to make them look as
similar as possible
they're actually not identical and
really the thing that exposes the
differences
is the the failures or the survey
crashing
any quick questions about this quick
intro for rpc
okay if not then i'm going to stop the
lecture here so that people that need to
go or students that need to go to the
next class they can go to the next class
i'll be hanging around so if there's any
more questions i'll be happy to uh
to answer them and i'll stick around for
a little while
in the meantime enjoy lab one and good
luck with it