okay here
good afternoon good evening or good
night or good morning
uh whatever time zone you're in and
watching this lecture um
just double checking on sound uh people
can hear me
yes yes okay sure okay uh i'm going to
talk about two things today i want to
finish off our discussion a farm
and then i'll talk about spark and just
to remind everybody else
or everybody where we were farm were
talked about executing a transaction
without any failures
and we looked at one example of whether
actually the
transaction provided uh external
consistency or
strict serializability and
so i want to talk about one more example
uh to look about
to talk about serializability and then
uh let's talk a little bit about fault
tolerance
but before doing so uh it's probably
helpful to remind uh
my reminds ourselves exactly you know
how a
transaction works uh if there are no
failures
uh and so in farm an application goes
through for two phases the execution
phase
uh where it fetches objects from uh
different
shards and then the commit phase and so
we look back at this uh
picture here you know where there is in
the execution phase three objects are
being
uh three objects are being read
you know one from each uh different
chart uh you know we have shard one gr2
and chat three
and every chart has one backup so this
system can tolerate one failure
uh so the objects are read the the two
objects are being modified
uh as we see in the second and then
uh once you know the the free object red
and two are modified
the application might decide to commit
and then so the whole commit phase goes
into action
so this is this whole story from uh
steps one through
five and in step one
uh the transaction takes out locks on
the objects that
have been written written so we see here
there have been two objects that have
been
uh written to by the transaction and so
we're propagating what's called locked
records
you know to uh every primary
so every primary is going to have a lock
record for this
transaction and for the objects involved
in
that transaction so and the lock records
you know contains
an object id which identifies the object
uniquely
a version number so at the time that
uh the transaction reads an object
it gets back a version number in fact it
gets back this
64-bit number which in the top is a log
bit and the rest is the version number
and then a new value
uh so you know primary one and primary
two
is going to have frame one is gonna have
a lock record for object one primary two
is gonna have to lock uh
object for primary for object two then
there's a separate phase uh for the
validation of
the read-only operations or operations
or
objects that are only be read but not
modified
and as we can see in those in this
validation step
the dotted lines represent one-sided
rdmas
and as we talked about on tuesday you
know those basically involved no server
involvement you know the
the sender can just read a an object out
of the memory of the
server with actually without actually
having to interrupt you know the
computation that's actually running on
the server
so they had to be very fast unlike you
know these operations that we saw here
which are actually right rdmas
they're cool too in the sense that you
know you get the right you know to
the appends you know to this log record
without actually interrupting the server
but the server actually has to process
these log records and
um then the server in this case once it
actually processes one of these lock
records
uh you know it tries to take out the
lock if it succeeds trying out until
they take the lock
the version number hasn't changed or the
lock bit or no other transaction is
taking the lock
then it will reply back you know using
another one
uh right rdma saying okay
and so you know we see that on the
acquiring the lock requires action on
the server
but the one-sided rdma for reads
validation doesn't require any action on
the server
then there's the if
everything turns out to be okay so the
transaction is basically able to
obtain all its right locks and validate
the reit
operations it actually makes a decision
to commit
and to commit it uh first communicates
to every backup
the object the change
so right to commit backup record
and it appends that to every uh to the
backups of the
objects that have been modified and
again you know it's basically a copy of
the
bach record you know oid goes in there
the version number goes
in there and the new value
once you know all the backups you know
have
uh we have reported that they actually
have a copy of the
object now we're basically in pretty
good shape right because the primary has
a copy
the backup has to copy except the
primary doesn't really know if the
transaction has been
uh committed yet or not and so a final
step is that actually the
uh the coordinator or the traction
coordinator write out a
commit record and commit primary record
informing the primaries that actually
the transaction actually has committed
and as soon as it gets an
acknowledgement from one of the nicks
indicated by the dotted lines uh it
actually reports back
to the application saying that the
transaction committed
so what we want to do now is look at two
cases
one we wanted to talk a little bit more
about the serializability just to see if
the concurrency control worked out and
then we want to talk a little bit about
fault tunnels and see if the full
tolerance story works out
so let me first start uh with uh
serializability
or excel maybe before doing that let me
just ask if
there's any questions so far and whether
everybody sort of has swapped
successfully swapped far back into
into your memories
what does the rectangle mean in this
picture so what's the rectangle
what does it signify along the oh is it
an object
oh it's an object okay
okay any other questions
okay good let's uh uh
so let's uh look at the correctness
from the concurrency perspective so the
correctness correct is
strict serializability
and on tuesday we looked at a
transaction that
didn't really involve a right validation
because there was no object that was
uh read but not written and so i want to
look at another transaction this time
around where actually the validation
phase
plays a role and so i'm going to look at
two transactions
and this is sort of this example is a
classic uh example to test
uh whether a protocol provides
serializability or not of course it's
not going to be approved
but it's sort of one of the key examples
that generally is very helpful to see
to understand whether how the protocol
works so the protocol uh the
transactions are if x is zero
then we're gonna set y to one so if
object x
is zero we'll set object y it's one the
transaction two
is sort of the opposite it looks if y is
zero
and if y is zero we'll set x to one
and the reason that these uh sort of
this is a good test for serializability
uh is that you know either transaction
one should go after two two correct or
two should go after t1
and depending on which order you run you
know either y is one
or x is one but you never should have
you never should have the outcome since
x is one
oops x is one
and y is one and that should not be
allowed because that would be definitely
violate serializability
does that make sense
okay so what we want to do is you know
test whether uh
firearm actually is successful in uh
where we want to understand refinements
indeed uh it is not possible that
x is one and y is one uh get produced
so let's look at the timeline let's say
here we have t1
here we have t2 uh here's the timeline
so they both you know in their sort of
the preparation or the execution
phase they both read these objects so
let's say they run
truly concurrently we do a read of x and
at version number zero
we do a read of y version number zero
same here
and of course you know t1 will update y
two will update x and they base at some
point you know both
start the commit phase
and you know let's uh uh
so let's say the t1 starts first and
basically it grabs the
you know it needs to lock on y
uh since it's going to be writing y so
let's say
x successfully graph the log and y and
so that actually will set
you know the log bit okay in the version
number of the
y object and then you know let's say you
know actually
since it's going to read it has has red
x but it's not v
uh uh it's has a red x but it's not
modifying x
and it's going to be validation of x
uh you know x was read at version number
zero
uh the you know uh
at the validation files you know nothing
actually has changed yes with x so the
version over still zero there yeah we
run executed in this order
and so things are sort of are fine
and you know at some point you know this
transaction
might commit so let's look at t2
and let's say you know t2
runs after the validation of x so it
grabs the log
and um and then you know the
it is has red y so it needs to do a
validation of y
and so it's going to do a validation of
why
and the question is is that validation
could
succeed or not
no because the previous the other
operation has a lock and modified the
value so it's not the same
that was originally read yeah so the the
version numbers might mean they're still
the same but the
y you know t1 excel has set the lock bit
right
or the object of y and so at this point
this validation will fail
because it's not the same or the log bit
has been set
and so to t2 transaction the t2
transaction will abort
okay does that make sense so we see at
least in this particular example
that you know the it is the case that t1
and t2 both don't commit
which would result in this incorrect
outcome
any questions about this
i i had a question yeah
yeah so um like for for the transactions
so the these are like these have to be
like update transactions like not like
re write
correct because we always read they
could
do it yeah go ahead i just wonder like
if
they were like read operations you could
do that like
log free right and as long as the yeah
so this is actually good let's go back
to this picture here right then let's
look at the
let's say there were no rights involved
in this transaction at all right like so
for example the two objects that are
being read correct or stored at
p1 and p2 so let's assume that these
guys are actually not involved
so those objects were not written so the
only operation that's happening is a
read of that object
and if you see in uh and so the protocol
is carefully designed
so that if you only do reach you only do
one-sided rdmas correct
uh here in the execution phase and then
one rds ada to do the validation
and no locks are taken out no rights are
being done
no records are being appended that's the
only thing that happens
and so this is one of the cool features
about farm
is that these transactions that only do
reach
uh can be executed without
with only one-sided rdmas and
only with no rights to any
logs or grabbing any locks and so that's
why one reason that they get extremely
high performance
and this is also the reason why for
example the
lock fade the lock step and the
validation steps are two separate things
because uh in for read only transactions
there's no lock step
okay actually a question on that
um for read-only transactions why do we
need the second
val why do we need the validation phase
because aren't you like reading a value
and then you're immediately validating
right after it like the version
it seems like there could be another
transaction that
has been has modified the object yet so
if a transaction ran
or started and committed before uh okay
a concurrent transaction actually writes
might modify the object
and that would be bad right so the the
the the the transaction that uh
writes then the transaction that
actually follows it you know should
you know see you observe that last right
but if they occur at the same time then
we can reorder them either way
yeah as we occur exactly at the same
time we can over
order rewarded them yeah
so it still seems to me like this the
second validation
because the first time you read it the
second time you just immediately ping
and see if the version is the same as
scene
it still seems to me like the second
validation is like
almost unnecessary i i i i you might
you might be right i haven't thought
very hard about this that they're if
they're
if there's if there are transactions
there are only read-only transactions
you know then the validation is
undoubtedly not necessary
i haven't very carefully thought about
like when there's a mix of transactions
uh where there is a case where you need
the validation yeah
what would that be the case where like
you have like if you read a value
um like you expect to read like two
values atomically you read a value
after you read a value like some
transaction modifies the other value
um yeah
um yeah i shouldn't i'm not i'm not
quite sure
actually in that case if that's a
problem
like for example in this case you know
this t1 and t2 case it's
really crucial that y actually does the
validation correct
even though actually that transaction
you know t1
only reads y
correct what if
uh transaction two was just x equals one
instead of like without the f statement
uh blind right
if it's just a blind write yeah it's
just x equals one and then it executes
after the validation of of t1
yeah that's fine correct
is just like uh right like you know
write
x equals one within the validation step
like after and and it executes after the
validation step of t1
wouldn't then t1 think that x
equals zero but then x becomes
one before the commit
uh okay so okay let me maybe we can we
can hold this up because
i gotta you know redraw you know the
whole picture and figure out exactly
what the scenarios you're talking about
okay so maybe we can go back to this at
the end
sorry i had a question what is the use
case for the only transaction
uh if you
if you think backup spanner and this
paper like uh
there's often the case in these
workloads uh
the tpcc workload and the tatp workload
where
you know there's a transaction that only
does reach for example
i've computed the balances of a set of
accounts you know nothing is being
written
uh but you know a lot of things a lot of
accounts are being read
thank you
okay so we see here that there's
actually the validation phase is crucial
correct for this t1 and 2tk
uh transaction uh in uh and furthermore
that actually things that work out
correctly you know we get strict
serializability of course this is not a
proof but it gives you
uh you know this example that sort of uh
try to get at the tricky case
uh you know actually the farm seems to
work out correctly
okay so so that's on the concurrency
control
uh then the second part we want to talk
a little bit about
is fault tolerance
and she's going to want to get the i'm
not going to go with great amount of
depth here
just want to talk about the you know key
challenge
and see you know and build some
intuition
why we might actually be hopeful that uh
farm actually uh uh addresses that key
challenge
and so the key challenge uh
maybe actually the key challenge is that
the trajectory
crashes
after telling the application
and then it has to be the case right
that the transaction
persists because we have informed the
application that the detection is
committed so we can't actually
lose you know any rights that the
transaction has
done and so we can look at this picture
again
and see if we're going to be hopeful
that this is the case
so you know there's a couple things to
observe
uh after you know the lock phase
uh it is the case that
after the lock phase it is the case that
the two primaries p1
and p2 have a lock record
which describes the update we don't
really know the transaction
you know that record doesn't say whether
the record actually
uh whether the transaction is committed
but we have
information about the transaction then
after this step to commit backup step
now we know that
you know backup p1 b1 and b2
have the commit record
and then before you know the transaction
you know the transaction coordinator uh
reports to the application that
uh it has been successful we know that
one of the primaries
or let's say p1 also has the commit
record
so you know let's assume there's a crash
you know like right here
so at that particular just after that
commit point you know
and the system crashes and what we want
to convince ourselves of
is that uh if there's one failure uh
for for each chart you know things
actually work out correct
and so the worsen case basically erect
is
that you know b2 fails
so here where is v2 uh usb2
d2 fails um and so we lose you know that
commit record that is actually there
the primary might actually have not a
commit record yet
because you know it crashed after we
received the acknowledgement of one
primary so let's say the p1 must
actually have to commit record
so in this case p1 will have to commit
record
and you know and of course you know the
backup has a commit record for
b1 and so this is enough information
correct to for
to convince the uh during recovery that
actually the transaction has
committed because you know we have a
commit record you know which
is just what the tid is that's committed
and we actually have all the information
that the backups
namely the lock the commit records which
describe
the the right transformations on the
backups and so during recovery
we actually have enough information to
decide you know that the transaction
actually has committed
um and so that's sufficient of course
there's a complex protocol that actually
needs to go into action and sort of look
at all the
pieces that are left behind by the
transaction but there are enough pieces
left behind for the transaction for the
coordinator
for the sort of new uh coordinator or
the recovery process to decide that
actual distance action indeed has
committed
and should be persistent
okay
good um so let me sort of summarize farm
and before we jump into the discussion
of spark
so you know top level you know what what
is sort of cool about
farm is fast it can execute many many
many transactions per second
you know there are some restrictions of
course you know on farm
you can't do it in all
all the time
so first of all it assumes few
conflicts so it uses this optimistic
uh concurrency control scheme
and the reason that it uses this
optimistic recurrence pro screen because
it doesn't want to take out logs because
it wants to do this one-sided r dnas
without actually any server involvement
uh so use an optimistic
currency control control scheme uh that
means that
uh if you want to get good performance
and you know avoid
transaction boards the workload better
actually have few uh
conflicts and we've seen in the
evaluation that there are sort of the
two common benchmarks that are being
used in the transaction literature to
measure systems uh for those two
benchmarks
uh you know clearly is doing extremely
well this
doesn't mean there are not that many
conflicts
the second assumption it makes is that
the data must fit in memory
so this either means that if you have a
really really big database you have to
buy more machines
uh or if you really the data's too big
and you don't want to buy more machines
then basically you can't use farm
and you have to sort of go back to a
more traditional database that actually
has you know persistent storage there
and
so you can read and write
records to a much larger storage device
replication is only
it's only within the data center
so in that way in that way respect it's
quite different from
spanner the whole goal there was to do
synchronous transactions across the
synchronous replication across
data centers uh you know to support
applications that you need to be able to
survive or continue while some data
centers are down
in the case of you know farm that is
just not the case
it's not targeted to those kinds of
applications
and then the final point is it requires
you know pretty fancy or exotic
hardware in particular it has two things
this
uh ups distributed gps to
survive complete data center outages and
more importantly you know uses this rdma
mix
to get actually really high performance
okay sort of all i wanted to say about
farm unless there are any further
questions
okay um so that basically ends uh our
uh set of papers uh
or this is the sort of transaction side
of the this uh
of eight to four so we've like sort of
done three lectures on
uh transactions and uh that was
basically uh this is the
the end of talking about the
transactions that will show up in other
papers but you know we're not going to
talk about that in any more detail
in fact we're basically sort of done
with
talking about you know sort of the most
challenging part in distributed systems
namely
you know building fall tall and storage
systems
and you know we're now seeing a broad
spectrum of different designs
including designs that there are
actually support this very powerful
programming extraction of transactions
so in the next this lecture or the
remaining of this lecture and
subsequent lectures you know we're going
to sort of look at different topics
that are sort of unrelated to storage
systems
and so the first topic that we're going
to be talking about
is spark