okay good uh good afternoon dinner
can everybody hear me
yep thank you yes i will post the
lecture notes
uh at the end of lecture uh in response
to the
chat uh okay so uh
uh today basically uh i want to start
with a new topic
in uh in 824 and sort of uh
the last topic that we'll be discussing
the topic is really decentralized
systems
and these are typically uh the
decentralized really refers to the fact
that there's no
single authority that is in control of
the system
uh a lot of the systems that we've seen
so far you know all the machines and
servers sort of cooperate
uh and are on the under control of a
single institution or any single uh
authority um and the systems over and
a lot of you ask questions about like oh
how would it work if
there's no central point of trust
and so from now on the three systems or
the three
papers that we're going to be discussing
are all sit in this form of decent life
systems
and decentralized systems are harder to
build
than the sort of single trust systems uh
because you know you might have to
account for byzantine failures or visit
byzantine participants
and these are participants that you know
sometimes follow the protocol and
sometimes they don't follow the protocol
so you know the really they think about
it they're basically adversaries
and they may try to abuse
or trick other participation systems
you know for their own goods but not
maybe for others
and um and so that makes actually system
design with these distributed system
designs much more challenging
and much more difficult to reason about
we feel like in the last you know
you know 18 whatever lectures uh mostly
you know where we
talked about when we designed protocol
or we thought about draft you know we
just assumed that actually every
uh participant in the protocol follows
the rules
and in the business with distinctive
participants that is not the case
anymore you know
the the participants can cook up new
messages you know
send messages out of order trick uh
other participants
and so the we the thinking about those
kind of protocols is much more difficult
because we have to consider like what
what the adversary could do
to sort of make our life to break
basically the
the properties of the protocols that
we're shooting for so this tends to be
make the problem much harder
and really you know where what this sort
of topic is it so sits on the
intersection of distributed systems
and security
and as we'll see in the you know the
next uh this paper the next three paper
uh you know for cryptography or security
ideas like signing and hashing and
are going to play a crucial role to
actually uh make a forward progress
um in fact you know the paper actually
that we're reading for today is also
is a paper that we use in uh 6858
so if you're taking maybe six five eight
last uh
spring uh we we talked about this paper
too although
then from mostly from the perspective of
security and today i'm going to mostly
focus it is on the perspective of
distributed systems the sunder itself
a lot of people asked a lot of you ask
you know this summer being used
uh and as far as i know there's actually
no systems
that actually uh implement sunder
directly or
directly based on sunder other than uh
lab four
in six eight five eight um i mean lot
four
uh what if you do the blackboard the
default project which is like four and
eight five eight
then uh you actually implement uh sunder
now uh the reason and so you might
wonder why are we
studying this paper at all the reason
we're studying it because it actually
proposes a number of very powerful
techniques for powerful ideas
uh and so particularly the same log
uh even though it is a sort of a straw
man designer or a conceptual design
um is incredibly powerful and you see it
back
uh that same idea appear in lots of
other decentralized systems you know
ranging from
you know systems like git you know to
you know systems like bitcoin or any
other sort of cryptographic ledger
which we're going to be talking about
monday or next
tuesday i know one system that actually
is
directly influenced uh by sunder which
is a system called key base
uh i mean key based users uh some of
their techniques
and and many more uh if you're not
familiar with key base that actually uh
was originally acquired by zoom which
was only all familiar with
okay so that's sort of for the quick
intro
uh to this paper um before i'll dive
into
more of the setting any sort of
questions before
diving a little bit deeper in the table
okay um so let's talk a little bit about
the the setting
uh of this paper or the the motivation
of this uh
paper so the setting uh in
that the hour that the officer set
forward is a network file system
and um you can think about this a little
bit in the style of uh
an earlier paper that we've read from
chimpani
where the topic also was to implement
and consistent you know network file
system
um so you know we have a file server
we have clients that interact with the
file server
you know somebody might actually create
a file f
and you know maybe vdf on another client
um and you know the the setting
uh that we're in is that basically the
file server
as opposed to in uh in front of only
uh the file server actually can be
visited
and byzantine um really is creating an
extremely powerful threat model or
you know gives the attacker an
incredible amount of power
so in byzantine you know the server
might
send different rpcs back you know cook
of its own rpcs
um the the
the take over the machine uh
you know bribe the administrator uh and
enter everything is
basically you know the way to think
about it is that the address area gets
complete control
of the file server
um and so this covers sort of a wide
range
of you know sort of more common attacks
or like in the typical attacks that you
might see in
a real system so real attacks one boxing
software
so if there's a bug in the software then
you know the assets area can exploit
that bot maybe to obtain uh privileges
and you know the the business model you
know completely encompasses that
or you know the system administrator
might have a weak
we have a weak password that the
attacker compromises and then
takes control over uh the system you
know that's also covered by byzantine
uh physical breaking
maybe the attacker ranger you know gets
access you know to the physical machine
uh and uh you know can therefore control
the physical parts of the machine
again that's all covered by this you
know byzantine threat model
or even you know maybe you know the the
attacker
bribes
uh an operator
or colludes you know with uh
a malicious client you know that is also
covered by this model
so this is a threat model that is very
very
uh gives a lot of power to the adversary
it covers a lot of sort of standard
attacks
um and you know the first thing sort of
observed the you know the game that
summed their place is that instead of
actually
you know sort of maintaining the whole
file system on the file server
uh the file server is as simple as
possible
and in fact you know the the file server
is very much like almost like pedal
uh it's almost like a block device with
a little bit more
so the sort of central place where all
the you know blocks are stored
and but the clients really implement the
file system so
it's not really you know that the client
sends a creates for a file actually
you know sends blocks and reads blocks
uh
from you know the block server and uh
and basically constructs you know from
the blocks with reach and right you know
its own view
of the file system and serve you know
file system
operations basically on the straight on
the client and so here really we have to
create you know f read f
etc so very very similar to uh the front
japan
except you know the big difference in
france epony is that pedal and all the
clients were completely trusted
and in this setting uh the coins are not
trusted
and uh the file surface that uh it can
be
also is also not trusted okay
okay so the paper focus on a particular
set of security properties
and the focus is really on
the focus is on what is called integrity
properties
and in contrast to confidentiality so
confidentiality is about you know
protecting data from
so that nobody else can read it uh
integrity is just assuring that the
the system structure uh is correct and
uh the
modifications uh illegal modifications
to the data are being detected and
whether the data is public or not public
you know that sort of besides the the
point here
uh and to make it a little bit more
concrete you know what they're sort of
the
thing that they have in their minds is
we have a set of
you know we have developers
uh we have you know dev1 you know dev2
they may share you know some machine
that contains the source code repository
of some
you know source from project the
developers you know
collaborating on that project uh and
uh and sort of think about this as you
know the example that the paper mentions
is
in the paper maybe this is the
development machines and the server for
uh debian linux and the
what they want to again defend against
is trap or
trap door
you know trapdoor in the software
so the um you know an
attacker you know takes over control
breaks into the machine that contains
the source repo modifies the
software unnoticed and then at some
point that software gets deployed you
know for example that
linux gets deployed to lots of lots of
machines and
now the attacker has control over
those machines because it can exploit
the trapdoor
um the the paper talks about this attack
this particular instance of w linux in
you know 2003
where you know attack was able to
compromise you know the
development uh server or cluster uh
and recovering from these kinds of
attacks is very painful
uh in fact in 2003 you know they report
that
the demolition froze development for a
couple days
and while they were trying to sort out
which you know parts of their source
repo were still
you know correct and which parts were
actually modified by the attacker
and then these attacks happen sort of
periodically uh i think
last year you know ubuntu had a similar
type of problem
in uh i think in 2018 or 2019 i can't
remember exactly
uh and it was a similar case where the
one of the the core development uh
servers was the the broken into
and you know they had to sort of sort
out uh
what was really what would uh see which
software where
which files got effect affected by that
breaking
okay so that's sort of the setting of
the of the paper
uh and i'm going to make it a little bit
more concrete a little bit of a toy
example
to help us go through the techniques
that this paper actually uses
um so the example that i'm going to use
partially inspired by 6858
uh is you know let's say you know we
have a file system
uh there's a you know you're doing the
and the file system contains you know
the source code for this application
that yeah
we use in 858 called zoobar
um and zubar is a
sort of a virtual bank type application
where
uh users of the system uh registered
users of the systems can you know
transfer
zoo bars to each other and so it has a
file
called off.py you know that does uh
authentication
and it has a file that basically you
know implements sort of the bank
it's called bank ui and
uh and so now let's you know consider
the case where
uh you know a set of developers a b and
c
and you know they decided that they want
to sort of include increase the
usability of zoobar and actually deploy
it for real
and to make it real basically you know
they decided to divide the work as
follows
a is going to modify
off.ui
to support
mit certificates or mi2 certs
kerberos tickets or certificates and
with the idea that you know uh what
they're going to do is
uh uh you know they're going to the fbi
is going to be modified so that onlinely
legit
mit community members actually can log
into the file server
file server or into zoobar and so that
we actually know you know who it
actually really is
that is associated with that particular
mit certificate and then
you know to make a little bit more
useful you know b is gonna actually
modify the bank
ui to actually link it you know to
uh hashtag for tech cash
and so uh in the idea that basically uh
we can actually use the zoom bars from
the system of course you should never do
that but like we can use the zubair
system to actually
uh uh transfer money you know uh
real money instead of zoo bars between
users that are registered uh
with uh this service now this sounds of
course like a crazy idea you should not
really do it but
you know it's not completely ridiculous
uh you know because the
app ui really checks you know who it
actually is
based on the mit certificate and so
maybe it's not unreasonable that you
know we could connect
you know back into poi to actually tech
cache
and then you know basically c in our
scenarios is going to be the person
that's actually going to deploy the
software
and find the machine takes the software
installs it there and runs it
and uh and opens it up to the mit
community
now uh in the case now let's consider
you know what you know what could happen
what could go wrong
uh if actually the file server was
compromised and so
it was visited
well the obvious you know problem
there's a couple of obvious problems
you know bad outcomes possible
uh so let's consider them
you know that outcome one which is the
one that we should be talking about
and also in the previous examples is you
know basically
the adversary gives arbitrary code to c
so adversary
provides own code
to see
and you know that's sort of the or you
know maybe the ads are slightly
subtle about it or clever about it you
know whatever
makes it a little bit hard to spot that
actually uh modified off.pui
uh for example to delete the mit
certificates uh but this is basically
you know there's really no way for c
to check that actually it got the
software that a and b produced
and uh without any modifications from
the adversary so that's sort of the
obvious
problem we're going to talk a lot about
it there's a second
uh sort of bad outcome which may be a
little more subtle
which is that the adversary
provides the changes you know today with
poi
without the changes
to off.py
and so at this point you know this this
is pretty problematic right because you
know bank bpi is linked to
tech cash now but we actually don't have
appropriate
notification of the users anymore in
fact you know anybody that actually
uh creates a zubar account can now
actually interact with
tech hash um and so yeah clearly very
very undesirable
uh and harder to spot right because
basically
the adversary actually doesn't really
modify any software i just
selectively you know presents and takes
pieces of it and
presents that to see who then actually
goes off and deployed
and so it's it's really you know of
course the the
the tax the the paper uh
considers is of course attack number one
to the two uh but you know a lot of some
of the subtle issues actually
are brought out by this sort of second
case that we'll be talking about
any questions so far
about the setting and by the motivation
and
before we're gonna try to discuss
solutions
so the problem with the second case is
that the user
um that the author the authentication
does not
authenticate yeah it doesn't use mit
certificates anymore
and so we don't really know actually who
logs in
thank you what about the case where um
uh a or like b won't see
is like the fork
let's assume for a second that a and b
actually you know i have talked to each
other and divided up the work so they
know
that they're supposed to be doing this
together
i mean they form a team um they're in
close collaboration and contact
you know and they've divided up the work
and so they know
you know b tells a when he's done b
tells a when he's done and then they
tell see there
go ahead we're all done okay
okay so uh let's start
with considering a simple design that is
too simple meaning it doesn't work
but it gives us some you know uh
starting points
for a more uh sophisticated design that
you know hopefully it might work
and so the simple uh point is that uh a
and b or any
uh all the files are going to be
signed with the person who modified it
so
when like a modifies you know off the py
uh a actually produces a signature
and that signed with the public key
which signature assigned to the public
key of ah
and you know that signature covers the
data
of the file
and so when c uh downloads
the uh off.py know check the signature
and if the signature checks out you know
then the c knows that actually this file
was
produced you know this is indeed
produced by a
and uh you know might all believe that
things are good
um and that's the basic plan and
you know we'll talk a little bit about
again where the keys are coming from
although
the issue sort of public key
distribution is really an
858 topic so i'm not going to talk too
much about it but just assume for now
that
uh every user has a key um public
private key pair and the
private keys are secret and the public
keys are public and
every user knows whose public key
belongs to who
so now let's consider some uh
attacks and see which ones sort of you
know fail which ones you know
uh work so of course the obvious attack
was number one
uh that we talked about on the previous
slide which s modifies
files and
that is not a little bit uh that's not
directly
uh as modified out of gi
uh that's not really going to be
possible anymore
uh because when c downloads you know the
file and the signature and checks it and
it will see that the security rejection
check
because the data that actually was
signed is different than the data that
actually
the server produced and so it's not
really possible for
the server really to modify off not puy
without actually being
attacked or we leave out being detected
so you know this is we're sort of in
good shape here on this attacks
and that's sort of the core attack right
but
there's a lot of other things that still
could do
so let's consider some of the other
things um
s you know could actually in the way i
would describe the fps in another file
and pretend to be off.py
uh and because the signature doesn't
really say
uh which actually file the data belongs
to
and so s could just you know produce
some other
file and say like oh yeah see this is
actually after py
uh you could believe me in here you know
the science they use the signature that
was of course produced by s
so uh of course this could be fixed you
know maybe the signature should not only
include
you know the data but it also probably
should include you know the file name
so you know maybe not too uh too bad and
something that you could be
addressed a third you know another yet
another possibility
is to for s to basically send
the contents of old files
old content and maybe some new
and that's a little bit more difficult
now for us to uh
to handle correcting this too simple
plan uh because
you know the there's no way you know
basically the files are indefinitely
authenticated but not you know together
you know it's not that uh
c gets sort of a consistent picture of
the file system
uh it just gets like signed files and
how those signed files relate to each
other in terms of their histories
is completely not covered in this too
simple design
this is exactly of course you know the
issue this there's more subtle attack
that
now could just completely work out
correct because you know
s could send the uh as could said the
old version of after py
uh it will completely check out uh and
then send the new version
of the uh of the bank.py
uh which actually talks to is linked to
techcache and now we're
exactly back in the warzone case where
you know we have an old version of after
py or not the changes to office by not
the certificate changes to the off.py
uh in the new version that actually
linked to techcache and so that
this is not so good uh so and the simple
point that we have here just just
doesn't
deal with this uh there's a similar sort
of another sort of version of this that
where
you know of course you know s can also
just claim that the file doesn't exist
and c doesn't really have any
way of checking whether that actually is
true or not because again it doesn't
have a global picture
where it's a consistent view of the file
system yeah and it only
knows about signatures for each file
and so you can see that you know there's
this simple design you know maybe a good
starting point but we need something
more uh
more complete and particularly we need
something that really tastes good all
the file systems all the files together
that ties
the directories together the content of
the directories together
and and we have to be able to decide in
some way you know what is the latest
version
of the file system and so that nc can't
be tricked into
uh in this sort of problematic case
where one file is installed and the
other other file is not installed
so that's really what the uh some of the
paper tries to uh
address um and
and the big idea uh in the in the paper
uh and it just turns out to be just a
big idea in general
and it's a conceptual idea even though
the paper actually doesn't really
implement this big idea directly it
implements it in a more indirect way
it is an incredibly powerful idea
so the big idea is to
have assigned log
of operations
and of course you know you're well
familiar with blocks of operations
and and you know you can and this is
basically a
sort of a beefed up version of it uh
where there are signatures on the log
entries that
both consider cover the entry as well as
you know preceding entries
um and uh this turns out to be uh
as you've seen in all the previous
disabled systems and failure recovery
protocols we talked about the log is
actually a very powerful idea to
think about like the correctness of the
system and in
the same way that the idea is sort of
carried forward
here in this byzantine context
uh and so like you know let's let me
draw you know
the log
so it captures in the paper uh so blog
whatever has some entries and let's say
you know we're
covering the page that we are talking
about so there's a modification
okay a lot you know off dot py
you know by a and assigned by a
you know there's a mod so if it goes
well you know there's a mod of
the uh bank
py
signed by v
and as we'll talk about in a second you
know it turns out that not only
are the modifications uh in the log but
also
the fetch so the read operations
so fetch
fetch of the log you know site by c
effective off dot p y
and the fetch of think that p y
sine by c
we'll talk about uh those operations of
the the fetch operations a little bit
uh first i want to talk about the
the preceding operations first
modifications
um so first of all the
what is important to realize is that the
signature that is in the
record not only covers the current
record
but it also covers all the records
before
um let me stop for a second here because
i'm not 100 sure
can everybody still hear me yes
yeah yes okay okay like my ipad
uh walked out of the zoom session uh i'm
always logged in twice
uh and my ipad logged out so
i just want to make sure that i'm still
talking to you and you can hear me
and so that is the case okay so let's
just proceed uh
i think we lost friends
can people hear me now
does anybody hear me
yeah yes okay good good okay uh i don't
know if anything weird happened on your
end but on my end
uh i got logged out of zoom and logged
back in
maybe there's a byzantine server at work
okay let me hold on one second
and get myself in it
and let me see that video off
camera okay uh let me know if i'm good
good okay good no screen sharing yet but
yeah
okay well i'm hoping i hope this works
out better
okay um so i was at this very important
point
where uh the signature does not cover
the log entry itself
uh but it also covers all the preceding
log entries
uh and so when you know a
adds this modification to off py to
the log it signs the log record itself
plus the preceding lock
records and you can think about this
that the receiving log is maybe
represented by the content of the
preceding
log is a cryptographic hash and
uh in the record basically uh of the
modification
to off top ui you know the uh
the cryptographic hash the proceeding
part of the log is uh included and
covered by the signature just to be
clear we still can't see the
screen ah i can can't see the screen oh
good
well the screen hasn't changed yet but
uh let me uh
see if i can do something about that
oh yeah i guess huh
zoom still thinks that there's actually
sharing the screen but it doesn't look
like it actually is
how about this yep you can see now
okay thank you okay so i didn't change
anything yet
other than i think i was going to draw
the next era which basically when these
signs
you know it actually covering all the
preceding entries too
and this is sort of good correct because
uh when
uh uh the client you know c
actually receives you know or gets
actually sees the walk entry for b
then it is impossible for the server to
drop
you know the log entry of a because you
know that will be detected when cx
detects the
signature on the log entry of b and so
we already made sort of a big step
forward
uh in the sense that uh it's much harder
for the server now to selectively
uh draw block entries so that that so
that we're
pretty good pretty good shape you know
the server cannot drop a
and keep
these modifications
so that's actually a big big big step
forward and so let's just look a little
bit more in detail
how this actually is going to play out
so we're the client c
and you know we're fetching uh the log
to basically roll out you know the
distribution of the software or to
install it on a particular machine
the first thing the client does it
actually
checks all the signatures
and uh you know always the question of
course is like when you know you want to
check the signature log entry you know
which public key do you use
uh and uh because you want to make sure
that uh
you're not being tricked in accepting a
sick mirror or
a modification by a but it turns out
that actually a was not the person
actually
who signed it and it turns out that
basically uh
to figure out like which key to use to
actually verify
the signature the the key you use is the
owner of the file
so the public key needs to correspond to
the owner of the file
and ignoring groups for now uh you know
basically only the owner of the file is
allowed to modify a file
so for this for simple for slightly
simplified you know we could think about
it the
off the ui is owned by a and the id of
the file is basically the public key of
a
and so we know which
public key to use and
and can verify the signature with it and
so
if somebody else you know makes a
modification that pretends to be a
that actually is not going to check out
so it's really only a that can actually
make the modifications and similar for b
so that's part of the you know one thing
that's actually clever
about sunder which i'm not really going
to be talking about in some sense the
file system is actually doubling both as
a file system as
and as a public key publicly uh
infrastructure distribution
infrastructure
and so it is actually possible to do
something basically reliably determine
like you know which user has which
public key
but i'm not really going to talk about
this i really want to focus on the
consistency
aspects and the more distributed systems
aspects
the second thing that the client does is
check
its own last entry
and this is to protect you know the
client from actually being rolled back
by the server in time
so the server can't actually by if the
client checks always his last entry
if his last entry is in the log still
then you know the only way forward for
the
attacker uh is to actually enroll the
file system for
it can roll backwards so c will check
whether a venue of its previous
operations are in it
and you know confirm that they're still
in it
uh actually it's last entry still in
that is the question here
this only um i think
this attack from the server to roll back
would only work
if no other client wrote to the log
um like after
this client's last entry right because
otherwise checking signatures would
figure that out uh yeah although
let's talk about it in a second maybe i
mean you could always play a fork attack
right so you can always split you know
the view of the file system to multiple
users uh but you can at least not grow
back the client once the client saw a
particular file system
you can't go backwards in time now the
client can the server can present
different file systems in the future but
you can draw back
uh third part uh
the different like what you call
industries and construct the file system
after you know it knows that actually
it's not enrolled a past version of the
file system
uh it basically applies all the
modifications and basically builds a
file system tree
you know on the client and uh and then
you know before whatever operation it is
it wants to perform so let's say
in the case of uh c uh what it will do
is you know it will read you know uh
off.py
and append an entry to the log
and cite it
so in the case when it reads off.ui it
will
produce basically a signature an entry
for this log entry
and basically then and then the final
step in this protocol
is it uploads the log to the file server
and you know clearly this protocol is
completely impractical
uh and and really what it is is sort of
more conceptual protocol to help us
understand
uh why actually we might even be
successful in achieving uh security in
the context of
an uh byzantine server
because it would be ridiculous correct
to download the log for every operation
and the law contains the history of all
the operations ever happened to the file
system
in step three you know the client
actually constructs a file system at all
the operator
all doctors ever perform and since the
beginning of time and then finally in
step five
uploads the whole log back to the server
uh that seems completely ridiculous
and it is ridiculous uh in terms of
performance but it will help us
understand
uh you know when we sort of look at the
implementation
of a scheme uh where it actually has the
same set of properties that this sort of
conceptual
design has and we'll see later you know
for example in the case of
bitcoin that literally does actually
have a log you know since the beginning
of time with all operations in it
and so uh maybe it was a crazy idea
maybe in the context of 2004
but you know people actually do uh have
these sort of sign logs and really
maintain them
and so in that sense you know it's not
only a big conceptual idea that's where
people do it in practice
any questions so far
okay so the one thing
you know that you're uh probably
wondering about and uh
that was a proposed as a question for
the reading today is now what is up with
dispatchers you know why
are the fetchers in the mark too and
um and the because you might think well
you know the only thing that we really
care about like if we think about
uh the way we care about is that only
the modifications
have to be in the log because they're
not actually other things that actually
modify the file systems reads don't
really modify this file system so what
is the what's the problem
um and so i think i want to do a
quick break out here and sort of you
know you can brainstorm to each other
about what you thought the answer to
this
particular question was and hopefully
maybe uh
sort of this initial uh coverage of like
uh sunder
you know maybe hasn't now improved your
understanding uh
and you know you can sort of figure out
like what the answer is or talk about
something else
so i would like to take a you know maybe
do a five minute uh
breakout group
yes
so
i'm just double checking everybody back
one second thank you okay so what uh
i guess i'm like let's start with the
homework questions uh with no more
questions
why do why are the factors in your log
anybody um
if you have a read only server if there
are no fetches
this the file system can give it
anything
good it can give it because it
because there are no fetches in the log
that would mean that
um there are
the the read-only servers would not
be doing a lot of the checks that we
talked about before
so they um they go back in time for
example might
maybe not work because it did not put
anything in the log
because it only fetches yeah yeah okay
good good good okay so
i think you're totally on the right
track uh it was like trying to make it a
little bit more precise
or more concrete i think you know that
is correct so let's assume this is the
log looked like and the c's fetches are
not in it
um and let's you know uh so this is the
the log before actually c
downloads uh the log and so let's say
you know we're
see a catcher
the file that was modified by a and
basically what the server does uh the
server instead of actually providing
both the modifications a and b
because it has it correct which a and b
were done with its modifications
it sends the c
basically prefix
since the prefix that excludes
the modifications to a and b
so we have mods a and b
right then so c you know fetches this
file uh let's fetch the log
and so this is basically it's this part
of the log here's the prefix
uh you know the c
the signature she checks whether it's
proceeding operations are in it
you know then they're all there because
she hasn't done any other operation yet
and so basically it will accept the log
and the log as it is or the prefix as it
is
and basically returns you know after the
py to whatever
application that is copying the software
into the machine that actually is going
to run the
installed software so then cefetrix
bank.py
and this time around the server
sends the whole log
and you know the c uh
she looks at these uh entries and it's a
valid log
uh and its own operations are visually
in the prefix
uh since we didn't care about fetches
you know it's of course not in the log
um and so everything looks you know good
uh you know these are valid
modifications
uh nothing has been changed and
um and so you know civil you know
without the fetish in the log
c will actually accept you know this log
and
uh basically build a file system that
has uh
uh that deploy that includes the
modifications to the amb
and returns the result you know to the
application for bank.py
so that i can install it on the machine
that actually is going to run you know
the service
and as you can see now we're sort of in
a bad situation correct because
we took the old version of off.py
and the new version of banker to pui
and the one way you can think about this
is that you know from
you know c's perspective uh what really
seemed to
have happened is that i don't know while
uh
uh while you know it was uh
reading off the py you know there were
concurrent modifications to
a and b and just happened basically at
the same time or at least the server is
pretending it happens at the same time
and so and so it gets confused or it
can't detect
that in fact you know these applications
were did happen before
anytime so this is the this is the
problem that you know basically
putting the fetches in the log sulfur
sauce
and it's like let's make that actually
uh just
also concrete
uh and so see why actually this problem
is uh
solved in that case because i i had a
question
yep um so i i'm having a little trouble
understand like
understanding what the um like
sort of like um the interface like
for for fetch and modify is like what
um i i thought you fetched pretty much
like the whole
tree and had to rebuild the whole file
system
a basic example um but in this slide
before you're fetching like specific
files
the server is the one that returns the
log correct right
so the server can decide you know what
entries to include yeah
and we're already seeing that it can
they can't really delete anything out of
the middle of the lock right that's not
really possible
right it's always send a prefix of the
log because the prefix is always
consistent with itself
yeah and so in this first case
correct it sent the prefix and in the
second case it's in the whole walk
yeah and so the server can decide to do
that right because there's like nothing
that the client can
or at least have like so far you know
discussed there's nothing that the
client
how the client could detect that it
didn't get like the whole log
right right i i my question is more
towards like
what the interface is for for clients to
use like fetch and modify like
like because i thought initially i
thought okay like fetch
fetches like the whole file system no no
no
it's a single file okay and
and so basically what effects does is it
gets the law again like modifications
defense okay so modifications are all
the operations and modify the file
and like if you go back to a slide a
little bit earlier you know in the
modification record it says explicitly
which file
is being modified and you know
what's being cited similarly in the
fetch actually it says with file like so
this client shop
okay and then so so so
for a fetch like a client goes through
the log but only looks at yeah the final
thing it does is actually read the file
that actually is looking for
okay but does it check every single
entry in the log anyways
for the signature yeah yeah okay the
first step is always
check the whole log go for make sure
that your last you know
operations in it whether it's a factory
or modified uh although
in this broken scheme you know we we
drop the fetches
uh it applies all the it checks all the
signatures
and then it builds up uh the file system
by replaying the log from the beginning
of time and get a file system
and then it does its operation and so in
this case the operation is actually
fetched off.py is basically reading it
okay the reason you know basically we
talked about fetch and modify
is because all operations are basically
following one or two camps either it's a
fetch
or it is a modification operation like
writing a file creating a file those are
all
modification operations the fetch
operations are reading a file maybe
lsn directory spata file that kind of
thing
okay and then the modify is also like
a modified like doesn't fetch
the okay also fetches the log but then
builds the file system yeah yeah so
maybe the fetcher here i'm using fetch i
guess in two ways
one describe read-only operations and
actually to get you know to obtain or
receive the log from the server
okay but then modify modifies also one
single file
yes yeah for every modification in the
file system you're going to have a lock
entry
okay thanks
um sorry i also have a question i'm
i i don't really understand why this
scenario is a problem
because as you said it's it's possible
like from the perspective of the client
it may well be that
amb got uh created or modified
from the last fetch yeah in principle it
could have happened correct that was
recovering modification
we do know because like we were sort of
look from the top
and we know that basically c you read
the file after a and b modified it
but the server can pretend as if it
actually happened concurrently
and and in a second we'll see that if we
stick the fetches in the log
the server cannot pretend to do that
okay but even if the server pretends
that
does it even is that even a
problem does it break anything because
the plan can
yeah this is the example where it shows
that it breaks something correct
like step one you know c fetches off.py
the server gave it one you know as far
as the fetch
it gave it the prefix and so the client
constructed the file system executed the
operation
returned off the py to the application
that the and
installed the software around the
machine just to make it very crisp
so now the first reading of the py that
operation is done
right finished already executed and has
installed
the old version of after py on the
machine
then the client you know can fetches
bank dot py
now the server actually uh the client or
the application wants to read bank.by
so the client fetches the log from the
server or ask the server please give me
the log
the server this time around gets the
whole log and not
just the prefix yeah but you know builds
up the whole file system
and returns bankwy to the application
but in like i wouldn't this happen in an
incorrect implementation of the client
because if the client
finds that receives the log and it sees
an additional modification on
a if the client knows that its logic
depends on
a and b being in sync it will also fetch
a again
yeah yeah okay so the the there's a
great question c doesn't know
correct that um
ac okay in this particular scenario
uh the the the we're trying to establish
whether actually you know so you can
determine whether actually
democratization happens concurrently
or in the past before it read it you
know we want to be in the case that
actually happened in the past because
actually really happened in the past
but you know what this you know uh
server does it just pretends that the
modification actually happened
concurrently with actually seize
operations uh
and your c doesn't really have any way
to detect that
other than a new you know maybe that a
you know there should have been a
modification for a and b together
uh but that only could have known if
there's a sort of communication between
c
and a and b and second let's talk about
that in a second but if
c had not talked to a and b then you
know
it could have gotten uh it could could
ended up in this
scenario where it installed the old
version and off.beyond the new version
of bankwi
and we'll see in a second if we stick
the fetches in then this probably just
cannot happen
somebody asked if we timestamp
everything then you know we could detect
things
hold that thought for a second
okay let's look at the the vid fetch
scenario
right so and see what what actually
happens in that case
so client fetches
once the fetch of off wpy
oops what happened now
hold on a sec something went wrong
i presume nobody can see my screen yet
it's black yeah yeah it's coming back
hold on a second
i definitely feel today there's a
byzantine
component to e24
okay i need to stop sharing the screen
for a second
all right we're back hopefully okay
um
okay uh so back to uh
this example uh we're now the fetches
are in the log c fetches the off dot py
actually let me continue right then let
me
save this for just uh if it fetches
py uh the server you know sends the
prefix
so basically since you know these
modifications
correct because the server can just
return whatever it likes
then uh you know in this new plan grid
where where the fetch rejections are
being logged
then uh c constructs the file system
using a and b
uh and then uh returns that of course
you know off dot
py to decline to the client or to the
application
and then it adds a fetch
to the log
and uploads that log
to the server and then you know the
it doesn't fetch off you know bank.poi
and uh you know the server uh
you know in our previous example the uh
so first it says it said just the prefix
so here's the prefix
uh now you know now the client sends the
whole thing
right so it says the uh the whole log
and uh but if the modifications are not
in it
so and we'll have to send the whole log
well to send the whole log it must
include the fetch from c
right and so uh the
uh and if it doesn't you know the center
the effects we see
uh it actually uh sees
the the c is not actually not there the
the
the read operation and uh basically
the uh client will reject uh the log
because actually its own fetch operation
is actually not in it
so it is not possible for the
server to pretend you know that to send
the log later on because actually the
new log
should have included that fetch
operation that was in it
and the upgrade the c or the server
cannot splice that fetch operation into
here
to make it consistent what actually
happened before because that would be
detected
because you know the modifications on
the records of a and b are not
wouldn't check out
okay so basically what what this really
does is
to sort of step back is that you can
think about this attack
that um the server sort of pretends that
the modification to a and b happen
concurrently
uh with the c reading it uh even though
we know that actually is not the case
and by sticking the fetches in it uh the
that attack cannot happen
i have uh two questions um
maybe first just if you could like
define for consistency and the
fetch modify consistency and then the
second is
in this example so what exactly is
stopping the uh
server from placing the fetch
in the right place of the log because
remember every log entry
covers all its preceding entries
okay so if if the server could not
splice that
you know fetch you know after the prefix
before the modifications of amd
so let's say it only wants to send the
modification of a it knows the hash of
the modification of a and everything
preceding it
and then it could insert like the fetch
to see there because it knows that
you could say of that yeah but then you
could change that
yeah but then they couldn't send the
modification to b
because the modification would be you
know is directly after a
and so a must and so he can't splice it
between a and b
either i see it okay
sorry and what was the problem with
having it where it is in the picture
um well where it is and now the picture
is perfect that's fine
correct and in fact you know this
basically suggests you know that
the fetch of c actually included the
modification of a b
like the blue was the real log and we
have the fashion to see
in it and you know the everything is
going to be perfect
so just to clarify the definition for
consistency oh yeah
hold on hold on a second because this is
the topic of this slide
i haven't talked about the definition
focuses yet i'm going to do that right
now
okay so we're going to talk about four
consistency
so uh so what we've seen right so far
is that the the server cannot really
manipulate the log it can only sort of
send prefixes or it can hide parts
you know it can hide it can send the
prefix back to
the client but it can't really modify
the log so it just basically has an
opportunity to you know sort of
uh show different logs to different uh
clients and that is basically what
uh for consistency is and so
it cannot provide you know so the kind
of the server cannot provide the type of
constituencies that we've seen so far in
the past namely like linearizability and
external consistency and things like
that that's just not possible
uh but they can provide this with the
paper calls or introduces
is for consistency and you know let me
abstract a little bit away and to
explain what that is
so let's say we have you know client a
we have the server s
and you know that has a log
let's say i'm just going to extract
everything away it has entries a b
c and d and e
and uh you know a you know whatever
maybe you know dependent dot entry to
the log
uh and you know yeah and
and that's basically it um and
you know maybe we have another coin b
and uh what the server can do is sort of
give the other client a completely
different view of the world
by basically have another copy of the
log
or its own copy or give it a different
copy of the lock for example maybe that
log you know contains the record a
uh but then every operation that b does
you know goes into this log
you know b1 b2 maybe even some
operations from other clients that also
get this view
end up in this log but they're not
actually shown to a
you know a basically you know a made
actually also add more entries to the
log
like maybe it had b c d and e uh and
those are not actually shown to uh d and
so these two logs
to to the oral view of a you know looks
completely consistent
because it's unaware of any of these
changes and to be
you know this log looks completely
consistent because we're really aware of
any a
changes right because in this model of
the world
the only shared communication uh place
that is there
is the server you know that is sort of
the you know the thing that you know
uh shows you know what actually is the
state of the system
um and one way you can think about it is
like in terms of we've talked about
before this is sort of like a split
brain
you know basically uh you know a gets
the
c1 view of the world you know cooked up
by uh
by a log that's consistent with age view
and you know b
you know it gets another view of the
world and basically the server keeps
them sort of carefully separate
and uh and therefore can pretend that
you know
a is looking one you know sees the left
of the other underside of his brain and
b he's actually the right side of s is
great
okay does that make sense
so that's sort of what you know
basically they're saying is like you
know we can't really do better than ford
consistency uh because it's always
possible for the server
to uh to basically make a copy of the
log
and then from then on you know present
different views to these
uh clients now s could not
merge the two logs again correct you
know these logs have to be separate you
know for a
and b uh because it could be it's
impossible for us to sort of take
you know the logs you know let them grow
for a while and then basically splice
these two logs together again
uh you know the the the because these
entries you know protect all these
preceding entries these entries project
all the preceding entries of those
and so you can't like put them back
together
and because the signatures wouldn't
check out because the signatures always
cover the current entry for all the
proceeding entries
uh and so the only thing that you know
basically the server can do
is basically uh split the world fork the
world
and into different uh into two different
logs
so they might have a common log in the
beginning then the server forks them
and now the a and b basically operate in
different worlds
um so and that's sort of the
what the definition of our consistency
and that is basically the best you know
this particular file system uh this this
particular system can do
if there's the only communication
actually happens between s
notice actually by the way that sort of
four consistency is good enough for our
particular application zookeeper correct
uh because the uh either the server
shows the old
version you know without amd uh
or you know the server shows the s you
know the modification with a and b
okay so what do you do it seems like you
know maybe this is actually properly
uh you know how do you detect forex and
how could you
so how do you do tech force well there's
sort of two uh schemes that there's a
paper
uh mentions one is out-of-band
communication
it is pretty straightforward if you know
a and b ever you know talk to each other
and for example ask each other hey what
is your last entry in the log
and they get different answers they know
you know that they have been forked
uh and because either they okay they
could have different answers but like at
least
uh that one should be the prefix of the
other uh and if that's not the case
then they know that they're actually
being uh they're happy for it
so that's one possible uh
scenario that they discussed in the
paper to basically
share you know the the clients
periodically exchanged you know the last
log entries
the last entry in their log another
solution which actually has mentioned in
the chat
is uh you know introduce what they call
sort of a trusted machine
uh that is a timestamp box
and basically like every you know a few
seconds you know it actually ends
uh adds a time stamp to the log
and uh and every client knows that that
you know basically it's a file in the
file system that just contains you know
the
current time every time uh the timestamp
block
you know every couple seconds timestamp
box updates that file
the clients read that file and they know
there should be a new modification
like every couple seconds and that
basically you know that
that fork that contains the timestamp is
sort of the
forex that the the clients
that the server actually has to present
to the clients
okay so that's the two things that
actually the paper discusses
and what's sort of interesting and we'll
see on tuesday uh
is that this you know this whole fork uh
detection and fork resolution approach
is
sort of a key problem basically in
bitcoin correct and
we when we're talking tuesday about
bitcoin you know we see
a way basically to settle on a fork
so even if the file system or the server
the
the byzantine servers actually have
created a forex
uh you know bitcoin basically has a way
of just deciding well
we're going to reach the consensus on
like which fork we're going to actually
proceed with
uh and so we'll leave that up until
tuesday
but here's sort of a connection you know
between uh
you know sunder and actually bitcoin
any questions about this
okay okay i want to talk very quickly
because i have sort of three minutes
left
uh about um
the other so i think the key thing i
would get in the paper is this actually
this
log conceptual view of the world uh of
course you know it's impractical as i
mentioned earlier
and so some direction has a proposal for
how to do it better
uh even though like other systems like
bitcoin actually do maintain the whole
log
and so what does something do two things
better
instead of actually maintaining a log
you know that's actually has snapshots
similar to sort of the snapshots that
we've seen before you know in raft here
where we
construct a part of the world based on
the log you know we take a snapshot and
that actually forms the
the current state in fact really what
the
sender does it actually doesn't really
make literally take snapchats it really
maintains a snapshot view of the file
system
and does it per user
so one way to think about it is that the
file system is sharded by user
every user has its own view snapshot of
the world
and you know there's a little bit of a
protocol to make sure that these
different snapshots from different users
are actually consistent uh and let me
talk a little bit about uh how actually
sunder actually has
makes that snapshot basically
in sunder uh
it's on there basically there's
something that's called the user eye
handle
and the user eye handle basically
uniquely identifies snapshot in the file
system
and basically is a cryptographic hash of
the
i table which completes all the inodes
in the system
and you know and uh and for every i know
there's a hash
the inode would basically covers all the
data all the blocks belong to that
particular i node
so for example when uh say
a modifies off.by it might write one
block
uh the client recomputes the hash of
this block
updates the entry here you know updates
the entry here
updates the entry here and that's
basically a new handle
that describes basically the the capture
the complete you know file system
i'm going to ignore the group and the
directory uh
block for an item for a second so this
basically gives you a complete
uh checkpoint or a snapshot of
user two's view of the file system
now and then to deal with this issue
of how to get a sort of consistency
across users
they have this notion of version vectors
what inversion vectors is pretty
straightforward every version vector has
an i handle like a's i handle is in it
after
it modified say uh
off why and then for every user in the
system the version vector has
a counter for the number of
modifications that were made by that
user so if a made
this update to off.ui that counter is
set to one
you know b didn't make any modifications
you know c didn't make any modifications
they're all zero and this whole thing is
silent
and so when b makes this modification so
we use the version vector for b
gives us a version vector so b makes a
version
it creates a new handle that includes of
course all the
modifications or represent all the
modifications
and in its version handle it actually of
an insertion vector
it includes which uh how many operations
are read by ed user so it will record
the fact that for example
that it actually saw ace modification it
updates you know views to b1
and c to d0 and basically assigns this
whole thing
and now c when c next does an operation
uh wants to read you know off.py and uh
fetch the and uh
bank.py it basically downloads all the
version vectors
from every user yeah and so in this case
it will get the version vectors for a
and b
takes the latest one which in this case
is b
because actually it includes all the
operations of a in it
and that's basically the represented
version of the file system and from that
version it reads you know off dot ui
and bank.dui
and note you know that basically it's
impossible for the server
to basically present uh bank the py
and not after pppy because
you know it cannot you know it can the
only two sort of version factors that
can be returned
is this version vector or this version
vector the version of vector a doesn't
include actually the
changes of bank vpy if you know c
actually does get the versions of bank b
to y
it must actually have the versions the
modification that a is made
because the version vectors are
constructed in that way
and so that's basically the way for uh
using version vectors to detect that s
doesn't drop changes as we
as the same way that the logging system
is done
okay so that's the essence of the
version vector plan
um so in summary
okay uh byzantine participants you know
sort of a problem that you have to
handle in uh
decentralized systems
because there's no single institution
that sort of uh
it can be either a source of trust and
we've seen this notion of some blogs
as a very powerful tool
to uh deal with malicious servers
and as i said on on tuesday
and we're going to continue this
discussion and you'll see how the sort
of design logs are used
in uh bitcoin in particular like how for
consistency or how uh the the fact that
forks are sort of
being created are being resolved in the
case of bitcoin
all right so that was it for as an
introduction to
decentralized systems uh and i hope the
paper
uh is a little bit more understandable
than maybe
when uh before you start reading it uh
earlier this week or today
okay see you on tuesday
and of course if there's questions you
know peacefully uh please feel free to
hang around
uh if you need to go somewhere else uh
absolutely go somewhere else
i have a question about the data
structure that they use the
b plus tree or whatever like what's the
difference between that and
like yeah like uh like a miracle dac for
example
oh it's a miracle data structure uh you
know i think uh the
person who's uh sort of credited with
his id is merkel
and that's why it often is called the
miracle data tree
so this is the same thing yeah
okay yeah sunder basically uses a
miracle tree
um sorry when when you are verifying
the um the signatures doesn't mean you
have to like
basically as you go if you're 100
entries into the
log you have to compute
you know the hash of all the 100 entries
concatenated
and then compute and yeah so you need to
keep the running hash
okay let's go back to verify yes
uh let's uh
so here's probably a good place to talk
about it uh
so um so here
so let's say let's say take the last
entry correct
um the last entry you will have a hash
of the preceding entries so everything
you know from the like or whatever
records let's say this is zero one and
two you know zero
one and two or basically has the hash of
the previous
entry number two
in it and uh that needs to be that needs
to be checked
and the way uh
that is being checked is the you know in
principle if you start really from the
beginning of the world
you know you would have to compute the
hash of record with zero you find out
what the hash is
uh and uh double check you know that the
uh
that corresponds to the entry that's in
here and that the signature is valid
etc etc now of course you know in the
real system you can remember most of the
log
and just double check that like whatever
the and start from there
oh it's it's inefficient okay
yeah if you have to replay from the
beginning of time you basically have to
really
validate the whole lot from the
beginning of time
thank you that makes sense yeah you'll
see this in the bitcoin paper right
so are the hashes like almost like a
merkle
chain like yes okay same idea
so are the uh
uh like if uh is this like leaf
in the sort of tree or chain
like uh an entire file or like blocks of
a file
this is a block one block so this is
four five for 96 bytes
and all the other hashes don't change
correct so it's actually not that
efficient
inefficient yeah because if you only
change part of the file it only
rehashes that part you just have to
rehash that one and then you have to
recompute the hash of the tree you know
all the way to the user's eye handle
and the paper talks about the sort of a
couple of optimizations to make this
more efficient
but hashing is actually generally not
that expensive the signing is
the more expensive part operation
i had a question about version vectors
yeah so
uh we use version vectors to make sure
that the system can't return like an old
state
yeah so why can't the uh why can't the
system just return the old state and the
old version vector if it keeps like a
second copy yeah it's good fork
right so so we only have four
consistency then with the
reversion vectors only for consistent
either thunder for consistency no more
so for consistency you need the
timestamp
before consistency i mean that you know
the uh
the server can fork the log
at any particular point in time and
present a consistent view
of the uh what they can merge logs back
together
so really this picture that
the uh server can actually construct you
know different views of the world
and split you know the world in multiple
worlds uh but it can
merge the worlds back together
undetectably
so the best we can do is for
consistency which allows for forking but
we can detect forking
so if we detect forking can we then get
something stronger than
for consistency well yep well we can
settle on a fork
we're going to have forks but we can try
to settle like pick one fork as the one
to go for it with
okay but stunder doesn't have a way to
do that
nope okay so that doesn't happen happens
i mean sandra does propose some some
methods no
methods you detect and basically you
know one basically proposes like you use
the timestamp box to
you know use that one right
thanks you're wondering
the time some the timestamp box is just
a server that
appends entries and yeah and is trusted
so it's not under control of the
adversary
thank you uh can i
also ask one final question about the
debian example you said in the beginning
um can you say again what happened there
uh yeah sure uh so basically the
this is the source repo the development
machines for
debbie and linux in 2003 uh
an attacker compromised broke into news
machines
and modified files
and this is the distribution that hasn't
been sort of handed off you know which
you know if you're on demi and linux
you know you're you're uh anybody who
got like the
the debbie limbs after you attack and
i've got maybe a compromise deputy in
linux
and so when as soon as they discover
this they uh
didn't do any further development and
they would refer to distributions they
sorted out like you know they went to
backups you know started comparing files
and backups with the
files that they have and you know
basically double check that all the
changes that were in the
repo are actually really legit
and roll back and roll back any changes
that are not legit
like that that isn't bad yeah it's
pretty bad
it just just occasionally happens this
is a real problem
there's a real problem in practice thank
you so much that was a very interesting
lecture
thank you you're welcome thank you
you