good evening good night wherever you are
let's get started
so today i want to talk a little bit
about the chain replication
the paper aside for today from 2004.
uh before diving though into the paper
with a couple quick uh logistic things
uh just i want to remind you of uh one
is we have a quiz on thursday
uh and you know the instructions uh of
the topics that's actually being covered
the quizzes are on the schedule page uh
we'll try to send out uh an announcement
on piazza with more details
about exactly how we'll do the quiz
uh it's going to be a great scope and
it's you know basically during class
hours or 80 minutes um
and more but more details to follow
the second uh thing i want to remind
people off
is projects
[Music]
if you would like to do a project
instead of lab four
uh then um
uh you can do so uh but you should
submit a proposal for a project and
just a couple paragraphs uh to uh
through the submission website uh so
that we can give you feedback and so to
tell you whether this project is
actually
appropriate for a final project in eight
to four
uh if you're just planning to do log
four there's absolutely nothing you have
to do at all
uh any questions about these sort of two
logistical
uh points
okay then uh let me move on to one other
point that i wanted to bring up which is
the uh sort of a correction
uh from uh uh
a lecture a little while ago uh we uh we
walked through the
go code for the raft implementation of
2a and 2b that i had and uh we talked a
little bit about the
go defer statement and i mentioned that
you know you can actually have
the first statement inside of this block
um and
that is correct and i think it was maybe
a philippe who asked the question oh you
know what is exactly
what is that that can execute it and i
answered that question incorrectly
uh the first statement gets executed at
the point they get you return out of the
function not in your turn out of the
basic block
and so i apologize if that caused any
confusion
any questions about the
that clarification
okay good then those are the two topics
and really the
two technical topics i want to talk
about today is the zookeeper logs
which i didn't get to finish the last
time
and then i'll talk about chain
replication
all right so uh both for chain uh
replication and zookeeper you know we're
sort of still
in the same context as uh before
namely uh we're doing you know
replicated state machines
and you know just the usual diagram
uh you know we have a service you know
that runs on some you know replication
library like you know zap
or raft
we have clients you know talking to uh
the service for example in the case of
you know
a zookeeper they might actually send the
create call
you know if you keep your internally
house from state you know some z
notes you know that are hanging off in a
form a tree
and so when an operation comes in you
know superkeeper you know
forwards that operation basically to the
rav zab library
it does some chatting back and forth and
to
get a majority of the servers to accept
you know that uh
command and then at some point you know
once it's accepted it comes out
uh the server applies the operation and
sends a response back to the client
and so the standard story of uh
replicate the state machine if you start
all the replicated state machines start
in the same state you apply the same
operation in the same order
then you will end up in the same state
and so any of the machines can then take
over if necessary
now one of the things that was cool
about or interesting about
zookeeper is that you know read
operations can uh be served from any
uh service or for any of the peers or
any of the one of the servers
and this allows you keeper to get
extremely high performance you know
because you can actually uh
scale the number of viewed operations
with the number of servers
uh as a flip side of that uh you know
zookeeper
actually gave up on in that particular
scenario gave up on linearizability
because we know from you know for
example in raft you know you can't
actually
arbitrarily serve a weed from any server
because i have not seen the latest
updates yet
and so in case of zookeeper that is true
too
and uh and so read operations
are not you know or the the operation
that supergroup defines
don't provide a linearizable interface
um but nevertheless you know we saw
that actually is uh it provides a
slightly different sort of correctness
guarantee than linearizability
uh and that actually correctness um
is useful uh and useful enough you know
to be able to write x-men programs and
the particular
set of programs that you know zookeeper
was you know focusing on
is uh these what they call configuration
or coordination
programs
and so the definitely think about it is
that a lot of systems that we
looked at in the past they typically
have you know some replication story and
then they have
a coordinator or a master
uh that sort of coordinates the the
group and
zookeep is really intended you know for
as a service you know for that kind of
you know master or coordinator role and
it provides a bunch of primitives you
know to
make that uh doable and uh the two
you know we talked a little bit about
atomic increment uh last week
uh and uh with some of the other
surfaces and i want to sort of
finish off you know talking about box um
one because there were a lot of
questions about it and two it actually
is quite interesting
and there's sort of two different
walking team limitations and the first
one to talk about the simple one
namely where uh let me just write down
the
pseudo code and then we can talk about
it in a little bit in detail
uh so the pseudo total code for
the block was something like this you
know acquire
uh in an infinite loop you know try to
create the log
file
i'll name it lf and set ephemeral to
true
and we'll talk about that in a second
why you know if the create succeeds
then you know the that process where
that client was the first one to create
that file and basically
successfully gets the lock and so it
breaks out of the for loop and returns
um if the
client did not you know be able to
create a file then a call
exists and the call to exist is not
really for
you know see if it exists or not because
you know we know it doesn't exist
but basically we set a watch
and the idea is that you know the watch
will go off
if actually the file disappears
and if it disappears then you know the
client will get a notification and so
basically
we're going to be doing here is just
wait for that notification
so that's sort of the acquire operation
then the release
is very simple
the release basically is does nothing
else than sending a delete
operation to the zookeeper service you
know for the for the log file
so lf in this case and so what does that
do well if the
delete you know sent to the zookeeper
servers you know the zookeeper serves
the
performance the ddop delete operation
that will actually
let the that make all the file would go
away uh that will fire
the watch and so every client that
actually is waiting
you know for uh the notification will
get a notification
and then they go retry and uh you know
one of them will be successful on the
retry we'll get the log file or create
the lock file
and then proceed and then the others
ones you know we'll go back into
uh their uh call exists and i'm gonna
wait for
a notification and the zookeeper
semantics you know are good enough
you know the the strong the the the the
limit the linearizability for write
operations
plus you know the rules for when
notifications go off
are strong enough that basically this
actually implements a faithful lock
where only
one client if there are many clients at
the same time trying to get the lock
only one will get it
and you know when the release is done or
when the
file has been deleted only one in the
next round will get it
so that's sort of cool uh and it's
interesting that you should
build uh you know sort of a sort of this
foundational primitive
uh using the primitives that the
zookeeper offers
and you see above the role of the you
know the the watch
and then there's the second row for the
elephant you know the ephemeral
is there because uh what happens if a
client
uh fails or crashes before it causes
release and
the semantics of the femoral files is
that the zookeeper server will
if it decides the client has crashed it
will do the operation
uh it will remove the file on behalf of
the
client so even if the client fails or
crashes
the search of the site and at some point
the client is done
and then we'll remove you know this file
lock f which will cause notifications to
be sent to
other clients that actually are waiting
for it uh so
it's a you know a cool set of primitives
to build in a powerful abstraction that
can be useful in applications one
downside of this particular
implementation
is that it has what's called a herding
effect
namely you know let's say you have a
thousand clients don't want to
grab the log file or make the log file
acquire the lock
uh no one is going to succeed and 999
are going to call uh exists and wait for
a notification
then when the first client deletes the
file or releases the file lock
999 are going to try to actually acquire
the lock and of course only one is going
to succeed and then 9998 they're going
to be sitting for a notification
uh but you know the the this you know
every sort of
round of disappearance a huge amount of
traffic uh
and uh you know basically bombarding you
know the zookeeper surface right because
there are 900
you know all but one uh uh are gonna
fail
and so that's a little bit of an
undesirable uh property
uh this hurting effect uh and it's a
real problem in practice you know both
on
uh small scale multi-core machines as
well of course in a setting like this
where you know network
messages are not free so it's
interesting that
actually zookeeper provides enough
primitives that you could actually do
quite a bit better
you can actually build a lock that
doesn't have suffer from the herding
effect so a better lock
and this is interesting let me uh pull
up the
pseudocode for this which is in the
paper
so that we can look at it and discuss
you know why you know this lock is
better
and particularly what we'll see is that
this lock is better because basically
there's no
there's no retry where all clients that
didn't succeed
getting the lock will retry to try to
get it instead you know basically
the all the clients are sort of foreign
and
they get the log one by one and the way
you know
that you can program that using
zookeeper's primitives is in this
particular
pseudocode and there are a couple
differences
compared to the previous one first of
all
the
there's an additional flag you know
passed to create namely
sequential which basically means that
every
these files are created the bug file is
created but it will be created as
you know the first one will be log0 then
the next one will be lock one
etc
so we have like you know if i was a
client just rushing you know to the
servers to actually try to acquire the
lock
basically a thousand files will be
created all numbered from zero to
99.99 then
uh so i'll succeed in creating a file
uh the the create returns actually the
number that the that you got so if the
client zero
if the first client gets no block
creates log zero
then it will get a zero back and the
second one get a one back et cetera et
cetera
then you know the sugar could basically
ask you know to get all the children in
that
directory under which you know these
files are created and so in this case
maybe there'll be a thousand
uh children a thousand z nodes uh
and then you can just look at the n and
uh c of your n in this case zero is the
low
z note in c uh and if that's the case
that means you got the lock
and so that makes totally sense correct
the first line gets actually a zero back
uh all the other clients have a higher
number because they're sequentially
numbered
and so the first client will succeed in
getting it and all the other ones
what they're going to do is they're
going to
look at they're going to find the p you
know the number that's right in front of
them so for example if this is client
that got back you know log 10 it's going
to look you know for
z node 9 you know log 9 and basically
put a watch on that file
so this means that every client uh will
have a watch
basically on its previous session so
here you're going to see that sort of
all the clients form a line
and um and then you know the client is
going to
wait for that notification to go off and
so that means for example when client
zero
you know we've got the zero back you
know uh releases the lock you know we'll
delete in
uh this will get a notification to go
off for the file
one and so the client that's actually
waiting for that particular notification
then
uh will run but it's the only one it
runs
and uh and it will succeed
and so here we see you know this is some
sometimes these are types of blocks are
called ticket locks
in uh multi-core programming if you're
familiar with them and they have sort of
the same uh
the sort of the same idea of certain
ticket locks exceptions are built in
into this using zookeeper primitives
and again what is interesting about it
is that
you know these primitives are powerful
enough that you can actually build these
kind of blocks
any questions about this
okay i want to make one more comment you
know about the uh these locks
uh before moving on to uh chain
replication
we have a question in the chat yeah okay
what's the question in the chat
what is the watch for online for
good go back on this four line four
yeah i think that's the question
[Music]
that watch my comment of the watches
actually should go with you know
line five so there's no watch on line
four correct
uh line four just finds p you know the
number that's right before
you know you're in
if that doesn't answer the question
please uh you'll come back later that's
fine
i actually have another question yeah
this is going actually i think back a
few slides but
how does zookeeper determine that the
client has failed and thus released the
ephemeral lock
like if it it's just like partitioned
for a moment
yeah so uh well so that could be
happening so the client might actually
so the client has a session
right with the zookeeper service
and the client needs to actually the
zookeeper and the client basically
saying heartbeats to each other
and if the zookeeper service doesn't
hear from the client for a little while
then it just decides the client is down
and closes the session
and so the client can try to send
messages on the session but the session
is just closed it's gone
and any files that were created in the
emphasis that were created during that
session are basically deleted
and so if the network recon uh
reconvenes or
reveals then the client can will try to
send messages over that session and
basically those upper servers will say
like ah
that session doesn't exist anymore you
got to retry or restart a new session
got it thank you okay good
so there's one important point about
these uh what i call z
locks where z zookeeper locks
and that is they're not the same or have
similar semantics
like the locks that you were using or go
locks or mutexes
and it's sort of an important point to
realize even though they're different
we'll see in a second they're still
youthful
but they're not as strong as the sort of
the go locks
in particular the case that is
interesting is like when the lockholder
fails
so if the lock holder fails
basically zookeeper decides that
lockheed holder has failed correct as we
just discussed
then it is possible that we're going to
see some intermediate state
and remember like the whole rule that
locks is like you know it's a critical
section
you know you're some invariant is true
you know while you're going
or through the critical sections on that
invariant might not be true but then at
the end you
re-establish new variants uh
in here it's the case like you're
required to walk a client requires walk
does some steps
and then you know maybe zookeeper
decides that the client is decided to
decline this crash
and uh basically revokes lock but you
know the state you know the system might
actually
be in some intermediate state for return
on the invariant was not true
right so it's not the case that
basically uh these logs guarantee
adamicity of a
critical section uh so what
so what they do what they're useful for
is for some other purposes
in fact there's sort of two primary use
cases one i think is leader election
so uh basically if we need we have a set
of clients that need to select a leader
among them you know we can just
they can all try to basically create the
log file
one of them succeed that's basically
then become the leader
and that leader you know could clean up
any intermediate state
if possible if necessary
or you know do these atomic updates
using the ready trig
where basically you do a bunch of writes
you know to some file but then you
expose the file only at the very end
and that way make a set of uh writes
actually a sort of more transactional
work so that's one use case for these
kind of locks
the second use case is what i will call
soft locks
the soft locks you know the way to think
about it is that uh
let's say we have a worker like in the
macro do style
and the map we want to basically arrange
that you know every
uh worker executes a particular map task
only once
uh and um and so now one way to do that
would be basically take a lock out
you know for that particular uh input
file
uh run you know the computation and then
uh
once the mapper is done then you release
the log file so this will cons
this will cost only one mapper to in the
common case to execute
a particular task and um and that's
exactly sort of what we want but of
course you know if
the mapper would fail then the lock will
be released and then you know we might
execute it a second time because
somebody else will try to require to
lock and so in that case you know for
the case of mapreduce that's perfectly
fine correct
the it's okay if the task gets executed
twice
it happens twice
and in some ways what it really is it's
more performance optimization that in
the usual case you want to take uh
you want to have it actually it's
actually could do that only once uh but
you know if there's a failure you know
it might be the case that you're
executing a map drop twice
and then that thing you know and the
mapreduce usually meant to set up in
such a way that actually that is
uh that's okay and so in those cases
these sort of locks are really useful
too
any questions about this about the
this perspective on locks you know that
the zookeeper walks are not exactly like
the go
locks and you know it's just an
important thing to keep in mind
all right go ahead alexander
i guess uh yeah i had a question you
said that uh one of the differences is
that um
in in z locks the
if if the if the server holding the lock
dies then the lock can be revoked but
does that still happen if you don't pass
the because there's that flag
called uh yeah fmero yeah fema yep
that have only happens with the
ephemeral fire right so can can we just
like
um emulate the golocks by not passing
ephemeral
okay good what would happen then
so you created basically a persistent
file the client
dies you sub deadlock
and so the lock will keep on existing
and nobody will release it
and we have a deadlock
because the one person that could
release it is dead
or crashed and in fact this is like why
i get ephemeral partners there
um is is it actually the only
the only person who could release it
because anyone can delete that file
right
because you have like a background like
but that would break
but that break you know maybe the other
clients are still running you know also
still thinks it holds a lot
that's true now you guys are getting a
sort of this
basically you're this is the consensus
problem all over again right
uh and you know we
so this is sort of a clean way to get
most of it uh but not all of it
if you will and i think you know if you
want to make things atomic across a
number of you know a set of rights
atomic
you know you basically use this trick of
um
uh you use this trick of basically
the ready trick where you do a bunch of
writes and then you expose them at the
same time
could you explain the soft locks again
uh okay soft locks uh means that
basically an operation can happen twice
uh and so in the common case if there's
no crashes it will happen once
you know because the the client will
take a lock out they'll do the operation
release
and but if their client failed uh
halfway through for example then the log
would be automatically released by
zookeeper and then maybe a second
you know client will execute the same
map task
so in the case of later election i uh
what's the intermediate state that could
get exposed here
it seems that uh the first yeah okay in
the pure leader election there would be
no intermediate state but typically the
leader will create a configuration file
right as we saw in zookeeper where you
know uh
using the ready trick i see and so you
just write the whole file and then
convert it atomically as we
name it okay thank you um sorry could
you
explain what the ready trick is
i was hoping not to because i think we
talked about it last time sorry
all right so uh maybe we
you can hold that question and well i'm
happy to do it at the end of the lecture
again
because otherwise i have little time to
actually talk about uh chain replication
any other last-minute questions
okay let me set the chain uh the states
were chain replication a little bit
and that will also come back to
zookeeper in some sense
uh and basically it turns out there's
sort of two
common approaches to build replicated
state machines
and we really haven't called out these
two approaches you know we've seen them
but i've really talked
explicitly about them and i want to do
this at this time explicitly
so
because there are some interesting
observations to be made
approaches to building replicated state
machines
and the first one is
the one we basically have seen in the
labs which is you run
all operations
you know through raft
graft which you keep a raft or you know
access whatever
you know consensus you know distributed
consensus algorithm that you're using
and so this is sort of like the key
value store right in
lab 3 where you know you do put a get
operation you run all the put in get
operations through raft
and you know the surfaces basically
update you know the key
to our state as the operations are
coming in
on the applied channel and uh
you know and basically we have our
replicated state machine
so this is sort of like how lab3 works
it turns out that style where basically
raft is used to also
uh run all the operations it's actually
not that common
uh we'll see some other designs later in
semester to do that too like
spanner does it but it's not actually
completely
the standard approach or the more common
approach actually is to
have a configuration server like
zookeeper
service and the configuration service
itself internally you know might use
paxos raft or uh
uh or zap or whatever and uh and
really the configuration services really
plays the role of the
coordinator or the master like the gfs
master
and in addition to basically having
configuration services actually
implemented
uh using you know one of these uh rav
texas algorithms
you actually run a primary backup
application
and so think about gfs you know or that
we saw early in the semester
has that sort of structure right in the
gfs that was a master
and that basically determined you know
which set of servers hold the particular
chunk
and so basically determine the replica
group for chunk
and then the replica chunk group
basically executed the primary backup
replication
one of the chunks was the primary and
the other ones were the backups and they
basically had a protocol that they used
for primary backup replication
you could think about vmvt in a similar
style where the configuration server is
basically a test and set server you know
which basically recorded who is actually
the primary
and then the primary and backup have a
protocol to basically send you know
channel
operations down to channel and so that
the primary backup is sort of
roughly in in sync and implement a
replicated state machine
and this this approach you know tends to
be sort of the more common approach
although you know the approach number
one also happens
uh one we one way to think about this uh
is that you know um if
the raft states like for example our key
value survey laptop would be gigantic
you know have a
huge amount of this state you know
terabytes of key value server
would rather be very good match for that
kind of application
or what is the risk
or the potential problem
um we flush the log very often so
maybe that could be problematic that
could be problematic yeah like
what what is it what's the size of the
checkpoint
if our key value server is really big
it's linear in the size of the key
values yeah so the techniques could also
be gigantic right so if any
you know if any time the checkpoint has
to be sent you know it's going to be a
big checkpoint
and sort of like graph it's not really
sort of set up you know
and so the primary is going to
communicate you know the new primer is
going to communicate these
snapshots as you did in lab2d you know
to the the backups and you know they're
going to be big
and so you often want to maybe a little
bit more clever plan
to sort of synchronize you know
re-synchronize new servers
and uh so one reason that basically
often these things are split into two
different pieces where there's the
configuration servers that basically
small in terms of state
and then a primary backup plan that
actually you know may
replicate a huge amount of data and so
this is why one reason you see sort of
both approaches
does that make sense i'll come back to
that at the end of the lecture again
uh but it's important to keep this in
mind so what approach
or what benefits does one give over to
uh you don't have to have two of them
right in one you basically have raft you
run the operation for a fruit and an
industrial configuration for you too
so everything is in a single single
component
and here in number two we have two
components you know we have a
configuration service that includes
draft
and we have a primary backup scheme
so maybe this will become become more
clear as i talk about chain replication
um yeah i had a really quick question so
like
essentially for two i guess would like
what the advantage be that you have like
like it's consensus reached through the
leader and the leader never fails right
like
yeah so the advantage of two is that as
we'll see the second in chain
replication
is there's sort of a separate process
that takes care of the figuration part
and you just don't have to worry about
it in terms of your primary backup
replication scheme
uh and that just decides like in gfs
that's sort of like the master it just
decides to have a year to set the
servers that form this particular
replica group
and the backup primary backup protocol
doesn't have to think
about this thanks
and so and this is a good introduction
to chain replication because the chain
replication is exactly
uh sort of a primary backup
replication scheme for approach two
and that is to say that you know uh
chain replication assumes
there is a very configuration servers
uh i think they're called the master
processing the paper
then chain replication themselves
there's a couple cool properties
one read operations or
they call them query operations
involve only one server
namely the tail as we see in a second
another nice property about chain
replication that has a very simple
recovery plan
and we're going to talk about all these
in more detail in a second
and then presumably something that you
started having
you you appreciate given the fact you
know how complicated it can be in raft
uh and you know it provides actually
strong
a strong uh properties namely
linearizability
for the put in the get operations uh and
finally just a lot of people ask this
you know there's actually a reasonable
influential design
and it's used by quite a number of
systems
uh so this has been used in practice
so this is so i'm going to talk about
each of these components in a little bit
more detail
and and then we'll come back to this
sort of approach one versus approach too
uh so in terms of an overview
oops what happens here if there's an
overview
user delay of the land you know there is
a a massive process
or a configuration service
and that basically keeps track you know
which servers you know belong
you know to a particular chain so
s1 s2 s3 you know basically have a
record of what the chain is
who the head is and who the tables and
so
that's the configuration server and here
we do actually have our servers you know
s1
s2 s3
and one of them is the head
typically the one with the smaller
number and
one is the tail
and so if we have a client
the client may talk to the configuration
server learn you know who actually
is part of the chain uh and then it
sends a write request
to the head so this is the protocol
in chain verification the right request
always goes to the
uh the head and what the head does the
head basically pushes
you know the head actually applies the
operation uh on its
state and maybe it has a disk you know
associated with it you know where
whatever stores key value server on it
and then it sends the
update you know the result of the uh
operation
down the chain in fifa
order and reliably so s1 will send the
update to
s2 it has to have made his own disk
apply the
operation word state change to its
state once it actually supplied it you
know it will forward it to the
last uh node in the chain and this can
be because there are only three nodes in
this particular chain
you could have chains that are longer
you know if you want more availability
um and when the last node gets the
message or the state change uh it
applies it to you know its state
and then now this is in charge actually
we're sending an acknowledgement back
you know to the client
so it's the tail who sends the
acknowledgement back
um and so uh one way to think about this
is that when the
tail or in this case s3 you know
actually applies to state change
that's sort of the commit point
and the reason is is the commit point is
because subsequent reads
always come from the tail so if anybody
or any other client
you know does a read operation they
always go to detail
and the tail basically responds
immediately back to them
so read operations go to detail so here
is client one here's point two
client two does read operation uh it uh
goes to the tail the tail responds and
that's it
and so there's a couple things that i
want to sort of point out um
the one one of the interesting points
out is that the read operations just
involve one server
right and like and if you remember from
uh lab three or if you're in progress if
you're
starting to do lab three read operations
actually involve
uh you know in our implementation read
operations go through the
raft log and all that kind of stuff
the paper discusses in optimization but
the read operation always goes to the
leader
and the leader first has to you know
contact the majority of the servers
before it can execute the operation
locally
uh so what you see here is that the read
operations actually go through
completely so
to a different server from write
operations so the read and write
workload is actually spread at least
over two servers
furthermore the read operation involves
only one server
there's never he doesn't have to talk to
any other server it can just respond
immediately and we'll see a little bit
later
why this is actually uh important or why
this is actually what what further
optimizations this
allows and so the commit point is really
you know
at the point that the right actually
happens at the tail end
because at that point the right
operation is visible to
readers and not before any other point
and this also you know provides this
linearizability so it's pretty easy to
see that in the case of no crashes you
know this
scheme guarantees or linearizability
because the rights are all applied in
some total order
at the head and
when the tail receives you know that
update it's the commit point
it wants to respond you know to the
client and send the request back
if you know that same client immediately
does a read operation
it will go to the tail and it will
observe the last change
so uh certainly within a single client
basically all
operations are totally ordered it's
pretty easy to see that
incline if client two start to read
operation after
you know clients one uh operation has
finished and when is it finished then
when it the tail has responded
so any read operation that starts after
a write operation
will observe you know the last or the
result of the most recent right
and so it's pretty easy to sort of get
an intuition here that you know this is
going to
provide us with later activity
okay so uh what i'd like to do now is
actually you know take a quick breakout
room uh section and where i would like
you to discuss
the uh question that wasn't a post in
lecture
you know what could go wrong or like
would a great linearizability if instead
of having the tail
respond to the client uh have the head
respond to the client immediately after
it has received you know the
uh write request
and maybe that's a good topic sort of to
debate a little bit and if you want to
go in any other direction
to talk about the chain replication
portrait welcome but maybe that's
something to start with
so let's take a five minute breakout
room and then
uh we'll do this and i think
uh let me see jose are you gonna do it
um yeah and okay
do i have to make you something or i
don't think it's necessary
um i think it zoom changed so it should
be possible now too
[Music]
yep that's right
yep okay
uh
[Music]
hey okay are we coming back uh yeah
whenever you
i'm ready okay and then i think i can
close
so
back
okay good uh so you know just very
quickly uh to summarize you know why
uh you know that would break
linearizability yeah so the
the protocol change change that was
contemplated was to
you know both you know keep propagating
to s1 and s2 and s3
uh but you know as soon as s1 actually
is done uh
with its propagation the that responds
back to the client
and clearly that is will would break
linearizability because
uh let's say this client wanted to write
got the announcement back
you know from s1 as one of course has
you know the right also in progress
s2 and s3 but maybe before you know s2
actually contacts s3
the client actually sends a read
operation you know to
uh s3 and of course now it will return
uh
the value from before the write was done
so the client doesn't even observe its
own rights and so that would clearly
break linearizability so it's very
important
that you know as i said earlier that
these the tail
actually sends the acknowledgement back
you know to the client
because really the once the tail has
processed the
right operation that is actually really
what the commit point is
any questions about that
okay now so this is sort of normal
operation
and i want to talk a little bit about uh
crashes uh you know
since it's 8-4 distributed systems so
all the actions is where when the
failures happen
and one of the things that is cool about
chain replication
is you know the number of failure
scenarios is actually quite limited
and so let me uh so basically the three
cases namely the head fails
the one of the intermediate search fails
or the tail fields
so let's look at one of each one each of
those cases so
here's our they're the case we have
ahead it's s1
let's say that it applied u1 u2 and u3
for free updates
uh talks to s2 well maybe s2 has done u2
uh and u1 and you know
where we have s3 which is detail and it
only has done year one so far
and so the client was the client was
talking to
s1 um and
we now want to think about like what
happens uh what needs to happen
if one of these crashes and so let's
start with the case that the
head crashes and so the head crashes
what needs to be done
this is an easy case this is a hard case
it's easier i hope it's an easy case why
flip it
uh you can just cut off um the head
oh sorry the yeah the head and you know
make
uh s2 the head now yeah we can just
promote
you know so what's going to happen
correct is that the configuration server
discovers that s1 is gone
or decides that s1 is gone and uh
then uh basically uh can promote s2 to
be the
head uh in subsequent uh operations
and clients now in the future then talk
to this guy
and why is this correct so what
operation have we lost
we lost you three yeah is that a problem
that's valid to lose operations
yeah it's fair game to lose you're free
correctly your free has not been
committed
because only operations at the tail are
committed and so it's just as if the
operation never happened you know the
client could not even have observed you
know that actually you
uh that this uh u2 or you're free
actually has happened or you three yes
okay so it's perfectly fine to do this
why is it important that the
configuration server is actually
involved here could like stu ii decides
on its own to become the head
let's say s2 couldn't talk to he has one
anymore and decides like ah whatever i
want to become head
would that be valid
wouldn't that uh like maybe create a
split
uh yeah yeah that would create a split
break right because it might you know f2
might then just be partitioned
from s1 and so now both are heads
and maybe both are processing commands
you know we you know violate our
uh you know basically sort of this whole
property of having a total order
you know um does this to even know that
s1 is ahead
uh because it just receives um
it probably got it from the
configuration information in the
previous time
right like when you know configuration
service decides on the new configuration
they can tell all the servers and
whatever and the clients that actually
care you know here's the new
configuration
wait does this only happen when like s1
to s2 connection is separate or
wait what so what causes the split brain
again
display brain would happen if s2 on its
own decided that as one has failed and
became the head
and so we're not allowed to have that
happen and the way actually the
will work out in practice is that there
is a configuration server
that actually decides what is actually
the current configuration
and so if it decides that s1 is dead
then it can inform s2 and f3 saying like
hey
you guys are now the new chain and s2 is
the head
and when that change happens so in this
case basically s1 is dropped
nothing else has to happen uh because uh
s2 ha the only update that we lost is
the one that actually was not committed
anyway so there's nothing to be repaired
further
so making this going from this setting
from free replicas with the dropping the
head is a basically pretty
straightforward operation
okay i have a question
so there is there's an assumption here
right that um
like the uh commands that like
like leave s1 like will arrive
in order uh in s2
is that like is that a reasonable
assumption for like
well i think the way they uh so they
basically say you know we
need a reliable fifo between s1 and s2
right and from s2 to s3
and i think the way they basically
implement that is probably using tcp
connection
okay thanks okay so
uh let's look at the second case uh so
we
have you know s1 you know
s2 s3
and of course there could be more you
know servers in the chain but like you
know
uh three is enough for us to consider
all the cases
and so now what we want to do take the
case where a middle one crashes
so this one crashes and uh
so the configuration server at some
point decides yeah s2 is crashed
you know informs s1 and s3 uh basically
they form the new chain
uh and we're wondering about like what
else needs to happen
okay we saw in the first case the head
drops then nothing really has to be done
other than updating the chain now we're
updating the chain and the question is
is anything needs to happen
the s1 needs to send to s3 the request
that it's sent to s2 but didn't make it
to s3
yes exactly right so we have you know u1
u2
u3 uh we this was guy had seen u1 and u2
this guy has ceo one uh
and you know the u2 that's actually in
progress you know
uh uh
and then i got lost mass two basically
s1 has to bring s3 up to date
and basically four and u2 and u3
okay so there's actually a little bit of
work involved let's consider the final
case
the tail so here we go again
we have three cases it's one
or the three servers s2 yeah the third
one s3
and uh and let's see so
the tail crashes
and so at some point in time uh
the configuration server notices decides
that the new chain is going to be f1 and
s2 tells f1 and m2
that they're part of the new chain and
uh what else needs to happen
well let's write down we know
these guys have seen u1 u2 and u3 this
guy has seen u1 and u2
so who becomes the new tail in this
scenario
s2 yes student becomes a new tab and
anything else that needs to happen
um i guess the client needs to be
informed that s2 is the
yeah that's what the client might learn
is from the configuration server correct
uh and so yeah but nothing else has to
happen right because
uh the all the committed you know the
no committed operations are lost uh and
uh you know and as we are still in
uh needs to still be actually propagated
to s2 and won't be just happening
okay so dropping details also reasonable
straightforward so dropping the tail in
the head is
reasonable straightforward dropping the
middle one is a little bit more
complicated
but not much more complicated and the
key thing though i want to
sort of emphasize here is how does this
compare to figure seven and eight
in the rafter
these new operations have been
automatically committed
uh sorry i didn't hear you uh you were
pretty uh
it was a pretty noisy connection there
yeah so i was just saying that this too
becomes a new uh
tale don't we have to send
acknowledgements back to the client that
there are some entries that have been
automatically committed
uh yeah that might be the case that uh
what
will happen is the client is probably
gonna retry correct and
uh we have to have a separate dude
duplication scheme like in
uh lab three anyway and so there's
a probably a couple different ways about
how to do it the paper is actually not
particularly clear
which one it will take
thank you yeah like in that in that case
then in the paper just say like you know
it might
like even if it doesn't respond it could
or could not like have succeeded
right like yeah okay so
back to my actually original question
which is like you know how does this
contrast this picture my you know my
drawing picture here on this white board
how does that contrast to figure seven
and eight
simpler yeah i mean that's the key point
i wanted to get across right these uh
you know there's
not that many cases to consider here
basically three cases
uh which is like slightly uh you know
quite a bit simpler than
uh the in the case of the wrap paper
where you know the many convenience to
consider and
the scenarios are quite complicated now
part of that is because
you know it's a chain right you know
things are pushed down
uh the in a very sort of uh
straightforward manner
down the replication chain and part of
that is of course you know the
configuration part
is sort of outsourced to the
configuration manager manager
but for the primary backup uh part of
the recovery plan that's a reasonable
straightforward you know there are only
three configurations to
consider
now one more sort of point i want to
make which is like you know how to add a
replica
because any system you know that you're
going to run for real time really at
some point you got to
add a new one in because otherwise you
know you're going to lose when you start
your three then you have two then you
have one and then you have zero and then
you're unveiled
so you know you have to add new
replicas so let's consider the case uh
so here's s1
it is the head and let's say we're in
the scenario where
you know we have s1 and s2 which detail
and basically we want to bring up you
know s3
and it turns out you know as the paper
described that it was most convenient to
actually do this
at the uh at the tail end of it and so
basically make the new server
the uh the new tail and so the way that
would proceed
is like so the client is here it's
talking to
uh s2 because that's the current tail uh
s3 comes up
and basically what the first thing it
does is actually copies you know all the
state from s3 to
from s2 to s3 and so this may take hours
right or you know tens of minutes or
maybe indeed multiple hours is like
we're copying
you know gigabytes of data or terabytes
of data from s2 to s3
but while that's happening you know as
two and as you know as free can just
surf requests of course it does have to
remember which ones uh
are came in after you know s3 start
copying so keep a list of like all the
updates that are sort of
have happened but there have not been
propagated to s3 yet
at some point s3 is done you know with
all the copying and basically tells us
to
okay man i'm ready you know to become
detail i got the whole state
uh s2 says uh and so sends an email
basically it says emails it's a message
s2 saying like okay i want to be the
tail
has two responses like yeah that's okay
but once you're
applied all the updates
and so basically s2 sends the updates in
response to
this i want to be go on become the
tail uh requests you know in response to
that to s3
s3 applies the updates and then becomes
the the
detail and you know clients that were
talking to s2 and s2 can tell the client
you know from now on i'm not the tail
anymore you should talk to that screen
and so they can swap you know that
direction
and so that's the way to add a replica
into a chain
so question on this um don't you run
into this like infinite loop problem
where s2 sends updates to s3 and when s3
is like
updating it's also serving more requests
and so has more updates
that needs to send and goes back and
forth no no like
once s2 has sent the updates that s3 has
not seen yet you know to s2
to f3 then from then on its normal chain
replication whenever s2 gets a
request you know an update from s1 you
know it forwards it to s3
right but s3 can't become the tail until
it is successfully processed
all of the updates oh yeah so uh yeah
once it sets up the tcp channel
basically s2 can just say like
from once you have processed these guys
you can become the tail because you have
seen everything
i mean and everything else you know can
be pipelined after that right in the
same tcp channel
it it it could become the tail right
right after
like even before it processed the update
right as long as it doesn't serve
requests
and as long as doesn't serve requests
exactly right it just has to process all
the updates that s2 has received in s3
not
once it's updated those then it becomes
the
tail and start processing requests
i see so it blocks like requests for a
moment while
it processes the new updates got it
exactly
okay
okay so now uh you know i want to come
back you know go to
basically questions lots of people ask
you know how this contrasts to
sort of you know how are the cr
properties
or chain replication properties how do
how does it compare
what are the good ass what are the good
properties and mostly you know with
respect or in comparison to
rap and of course you know
i gotta say of course like uh the the
the chain replication
just implements the the primary backup
scheme but not you know the
configuration surface
and so we'll come back to that a little
bit more in detail but a couple of
things that we can note
if we just compare sort of uh
the way the raf protocol works with the
chain replication protocol
and first of all you know we can you
know positive aspect of you know chain
replication is that
the client rpcs
are in a split between
between the head and the tail
and so the load of actually serving any
client operation that can be split
actually between two of them
they don't have to all run through the
leader as in in raft
furthermore the head sends an update
once so unlike in raft
where the head or the leader basically
sends updates
the log entries to every appear in this
particular scheme
actually it's only happened the the head
only sends one
basically rpc and so there are fewer
messages involved
reads or query operations
involve only
only the tail all right in the raft you
know the
if you even if you implement the
read-only optimization
the read-only optimization avoids
having the read operation to go through
the log and
being appended to all the walks that
appears but it still requires that the
leader actually contacts the majority of
the peers to decide
whether to actually the operation can be
served
and so another positive aspect of the
spinosa simple
crash recovery as we talked about
uh but you know a major downside you
know compared to
sort of the raf scheme is that one
failure
requires reconfigurations
and the reason that the recognition uh
required is because like
a right actually has to go through the
whole chain
and so and the right cannot be
acknowledged until that every you know
server in the chain actually has
processed it and that is actually
slightly different correctly wrapped as
you well know
because as soon as basically a majority
the peers actually have accepted the
particular write operation and appended
to their logs
the system can just proceed and so
there's actually no
interruption at all if like one server
fails for example
and if the remaining server still form a
majority now while in chain replication
if one server would fail then you know
some refrigeration actually has to
happen which means you know there's
going to be a short period of you know
probably downtime
right does that make sense
now i want to make one more point uh
sort of in contrast you know to sort of
the
rafter replication scheme is that this
because the read operations involve only
one server there's a cool
uh extension if you will that actually
gets really high read performance
and so the basic idea is as follows
uh the basic idea is basically to split
you know the
split objects or they called volumes in
the paper
split the objects across multiple chains
so instead of having one chain as i
would have done in the previous
boards you know we're going to have
multiple chains and so for example we
might have a
you know ch1 and in chain one
you know s1 is the head s2 is the
middle guy and s3 is the tail in chain
two
yeah we're going to rotate things around
s2 is the head
as one is the where s3 is the middle guy
oops
s3 is the middle guy and s1
is the tail and then chain 3
we're going to arrange basically s3 is
the head guy s2 is the
uh s1 is the middle guy and s2
is the tail and basically what we're
going to do is we're going to split
objects across these multiple chains so
the configuration server basically has a
map you know saying like you know
shard one you know objects insured one
go to chain one
uh objects in shar2 go to chain two
objects in shard three now go to chain
three
uh and what is the cool part about it is
that uh
you know we have no multiple tails and
we as well as three is the tail
for some chain as one is a uh a tail for
some uh
chain that's two is a tail for some
chain and basically
read operations for these different
chains uh can now be completely executed
in parallel
so if the read operations sort of hit
all the different charge
uh sort of uniformly spread that
basically you know the our read
throughput is going to increase you know
linearly with the number of uh
tails that we have and in this case we
have three tails so we get three times
the read performance
so we can basically sort of same with
some you know we get a little bit of the
same properties that zookeeper had
where the real performance can be
excellent you know it can scale with the
number server
uh but we also get not only that we get
the scale part
but we maintain the linearizability
in this scheme we don't have to actually
give up on linearizability
so we get sort of the two nice
properties mainly you know good
re-performance in fact the scaling with
the number of servers
at least for reach or two different
chains uh and
we got actually uh and we maintain
linearizability
any questions about this
sorry in this case the client when they
are deciding
which um chain to read from
would they be able to to do it like to
decide themselves or do they need to
contact the configuration server to
decide
yeah so this is a great question uh so
typically and the paper actually doesn't
really
it's explicit about it you know they
talk about maybe talking through
proxy you know to the servers uh what
you will do in lab four
is basically you will download the
configurations the configuration will
include
the shard assignment and you will
download that from the configuration
server
you need to be careful about how you
ordered the servers in each of the
chains to prevent like
a particular chain from being
oversaturated or a particular link
between like two servers
uh yeah this this this scheme doesn't
really take that into account uh you can
imagine like
the configuration planner uh the
configuration manager has a
sophisticated model of actually how the
network
is laid out and you know can be very
careful about how the chains are done
maybe even shower more shards to one
chain or fewer shards to another chain
uh all that stuff is in principle
possible right because the configuration
can just manage you can just compute
anything it likes and basically says
here's the assignment
thank you i can even rebalance if it
wants to
answer the question could you explain
again how linearized deal is kept under
this
uh extension well nothing has really
changed
uh we're still doing primary backup uh
using a chain
uh and uh and so you know the
we basically carry over the
linearizability from the single chain
and that's it
this might be like speculative but how
this compared to
or i guess maybe it's equivalent of just
like having groups of servers for each
like link instead of having reusing the
same ones or
not for each link but for each uh
step in the chain so like s1 is like
three servers s2 is three servers
instead of reusing the same one and
entering from different points
uh yeah what would be the advantage of
that
scheme that you imagine i mean just for
scalability um
while also maintaining mineralizability
well the
the reason that this scheme is
attractive is that because we have in
the tail might have quite a bit of load
but the middle guy doesn't
and you know by having sort of this
arrangement we spread the load across
all servers
i see okay
okay good so well maybe i want to
summarize here
and sort of talk a little bit about so
we saw this approach one
which we do which we do in lab3 which is
you know we run all the operations
through raft and all the uh
replication you know the configuration
and the replication is all built using
uh
a raft and nothing else is involved and
then sort of this approach to
you know which is the topic of this
particular paper
uh where you know there's a
configuration server perhaps built
using raft or you know packs with anyone
and a primary backup replication scheme
and primary backup
using chain replication
and you can see you know hopefully you
know this lecture makes it
clear that you know there's some
attractive properties to approach too
uh in the sense that uh you can get
scalable re-performance
uh on the primary backups uh of course
not on the configuration server because
you know it
runs raft like you know you do in
approach one
but you get at least you know maybe
scalable reperforms for actually your
operations on the replicas or on the
the primary background scheme like to
put in get operations
um and the other uh thing that is nice
about this is that sort of
the if you have your data is very very
large you know you can have more
specialized
uh uh synchronization
or uh uh schemes to basically copy the
state from one machine to another
machine
uh and you know the chain replication
order but any sort of primary backup
scheme that sort of separated from the
configuration server
allows you to do that easily and so it's
a quite
common that you know the in practice you
know people call products too
although it is also not impossible to
actually uh
use approach one for your replicated
state machine including servicing um
operations like you know put together
operations and the factors receiving
lab3 would do it
we will see later a paper in uh semester
called spanner
that actually uses you know access to
actually also do the operations
any further questions here
if not then i wish you all good luck on
the midterm on thursday
and i'll see you in person well
virtually in person
uh next week
and if you have any questions please
feel free to hang around
and i'll try to do my best to answer
that
question yep i have a question about
something that
you mentioned about raft so you
mentioned that all of the reads have to
go through the majority of servers
but i'm not quite sure i understand why
because the leader
has all of the committed entries right
yeah there's two
two schemes uh if the leader
so either you run in the situation where
all recent rights are served by the
leader
right or you know there's a possibility
to serve in principle
a read operation from another peer but
then you have to contact the first and
majority
of the service to make absolutely sure
that you have the last operation
got it so that that requirement is if we
want to
spread all the reads across every year
and then we have to be more
sophisticated and we cannot do it on our
own because that would definitely
directly interact ability
right but if everything goes to the
leader we don't then then you're
in your golden correct except you know
you have to do this trick where you have
sort of an empty agreement
uh at the beginning of every new term
just to make sure that you actually are
up to date
okay thank you could you um
quickly go over again uh when you're
adding a new server at the tail
so just to make sure i understand so
essentially
it starts this process for like copying
all the data from s2 to s3
yep and then if it receives requests for
any of that data while
that is still happening then s3 is going
to like
ask s2 for anything that it still has
directly and it's going to get it and
then respond
yep and then it keeps doing that until
it gets
data that s2 no longer has and then it
just goes live essentially
yeah well you could do it slightly
differently you know you could actually
have
s3 you could uh basically tell
s2
s3 can become the leader or the sort of
detail and
basically don't process any comment
operations from the client yet until it
actually has
has received the remaining operations
from s2
oh so in that case s2 is still the tail
yeah you do not know s3 gets everything
yeah
okay thank you there's basically
the paper describes one particular way
of doing it there's a couple ways of
doing it
but if you do that then um like
how long do you wait to get everything
um i think i also have the same
confusion as someone else well you know
you know in what order the switch is
happening correct like so for example
like
s3 uh so s2 is let's say maybe has
update operations
through 100 you start the copy operation
it's like with the snapshots in the
raft you start the copy operation so
when the copy operation is done s3 is up
to date until 100
right then you know maybe s2 already has
done
10 more operations so it has 101 102 and
right and basically uh
as free you can you know contact us too
saying give me
your remaining operations and stu says
like well my remaining operations 101
through 1 and 10. and and as a side
effect you know
s3 also tells us to like stop being
detailed
and s2 responds with those operations
s3 applies those operations 101 through
and then tells client and in the
meantime it is tail but it doesn't
process any commands from clients yet
or read operation client yet until it
actually has process 101 through 110.
okay okay i see i see
like that oh
my question was a little similar to the
uh extension that he talked about
um i thought i thought about
could you could he do a tree instead of
a chain
so ah uh i think there's
the uh there are other data structures
possible
uh like for example you know a number of
people in email proposed
that you could like have s one then you
could have like uh
s two three four five all the
intermediate ones you know s1 talks to
them in parallel to all the intermediate
ones and then the intermediate ones in
their top all to
the tail uh is that what you mean with a
tree
i meant morph there would be
like a number of leaves that would be
at all roughly the same height so like a
balanced tree
and then the leaves will have like a
chain going through them
um and i think that like linear
disability
can be broken here if you like
um if you think harder about it but
it would it would have the nice property
that you wouldn't like
then the propagation delay would be like
logarithmic instead of linear
as here and you could read from all the
leaves but yeah okay reading from all
the leaves is dangerous correct because
uh they might have you know one client
might have talked to another
or another leaf earlier and these guy
might not be in sync
uh so that sounds dangerous to me
but maybe your your scheme is a little
bit more sophisticated than i'm uh i'm
thinking
um the depth of the tree or the depth of
the chain is really uh
governed by the mean time between
failure correct
uh if you're on the main team uh if you
typically run with free service or three
to five servers because that's good
enough for your
high availability then because you can
you know recover from four
servers before the whole thing is down
um
then uh that really governs the depth of
the chain
um and yeah that will introduce some
latency
okay that makes sense yeah thank you
change will generally be short
right okay okay that makes sense thanks
is this the only case where the entire
chain would go down
if all of the servers in the chain went
down yep
thank you uh
i also was curious how you like maintain
the strong consistency when like
uh s1 s2 and s3 can all like do the read
in this slide you get strong consistency
per shard or per object you know that's
assigned to the chain
right so you read uh
you write one object you write object
one you read object one
all those operations are going to go
through the same chain and so you get
strong consistency for that particular
object
oh got it but it may not indicate that
across all the objects we have strong
consistency
no i don't uh i will let me hesitate or
not
uh
let me have state i think you know that
requires maybe more machinery
well what does that mean like across all
the objects
getting stronger you read write object
one
you rewrite object two and
then uh some client reach or object one
uh are you gonna yeah basically you know
if you have a client that reached
both objects are you guaranteed
guaranteed to see total order and
uh linearizing that like serializability
uh the serializability is slightly
different um you know i mean
let's not talk about serializability
we'll come back we'll get to get that
later in a couple weeks
uh yeah and um
i'm having to do actually make a
commitment right now i need to think a
little bit about it
okay that's totally fair
so the question is like you know you
have consistency or linearizability for
a single
client reading and writing but not for
multiple
on multiple objects you have even
multiple clients
talking to this you know doing
operations on the same object have
strongly interacted have linearizability
correct in this scheme
the question is do you have you know
linearizability across
objects too but
why is that important i i don't see
where like
where that would be important like
because you're you're gonna like
you can't group operations right so like
a right and right right i mean you read
object one
you write update one you read object one
then you read up direct q you write
object two
uh and you know the
the question is you know in
linearizability you know those
operations need to be total order and
they need to pursue uh
preserve this property off uh real time
and since you're here you have different
chains that might actually
not happen but i don't want to commit to
no statement about it all across change
you know within the chain that's
absolutely guaranteed linearizability
even if you have different objects
there's something i don't understand in
the paper which is the um
update propagation invariant where like
uh sort of the for
in this order of the chain yep the like
uh commits are prefix of each successors
commits is that guaranteed
after like a full pass has gone through
the chain
well it's always true right like you
know if you go back to this picture here
um i think the
makeup basically very simple observation
which is let's see if i can find a good
picture
i probably scribbled over everything so
it's going to be maybe not as clean
basically what they're saying like if
you look at this figure correct
that um s3 always has a prefix of s2 and
s2 always has a prefix of s1
and that's the only thing that basically
that invariant says
oh the so i and j
so the the one out the successor is has
the prefix of the predecessor yeah
and this is slightly confusing i just
realized that later uh
after somebody else asked this question
uh
in the definition the
are is in two different ways uh well not
really in different ways one is a
definition
uh and one is actually the the the
invariant
um and uh you guys are gonna be a little
bit careful
the uh the roles of the ice and in the
very
other around yeah exactly how is that
possible
exactly thank you you're welcome
uh yeah sorry go ahead
come on i was just gonna ask um what
happens when you have like a network
partition instead of a crash
um so if you go to like the crash slide
uh
what happens to the chain if there's a
network partition so maybe s
something like uh uh like s2 is actually
still alive
but there's a partition between the
configuration manager and
an s2 or something and so now both s1
and s2 are pointing to s3
no no no uh yeah okay yeah
okay there's there's gonna be some uh
presumably but i
i think the the paper doesn't talk about
this but i presume that all
configurations are numbered
uh like a view number and uh s3 will not
accept any commands from s2
if the few numbers don't match
oh you got it thank you so related to
that uh one thing i couldn't figure out
is even with like uh configuration
numbers or something
how do you make sure that when you get
rid of the tail in like the third
scenario that you've drawn
now that when you get to the tail that
uh all the clients that might issue a
read
are aware that this old server is no
longer fail clients
i think the the way you would do it is
that the configuration
when the client download the
configuration from the configuration
manager they also include the view
number
and every operation includes the view
number and and
s3 you will see hey that's an old view
number
don't talk to you i i guess uh when then
does the clients talk to the
configuration server to get a new view
number
so for example the the s2 could just say
like retry
and the client then could go back to the
configuration server and re-read to the
state
uh i i guess what i'm worried about is
like s3 has been network partitioned
away from the
the court uh from the coordinator and so
the coordinator like gets rid of s3 from
the tail and increases the version
number
uh but some client out there doesn't
find out that the version numbers
increase
and still thinks s3 is the tail talks s3
does a read
meanwhile people are doing rights to s1
s2 and
they haven't heard it or they haven't
seen that basically
yeah this is probably the reason why in
the paper go through the proxy
see okay
i have a question kind of going back to
that
like i noticed a question about um kind
of like cross
object linearizability
um i guess like is that a whole another
can of worms that we haven't really
talked about which is like if you want
to do
i don't know what the right term is but
like transactions that like
across multiple pieces of state like if
you're
trying to implement an operation where
it's like you're setting a to one and b
to two and you should only see those
together or not at all like at ethnicity
of that have we
talked about that in any of the things
we've seen before no and we'll talk
about within a couple weeks
okay they're going to be a big topic
basically how to do transactions
okay that that's good thanks
do you mind going back to like the third
slide
yep i think it was the third slide
um maybe not fourth slide
oh if it's light sorry um
so i was a little bit confused uh when
you mentioned like if
lockholder failed an intermediate state
stuff um
what exactly on this slide applies to
z-locks and what applies to the
locks again uh these are almost all
statements about z-locks
so is the first statement that if the
lock holder fails then the intermediate
state is
not cleaned up or is cleaned up no the
immediate state is visible but then for
example if you have a leader election
you could clean up that intermediate
state that was just like the
the point oh so with with go locks is
that also not the case like if there's a
machine that's holding a golock
that's doing stuff and then it all of a
sudden dies
isn't still the intermediate state
visible
okay i think what i'm talking about is
gold locks you know is something that's
a statement about
multiple threats running on the same
machine right and so
if the go lock disappears because the
machine crashes all the threads on that
machine crashed too
right but when you say that the
intermediate state is visible
to other people it that's still true for
gold locks though right
you know if they written persistent
state to disk uh
or into some shared file system but like
no the machine is gone the disk is gone
everything's gone
oh got it okay so it's saying that the
pers like the persistence
like the intermediate state is
persistent the zookeeper intermediate
state might be visible right not to
delete the thing the guy might have
created some more files and you know
those are visible now
okay i see thank you so just to follow
up on that so it's the implication that
if a goal routine ever dies while
holding the walk the entire go program
must have died too
and there's you can never have a go
routine die holding a lock with that
with
and like have other parts of the program
continue no
okay the go routine crashes the
application crashes