Okay, good afternoon,
sound check sound checking,
people can hear me?
Yeah.
Thank you,
okay, good, so good afternoon, good evening, good morning, good night, wherever you are,
I'm going to talk today more about raft
and we want to cover following different topics,
which are going to be relevant to labs.
So, first of all, I want to talk a little bit more about log divergence,
we sort of had a cliffhanger at the end of last lecture,
where we got in a discussion that figure six,
I want to resume that discussion.
I want to talk about log catch up and what happens,
if how do followers catch up,
then a little bit of a persistence like what state must be,
what's raft state must be persistent in storage
which is really relevant for 2c and 2d,
and also talk about [] out to snapshots.
Yeah, if there's any questions, please feel free to ask
and then finally I want to talk about linearizability
and correct criterion that comes up quite often in the paper
used also in a bunch of places,
and this will allow us to talk a little bit again about how does this server use raft.
So, those are the topics we plan to talk about,
you have any questions right now, please feel free to ask,
and of course always jump in at any point.
Okay, so, so we saw it last week,
we started talking about raft,
you know we saw that the leader has served this job of replicating its log onto the onto followers
and but you know due to crashes in leader election,
the state of the system, you know the logs can actually quite can diverse quite quite a bit,
in figure six is an illustration,
you know why, how, how that could happen,
you know the leaders can go down,
they may append some more entries
and so there's a whole bunch of different scenarios,
yeah that our system can end up in
and so the figure six, six, seven actually shows a bunch of those
and the, and the main reason, for the figure is that,
it actually sharpens up the leader election rule,
so once the leader goes down
and we need to elect a new leader,
there's actually some restrictions that must be applied
to actually make sure that we can get converged on the right log in the end.
And so, first of all,
one part of that is that any leader need to achieve a majority,
and this is a part of the idea
to actually avoid just brain split syndrome or split brain syndrome,
sort of we can actually make sure that
you know in any two subsequent elections,
there's going to be at least one node,
that participated in both majorities,
because you can only do two majority must overlap
and that node must actually have you know operations from a recent, from the recent term.
The majority is important,
but turns out it's actually a little bit more shuttle,
you might think that like the longest log that should be sufficient,
because the longest log has most information,
so we're just picked out as the next leader
and then we're in good shape
and that turns out to be not the case.
And and so, and leader rules a little bit more subtle,
you know actually majority plus at least as of date, at-least but up to date.
So, so to you know the leader election is running a follower,
so the candidate is starting to run leader election approaches,
bunch of followers
and the followers response with a positive vote,
if the candidate actually is at least up to date as they are.
And what that means is that,
the last log entry must actually have the same term
or in if they actually have the same term,
the longest one sort of wins.
And so, so that the leader the election rule you know we look at this problem last week
as part of the homework
and what happens if you know this note you know what's worse about the leader actually is dead,
it's gone,
you know and who could become leaders,
and you know quickly discovered that,
you know there there's a bunch of them that cannot become leader,
but then there's potentially a number of scenarios in which some can become leaders.
And so, in particular, you know we identify that a can become leader,
c can become leader, and d can became leader.
And so then, and so there's probably the most important part of this whole discussion, right,
who can become leader.
[] there's question.
There, let me hold on.
Okay.
So who becomes that's the most important part,
so there's a bunch of different scenarios,
in which a can become a leader,
there's a scenario where c become a leader,
in the scenario where d become a leader.
Then the discussion focus a little bit,
like well at least there's one particular scenario,
in which one of these becomes leader,
others multiple scenarios in which take over the leader,
particularly focus this discussion focused on a,
because like one way that a can become a leader
is when c and d are down, right,
because c and d are down,
a will talk to b e and f form a majority with 4,
it has the most up to date log,
you notice that you know even though f is a longer log,
that actually is not the most up to date one,
so a actual succeed in becoming the leader,
and then things proceed from there.
But there was an interesting question that came up is
are other scenarios in which a can become a leader in particular,
or is there scenario where even if c and d are up,
or reachable or participate,
is it possibility a becomes a leader,
so we see c and d up
and so the question is does c and d always vote for a,
if a is the candidate.
And it turns out is actually slightly complicated,
it is not completely straightforward,
so if a starts this election,
presumably it will start the election in term 7.
And so if context c and d you know c will be perfectly fine with that,
because the a is at least up to date,
and so we'll be able to achieve a majority,
but you know it is possible correct d,
there's one additional rule that if d actually has,
if follower follower has a higher term as c in higher term,
its current term is higher,
then the or the candidate then actually it can stop the election,
because it will respond saying like hey my term is higher than your higher my term,
my current term is higher than your term
and so therefore you have to become a follower,
so a will then be changed back from candidate to follower.
And this can happen correctly,
in case of d, this d might actually have seen term a
and we can't really tell from this picture,
what actually the outcome is going to be,
let's assume that example,
you know the it has run once and has increases term to 8,
it didn't become succeeded leader
and then its current term will 8
and so it will vote when a ask to for its vote,
you know d will say no,
I won't vote for you,
and furthermore by current term is a,
so a will see that message,
it's higher than a 7
and so a will actually step down
and become just a follower
and then at some point later,
presumably you know d will run its election timer will go off
and actually it will run.
And so the short story of this you know morale is gonna,
really this picture is that,
it's absolutely possible,
that a c and d can become leader in different types of scenarios,
and that's probably the main thing to get out of this.
Professor.
Yeah.
So, I I just want to ask,
because I think I I'm not sure if I understood correctly,
but then you said a might be elected in terms 7,
it is not true that it cannot for any reason be elected in terms 7,
even if d was down, right,
because people like like d, like already got a majority, right, in 7.
d got a majority in 7, because it actually was able to get something done,
so presumably right, you're right,
you know the good observation,
so it has to be the case that,
there's a number of people that actually already in term 7,
and the picture is incomplete,
we don't really know what the current term is,
that people have seen so far.
Yeah.
Right.
Well, yeah, I mean the only thing is like, I think like a majority of the servers already voted for someone in term 7, so.
Absolutely, a will go to term 8,
and you know we'll run the election for 8,
but you know for the same reason, d might already be in 9, right
and so it all depends on what the current term is,
what these actually these participants are in.
But the main conclusion, correct the main top level conclusion is that,
a can become leader certainly when c and d are offline,
c can become leader and d can become a leader.
Thanks.
Okay, then, let's so so we now know that the raft can sort of ended in states,
where the logs are diverged
and so that needs to be repaired
and it's like one a key component of the raft protocol is
to do the that log catch up as they call it,
so I talked a little bit about that.
And this is basically what you're sort of have to deal with in part b of the lab.
So I may be easier to illustrate with this picture,
so let's, it's going to make it a little bit simple,
let's have 3 servers,
here's S1, it has, you know. term 3 in index 10,
the index 11, has no entries in [] and 11 12 13,
here we have S2, S2 has entries you know 3 3 5,
and so this is index 10 11 12 and 13 13 used to make it complete,
and here is S4, oh sorry S3,
and let's do where in the scenario 3 3 4, and 10 11 12 13.
And I'm not showing like the indexes before 10,
they're not be very relevant.
Yeah, you know use the timeline, these different servers.
And just let's start out assuming that,
the S2 becomes the leader,
because it has the highest,
it is mostly to date,
it has the highest term number in the last log entry,
so it becomes leader.
And now, when you need to understand how about the protocol is to synchronize these particular logs,
in the way you know this almost happens is sort of a side effect of you know either the append entries,
because new log entries are appended or because of heartbeats,
which basically are append entries with zero new entries.
So let's assume that the leader actually sends heartbeat out,
in fact it does it correct,
the election immediately sends out a heartbeat,
and so it will sends out the heartbeat,
and the heartbeat basically has no log entries,
but it also indicates two other pieces of information,
namely the previous term,
so the previous term, which in this case it's going to be 5 right
and the previous index, it's gonna be 12.
So it sends it off to the leader S2 sends to S3
and S3 looks at this
and says well look my previous terms,
actually is not 5, it's actually 4,
and so, it actually sends back a message saying no,
you know I'm I'm alive in principle,
but you know I I know I cannot do your append,
so I'm not up to date.
And now S2 have some information to actually bring it up to date
and the way it works is,
there's sort of two variables that are of importance,
one for every node, S2 for, keeps a variable next index,
and next index when it initialize it, becomes leader,
it is sort of an optimistic variable,
it just assumes that the logs are actually up to date.
And so, when S2 becomes a leader,
it actually just sets it to 13,
you know the same value that actually it has for itself.
That's perfectly fine,
because it's just a guess,
if one actually the where S3 might be
and that we might be behind,
and then you know because there's no message,
the leader actually learns that.
And so, in fact you know when it gets there's no message,
in the unoptimized version,
so I'm going to first talk about the unoptimized version,
the leader just decrements the next index by one
and so it decrements 13 to 12,
and then we got some point will send another append entries,
and this time around you know it will actually say okay we'll make next in this 12,
you know got a send you know log in 3 5,
and you know the previous term, it's gonna be 3,
and the previous index is going to be 11.
And so when S3 actually received this message,
you know check the previous term 3,
the previous index is 11,
that all works out,
it seems that it has append 5
and so it will erase the 4 and stick a 5 in there
and basically respond saying yep, good.
So at this point, the leader knows that actually the log is up to date,
because you've got an okay message back,
then there's the second variable that plays an important role in all this,
which is match index, which raft also maintains for,
leader also maintains for every follower.
So there's an next index you know for S3,
here's next index for S1,
and similar there's a match index,
you know for S1 S2 S3 too.
And this one is sort of, if you think about this as pessimistic or lower bound,
so when the leader actually you know becomes leader,
it actually sets the value just 0,
and to indicate that basically as far as knows S3 doesn't really have any log entries at all,
and so it hasn't delivered any log entries to the application,
and so for S2 also has to be very careful about what actually it can be delivered to the application,
there goes if he needs to know,
that at least a majority of the followers actually has a copy of a particular log entry, before it can deliver.
So just start to be pessimistic,
but then once it learns you know that for example once it learns actually got the follower is okay
and we've gotten okay the append message,
it can actually update you know the pessimistic,
lower bound or the match index from 0 to actually 13,
because it has learned that the follower is actually up to date till 13,
and that's the next index that expect is you know 13.
And at this point in time,
basically it has learned from two different,
knows that, that particular log entry 5 is actually now replicated at least in two nodes.
And so you might think well good,
it has been replicated in two nodes,
we can deliver to the application,
because the majority clearly has it,
and we're in good shape.
And unfortunately, that actually turned out not to be the case,
it's close to true, but not completely true,
and this actually has to do with figure 8,
so I want to talk a little bit about figure 8
and the real reason what's going on here to make this slightly complicated
and you also should think a little bit fishy.
So this leader S2 just erased the value out of the log of S3
and you know somebody put that in,
and you know raising it,
you know, yeah it seems a little bit you know dangerous
and as in and so it turns out there is a corner case,
where you have to be a bit careful,
by when you deliver when you declare a message actually committed.
And it turns out that basically, yeah, if figure 8 illustrates that.
So let me talk a little bit about this erasing log entries.
And we will see is that the rule for actually when the message can be delivered to the application is
is slightly more subtle than just counting the replicates.
Let's see actually gets figure 8 load it in.
Okay so here's figure 8 and so as usual structure.
Okay, let me get back to the question in the in the chat in a second,
so here's figure 8
and so let's walk through what the scenario here is,
correct in figure a you know what log entry one has been committed by everybody,
you know the S1 or S2 became leader in entry in term 2,
they committed or they started appending an entry 2,
hasn't been committed yet,
because it's not a majority for sure,
then indeed what actually happens,
you know S5 wasn't disconnected has word of this term 2,
became a leader in term 3,
appended an entry to each log,
that certainly is not committed,
because there's no majority,
then we end up in c,
maybe the S5 actually got disconnected again,
S1 becomes a leader in term 4,
it starts replicating you know entry, this log entry 2 to other nodes.
And, in fact you know deliver it,
you know it gets back,
you know like shown in the previous slide,
in those actually on S2 and those actually use S3.
And it turns out you know that actually you might think,
okay, well you know S1 knows you know that actually 3 3 nodes actually have a copy of this particular entry
and so I might be able to deliver it
and it turns out that's not true,
and there's more subtle reasoning that needs to happen to actually commit
and namely you can only commit.
Oops, sorry, you can commit after the leader has committed,
one entry in its own term.
And if we think about this number 2,
it actually isn't from leaders in term 4
and and so the the the commit rule wouldn't allow actually commit 2 immediately to the servers,
because that actually is one from a previous term and not from the current term
and so for example your code to decide whether actually something can be delivered on the applied channel
needs to take to this account.
And the reason you need take to account is illustrated by d and e,
basically what can happen is that,
you know for S1 actually might might actually end up in a different situation,
where d actually becomes the,
after, d actually becomes the leader, for example S1 example is particularly disconnected,
and it might actually start connecting,
it can form a majority
and actually it starts copying its particular, its entries to actually,
yeah, all right, it erases you know the 2s
and actually copies it's 3 in the entry for each term 3 into whatever used to be 2
and this is erasing that we talked about on the previous slide.
And so we'll see, actually though even though it was on the majority of the nodes, right,
on the majority of nodes, that got erased.
And so the rule and therefore the rules as I stated here,
because now 1s you know this is illustrated by e,
1s actually S3 S1 commits an entry in its own term,
and so it knows that every no there's a majority in its own term,
so at this point, it can actually deliver 4 you know to the application
and as a result of that,
you know any nodes that were committed in previous terms can also be delivered to the application.
So you see here that this erasing of log entries,
that basic commits makes the commit rule quite slightly more complicated.
And that's just the design decisions that the designers of raft made,
you know they could have done it differently,
they could have counted
and made basically 2 survive, if they wanted to,
but they decided to go for this particular approach on the grounds,
that they think it's simpler.
Okay, so this is suddenly that will show up,
you know in a test cases for the labs,
so you have to be a little bit of careful with your commit rule.
And then you implement it correctly.
Okay, so, so far, you know if you go back to this particular picture,
the an optimized version of this protocol is a little bit of bummer, right,
like if you think a little bit about this,
let's look at actually what happens with S1.
So let's see, let me switch things,
let's see S2 tries bring S1 up to date,
will do the same thing,
you know send append entries, you know with nil entries,
past term previous term to be 5,
and previous index 12,
it will say no, right,
actually the index you know previous index is actually a 10 with term 3,
so it will, this guy will decrease its next index go from 13 to 12,
then we'll do the same thing again,
you know sent I guess it's gonna send 5, the log entry 5,
it will set the previous term to be 3,
and index previous index 11,
it's going to get a no back,
you know, then the index goes to from 12 to 11,
and now basically it's going to work
and so we'll see hear that basically for every log entry,
we're going to have a round trip for sort of append entries.
And it turns out that that can be expensive, and like,
and and the real question is like you can follower be far far behind.
And let me ask that we're [] for a second,
so you can reflect and think about that case,
is it possible that a follower can be far far behind for a given leader.
If a new machine joins the cluster?
Yeah, new join cluster is a good example, any other cases?
A machine crashed and is only coming back online after several terms.
Yeah, exactly, it comes back after a date,
it might be far behind,
so that would mean like in the protocol and unoptimized version that you're gonna go back one by one from the log entries.
So that's a little bit expensive
and so the paper actually discusses an optimization,
so to catch up quickly.
And, and the idea basically is
instead of like backing off as I said earlier,
the next index is basically optimistic, just guess right
and it doesn't really have to be that accurate,
and and so the observation is that
you know we don't really have to go one by one back,
you know it's perfectly fine for example to go a whole term back.
And in fact there's a logical
maybe that's just a node you know you know it's a couple of terms back
and we back off a couple of terms
and then we'll scan from there.
Alright, so to illustrate a little bit how it works,
let me use the full example,
and I'm just gonna do two servers,
even though they might be you know need 3 to sort of have a majority,
but let's assume there's a third one
and it just plays happily along.
So, here's S1, here's S2,
and let's see you know we this guy has 5 5 5,
and this is 1 2 3 4 5 indexes,
and you know let's say,
S2 has 4, basically all 6s,
so basically S1 is you know quite behind,
because that's the only place where they actually line up is in the first entry, in first which is term 4.
So in the unoptimized scheme,
we would back off one by one, one by one until we finally got there.
And to optimize this, the paper describes an optimization,
unfortunately the opposition is not as described in the same amount of detail as figure 2
and so in fact you will in the for 2c actually pass through c,
you do actually have to have,
and this optimization, a form of this optimization implemented,
your reasonable free actually how to implement it,
because paper doesn't describe very precisely,
you know which how you should do it,
then you have to do a little bit of work,
but the basic idea is as follows.
And just instead of just voting or just saying no or yes, as we know on the previous slide,
the rejection, so you say no,
the rejection includes a little bit of more information
and then that information is going to help the leader to basically back off quicker,
and so includes something what they call the conflicting term,
in response the conflicting index.
And the, the conflicting term is basically the,
you know if let me actually make this a more clear,
let's say here's S1 timeline, here's S2,
so S2 sends you know elected leader in 7, correct,
because it has the most up to date,
a log it sends a message to S1 you know a heartbeat,
and, in a heartbeat,
it will say you know the previous term was 6
and previous index was 5,
and now, when this one gets this you know looks at this log and sees that actually the previous term was 5,
and so instead of actually and so it will include in response
you know conflicting term term conflicts on in that index and that was 5.
We're going to the final entry
and then it also includes what the first index of that term is in this log,
so we look at this term like 5 5 5
and the first time like the index 5 showed up its log is at index 2
and so we'll include that too,
and we'll send that back you know to the leader,
so here's S2 was leader,
and so we're going to send back you know 5 comma 2,
that's the conflicting information
and leader uses that information to basically skip backward further,
in fact it skips back from,
so initially it's guess was next index for S1 was 6.
And based on this information
and it actually scales back to 2,
so it turns it into 2
and then the next append entries is going to include everything from 2.
So its gonna to include you know 5 5 5,
and previous term is 4 and previous index is 1,
and now S1 can one [] [] [],
basically copy you know the new log entries over the entries 2 3 4 or 5 actually back up to date.
So this basically reduces the number of heartbeats,
you know to catch up follower by one per term instead of one per entry.
Any questions?
How do we make sure that we don't you know overload the bandwidth,
because imagine if you have like, you're trying to send back all of these log entries
cause that caused problems in terms of like packets that are too large.
Yeah, so a great question,
like and because it sort of indicates an alternative scheme, right,
but you know the go back here,
is that instead of actually making this optimistic guess
you know why make a guess at all,
just send everything you know the leader could have send like though it's whole log,
it would be perfectly fine
and then basically you know any of the followers can fish out the ones they need, right,
and that would be an alternative implementation
and presumably we don't like the implementation,
because the log might be large
and that would be problematic.
So I think you know the basic guess here that's going on is
that in enormous typical situations,
the followers or you know hopefully reasonable close together
and so backing off a couple entries is actually sufficient.
And if not, then we might go back one term, but not all terms.
And so we'll send the log entries for one term
and that might be a lot, right,
that might be a lot
and we'll see in a second, like how we get around that,
snapshot is going to help you know reducing the number of log entries, that we have to send.
There was a question do you need to implement this sort of version of these optimization scheme in lab 2c,
and the answer is yes.
At least I believe, I haven't been able to pass the test without implementing some optimization.
So I have a question,
so I in my code,
I did the optimization by backing off to the commit,
so I made the the reply include the last commit index
and then I started from there,
is that much worse.
You might run into trouble
and so the the test keep track of how many bytes you sent,
and gives you a budget
and if you're like go across the budget you know by too much,
then the testing will say,
well, you're just sending too much data,
because your scheme it might be the case,
that I think you will send more data than really necessary,
whatever necessary means, but.
There is a question in chat.
Yeah, and did I said draw the wrong thing,
yeah 6 6 6 6 sorry, thank you,
6 6 6, I don't want to follower overriding the leader's log entries,
sorry about that, good catch.
Any questions?
Okay.
Okay, so let me talk a little bit about the persistence,
we have one question in the chat, first.
Okay.
They're wondering why does the rejection has to send back the rejected term number as well as the index.
Well, that depends very much how you actually implement the,
how what kind of state you maintain on the leader
and how the leader decides to back off,
do you need to know send some terms back,
because you need a [] in response get delayed for a long period of time,
you certainly should reject you know information from terms that are completely not relevant anymore.
I know this is slightly vague answer,
but it's really very much dependent on exactly how you implement it.
Okay, persistence,
we talked about the persistence a little bit,
in last raft of, the first raft lecture,
where you know we noted that you know the
and follower can only vote for one candidate per term
and therefore it needs to remember it's who'd voted for
and what actually the current term is,
but there's a larger issue around persistence
and that came up in one of the questions,
one of you just asked,
which is, you know what happens on reboot.
And there's sort of two possible strategy you can think of,
like one strategy is,
what strategy 1 is,
you know basically the node joins sort of freshly,
so joins basically when a node crashes and comes back up,
it just doesn't participate anymore,
it has to rejoin you know the,
rejoin the raft cluster,
and that means you know when rejoins you should you have to replay the log,
where basically has to receive every entry in the log
and then replay that.
And of course you know like if a node has been down,
for a node crashes down for a day or two days
or even if it just goes down for a second,
but you know the system has been up for a year,
that number means you have to replay a lot of log entries,
so there's a little bit annoying.
And so people prefer that strategy 2 which is,
you know you can back up,
and you just basically participate again,
so you catch up from basically you start from your persistent state,
the idea being that you know it's just a quick reboot
you crash you can back up whatever quick network failure,
and so maybe you know the rest can move one term along,
you basically have all the state
and you should be used for quick catch up.
So then, the real question is,
what needs to be at what state needs to be persisted across reboots.
You know where he talked about voting for,
that needs to be persistent,
because you are not allowed to vote for another candidate in the same term,
and but the raft contains a little bit more information
and also maintains the log on disk or in persistent state,
and the current term.
And for each one we should ask ourselves the question,
why maintain a persistent state,
because it means that whenever we update that state,
whenever we append an entry to the log,
whenever we increment the term
or whenever we change forward,
we actually have to write to disk or to stable storage
and stable storage is expensive
and so, it's very likely the example, the the writing or to stable storage could be the could become a bottleneck.
So we're only talking about votedFor,
so I'm going [],
but let's talk about the log,
why does the log have to be written to persistent storage,
can we reintegrate.
Another way, you've got a question,
let's say we don't try to use stable storage,
what would break.
Yeah, there's someone in the chat to answer this question,
which you could lose the majority on the commit write entries, right.
So here's the scenario,
we're, the raft replicated, the operation on a majority of the nodes,
so somebody you know majority nodes it's actually committed
to actually delivering have delivered having accepted that log entry,
so the leader sees the commits,
it delivers the message when their operation on the applied channel to the servers,
servers executes the operation
and lets the client know the operation has succeeded.
So now you know basically exposed the fact,
that the actually operation was actually replicated the majority of nodes to the client.
And so if we're not,
if the followers that actually received that entry,
did not put it on put on disk
and so that when the reboot they still have it,
we could run into the case,
the exactly that's the answer in the chat,
that we lose the majority on committed entry
and that entry will not be delivered on the remaining replicas to the servers
and so the client will see something strange,
where it sees that an operation that it did actually happen a little bit later,
actually goes into the operation hasn't happened.
And so it actually is important,
that this actually isn't stable storage,
we basically promised the leader to commit,
and we cannot back out of that promise.
Okay?
Any questions about this?
Why do we need to remember the current term for on disk,
does it does not need to be stored stably?
Well, the term, you vote for a different person in every term,
so if you don't keep track of what term it is,
then you don't really, you don't actually know who you voted for, right.
Yeah, exactly, you know you voted for,
that's one problem also current terms always have to go up,
you cannot go down in term,
because you're going to use that to detect rpcs from stale leaders and stale candidates,
but it always has to go up.
Okay?
Any questions about persistence?
Yeah, which is more about the way you laid out stuff,
but you say there's two strategies, right,
they need a log, and starting from a persistent state.
Yeah, and so I mean the way you describe starting from a persistent state,
do you like, do you are replay like,
like I guess it doesn't say in this slide,
like if you have does that assume you also have like a snapshot of obviously.
I have not talked about snapshots at all yet,
which we'll talk about in a second,
it's actually the next topic.
Okay, but.
The point is, okay, the two strategys after a node crashes,
there's two ways to treat that node,
one has a complete new node, that never existed in the system ever
and so when it comes up you know you added to the cluster
as if it's a new node,
so basically the cluster goes from,
you know, let's say you started with seven nodes,
one guy crashes, the cluster has six nodes,
it just happily proceed,
you know, whatever the other nodes do their application and all that kind of stuff
and then the second node actually comes back up.
And so there's two ways you know then join,
one way is to say like well I just forget everything I did ever,
I'll join the cluster again
and the other six nodes will bring me up to date
and they'll send the log to me and I'll redo operations,
and that can be costly, even with snapshots.
So the second strategy is to say,
well you know if the same node seven comes back up again,
it tries to reintegrate with its with its persistent state that it has,
you know basically the hope that you know example you went down for a couple nanoseconds or microseconds or milliseconds,
there's basically not much catching up to do at all,
because it already has on the state.
But it would like,
the aside from the log,
there's also a state machine, right,
that you've been like apply changes too.
Yeah yeah, so yeah let's talk about that,
so there's nothing, that's the next topic.
I think, yeah,
so now what about service recovery.
Sorry, I actually have another question on persistence.
Yep.
When does the server decide to persist?
Good, great question,
you know what you think,
I'm sure you've thought about this.
I mean, I think a simple answer would be every time one of these variables changes,
but that seems like a very costly thing to do.
I I think that is the correct answer,
whenever one of these variable changes,
you actually flush to disk or write to,
in our case correct in labs you write to the persistent module.
Okay, and.
So for example when the leader you know accepts an entry,
you know through start
and appends to its local its log,
it actually has to persist that entry.
Right, and so does the persisting work incrementally,
so it like once you get a new log entry,
you append or to take the entire state
and like rewrite it into the file.
But, okay, in real life, you append, right,
then you would not rewrite the whole log,
you would just append one entry to the log
and that's actually one of the reasons that logs are cool,
because you know you can just append at the end and incrementally,
in our lab,
the whole thing is fake,
the persistent actually doesn't really persist,
you know it keeps the object around in between crashes,
because crashes are also sort of fake,
you know the tester basically stops nodes, restart them
and basically gives them the new state,
but in the real system, you would append,
so the log would be a file,
and you would append an entry to the file.
Thank you.
And yes, you know we actually you will have to,
a real system, if you append the log entry,
your first append log entry, then you response,
so in the append entries,
if you update the log append,
so if append entries on the follower,
receives a new set of log entries,
it appends them to its local persistent log
and then it can respond,
because you would be bad to respond before appending,
because then you might lose you know the,
if you responded before appending, you might be running a situation where just before actually the actual append happens,
you crashes,
and so you actually did not persist log entries
and so you would you know, you could lose committed entries.
Okay?
Okay, so how about service recovery,
so the service keeps its own state,
like for example in lab 3, you're implementing a key-value store
and so the key-value store maintains basically hash map from a key to a value
and you need to replay that state.
And again there are two possible ways of going about it,
one strategy one is to replay the log to actually reconstruct that state.
So basically if you're sort of similar to the strategy one on the previous slide,
you just take the log use replay all the entries in the log
and should basically create exactly the same state,
as if as before,
because you know the whole point of this replicated state machine approach is that,
the all the operations are executed in total order,
operations have no side effect,
so if you start in the same stage with nothing,
and you replay all the operations,
you should end up exactly the same state,
is any other node,
and so that's one possible,
and so that was one way to recreate the state.
And you know obviously this is expensive,
you know if the service actually has been running for a couple years
and then you have to replay the logs,
you know from the beginning of time
you know that is not you know so desirable.
And so you know people do don't really follow strategy one,
gonna follow another strategy
and we just basically making periodic snapshots.
And there are two reasons for doing that,
one basically will reconstruct you know the service date in the past manner
and the second reason to do that is
to be able to compact the log,
you know even the raft state itself can be cut off from the front of the prefix can be cut off.
And the basic observation is that,
if the application is running for a while,
then it has it the first thousand operations or the first million operations,
then the state does construct that point,
the states will contain all ops you know c through [i],
where i maybe a thousand or a million whatever you whatever you,
so, so one way to think about is
that there's a duality between state replication and log replication or replay,
the you could save the state after a thousand operations
and then you've got exactly the same thing as actually re-applying redoing every operation from 0 to the fast.
And so this means that,
once you have a snapshot,
you stored snapshots tabling on disk in persistent state,
you can cut off, you can log, you can cut the log you know through i.
And so, this allows you to control the size of the log,
basically by periodicly asking the servers to actually take snapshots
and then service telling the raft library yes, I've taken a snapshot through i,
then raft can say okay good, I just know we have to remember anything from i or until i,
that means of course that the snapshot has to be stored on stable storage.
And this is also good for recovery, correct
and so it makes our recovery scheme slightly more complicated
than I just described in the previous slide,
what it has to happen is that
when a follower comes back up after a quick reboot,
it loads its persistent state you know that includes you know the persistent state that we talked about on the previous slide,
you know this information,
but also its last you know snapshot installs that last basically loads that snapshot into memory, the service does.
And then we can replay any log entries
to basically bring the follower up to date.
Okay?
Any questions about this?
I have one question,
I'm not sure if I'm gonna be able phrase super clearly,
I guess, like I was under impression,
so I guess like does this not break some layer of abstraction,
that previously existed between the application on top of raft and raft itself,
for it now needs to understand how the state machine,
like how to apply commands to the state machine
instead of just like giving commands to some external state machine.
Yeah, great observation, clearly, we have to play to get the raft library in the service,
because first of all the service lies about it gives the wrong information about how far it has to apply,
then we getting inconsistent results,
but anyway so we don't assume liers anyway,
but it's clearly the case,
that the service and raft library we have to cooperate.
And, you can go with an abstraction violation,
I think the reason they do it is to limit the amount of state of the raft library we have to maintain,
otherwise, the raft library wouldn't know when it can cut the log.
And so there's basically no way around it,
that the servers actually tells it,
like well I got a snapchat through i
and so it's okay for you to remove log entry from 0 to i.
And you'll see that
and so this will mean a good point this is going to come up in 2d, right,
lab 2d is gonna is all about snapshots and log compassion
as it's also called in the paper.
There there has to be some API between the servers and raft to be able to collaborate
and basically in 2a and 2b that API in fact even to see,
that API is extremely simple,
the only API that exists is this delivering log message on the apply channel, right,
and almost nothing flows down from the service to raft,
like other than the service may start
and raft trying to append an entry to the log using where i start.
And you know and so in 2d,
there has to be a little bit more of an API between service and raft library,
and it turns out, you can design that API in any possible way,
there are quite a number of ways of doing it,
there's no particular one
and the paper doesn't lay out what API you should use,
the papers actually just nothing about this
and so it's up to you to sometimes up to us,
you know to figure out the APIs
and to be able to do 2d,
you know, we have to declare an API between the servers and raft.
And you know you'll see,
what you do today, you know that the API,
you have some funny you might be a little bit more different than you might expect,
and you know we had to pick one particular API in in that APIs as an operation called conditional install,
that you know has semantics that you know allows you to change the raft state
and the server state atomically in one single operation.
And and that partly you know that operation exists,
yeah you try to limit the abstraction [batteries].
Okay?
And it turns out you can do it in different ways,
you don't really need,
you could have written it in different ways,
but you know we are performing is actually one of the more simple ways of doing it.
But it will become more clear in 2d
and you'll see indeed that there's sort of an interaction between the servers and raft,
in a way that they have to play along.
How could you repeat when raft communicates with the servers in the snapshot process,
so the snapshots are driven by the servers.
So the server just says once in a while to raft,
I've made a snapshot,
here's my snapshot,
and this is a snapshot includes all the operations through i,
and then raft you know writes the snapshots and truncates log you know to i
and writes all that information to the disk.
And that's basically all what happens sort of, sort of regular operation periodically snapshots happen snapshot happens.
Then there's the other case,
you have to consider is like when reboot happens.
And so when a follower reboots,
it actually reboots from its persistent state
and so including its snapshot,
and so when the follower reboots,
you know basically loads, you know snapshot from from a persistent disk
and actually reconstructs the application state, the key-value store
and you'll do this in lab 3,
this is not going to be an issue of lab 2.
The only thing that there's going to be an issue lab 2 is that,
because the followers, because the, because the log has been cut, right,
like you know instead of like having all the entries from 0 to i in the log,
plus more, so i you know n the log is being cut you know from i to n, right,
and those are part of the log compation,
but that also means that if a follower is far behind,
like for example new node joins the system
and doesn't actually have the beginning of the log nor the snapshots,
then the raft has to communicate the snapshot to that follower.
So in the case that the follower is
you know before i because we rejoined lab and rejoins the raft cluster,
the leader actually has to set the snapshot you know to the follower
and the follower basically start from there.
And that will show up in 2d
and so there's an additional rpc called the snapshot rpc or install snapshot rpc
and that's described in the paper,
and then you will have to implement in 2d.
In fact, which brings me to a good point,
actually, let me go to [consumer],
basically brings me to the homework question,
which is here's the install snapshot rpc for equivalent figure 2,
would then just snapshot rpc
and you actually have to implement that in 2d
and one issue that came up in the which was the homework question for today is,
is every possible in raft, what avoids it it's not possible,
that the state machine rolls back.
Yeah, so for example,
leader since maybe you know maybe an old snapshot shows up you know at a follower,
is it possible that you know if it's possible,
if that follower would install the snapshot
and then implicitly basically roll back the state machine,
maybe it already has seen more information,
you know clear that seems not right
and so the question is you know how does raft around it
and so maybe this is a great place actually do a quick break out,
and you can debate that homework question for a couple minutes, five minutes
and then we'll come back
and we'll talk about a little bit more about snapshots.
Lily, will be like?
No lily, how about I try, you can.
Hold on, I'll probably have to make you host
and then you can do it,
okay, you should be host now.
Awesome.
Alright, it should be.
Okay, thank you, [] thank you to do it.
And I'll go ahead and make you make you host again.
That'd be great, thank you.
Let me see, I share my screen.
Okay, everybody back online,
we're good to go,
can somebody can respond would be great.
Okay I can hear.
Okay, great, I hear it you know sometimes people,
because of the breakout rooms here
just learning dropped out soon, unfortunately,
past rooms break up,
but hopefully and I don't know exactly what to do about that,
I guess work of fault tolerance is a little bit unfortunate,
that people could just drop.
Okay, so any I think the homework question this time around was reasonable sort of straightforward,
you know it has to be the case that you know you cannot install an old snapshot,
because you know a service that might have had a more recent snapshot,
might have responded to the client,
saying, yeah the operation succeeded,
and then if you would restore an old snapshot,
then you basically back out to the state
and the client would see there's certainly an old version of the server,
so that's certainly not a legit,
and so there's a little bit,
you should definitely reject all snapshots,
but you have to be a little bit careful,
if you know the follower has a log that goes beyond the snapshot,
you have to keep that remained part of the log,
because basically you have promised to a leader,
that you have accepted a message
and so you can't delete you know the rest of the log, that was not covered by the snapshot.
Okay?
Okay, so then let me return.
We had a question, actually.
okay, go ahead.
So it says, it says in the paper right,
if the follower receives a snapshot,
that's a prefix of its log,
the log entries covered by the snapshot are deleted,
but the rest are kept.
Yep.
In that case, it is the state machine wouldn't be overwritten, right, in this case.
Okay, so the interesting question is,
like how does a snapshot get communicated to the state machine
and as you'll see in lab 3
and it goes over the applied channel,
and so the state machine will get a snapshot over the applied channel
and then it's up to it to do the right thing.
Okay.
Okay?
Oops.
Okay good.
So just a follow-up on that, sorry,
though I was a little bit,
so that makes sense to me,
the part that I was confused by is,
in the, in the figure 13 like the box that describes install snapshot rpc,
on 6, it's says if existing log entry has the same index as the term snapshot last include entry,
well, hold on, I may have just misread it.
Okay, why do you keep thinking about it,
look if.
I have a question, I'll ask you.
I'll take it offline and we'll do it right after lecture, if you want to.
Okay, I want to go back actually for a couple minutes,
you know that we have remaining and talk about actually using raft,
which is sort of a discussion that we're already basically having here for servers
and so again I'm going to focus on the replicated key-value service,
that's going to be the topic of lab 3.
And so just to go back to almost like one of the first board
that I drew at the beginning of the raft lectures,
here's like our boxes, you know that correspond to the three replicas,
and each replica correct you know has a sort of split two pieces,
one is the service part,
and one is the raft library, right,
then we know that basically they communicate these two through the apply channel
unless the way that information flows from raft to service servers.
And so clients you know interact you know with the servers, you not directly the raft,
so we have a client here,
you know that sends you an operation like a put operate or get operation for the service,
the service receives this operation
and it basically calls start you know for that operation,
quick raft does it chit chat you know with you know the other raft libraries,
you know messages can flow back in at some point the operation is committed
and then it actually is you know raft will say,
okay this operation is ready to be committed,
sends it on the applied channel
and service then basically execute the operation and send the response back,
after it executed the operation, response back to the client,
saying well the value or the get you know key 20 you know is this, right,
so this is a get operation or put,
and this is basically the value for the get or you know okay would succeeded.
Okay?
And we also discovered in the last lecture,
it might be the case,
that the client sends an rpc to the service and the rpc disappears,
so the client must yeah must resend,
and by the time the resends actually,
you know the leader might not be the leader anymore.
And so in that case,
it has to sort of redirect itself to another leader,
so basically when there is a little bit of code
with a way to think about this.
There's a little bit of code at the client side,
sort of understands replicated state machines a little bit,
and it maintains some information,
it maintains like who's the leader
and who are the other followers,
and so that can switch between them, if necessary.
We also, last time we talked a little bit about its possible,
that you know operation can be duplicated, right,
because you know the, the client may send an operation put operation to the service,
in the you know the client doesn't get a response,
but the servers actually received,
so it went through, you know went through the whole operation sequence,
you know starting the raft appends can go through the raft motion
and then basically sending it out to apply channel.
And so basically the client actually might send a second one,
and you know the basically for the repetition,
you know that might actually go through you know the raft library too,
comes out in the apply channel
and so you know have to do some duplicate detection and detection
and multiple ways of doing it,
but either way you have to duplicate detection.
So, in addition to a sort of maintain state about like what the leader
and the followers are put and get also actually have an idea,
you know an id associated with it
and we're going to maintain what is the last id,
that it actually is trying to get through
and that is used to actually duplicate detection.
And this little piece of code is often called a clerk,
you know the clerk that interacts with the service
and it does a little bit of work to collaborate with the service you actually get the writing done
and so we have multiple clients,
all half a clerk of library if you will, which is Go package,
and you know the clients basically talk puts and gets you know over that interface
and inside of the clerk actually maintains these ids
or maintains one idea for the outstanding
you know put get operation as well as some information
about who's part of the cluster.
Okay?
Does that make sense?
So that's sort of the basic structure, correct,
like how raft fits into a larger picture.
The one question that comes always up is
what you know what is the guarantees you know that the servers and the clerk together make
to the clients about these put and get operations.
So this really means what is the correctness criteria.
And the way, we always have described so far,
we've been reasonable [sloppy] about it,
I've been sloppy about it,
and maybe I've said is like well should behave like a single machine.
But even that there's a little bit of an imprecise definition,
because what happens if two clients basically at the same time you know execute a put or a get operation
and what actually is the correct outcome of these operations,
so we really need to sort a little bit more preciser,
you know I think like maybe like a single machine,
the right intuition, but we need a little bit preciser definition.
And this definition you saw the term used in the paper,
this definition is called linearizability,
linearizability basically spec specification of what values put and get operations can return,
particularly those in put operations really what get can actually return.
And it basically successfully,
what are allowed things to be returned,
what are things that are not allowed to be returned,
independent by actually how you implement it,
it's just like purely specification.
And it basically has three components to linearizability,
linearizability says, if you have look at some sequence of operations
and some of them executed currently,
it has to be the case,
that there's a total order,
so you can arrange all the operation in some total order,
put or set operations.
Two, it has to match real-time.
With that, I mean that if an operation completed before the second operation started,
even if those operations are different machines,
it has to be the case that in this total order,
the first operation shows up before the second operation.
And that sort of makes sense, right,
like if it behaves like a single machine,
and you start an operation after another operation,
then the single machine would always return the results of the first operation so
and finally a read operation,
so this is like in out case, key-value server only has one read operation,
then we get,
but the read operation should always return the results of the last write.
So in our case, you know we do get operation and the put operation,
happened well before it
and completed well before then that get operation should observe the last, should observe the last put.
Okay?
So this sort of, these are three conditions,
you know that whether to determine whether system actually linearizability.
And you can think about the linearizability as well, just behave like a single machine.
So let me make a little bit more concrete,
because there's a little bit abstract.
And the way basically people think about linearizability
or argue that the system has linearizability is looking at particular histories or executions
and then see if you can use histories,
if you can turn that into total order,
even though the operations actually might have actually executed concurrently.
So let me give you one example, a trivial example,
so let's say we have three clients C1 C2 C3
and they do a bunch of puts and gets,
so you know typically the way you know,
basically it has to be some start point where the operation started,
and there's some endpoint where the operation ends.
So, for example when actually the client actually gets the return from the servers,
and so let's say this write operation you know to value to the variable x,
and we write one to it.
So the client one started at some point in the write operation to the variable x the write 1
and ends at some point here.
Maybe the second one and write to it,
and then maybe we have all the action and with linearizability is when operation happens concurrently,
so all operations starts before another one actually finishes,
so for example we might have the following operation client 2 does a read operation,
in our case would be a get,
and there's a read of x
and the value returned by this operation is 2.
And then we have a similar sort of situation
where clieng 3 it actually starts an operation a read operation,
and reads x and it returns 1.
Let me make this a little bit more clean,
the read operation actually returns before you know the write 2 operation starts or ends,
and same from [] one
and then the question that always comes up is this linearizability,
this linearizability execution.
And if linearizability, then basically it means like this could happen on a single machine, too.
So could this happen on a single machine.
We can just like abstract and think about it without actually having,
is this legit outcome from basically we need to look at is the outcomes of r2 and for c2 and c3,
you know is this a legit execution.
I'm not sure, I don't really know what it means for right to take like a long time.
Well. Take a long time for that matter.
If you think about the from the client perspective,
it sends a request to the service,
so that's the starting of the write,
and I've got a return value at some point from the service
and that's the end of the write.
And so in between all kinds of stuff happens, right,
it actually to the servers,
the servers put into raft,
raft went to apply channel blah blah blah,
lots of stuff happened,
we really care about exactly what the implementation does at some point a response.
And so you can think about this,
you know there's basically three concurrent clients,
you know they issued concurrent operations
and we are wondering if this is actually legit outcome.
I don't think this could happen on a single machine,
because the write for for 2 it finishes, after the restart.
Oh, sorry, yeah yeah that's right,
but it seems like the write should happen before the read.
And in this situation,
it couldn't happen if the write started after,
if the write finished after the write restart,
yeah.
Yeah, so one would think one way to think about is that,
we can move you know we have to construct a total order
and we can construct a total order where all the operations line up,
then you know it's a valid linearizable history.
And so, so let's construct a total order
and then go back to this question you just asked,
so a total order, here's a total order that I gonna,
so I'm going to do first the write operation,
then read x1, then the write x2,
and then rx read x2, right.
It's a total order,
all the operations are now happening sequentially.
And you know we need to check whether a total order is correct,
corresponding to the linearizability definitions,
well, it has to be the case that operations that start,
if an operation starts after some other operation,
ends it needs to be after in the total order,
and so we look at this.
Let's look at the issue, this one,
must start after wx1
and that is true correct, this totally order,
Rx1 must you start after Wx1,
because it actually returns you know the value, right,
then exactly in total order, that is also the case,
Rx2 you know must start Wx2,
because it observes the result of this write
and you know that's perfectly fine too, right,
we can basically, one way to think about it is that
you know even though they executed this way,
we've got to rearrange things to sort of fit the total order.
And so, if we think about this,
then this is a totally legit and execution,
where you know the operation for much of the order
and so this is like what a single machine would do,
so a single machine could be executed write Rx1 read x 1,
write x2, read x2 and real perfectly fine.
Okay?
So let me make it helpful to think about history that is not linearizable.
So let me look at the second one.
And I'm gonna come back on this on the first day anyway,
so don't worry if this a lot makes sense yet,
but here's another one,
I got C1,
same thing write x1,
I got a c and here write x2
and and there's gonna be a read that actually goes in x1,
and I'm sorry read x2,
and then I got C2 C3
and the C3 start after the other read and returns 1.
And the client here is that,
it's not possible to construct a total order you know matches linearizability,
and, in one way one indication of this is that this read returned x1,
started after the read that returned 2,
and I will make this a little bit more precise later,
but in a real you know single machine system,
that could have never happened right,
because that would have meant that the value changed between Rx2 and Rx1
and and you know with these few operations that we have on the board,
that has to be the case that,
this Rx1 what happened after that write,
and this write must have happened after that write,
because they're in total, there, we have to respect you know the ordering of the single of C1.
And so there's no way to basically slot you know Rx1 in the total order
you know according to this picture,
it should go after Rx1,
and but that can really not be true,
because if it got Rx after Rx1
that names also after Wx2,
so that must have write 2 and not 1.
So this is not a linearizability, not a linearizable history in execution.
Another way of saying that is that,
this is what, what is Rxn in returning here, really returning stale value, right,
and that is not allowed,
if the machine behaves like a single machine
or replicated server behaves like a single machine.
And so I'm gonna go back you know this,
to on the lecture when next week,
when we talk about zookeeper,
because this is going to be very important,
this notion of linearizability,
sort of thing that shows up probably in the paper,
and this notion of stale values also shows up probably.
And since I'm running out of time
and you're gonna I'll resume that next week.
Okay?
Any further questions
and people need to leave, please feel free to leave,
in fact I hope you did,
I want to make responsible that you miss other classes.
Is this a consider, like what type of consistency is considered to be strong consistency.
This considered to be basically strong consistency,
and what it really is sort of a precise definition of what strong consistency is,
so like our intuition about what strong consistency is namely behaving like a single machine,
that the precise definition that people use in the technical literature is linearizability.
How did they decide to have that property,
like why did they decide to have that property.
There's a couple things,
one reason, the reason,
okay, so it makes sort of sense,
you know if you think from this point of view,
like you want to behave, you want to make a replicated system behave like a single machine or replicated machine
and you want to only allow outcomes that actually correspond to executions that the single machine could have done,
the next linearizability are very intuitive definition for that.
The database world has also some other terminology like serializability,
this is also a term that will show up in the term later
and basically the only difference between sort of linearizability and serializability
is that serializability doesn't require that matches real-time.
And so people have different definitions of strong consistency,
if you will and the one that we'll see most probably is linearizability,
which corresponds closest to like the machine behaves that replicates or behaves like a single machine.
Thank you.
You're welcome.
I have a question about what happens during a network partition,
so I know like so if a leader gets partitioned completely on their own,
they'll eventually climb out,
but if they have sort of like a few followers with them,
they'll stay the leader,
and they won't be able to commit anything,
because they'll be in a minority
and they'll be a new leader
and they'll be,
so will that leader ever sort of recognize that maybe it's a stale leader
or do we just assume that eventually if the partition goes away,
it'll figure out,
because I'm worried if there's a client that's talking to the stale leader,
what does that client do.
The no,
okay so this is a great question with this picture here,
hopefully it will help,
so the client talks to talk to this guy, correct,
like who's the leader,
you see the picture,
I just double check, you can see.
I can see it.
So let's say you know this first box is the leader,
client talks to that leader,
the leader can't commit any operations, right,
and so it will commit anything on the apply channel
and so it will never respond to the client, right,
because there's no operation actually its operations are not being executed,
so the client will just retry, just keep retrying forever,
until you know until the client actually maybe tries another, you know, one of the other followers, correct,
that maintains you know who else is actually in the group,
or until the network heals,
and the leader actually commit an operation.
Gotcha, wait, so doesn't doesn't the leader immediately reply those,
saying I got your request or does it wait until committed.
No in lab 3, it doesn't know commit with a client until who actually has processed the request,
and which means that the operation actually has run through raft
and come out of the applied channel
and ask executed by the servers.
Okay.
Does that makes sense.
Yeah, so the client could just implement a timeout,
where like if a certain amount of time and they haven't received the commit,
assume that maybe I should try a different node,
and then if it gets the new leader or follower of the new leader,
it'll be back to normal.
For example, this clerk that's exactly what this clerk does,
you know the place along with the servers to actually do what you just said.
Got it, okay, thank you.
You're welcome.
Sorry, can you repeat again, what the clerk does.
The clerk is a little bit of a stub,
where like a little library,
that the client links with,
and the client calls puts and gets
and the clerk actually is the interface that it talks to
and the clerk can keep some information,
like who's part of the raft cluster
and so we're only who's the leader and who are the followers,
at least what it thinks is the leader and the followers,
and when it sends in rpc you know to the service is not sensitive to the leader,
what it thinks is the current leader,
and the servers in the, whatever thinks the current leader,
the leader might actually respond saying,
like hey I'm not the leader, should send somewhere else,
and then it will try one of the others and updates its information.
And also we'll tag every put and get operation,
that it receives from the client
and that sends to the server with a unique id,
so that the service can do duplicate detection.x
And this all comes up in lab 3,
so you know you'll see there,
in lab 2, there's no real clerk,
because the tester basically sort of sits on top of the directly of the raft interface
and doesn't really interact through the clerk,
but in lab 3 will interact through the clerk.
So how do the clients generate unique ids,
I think they conflict with each other.
Random, big random numbers.
Alright, so we're just guessing and hoping,
rather than actually guaranteeing some sort of like incremental.
One way to make it more guaranteed,
for example, take your IP address and append a random number.
A question about the homework question.
Yeah.
So I thought that it could go backwards in time,
like I read the paper
and it says on page 12 [],
it said that if there's a conflict, right,
then the follower just discards its entire log
and it's also preceded by the snapshot,
so I wonder why.
Again, let me, let me guess,
I I don't really know exactly this is,
what you're referring to,
I have to look it up again.
Oh, it's on page 12,
it's at the it's towards the end of page 12 the second column here,
so the second to last paragraph.
So the log can go back, right, but not the state machine.
Not, oh, the log can't, the log can go back, but not the state machine,
what was the state machine, like what you the committed entries, right.
Yeah, the yes, the log can't go back,
because of the uncommitted entries we can go back,
this is like this whole erase stuff that we talked about earlier.
Okay, so actually the log can go back, not the state machine,
which is basically what you committed already.
Yeah and the log can never go,
will never go back, never bailout of committed operations, correct,
it can only bailout erased uncommitted operations.
Yes, that's right, okay.
So that's what you ask question.
Can I ask a question about the third slide.
Yeah.
The one right before this one,
so could you just walk me through real quick,
what match index is doing on the write,
like when S2 is communicating with S3.
Okay.
So it starts out as 0.
Yep, so S2 is communicating with who.
S3.
Yeah, so basically okay,
so here match index is 0 right,
like so and when you write it down is 0.
Yeah.
Okay, then you get to know back,
so match index stays 0, right.
Okay.
Nothing there, but now it's an okay back,
so what does that imply,
that implies that you know what did it send that send heartbeat correct with for index 13,
and including and the S3 responded okay
and so it means that basically S3 is up to date through until 13, correct,
that is next index that it actually has and expects 14.
And so the S2 knows now that it's log matches until 13 after this message.
Is it until 13 or until 12.
It matches till 13,
so the next thing that will be sent will be going index 13.
So, so the next index and match index are going to be 13.
Yeah, the next index is not used yet, right,
means empty.
Okay.
Yeah, so basically the the way you know
they they you can do either way correct,
you can either save the last one or you know first that's gonna be,
for the first next to you know one,
in this case they go by the first next one.
So in this case, both of them are 13 for the next one.
Yeah, so basically you can think about this,
this stage before, like all the green stuff has happened,
the match index for 3 is 13,
and the match index for itself 2 is also 13.
Got it, awesome, thank you.
You're welcome.
Actually, can I ask a follow-up from that,
so when it sees something matches,
for example here on position 11,
it saw that matches,
then it is guarantee that everything before that matches too.
Yes, right, because, hold on let me double check you're talking about this message.
Yeah, about like when it says okay if you check.
Yeah, yeah, because that is the whole reason that the previous term or previous index or communicated correct to the follower,
to make double check that it can only respond to okay,
if indeed is the case that in the previous index 11 actually turn free,
and if that's true,
that means that basically everything before that must match
and this is like this,
whatever their whatever their statement they call,
this invariant initially maintained that,
like if something matches at like one index,
then everything before that match too.
Oh, okay, okay, this is [] to me.
Oh, and I had another follow-up question was related to the question,
on the lecture question that I wrote,
I asked about the copy-on-write for snapshots,
I think I don't really understand what is being copied,
is it, is it the page tables or is it something.
I think I responded to your email.
Yeah, I got email, but.
Okay, okay, okay, hold on a second,
[], the,
so okay, the scenario is snapshot can be expensive,
because snapchat might be large gigabytes,
you know key-value page table, sorry, [] it was a gigabyte key-value store,
then you know you need to write that gigabyte to disk, right,
and while you're writing into disk,
if you don't do anything clever,
you cannot process any other put and get operations,
that come in through the channels,
let me actually popup this picture.
Great, so basically servers decides at some point to take a checkpoint to gigabyte,
you have to write a gigabyte to disk,
that's expensive.
So the plan you know I think the plan that the papers hinting at,
is that what the service does,
it you know calls fork,
so when it wants to make a checkpoint, it calls fork,
and fork case a copy of that process, right,
now we have the operating system running,
and we have now basically two processes,
that correspond to this application servers raft, service raft,
and this is the copy, the child,
the operating system uses copy-on-write,
so when it made a copy of that second process,
and just copy the page table, didn't copy physical memory,
so basically these two processes share the same physical memory,
which holds you know the our key-value store, right.
And so now the idea is that,
the child when it starts running,
it starts making a checkpoint or snapshot,
I can just write out you know the key-value sort of,
the key-value store to disk.
And in parallel, you know the parent can you start processing new you know get and put operations,
because if it does put operation,
and it wants to modify,
it will write you know to pages that correspond to the key-value store,
that will result in a page fault, right,
and so the OS will get a page fault
and so the OS will copy that page at that point
and then you know the first pair process can updated,
this is all transparent to the child,
which the child had a consistent snapshot of the whole address space
at the point of the fork.
So, this allows basically the parent and child run concurrently
still make a consistent snapshot
and the parents actually make process new put and get operations.
Is that more clear, okay?
Oh, yeah, okay I see,
so the copy-on-write the memory that holds the key-value store,
okay, okay, okay I see,
yeah, this makes it very clear,
thank you so much.
You're welcome.
Any more questions?
Yeah, I have a,
I guess this is sort of a weird scenario,
I'm not sure if this could actually,
but what if,
so imagine that we're always in the same term,
and then you get to a point where some nodes have disconnected,
but they're still the same term,
the leader is still in the same term
and then at some point they will, they will do a snapshot
and then all the logs will be compressed,
and then they keep going forward
and now the logs are being populated again
and then, let's just say 15 logs have been added,
and then after 10, they compress them
and then they are at index index 5 again
and then the other nodes joined back in
and they're also at index 5 of the same term.
Is that a problem,
like how, how does,
it's almost like they're on a snapshot epoch of some sort.
Okay, so old snapshots correspond to an index, right, so.
Yeah.
So okay, let's draw out like maybe draw your scenario,
so we got a server gonna have some log,
and you know maybe I think you know you talk about 10
and it took a snapshot at 10.
Yeah.
Yeah, so let's say, let's say that basically,
yeah so basically the first 9 operations are maybe including 10 are in the snapshot.
And then okay, so there's another node is same term,
so all these entries have the same term, right,
whatever, you know 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1.
Yep.
And, so this node actually,
but this node has only through 10, then this guy through 15,
let's see,
I think that's what you're saying,
here's 1, here's 1.
Well, I think my my thought is,
well here's here's a question I can answer,
when you take a snapshot do you reset your index or do you keep counting? You keep counting.
Oh, okay,
I was imagining it was like an array,
and you saw your index goes backwards,
so that it would be possible for you to have two different entries in the same term with the same index.
Yeah, that's not allowed.
Right yeah, okay, I I see.
So, okay, okay, that makes sense.
When you remember reset the index.
When you cut like this part of the log,
in the index stays at 10.
Got it, got it.
And so in fact when you do this in 2d,
this is gonna be slightly annoying,
because you presumably take advantage in fact the start of log is 0
and what you're now going to get is that
the start of the layer of 0 might be 10,
people have to.
You have an offset of some sort.
Yeah, you have to add that offset everywhere.
Yeah, and then and then last thing really quickly,
I think the reason I was confused earlier was in the in the code for lab 2.
Yeah.
There's a comment that says,
we're supposed to return immediately from start.
Yeah yeah, well you, oh yes.
I mean, okay, so let me go back to this picture here.
Yeah, hopefully, it's getting really crowded,
so we get an operation correct
and we do the start operation, we call start.
Oh, return immediately doesn't necessarily mean reply, is that.
Yeah, exactly,
it just means reply back to return to the servers,
not to the client.
I see, I see, okay, totcha,
yeah, I guess operating under the assumption that return always is necessarily reply,
but that's not that's not always the case.
No, that's not the case,
I think this will become more clear in lap 3 than they you know lab 2,
lab 2 living wired, no application.
Yeah, okay, well, thank you,
this was really helpful.
You re welcome.
Appreciate it.
Have a rest.
You too.
Bye.
Good luck for the lab.