Okay, so good morning, good afternoon or good evening or wherever you are,
and I said the plan for today is to talk about the Frangipani,
this is a paper from 1997,
so it's a bit of an older paper,
the context of this paper is network file systems,
and you know you should think about systems such as you know Athena AFS
that you know the file system at Athena dropbox,
a more modern version of this,
but the general goal here is
to basically share files between a collection of users.
Frangipani itself you know it's not widely used
or wasn't widely used outside of the deck.
And so the real focus of the things you should get out of this paper today are three ideas
and ideas that actually will show up over and over in a couple of, next couple of weeks.
First of all cache coherence,
protocols for cache coherence,
second, distributed locking, and third, distributed crash recovery.
And these are gonna be three ideas,
are gonna be as I mentioned show up in the, in the next couple of weeks,
in particular, we're going to read,
you know we're starting next week to sort of heavy-duty transaction systems
and they build a lot on given some of the techniques
or to use some of the techniques that actually Frangipani also uses.
And so Frangipani is sort of a more gentle introduction to these three topics,
before we get to heavy-duty transaction systems.
And the idea is also Frangipani's itself is an interesting design,
from a distribute system perspective,
it is a cool system.
Let me make that point by sort of [trusting] sort of the traditional designs for network file system,
so traditional or the most common network file system design,
since if you think about like AFS on Athena,
if you have a set of clients,
and this is a very simple picture of a set of clients,
you know connected to some network,
represent the network basically a single wire,
you know sharing a number of file servers
and then a file servers have their disk.
And basically all the all the complexity although,
okay, I'll get to cache coherence in a detail in a second,
the, all the complexity in the design is basically here, at the file servers,
file servers implement you know the file system operations,
open close read write, you know stat on everything
and they write things to disk in the crash resilient or resistant way
and the clients are really sort of dumb or simple,
they didn't really do much,
you know perhaps do some caching as they do in AFS,
but you know most of these is,
they're relaying file system operations from client, from programs that are running
like whatever the [] on you're client one
and it does open close,
and most of what the client does relaying those operations to file servers.
And one reason that the design is popular is
because you know like [] from security perspective,
it is a nice design,
because most of the file servers have to be trusted,
but the clients don't have to be trusted.
And certainly in a setting like MIT,
we're like machines are just in public
and who knows who installs what kind of software on it,
you know that is a nice property,
Frangipani on the other end, has a very different design and much more decentralized design.
And in Frangipani actually a lot of the file server,
it's really there's actually no real file server in this literally sends the work,
but the the clients basically implement run the file server code itself.
So let's say with two clients and most of the file system code itself,
like the thing that actually has inode managers,
inode updates you know files, creates directories,
all the code instead of living on the file server,
looks like it lives on the clients.
You know the only thing that really the the file server share is a big virtual disk.
And if you will may be a good image you have in your head
or a conceptual image you have in your head
is that the virtual disk is basically like a big ssd drive,
and so the file servers, there's basically share one ssd, you know one disk with each other,
now of course internally this virtual disk is implemented using a system called Petal
and you know consists actually of many machines,
and but you know you know the machine replicate you know disk blocks,
there are patches internally to make sure that like you know operators can apply it in the right order
and all that kind of stuff,
but from the outside perspective,
you know the interface is really a read block, or write block.
And so it just looks like an ordinary disk.
And, as over those interesting in this,
you know design you contracted to design's,
actually a lot of complexity in this design is on the client side.
And you know one reason that you like that,
or why is that,
you know you can grow the file system with the number of workstations,
so if you increase the number of clients,
you basically get more CPU power,
because you get more clients
and you know each of the clients can drive on its own file system.
And so a lot of the really heavy-duty computation can all be done on the client machines
and doesn't involve any file server at all,
and it is true that in the left side,
the network traditional network file system design
is often the case that you know the performance bottlenecks arise you know in the, in the file server,
when the number of clients actually becomes too large
and often in that case for example we split the file system across different files servers.
Okay, that's sort of the,
so from our perspective at least from a distributed systems design,
Frangipani is interesting,
because it's much more decentralized,
than sort of the traditional network file system design.
And the reason they wanted to explore this design has a lot to do with the use case,
that they imagine or that they were targeting
and I want to say a little bit about the use case,
because, there were a lot of questions related to that in email.
So, so what is the use case,
the use case is basically a number of researchers and engineers,
you know compiling, compiling editing their programs or writing documents.
So it's really designed to papers from a famous research lab [],
and Thekkath like tens of researcher like 50 to 100
and they're really what they're doing is designing a file system for their use case,
so everybody is trusted,
all the machines are trusted, all the software running trusted
and so the security side of things is really not an issue for that,
all the these researchers are heavy-duty computer users
and you know and so they want to,
but mostly they're working on their own private files
and they're writing their own programs, their writing their own documents,
and so [] want to interact with the files with high performance file system.
Of course, you know they might share,
otherwise sharing would not be interesting,
so they both potentially share files and directories.
And it shows up in two ways
you know they may work together, collaborate together around writing a paper
like paper that we're reading today,
and so they want have access to a shared files
for the directory that holds that particular paper,
and so to user to user sharing,
and then there's a second form of sharing,
like the same user might log into multiple workstations,
more than one workstation,
so again whatever, user one of the researchers goes to the public library of []
or their library and the long general public workstation with indexer
and it wants to be able to read or write their files from that machine too.
So that's use case
and in this use case has a number of design implications,
or you know design choices that were motivated by a huge case.
And so the one of the primary ones,
that was motivated by this use cases caching.
So instead of leaving the data for example all in Petal
and every read or write operation goes through Petal,
they want to arrange it,
so the motive actually actually happens in the workstations
and so that the researchers since they're mostly working on their own private files,
it seems to make a lot of sense,
they're sort of captured data locally on the workstation,
then as you read or write files,
there's basically no network traffic really necessary,
and you can sort of write at high performance
and one reason one way they avoid having a lot of traffic to Petal
is to have a write back cache instead of write through,
so if operations happen actually did you stay in the cache
and at some point later they percolated to Petal,
as we'll see in a second.
So, combine that, like even though they're mostly you know workloads are going to be used for private,
where they're not sharing going on,
of course indicates they do share,
they want to have strong consistency,
or sometimes called you know coherence.
And so the meaning for example,
if a one user writes a file,
then another user, a lot of workstation reached the file,
we graded that user actually saw the changes
that the other workstation the other user has made
and so they want strong consistency.
So, those are the two design choices that really drive this design
as well as this basically performance.
So it may be helpful to think a little bit about
like what other use cases could you have for file systems
and so maybe one good one that we talked a lot about is to think about GFS,
you know would GFS be a substitute for Frangipani or the other way around how do they contrast.
And one way to think about this is
that GFS is really file system designed for mapreduce applications
and so it's a file system where files are not cached,
in fact the files tend to be so big,
that they wouldn't even fit
in the type of cache that we're talking about,
it's also basically sort of read sequentially from beginning to end,
and that's it,
and maybe you know some other computer will read that file,
because some other mapreduce application running on.
So think, you think about GFS,
there's really no data caching going on at all,
there's a little bit of caching going on to keep track of
where a chunk servers were,
but there's actually no caching of data going on at all in GFS,
so there's also no cache consistency probably in GFS
and so there's a type of applications that they were targeting
that just didn't make sense at all.
Similarly in GFS,
GFS actually it's not really a real file system
in the sense of the here was not intended to run like VI, GCC,
and so didn't provide straight sort of [positive] or unique compatibility,
in Frangipani, you can just run your standard Unix applications
and things should work out
and the applications behave in the same way as if there was not a distributed file system,
basically single file system.
Again in GFS, there is basically a little bit of library
you know actually application used to read or write files,
in GFS, but it was not one hundred percent duties compatible at all.
So let me give you a sense,
that we know these workloads drives really the design of these different systems,
you know in case GFS,
mapreduce application that drive the design,
in case of you know from Frangipani or the shared file system is a collection of users working on shared file system,
but most of the operations you know their performing probably just files day own
and performed locally.
That makes sense in terms of contrast in settings,
so you see actually there are quite a different number of file systems around,
like zookeeper yet another sort of provides file system interface,
but it's not really a file system,
it's like more intended as a coordination service,
you wouldn't store big files in zookeeper.
Any questions about this setting?
Can you briefly repeat why having the file server code running on the client machine enhances scalability,
versus having the client and the file server
being on different machines or on different.
Yeah, so, for example if you'd like to go back to this previous slide here,
on the left the network file system go,
so there's many many many clients,
let's figure there's only one,
there's let me simplify this picture for a second
and ignore the second file server, one one file server,
so everybody can share the files from the file server,
then all these clients will be handling on that single file server,
and so all the read or write operations are going to be sent to the file server,
the file server directory lookout,
it opens files and adjust security checks
and all that kind of stuff,
so all the computation really for the file system itself,
it's all happening on the file server itself in the traditional network file system design,
in the Frangipani, that's not the case,
in Frangipani all the file system operations are executed on the workstations.
And so we have multiple workstations
are basically you know the workload that the file system can scale
or it can support scales with the number of workstations.
I see, and then be a traditional architecture,
so every file server contains or stores,
let's say a section of the the entire file system right,
so it so it's not the case that every single file server has a copy of the entire system,
is that it might be partitioned across files.
Yes,that might be across,
for example AFS you know there are different volumes
and file servers managed different volumes
and the data of all users MIT spread across different volumes.
But all the data for one volumes are going to be one file server,
and so that file volume gets hit head,
you know you're going to get performance bottlenecks.
Okay awesome, thank you.
Any more questions about sort of the setting here,
before we dive in to more Frangipani.
Okay good.
So now the design choices they made,
immediately leads to a number of challenges.
So I wanna talk a little bit about the challenges.
And the main one that drives almost of a ton of the design is
let's say you have one workstations,
workstation one, in those days people had workstations
and laptops were actually not not really existed yet,
today probably will be all kinds of laptops,
but there's a workstation and somebody like whatever read a file,
read file f whatever,
you know maybe the grades database with a grades file,
and so basically, that means that that file actually is cached inside of the workstation.
And so the client you know whatever program running VI,
you know get to update and manipulate the file,
and then get up sometime later,
the result will be written back to Petal the disk as you will
and so the challenges that are basically around this model are 3 faults,
one, somebody else workstation two maybe at some point do a kind of f,
get the file f
and of course it should be the case that
you know at least normally expected we have a traditional Unix file system,
that you know you will see the last write to that particular f,
so even though the write might have happened at a different workstation,
when the second workstation reads the file,
we would like to see that data show up,
and this is what they were going to be roughly,
this roughly comes to cache coherence,
and other words synonyms for coherence are cache consistency,
which is like the term we've seen more in the previous papers,
but in the sort of out of the computer architecture world,
actually the the term coherence comes, comes from that world.
And so you can think about them as synonyms.
Two, the second problem that you know you that's going to occur
and we need to deal with is that,
let's say that workstation one and workstation two both want to create a file in the shared directory,
so here's workstation one creates a file f in the directory d,
workstation two also creates a file g and in directory d.
And now we want to be arranged at least at workstation 1 makes the changes
and then workstation 2 makes the changes,
like both files here
and that like one file doesn't overwrite,
say the directory of the other
or this overwrite directly in a way that actually other files disappears.
So this has to do the second topic,
really is atomicity,
these operations creating a file,
really have to be has to be sort of an atomic operation,
so they don't get interleaved,
then we get wrong results.
And then the final problem,
that we need to deal with is that
you know workstation 1, you know might crash
while doing one of these complex file system operations.
And so it has to be story,
you know how actually the file system recovers.
And so this is really a story about crash recovery.
So, for example like in this first case
where like workstation makes a file and directory d,
there's actually a complex operation,
you know the directory needs to be modified,
and inode needs to be allocated
and inode to be initialized
and then the inode number needs to be written into the directory,
so there's multiple sort of file system operations involved in it
and we wanted to be the case that
if the file system crashes between any of these steps
in this sort of complex file system operation,
there better be the case that
the file system recovers correctly.
And what we mean,
we file something recover correctly,
at least its internal data structures are correct
and so for example the inode does not lost,
because it doesn't show up in the directory, etc etc
or like even the whole of the internal structures are consistent.
So this is the topic of corruption recover
and so Petal basically were in Frangipani need to address all these problems
and my plan is just go walk through in one by one,
and discuss how Frangipani addresses them.
Any questions about the top level challenges?
Okay, let's you know proceed.
So the first thing is caching coherence or cache consistency.
And, so the key aspect in the solution that
Frangipani uses actually a lock server somewhere,
and so, and the lock server basically has a table
and for every file and actually inode number for every file,
who has to lock at this particular point of time,
so who's the owner.
So we might have to file f
and it basically says you know works and for which the web server has a record of the workstation one,
owns that particular lock,
and the locks are for itself is a distributed service,
you can almost think about it almost like zookeeper,
you know it's, it provides an acquire release locks,
it's fault tolerant,
in the case of a Frangipani either use Paxos based implementation,
and what is spread across multiple machines highly fault tolerance, etc, etc.
So that's the the the lock server
and it turns out that the workstation should also keep a table for their locks,
so here's workstation one
and you know it might be,
you know let's say workstation one cache file f and g,
you know maybe h cached by workstation workstation 1,
h may be cached by workstation 2.
And then the workstation 1 has a similar table
and that list for every file for every lock that holds,
where it's either busy or idle,
so it may be f you know lock status is busy
and it really means that actually the file server is just operating on that file,
so it's actively using that file,
the second state namely, let's say we have file g,
which also cache there
and maybe g is actually in the state that call idle,
that means actually the g at that point is not being modified
and were not being worked on by the files
for that particular instant time,
but it's basically what they call a sticky lock.
So that if you know the file server at some point soon,
it's gonna use file g again,
it can actually do so without actually having to communicate with Petal
or reload it's cache or anything like that at all,
because it has a sticky lock,
it knows that nobody else actually has required,
no other workstation as required to lock in the meantime.
So that's the sticky lock
and it turns out that,
the the you know these are two building locks,
that are then being used to what they call,
what's what is called cache coherence protocol
and set of messages, we're set of rules that are being followed
to actually get cache consistency
and the basic rule is that,
you know guiding rule is to cache a file,
you first must acquire a lock,
you'll see that rules stepping stone for actually getting cache consistency or cache coherence.
I'm going to make a smaller simplification,
in the paper, they describe their own locks,
basically being exclusive or read-write locks,
I'm just going to assume for the rest of the lecture,
the exclusive it doesn't really matter,
but there's an optimization,
based on multiple workstations can have a file cache in read-only mode.
Okay, so with that,
let me talk a little bit about,
let's catch out the protocol that Frangipani uses.
And again you know cache coherence or cache consistency,
the goal actually for even though the file systems distributed,
it should behave like a single file system,
so you only have one file server,
you want to basically the same results will be returned by the distributed file system,
so you can't tell the difference whether it's distributed or not,
and so this is how you remind me of likely linearizability,
so in fact you know I I believe actually what Frangipani shoot for,
it's actually linearizable file system operations.
Okay, so we got the lock server,
we got workstation 1,
and there's workstation 2.
And, there are four messages that are important here,
there's namely requesting a lock granting a lock
and revoking a lock and actually releasing the lock,
so those are the four messages that fly between back and forth,
between workstations and lock server
and lock server and other workstations,
so let's look at this,
let's say locks server has,
nobody has any locks at any time,
so let's draw some timelines,
and workstation 1 wants to request,
once they read write file f,
you know basically sends a request for a lock,
you know to the lock server for file f,
so workstation, but can't do anything really at this point yet,
the lock server you know checks it's stable
and sees that f actually is not used by anybody at all,
at least workstation 1 as the lock owner sends basically message backs
and granting the lock for f,
so at this point, workstation 1 requires to lock for f,
now it can actually read or write where now we can actually read the file from Petal,
actually can make modifications to it too,
you know those modifications should stay local,
nothing really happens is a write back cache, not a write through cache.
And so it just stays happily on the on the client side.
In fact the workstation you can even release the lock,
you know here in basically go from busy to idle,
and so it actually would need to lock again,
for example once write after write again,
we can actually do the complete local without any interaction with the lock server.
There's a slight simplification here,
there's we'll see in a second,
that the lock has least associated with it,
so the client at least has to refresh the disk periodically,
but it doesn't have to read write or reread the file f from actually Petal,
if the lease has expired.
Okay, so the instant case of course happens,
like what if workstation 2 wants to read the file f,
so you know what will happen with workstation 2 want to read
and basically it will do the same thing,
it will send a acquire or request message,
request message to lock server for saying I want f,
and the way it works is that,
the lock server actually looks at this table,
sees the f is actually owned by workstation 1
and then will send the revoke message to workstation 1
asking you know the lock back,
so that will revoke f,
and at this point,
Petal actually do a little bit more of,
Frangipani actually little bit of work,
because we have to make sure the workstation 2 observes the writes,
that workstation 1 is done
and so the way that is done is that basically this instant of time,
the workstation 1 writes actually f you know to Petal
and we'll see in a second, actually writing f to Petal actually a slightly complicated operations,
more sophisticated than I'm just making it out to be,
but just think about it at this point,
workstation 1 is basically flushing its states related to f and to Petal.
Once that actually completed,
so like once Petal are acknowledged,
that actually it actually has received all the data
and actually sends a message back, releasing f.
And you know once lock server gets the release of f,
you know that can update its table and allocate the lock the workstation 2
and sends you know a grant for f to 2.
Oops.
And at this point,
workstation 2 requires lock
and now it can actually read all the information from the file f Petal,
at that point it is guaranteed that we'll see the latest changes to the file f,
because the previous owner must have flushed the state you know to the Petal,
before it actually released the lock and gave it back to the lock server
and workstation 2 is guaranteed to actually observe those changes
and so here's where our strong consistency comes in,
these strong consistency are tied to the lock management.
Any questions about this?
There's a question.
Okay,
we need to write,
one question in the chat,
let me address the first,
we need to write to Petal,
when releasing both read and write locks,
why do we need to write to Petal when releasing a read lock.
Let's ignore read write, the distinction between read and write,
exclusive locks and read write locks,
in the, and just focus on exclusive locks,
you know read the whole reading is just a small [app],
as it happens an important optimization,
but it doesn't really change the designer system dramatically.
Any other questions?
So this sort of design, would be really inefficient,
if we have like two different workstations
that are both modifying the same file.
Yeah.
You just get like cache bouncing back and forth.
Yeah, you maybe if you're two workstations or two different engineers,
that server would be banging on the same file,
you know the file would go back and forth.
And so is not really suitable,
so you can see here,
the influence of like the workload that they're designing for,
you know they're really assumption is that
basically most engineers are working on their private files
and you know once in a while, they'll share files,
but they were probably not banging on the same shared file.
We're not using git,
but you could imagine if they have a share your code repositories,
or you check out your own copy of the code repository,
make all modifications
and some point you write it back.
I'm sorry, just to make sure you say,
you can release the lock while you still have the file in the cache.
You can, okay, so I'm going to be very careful with
when I met with releasing the lock there,
is not releasing it to the lock server,
but locally you know changing the states from busy to idle,
and since you know the lock is sticky
you know it still sits at workstation 1
and lock server still things actually workstation 1 has the lock.
Is that answering your question?
Yeah, yeah, thank you.
So what happens, if the request from two comes awhile to busy?
Yes, good question, what do you think happens?
Does it just reject them?
No, that's I think it doesn't reject it, just waits
and waits until workstation 1 is done,
modifying the file f for executing its file system operation,
and then the Frangipani code will release locally the lock,
will see that someone is waiting for it
and so doesn't change it to busy,
but actually starts flushing all the operations to Petal
and then releases the lock.
So this comes actually nicely to the second point,
which is this atomicity point,
so maybe that will make it more clear.
Let me talk a little bit about atomicity,
because it also use the same locks to achieve atomic file system operations.
you using locks,
so when for example you do create operation,
like you execute the create file system operation or whatever create f,
you know whatever the usual arguments.
And there's of course internally even though the application makes this create file system,
called this internally actually has multiple a file system modifications,
you know for example the directory needs to be modified,
actually let me do it in a slightly different order,
we need to allocate an inode you know for f,
we need to initialize that inode, write the inode,
and then you know update the directory,
update the directory to add an entry,
basically for you know the [] f,
and whatever inode number was allocated for f,
so there's typical way in which a Unix file system implements files
and so we need to arrange that these operations happen atomically,
because we don't want to sort of intermediate results be visible to other workstations
in the way that happens is using by acquiring those locks acquire the lock,
for this particular inode,
you know, for example later inode 10,
so you require a lock for f,
I'm just gonna use f the lock I think,
but yeah it's gonna be inode number
and then at some point, it releases file system at [], itself releases the lock.
And again this releases a local release operation,
it doesn't really mean immediately releasing it back to the lock server,
just changing the status from busy to idle.
And so, so if at any particular point in time,
as we just ask you know there's a request coming in for revoke the lock,
you know revoke f, that request is not actually being served into the file system,
the local [] file system at workstation 1,
has called the local release operation.
And then it sees that when does the local release operation,
it sees that there's a revoke waiting,
so at this point, it's going to flush its cache state, cache state you know to Petal.
And ones that actually have a flush cache state to Petal,
it will grant basically revoke or accept the revoke
and send back a release to lock server,
so then the lock can there be assigned to workstation 2. Is that makes sense?
So just make sure,
so in this create operation here,
we have to modify the inode for,
so we have to modify the inode for f
and inode for the directory that contains f,
because we have to update the references
and so that means that,
is like technically speaking we're actually holding two locks,
and we have to release both of them before we reply back to the the revoke request.
Yes actually this read the paper and then really talk about this issue,
but basically they sort of have,
not very coarse-grained locks,
but also very fine-grained lock, [] locks,
they basically have a lock you know per inode
and you know the directory's inode, file's inode
and in fact the directory is nothing else than a file with specific a format, format,
and so really create f,
we actually have to allocate, first allocate the lock or require the lock in the directory d
and then you would allocate or require the lock on inode for f,
and so do hold two locks.
And as you probably have noticed you know
of course you soon as you have to acquire multiple locks,
there's a potential risk of deadlock,
if one workstation allocates locks in a different order,
you can have a deadlock,
so Frangipani follows rules that basically all locks ordered in a particular way
be required the locks in a fixed order.
I say, thank you.
I think the locks ordered by lock, inode number.
So does that makes sense?
Yeah, so there's a bunch more complexity there.
Okay, so the.
You know, so having discussed [] and other [] of file system operations at least during crashes,
you know if there's no crashes,
you know at least it's guaranteed that these operations happen atomically,
because the locks ensure atomicity,
of course it could be the case,
that like we're unlucky right
and so the workstation 1 crashes,
right in the middle of these operations,
for example as allocated allocated the inode,
it actually has not updated the directory yet.
And, let's say the crash happens here,
you know and if we don't do anything special,
like what is the the concern that we might have.
Okay, let me concern we might have,
you know some file system operation actually is only partially apply to Petal,
and you know that becomes more clear,
if we actually think about the scenario
what actually happens in this particular state,
like when the state of the cache actually flushed to Petal.
And so this is the topic of crash recovery.
It turns out that actually updating the state in,
updating state in Petal also follows actually pretty careful protocol,
and this protocol some is typically called write-ahead logging.
And this is you know probably the term we've already seen
and you've seen probably in 6.033,
and you know Petal use it too is a very common technique,
and it will also play a big important role in subsequent papers that will see
and so Petal is actually a nice reintroduction
to this idea of write-ahead logging
and a way to think about write,
you know gonna Petal designed to write-ahead logging,
use of wirte-ahead logging is very similar to any other write-ahead logging scheme
and so you know the way to think about it as follows,
you know we have our disk, virtual disk,
I mean just think about disk as like a long general long array of blocks,
and what they've done is part of the disk is reserved as a log,
in fact in the case of Petal,
there's a log per server,
but let's, for now, let's just assume there's like one single log
and then there's the file system,
so there's part of the disk is reserved for logging
or part of the disk is the file system
and the file system contains inodes,
you know, and some data block, etc, etc.
And the rule is that when you update the state in Petal,
the first thing you do is actually your first log update,
so when, if we go back to the previous picture,
and after the point that the Frangipani on workstation 1,
I wanted to give back the lock,
you know to the lock server,
it first has to write its state you know to Petal
and that goes in two steps,
the first step is lock the, update the description of the update,
you know to the log, the lock operation,
here for example we'll get a record,
that's says you know create basic describes the create operation,
so that will have you know whatever allocate inode,
inode number whatever basically the result that would have happened,
if you allocated inode and the directory changed.
It will be a little bit more specific in a second,
but that's sort of the the update contains the modifications,
need to be made to happen to the file system blocks,
to actually reflect the change,
so first log to the,
first log the update
and then once you have updated the log,
then we, the second operation of the client executes,
the workstation executes is actually installing the update,
and the reason you know for doing sort of two steps is that,
you know once you've log all your changes,
then it's completely safe to update the data blocks,
because they always will end up and update the file system
and it should always will end up in a consistent state
and the way to see this is basically,
let's assume you know the client workstation
that was actually flushing it's data to Petal, crashes right here.
Is that okay?
Yes, because since everything is locked,
they what was it called the demon recovery service.
Yeah, the demon just gonna go back to,
there's gonna be a demon,
when there's a crash, there's basically demon,
sees if there's anything in the log,
if there's anything in the log,
just applies to the file system.
And why actually do this in the way,
why not just write immediately or update the file system?
Because we can crash in the middle of that update
and we don't know what we've done, we can't.
Yeah, exactly correct,
so we're serving, there's our previous example,
you know allocating inode is presumably you know to making some change somewhere,
like onto inode block
and actually adding the directory to or adding the file f to particular directory,
updates directory block, data block somewhere,
so these are two separate writes, right,
two separate disk los and they're not atomic,
so we would crash between one of the two,
then we might have allocated the inode,
but not stuck in the directory.
Then basically what will happen if we crash and recover,
basically lose the inode,
unless we could scan the whole disk, but that's very expensive.
And so they said what we're doing is,
we're basically logging the two changes first,
we're logging records describing both changes first
and then apply the changes.
So how do we ensure the operation is atomic,
so the first log to update.
The first log update,
yeah that's interesting,
so the paper tracking a hundred percent correspond this,
but there's a couple ways of doing it,
they mention that every log record has a checksum,
and, so they use checksum to see if there's actually,
before the read log record, you know read log record,
we compute a checksum,
just to make sure that the whole record is complete.
I see, thank you.
Another way of doing it,
which is a couple way of doing it as you write,
you know a couple blocks like one two
and then you write a commit record,
and the assumption is that
running a single block, single 512 sector is an atomic operation,
so either happens or it doesn't happen,
so you need to commit records says
writes are done or writes are not done
and so you can just look at the commit record,
and if the commit records is not there,
then you know the operation is not completely recorded yet
and you shouldn't execute any of it.
I see, and also to double-check on the previous slide,
if the crash happens before we flush things to Petal,
then this is not a problem right,
because if the workstation crashes,
well the cash goes with the workstation,
but there's no inconsistent state for any other workstation.
That's correct,just data would be lost,
if it's not written to the Petals, won't be any visibility problem.
So it's really you know the crash crash here, correct,
one doesn't really matter in some ways,
the one that actually matters is the crash during this flush operation.
Mhm, thank you.
Okay, so, you know there's one subtly in Frangipani,
which we'll talk about in a second a little bit more detail,
namely that in Frangipani there's a lock per server,
that's sort of unusual,
and, we'll see in a second,
you know how the one that actually creates some problems,
and so we'll see,
there's a small extension to the protocol
to actually make this all work out.
Okay, let me say a little bit about [],
what is in one of those log records,
it turns out to be important for the crash recovery,
particularly because we have Frangipani multiple logs per server.
So every log has a,
so your log, basically you know there are records in it,
they have a sequence number,
you know whatever number two, one two
and you know what the end of the log is,
if the next sequence number is now higher, one higher than yours.
So there's another way they mark it up,
basically in one of these records is array of updates,
now describe the file system operation,
and so it contains the block number, that needs to be updated,
for example in our case, that would usually be the inode number,
the block that contains the inodes,
that would be navigated a version number,
because in that record, we've seen second, why that is important
and basically the new bytes for that block number.
And so, for example, in the case of creating file, creating f,
it's gonna be you know two entries in this array,
two entries, one describing the update to the inode block,
one describing new update to the directory block, the data block of the directory.
And so basically what happens on replication,
just to like make this abundantly clear,
when request to [] block comes in
you know the first thing that happens is force the log to Petal,
once that is done,
send the, updates were sent the blocks, the updated blocks to Petal,
and then release the lock.
And this ensures that you know there's a couple things
that we need to think about,
if if there's no crashes in the middle,
then you know this is always as previously described
really you know interesting cases,
when a crash happens right after forcing the log to P,
but before updating Petal.
So let's talk a little bit about that.
Sorry, what do you mean by new bytes?
Good, let me go back,
so with another mean, changes to inode blocks,
so for example the inode block,
you know maybe you know updating,
you know some part of the inode,
then you sort of write down the bytes have changed,
like bytes zero to five and twelve the following value,
or bytes ten to twenty have the following new value.
But can those changes be like,
because each one of these blocks is at most 512 bytes,
but the modifications that you make can be a lot larger than 512 bytes,
there's gonna be a record for every block.
So, in fact in the, okay, so a couple points,
first of all,
data writes actually are not going through the log,
so there's an important point,
so thank you, thank you for asking that question,
so when you write a file,
in the application calls like write file f and a whole bunch of data,
all that data actually does not go through the log,
that just goes straight to Petal,
like once you flush the state,
the only changes that go through the log are meta update changes,
so metadata changes,
and what metadata means is really information about files,
so inodes directories,
that kind of stuff that actually goes through the log.
And so the description that you see in here is
really you know the updates to the metadata blocks of the file system,
so inodes and directory data.
And the application level data like the file blocks that actually constitute a file,
and that actually those blocks are just written straight to Petal
and they'll go for a block.
So it's interesting to contemplate what is the implications of that,
like that design choice,
what's the downside of not running everything through the log?
Assel.
The updates to the data they can be lost.
They can get lost, yeah,
what other sort of scenarios are possible,
so let's say you know the file consists of 10 blocks,
we're start writing the 10 blocks,
you know what's in what states can file actually end up.
Being consistent.
Yeah, well yeah consistent could have some of the writes,
none of the writes, all of them,
who knows what, right.
But does not guarantee that all 10 of them will be applied together.
This is, so this is important
when you have like like this like need for atomic write.
Yeah, like if you didn't need atomicity,
with this, like could we get rid of that of the log.
The I think so,
holds on the question a second,
let's first talk about the applications
and then we'll come back to that.
So, okay, the.
So the applications can't really write you know their data atomically to the log,
because the data is now written for log
and so now written to log and then apply,
so so that means that for example if an application you want atomicity of of your writes into particular file,
then you have to arrange that for yourself
and this actually turns out to be the case on most Unix files in anyway,
so in that way from Frangipani,
it doesn't really change the game,
you know you write a file in the Unix file system,
you write like a VM image,
it's not guaranteed like the whole image is written consistently in one single shot,
you know to the file system,
even when they're a crash.
So the typical way you know people solve this problem in applications is that,
it first write a temporary file,
write everything in a temporary file
and then do an atomic rename into the destination file.
So Frangipani basically relies exactly on the same set up,
sort of normal Unix would do,
like Frangipani doesn't change the game
and this is why as a writes of files are actually not logged through the log.
And what is the advantage of not logging,
so clearly there's a downside, right,
because you can't do a file writes atomically using the log,
you have to have your own plan for atomicity,
and what is the advantage?
Well, performance, because metadata is very small compared to the actual user data.
Yeah.
And also memory, as well.
Yeah, exactly,
so do the like if you write a gigantic file, correct,
saying gigabyte file,
that really means you have to write two gigabytes,
first you're write gigabyte to the log
and then write gigabyte you know to the disk
and so basically this cuts their performance in a pretty dramatically
and so which is why you know typically the user data is not written for log.
Yeah, it's very important portion of come back to this earlier question,
is very important that the internal file system structures are kept consistent,
where you're not you're not inconsistent
and so therefore, the metadata updates all go through the log,
so basically you know like when you create the file,
you need to update the inode block
and you need to update the directory block,
that's guaranteed to happen together.
So would the data block date go between step 2 and 3.
Yeah, I think they just send them out,
probably they probably after one they probably sent the data blocks in parallel to as part of step two and straight to Petal,
to the file system area.
Okay?
So I I had a question,
I think, I don't remember exactly how big the log was,
but I believe it could span like two blocks.
It can log is multiple records, yeah.
Yeah, that's right, up to to terabytes,
so what happens if we, if we send,
like a lot like part of a log and then it crashes,
as you're sending log,
when we get like an issue with like.
That's exactly what I want to talk about, thank you.
So there's a bunch of crashes that could happen right,
like so so, if we crash,
considered a bunch of cases,
like we run a crash before writing to the log.
So what, in that case what's the outcome?
Hmm, it's lost.
Yeah, lost.
So, then we go the scenario,
like we crash after writing the lock, what happens then?
It's actually a slightly complicated scenario.
Is this after writing like the log to a Petal.
Then the demon steps then.
Yes, then the deamon steps,
it's a little bit of a complicated story, correct,
because you know how, how does this all discovered, what actually happens.
So presumably what happens if somebody else wants the lock correct on this file,
that you know that the crashed workstation holds.
And you know here's where leases coming important,
so every lock has a lease,
and what the lock server will do,
it will not grant you the lock server will ask workstation one,
please give me your lock f back,
workstation one, it doesn't respond, because it's crashed,
and what the lock server does,
it waits until the lease expires on the lock.
And why does it wait until the lock, the lease is expired.
I I think I think in this case,
the the server,
yeah the server that crashed like also knows,
it didn't like renew its lease,
so it can clean up by its own.
Yeah, clean up its own stuff,
what's the fundamental problem here,
that we're actually trying to challenge,
almost like the scenario that we've seen over and over in previous lecture stuff,
there's always a challenge.
The partition.
Partition, exactly,
could be the case that you know actually workstation one did not crash,
but the lock server can't talk to the workstation,
because of the network partition,
but the log in the workstation you can talk to Petal,
and so it might still may make changes, right,
but whatever we guaranteed as you just pointed out,
once the lease expires, workstation one will definitely not make any changes.
Okay, it is not allowed to,
follow the protocol is not allowed to make any changes anymore.
And so this is why the lock server waits until the lease expires,
then at that point and knows for sure that nobody holds a lock anymore
or couldn't hold the lock if nobody's writing to Petal anymore
and so at this point, it will ask one of the remaining workstations to,
basically what they call the demon, recovery demon,
the recovery demon, and the recovery demon basically will apply, will read the the log the workstation one each log
and basically apply the operations that are in that log.
Okay?
You know the way to think about the demon,
it's sort of like, this is terminology,
it's typically just a service or a server or server process,
that basically does sort of house cleaning or house cleaning tasks
and those kind of services that are not really used continuously,
they're often called demons.
So once the demon is done,
then actually the lock you know can be,
lock server can resign the lock,
or grant the lock to somebody to another workstation.
But just to double check,
so, if you crash after writing the log,
then you'll get you're going to have a consistent state,
when it comes to the metadata,
but the user is not guaranteed to have finished writing the user data.
Yeah absolutely,no guarantees about the user data.
So the only thing the the guarantees
that like really the logging system helps achieving is
basically consistency of the internal file system data structures.
Okay, sounds good.
Which is important, correct,
because it would be pretty bad, if file internal file system data structures are messed up,
you know, everybody might lose their data.
Okay, so then there's another instant case, what can happen,
okay, so writing the log to P,
what happens if we crash during writing the log.
Is this what you mentioned before that their checksums
and we can check whether it was a complete or not.
Yeah, good point,
so what happens in this case,
is that a prefix might end up in the,
the prefix might end up in the log, right,
but each of the prefix might contain multiple log records with multiple operations, correct,
you know whatever sequence number one, sequence number two, the multiple records,
if we crash during one of these records updates
you know then the checksum won't checkout
and so will basically stop you know the the recovery demon will stop at that record.
So what will be in the log,
will be correct prefix of the operations,
so for example you know the create of file f is in there,
maybe to create file g is in there,
but the create file h is not in there,
but each individual record that describes one atomic you know file system operation,
you know is in there and is complete.
And so what will happen is
that basically we apply the prefix of the operations at the workstation is doing
and we basically lose the end of the prefix
or the end of its updates,
but you know undesirable, but we're totally okay,
because, you know in the other case,
we might have lost all updates.
But in the first case,
we were crashed before the one,
we would have nothing on this.
Does that make sense?
Okay, there's one, one more tricky case,
you know we need to consider
and that has to do with the fact,
that actually Petal has a lock per server or log per server.
So I talked a little bit about that,
and these are related to the question in a post you know for the reading.
And this is about many logs
and so let's say we have workstations,
each with their own log.
So here's workstation 1, workstation 2, workstation 3.
And workstation 1, at some point, does a delete of file f that happened to exist before,
then workstation 2 does it create fd of f
and but that create,
remember has written to his own log,
so this delete is written to the log of workstation 1,
this create is written to the log of workstation 2.
Now, let's say, workstation 1 crashes in
and then workstation 3 you know basically you know the recovery demon runs,
you know for workstation 1,
and you know the bad possible outcome, correctly,
that would delete, replay the delete,
which would overwrite the changes,
that workstation 2 make to Petal, right,
so that's the context
and the question is how is this fixed
and I think this the way I would like to address this
is by actually having you spend a couple minutes in the breakout room,
debate this with each other or any other aspect of Petal,
if you want to.
And so.
Lily or anybody else, any other TAs,
so you send people to breakout rooms.
Should I do it, or.
Yeah it'll be great.
Okay cool, right.
I'll close them in about five minutes.
Everybody back?
Okay, so just, just quickly summarized,
so we have 3 workstations,
workstation one at some point deleted the file that's in the log,
workstation 2 at some point later create create a file f,
it is in his log
and then one crashes and workstation 3 actually runs recovery demon on the log of workstation 1.
And of course, it would be disaster,
if the delete would be replayed,
because later create has happened on another workstation,
but it's in another log,
so demon doesn't know what,
how is this problem solved,
or has this potential disaster avoided.
We said version numbers.
Yeah, yes, you could say a little bit more if you want to.
Sure, so like it's guaranteed,
because we had the lock
that the operations have already completed for server one
and so the like the version number for the log is written in the Petal,
like the last operation
and so the recovery demon won't do anything previous to the current version number.
Yeah, that's yeah absolutely right,
so just summarize,
so we have two logs, correct,
actually of importance
and we have some file system state,
that's in the Petal right,
so these are the logs
and then here's the actual file system.
And here was you know like this is directory d,
you know and directory d was modified in the file f
and deleted that has a log number i say 10,
and this is workstation 2
and here is d,
those deleting d, f and d,
and you're creating f and d and what log number will be in this entry, version number, sorry.
11?
11 yep basically totally ordered and locking protocols ensured they totally ordered.
And on the, in the file system with the metadata blocks
like for example if the inode block for f,
inode have one version number is going to be on the disk or in Petal.
11?
Yeah, in the case that actually the operation was applied to the file system will be 11, correct.
And so when the demon we,
what role does the deme follow?
Never replace something that's already been applied.
Yeah, does it just decided it's applied.
Like a version number.
Yeah version number, right,
so if the version number
and only replies an entry, if the version number in the log record,
log version number is higher than the inode or the metadata version number,
you know then replay, okay?
So in this case,
you know the recovery demon will see the version number in the log record is 10
which is smaller than 11 or equals 11, doesn't matter
and so it won't replay it,
and so this problem cannot appear.
So does the 10 necessarily not,
does it okay such that like that 10 is not on the ws workspace 2's log.
Yeah, it's not there.
So like in the work,
because the workstation 2 wrote actually the inode after workstation 1,
so its version number be 11,
basically what you do to prepare and update
the version number in the update record is always one plus you know the current version number in the inode.
Okay?
This is a small question,
but what does the d stand for.
It's directory, creating a file in the directory d,
we're deleting a file from the directory d,
and the update must include you know some information about the directory.
Okay.
Sorry, I had a quick question,
so are their version numbers like always tied to the specific inode that's being edited.
Yes.
Okay.
Absolutely, the version number for every update, right,
like there's a version number for directory,
there's a version number for the file,
like showing a little bit wrong here.
Like if you go back to the log record.
Here, basically there's array of updates
and every update in the array completes block number version number in the new bytes.
Thanks.
Okay, so just stepping back and closing off the discussion of this paper.
It's probably the first paper that we've read
that basically in order, the system itself is not the one
you know it's not going to be dominant use,
and therefore it's really interesting to talk about,
but what is interesting about this system is the ideas in it
and so cache coherence protocol or cache consistence c protocol,
distributed locking, lock servers leases, granting requiring revoking,
and distributed recovery,
where one workstation crashes,
but like demon on another workstation actually does the recovery
and what particularly interesting is that
what's interesting is the interaction between the three pieces.
Then they interact.
And what we'll see in the next you know couple of papers
next week particularly not on the first day,
but the papers after that, which we're going to talk about some of the heavy-duty pretty involved transaction systems,
we'll see these three topics that come up too
and so hopefully this will help you in reading those papers,
understand actually what cache coherence is,
what's you know crash recovery is
and you know distributed lock.
And the other probably point it's interesting to make is that
you know Petal is really good for useful for the particular setting they designed it for.
There's the performance part of the papers,
but hard to understand,
because it's like from 1999,
but I give a look at the graph,
you'll see that the file system basically workload can increase with the number of workstations,
you know that's exactly what we're shooting for
and and they achieve that goal,
anyway I hope you find this design interesting
sort of not your usual design
and so I hopefully will have thought provoking.
And with that I'll stop,
of course you know stick around, if you want to ask more questions
and otherwise I'll see you first day.
Can I can I ask two questions,
so, my first question was just
in general the cache coherence protocol here,
it's not have one file cache in two places, right.
Yep.
Okay, and my other question was about the,
there was a page with the log,
in you have the log records, there.
Yep, let me go back here, Yep.
Yeah, I was, I was wondering you said that each, each like record is atomic,
but each record has a number of updates too, right.
Yes, again I think the paper slightly vague here,
what exactly what it does,
either it always fits in 512 bytes
and then the single sector 512 bytes is atomic
or they use this checksum trick.
So, you read to five [] sectors,
re-compute checksum and compare it with the checksum stored,
it's right then it must be a complete record.
Okay, okay, so if it's shorter than,
good, if it's not then you do the trick,
okay, I see.
Yeah, I'm not sure what exactly they do.
Okay, okay, thank you so much.
You're welcome.
Any more questions?
If you go back or forward three slides.
Yep.
Here, it was.
Oh, maybe back one slide,
there's a section where you talked about how if crash happens
during the middle of a write
and we get like yeah prefix in the log log,
that's like okay or something do you mind repeating what you meant there.
Yeah, okay, so so let's go back to this last picture,
I just showed earlier here,
so we have our, so the workstation 1 could have executed many, many file system operations, correct,
each one of them described by one of these lock by an entry in the log,
so like the first entry it might be creating file f,
second entry in the log might be creating file g,
you know whatever the third one might creating deleting file f.
And so there's a whole sequence of operations,
because remember the workstation just keeps executing file system operations,
as long as it holds locks
and nobody else wants the lock.
And so the lock could be a contained a whole bunch of file system operations,
now for each file system operation, for each individual one,
there's a log record.
And the log records, you know is the atomic file system operations
description of the changes that need to be made
to the actual files to lock
to reflect that file system operation.
And so what could happen, right
is that the revoke message comes in the workstation 1,
starts writing its log you know to Petal,
but it just doesn't get the whole way to the end,
it just happens to crash, like somewhere in the middle like anywhere, right,
in that case, the prefix of the workstation 1 is on the disk or in Petal.
And that means that basically the last couple files from operation are just logs,
and only the prefix will be replayed.
I see and we're just saying that's okay.
Yeah, we're accepting that outcome.
Got it, thank you.
Because we're already accepted to that outcome earlier,
because it could in the case,
that we've got the file system crashed right before or right after you got the revoke message,
but it actually didn't write any log entries get to Petal.
Any more questions?
I have a completely unrelated question to 6.824,
but I was wondering if you knew anything about 6.858 for next semester,
I saw professor Zeldovich is going to be teaching 6.860.
Yeah, I think we're, the current plan does not offer 6.858 in the Fall,
but we're hoping to offer it in the Spring.
Okay, awesome, do you know what 6.860 is,
I I couldn't find much information for.
Yeah, that's a good question,
it's intended to be a undergraduate class.
Okay.
Okay, nice.
So like 6.858 but undergrad.
Yeah, sort of like, maybe an intro to both 6.857 and 6.858.
Okay, what's the number?
It's an experimental number,
it's one of these experimental,
because the class doesn't exist yet
and will be offered for you know the goal is to offer it for the first time in the Fall.
Okay, so, is it gonna be mostly content from,
like is 6.858 gonna keep its original form, or is it.
You're asking me questions, I don't.
Sorry.
Yeah, I think the people involved in in designing the class
are people that are involved in 6.857
and the people involved in 6.858.
Yeah.
I'm not actually involved.
Okay, yet another reason,
but and they're trying to work out with the curriculum exactly it's going to be
and then of course he's going to have some calculations for 6.858 6.857.
Okay, sounds good.
But 6.858, 6.857, I'm not gonna go away, that's the.
Great thanks.
You're welcome.
I have a question,
I don't know how quick it is,
but in the paper, at the end of page,
like right before section seven, they talk about a case failure,
where with like the lease expiring
and the server not really crashing.
Yeah.
And then talk about like
basically that there's no real solution.
Well there is a solution,
there is a real solution.
Like human intervention.
Yeah, okay, so I think the problem here in the [] of the theme of the paper works
like a Petal and Frangipani are designed independently
and that has a lot of nice properties,
and this is going to where one one place,
where it would be very helpful,
hopefully that your Petal has some support to help Frangipani along.
And that support would be actually have a timestamp on the writes to Petal,
so that Petal could see where write actually is out basically too old.
Okay.
So unless you do that,
you need to like fiddle around with like the margin.
Okay.
And what happens if,
like that error occurs,
like outside of the bounds of the margin.
It'll be that's cool,
basically you get an older writes
you show up in the basically somebody else might have that point gotten the lock on the file, correct,
started writing to it
and then there's old write shows up
and basically presumably overwrite some part of it.
Okay.
So will break consistency.
So, thank you.
You're welcome.
Okay.
Because we'll stop that.