So the topic for today is raft replication [] protocol,
we'll discuss it quite a bit of detail,
in fact we're going to spend multiple lectures on it
and one because it's one of the core elements of examples of distributed replication protocol.
So, today been mostly focusing on you know the material that is necessary for labs 2a and 2b,
so the election of the leader as well as you know pushing the logs around
and then next week, we're focusing more on 2c and 2d, mainly the snapshots and log compassion
and give us opportunity to just any other aspect of raft.
In fact we'll talk about raft one more time in the week after,
we'll have a Q&A lecture on you know 2a and 2b
and so talk about the actual solutions to the labs 2a 2b.
Okay?
That's the plan
and so I'm going to just dive in with with a starting point for today.
The place probably start is to observe that
in some of the previous case studies of replicated systems,
we've seen as sort of pattern,
you know look at GFS, mapreduce, virtual FT,
they all have a single point of failure,
so even though they're replicated systems,
and they do replication for fault tolerance,
all of them actually have a single point of failure,
you know in case of and mapreduce was the coordinator,
in the case of GFS, you know the master,
that hands out the leases for example
and you know in the VM FT case,
the storage server really the test-and-set server.
And the reason why as we be discussed in the previous lecture,
the reasons that actually there are you know single machines instead of replicated machines
is to avoid you know split-brain syndrome.
And you know for many systems, in sort of one way in this sort of [bummer],
we're building a high performance, building a very fault tolerant systems
and and all these designs actually,
we do actually still have a single point of failure,
even though where replication is used for many other aspects of the system designs
and for many of the systems that we talked so far about,
you know this to avoid this split-brain center syndrome
and actually introduce a single point of failure
or maintain a single point of failure,
those are perfectly acceptable in many cases,
because in many of these cases like the store server,
or you know the master goes down,
you know hopefully it's only a single machine,
so the chance of going down to smaller than any out of the chunk servers
and you know probably there's somebody ready you know to be [beat] up,
you know indicates that the master goes down,
comes back up and we'll make sure there's only one master online.
So, you know many many circumstances is perfectly fine,
you know will lead maybe to a very short downtime.
But you know some systems it's really nice,
it would be really nice actually, if this,
we didn't even have to have the single points of failure,
that maybe we could reduce downtime even further and increase uptown.
And so, and that's really were you know the protocols,
so just kind of protocols that raft you know fits into come into play.
But just before diving into talking about sort of the key ideas into protocol,
let's remind ourselves why the sort of single point of failure leads,
why actually replicating the sort of crucial single point of failures like test-and-set server can lead you to this split-brain problem.
And so you might think,
why just replicate a single point of failure too.
So let's try to do that
and then we'll quickly see what the problem is,
so let's replicate the testing server.
And so, so let's do a simple straightforward case,
we'll just have one replicated, one test server S1,
and here we have S2, the other replicated test-and-set server,
and user remind correct like test-and-set,
it takes an argument new and returns the old value.
And the goal is that if two clients at the same time call test-and-seth,
you know one wins, you know get so basically falls back as the old value
and the other one will lose,
because it will get true back as is the old value.
So let's see how this might work play out,
so we have a client with calls test-and-set
and communicates with the first server, communicates to the second server,
and we don't really know, actually doesn't get a response for the second server,
so there's sort of two cases now right,
where you know why, if S2 doesn't response,
you know there's two possible reasons why that could be the case.
So one case could be S2 didn't respond, because S2 failed.
And in some cases that's really what we'd like to be doing is that,
at that point basically C1 just declares victory,
since nobody else can actually see observe value S2,
you know we should be done, we could proceed.
But the problem is that, there's the second case,
in the second case is that,
there's no repetition,
there's a network partition between C1 and C and S2.
So in that case really C1 cannot proceed,
because there could be another client you know C2
and actually communicating with S2,
and it would be terrible, correct,
C1 proceeds in this case,
because you know it might update S1,
get basically the false value, think it succeeds,
at the same time, S2 communicates with S2,
and also succeeds during the test-and-set
and so now we're violating our contract with the test-and-set.
So this is this issue of this split-brain,
when there's a network partition,
we can end up in a situation where both servers are up running
and serve different subset of clients
and thereby violating the contract with the specification of the system that we're building.
And the real challenging part here is that,
C1 just cannot tell the difference between these two situations,
it doesn't know, where it actually is,
you know S2 is not reachable,
because it failed or because of the network partition,
and so that's sort of the conundrum
and that that you know, that's behind all this the previous systems
and why they used a single,
why they don't replicate you know these crucial services,
that need to be up to avoid, to avoid split-brain syndrome.
So what can be done about this
and really the key problem here,
what do we do about network partition,
how could we handle them,
and so there's a key idea
that sits in raft and in many other protocols that underlies,
basically the solution or why those protocols, actually might succeed
and really what it is you know sort of in a nutshell,
it is this majority rule.
And you give the example in the context of test-and-set on your server,
instead of actually running the server with two replicas which I conveniently did,
I'm gonna run it with three,
so I'm gonna have S1 S2 S3.
And the rule that was going to be the like
server, a client can consider an operation succeeded,
if at least can update a majority of the servers.
So in this case,
you know we can send you know message to S1,
for doing test-and-set, we send message to S2, for doing test-and-set,
now we get back positive responses for both of them,
like a false in both cases,
then will return a false to actually application
and application considered the test-and-set succeeded.
And of course we do it also to the third one,
but the third one may actually, you know the message actually might not arrive or the server might be down,
we don't really know, actually we don't really care,
which is because consider the following situation, scenario,
where we have the second client are also trying to do test-and-set,
well, to be able to succeed,
it has to talk to the majority of the servers,
so, whatever majority is going to talk to,
it is going to include either S1 or S2,
and for S1 and S2 both of these operations actually have succeeded by S C1,
so S2 proceed to always observe the result of C1's operation,
because there's sort of an overlap.
Yeah, and you'll see this basically raft,
this is exactly the same thing as roughly what's going on, right,
like when a leader accepts or enters the operation in a lot of the majority of the followers,
then it means that a subsequent leader that's going to come out in the next term,
you know will also try to acquire majority to get voted as leader
and as part of that voting,
there's going to be one server or one follower that actually has seen the last operation,
performed by the last leader.
So that is going to basically be able to building stone on on which we can build the fault tolerance services,
that can handle network partitions in
and failures of servers while still achieving strong consistency.
Another way to think about this majority business is that,
if the network partitions,
there can be only one partition that has majority,
there can be no other partition that has majority
and so only the partition that actually has the majority can actually proceed.
Another way of saying that,
in another implication of that is,
it could also be the case,
there's multiple partitions and there's no majority anywhere
and in that particular case,
you know the system can just not proceed and the clients talking to this,
we have to wait until the network is healed enough,
that at least there's one, there's going to be at least one partition with majority of services.
The another sort of a quick observation here is that,
of course you may want to use this particular scheme,
that I just described three servers,
only tolerate one server going down, correct,
the two servers going down, nobody can actually obtain majority
and so therefore nobody can actually or no client can actually get the operation through,
clearly it's easy to extend this idea,
by what's typically called into 2f+1 replication.
So if you want to tolerate f faults instead of one,
you need two plus f one plus server or server,
so that at least you have always a majority majority if f fails.
And so in case you know here f is 1
and so we're running the 3 servers,
you know want f to be 2, you have 5 servers, etc etc,
you want f to be 3, you have 7 servers.
Okay?
One other thing, this may be important to point out
and I came up a lot in the questions
and what is actually the majority
and the majority is the majority of all the services that are there,
both upwards and downwards.
And so when you take majority,
you don't take the majority of the 2,
if there are only 2 alive,
you take the majority of all the servers in the system.
Any questions about this sort of key idea or.
Could there be an even number of servers,
like if you have 4 servers with the majority, then be three.
If you will see that in a couple cases, correct, in the graph,
that you know if you know the number of servers is reduced from seven to six and one is down
and you still want to proceed,
you need a majority which you still need enough 4 server to actually proceed.
But if you can get 4 servers,
then you can keep going.
Okay.
So I also have a question about the majority,
so does the majority consider the server itself,
so supposing raft does like the server itself considering this.
Yeah, it's part of it,
so like you know often as we've seen raft, correct,
the leader vote immediately vote for itself,
or the candidate vote for itself
and in the leader when it depends you know its own log,
it counts as one,
so it's part of it.
Okay, so, there's quite a number of protocols using this idea, and sometimes these ideas referred to as quorum or quorum protocols,
pretty obvious reason, and there sort of two,
the state of [yard] for a long time until the early 90s or late 80s,
was there's basically no protocol,
so basically we're always in the situation of this single point of failure.
And then in the early 90s,
there were two protocols came came,
were invented roughly at the same time,
one is called paxos,
which is mentioned in the paper quite a bit,
and the other one is called View-Stamped replication,
sometimes called VR
and these were these were again run around 1990.
They didn't actually get much attention at that point in time,
because people didn't really have pressing need to reveal to sort of completely automatic and fault tolerant systems.
But that changed in the last 15 years,
over the last 15 years with much use of these protocols.
And in fact interesting to observe, correct,
that in the last 15 years.
And that's basically sort of 15 years after these protocols were invented,
you know so basically they sat on the table or sit on the shelf for 15 years
until people actually have a real use case for that.
The protocol that we're going to be mostly we're gonna be implementing in the lab
and we're going to discuss in the lecture
and which the topic of the paper is falls in this [] protocol in this called raft.
And it was I think which came about or was written up in 2014 the papers from 2014,
and this is one of the more complete descriptions,
you know it touches on a lot of different aspects
that you're gonna be able to complete replicated state machine
and explains those clearly that's one of the reasons
why we're using it for the labs
and you know for this particular lecture.
Any questions about the history here around protocols,
before I dive into raft.
Okay, so before actually diving into raft,
let me first talk a little bit about how you one would use raft to build a replicated state machine,
because that's at the ends our end goal.
And it will help reasoning about what raft that should be doing for us.
And so the basic way you would use raft
and we'll actually do this in lab 3.
Let's say you have a server,
and raft is basically nothing else than a library
and so in our setting is going to Go package
and you know you can write a replicated state machine by basically importing that package,
so here's we got,
you know here's a raft at the bottom,
and you know you build a server using raft
and so for example in lab 3, we're going to build a key-value server using raft,
and clients you know talk you know to the key-value server,
and you know it's a bit you know put and get operations,
and the key-value servers when it receives one of these put and get operations,
it basically hands it off to raft,
and so it basically puts the raft
and actually sticks it in a, what we'll see much more detail,
it will put it in the log,
actually draw this slightly differently,
so appends it to the log,
it appends to the end of the log,
and then raft internally is going to talk to other servers
to basically replicate that log.
And so here are some other servers,
they basically structured to exactly the same way,
they have a raft library component,
and the key-value server,
like many other replicated state machines we've ever seen,
you know they're identical key-value server
and we're gonna play the same game,
as I know, the other previous replicated state machines machine were basically feeding operations to the key-value servers in the same order everywhere
and as a result you know the keys replicates all applied operations in exactly the same order,
we should see the same key-value stores being built, right,
so we have a key-value store here,
whatever key 20 has some value,
we're applying updates to this in a table exactly the same order and all replicas,
things should be should be good,
we're gonna have identical replicas.
So the way you raft instructed is that one of the replica is the leader,
so let me this for convenience,
you know that's going to be the first one on this side
and actually the clients do talk to the leader,
and then, what happens next is that,
the client talks to one of the leader,
the leader kv server kv server,
appends a log entry to the raft log of the leader
and then you know basically communicates with the other raft libraries,
and there's raft libraries do exactly the same thing,
basically they append you know the operation to the log, to their logs,
and send a response back you know to the leader.
And you know of course you know all these state is stored you know the log
and some other state stored on disk,
so that if any one of them fails,
they at least have the last part of their log,
still available and can build from there.
So once basically and we'll talk a little bit more in detail,
but once the entry where the log entries replicated on 3 servers,
then they can actually be delivered in order to the key-value server.
So every committed operation, there every log is an index,
wherever operation index 0 or actually 1 2 3 4 whatever in order
and they're going to be delivered in order to key-value servers,
once an operation commited,
it's going to be delivered to the key-value server,
the key-value server performs the operation,
maybe updates you know the key-value table
and then since actually the leader alone sends a response back to the client.
So that's sort of roughly the sequence of events that happens,
so client sends request to the leader,
leader put in [] [] raft,
raft you know chit chats with the other servers,
once you know it's replicated enough machines,
then you know the it's considered to be committed
and we'll talk a little bit more precisely what commit means
and then an committed operation is delivered to the key-value servers,
and then they execute the operation and respond to the client
leader response to the client.
So what happens on the failure,
failure, the new leader is elected,
and it will take over the role of the old leader
and so for example like in this particular picture,
you know it might be the case that,
you know this leader crashes,
and you know this becomes the new leader in the next term,
we'll see exactly what that means,
and then the clients basically fail over,
you know they will see, they don't get a response,
so they will time out
and they fail over to the second leader, the new leader
and basically retry their operation.
And so they insert you know that new leader will take their operation
insert it back into raft,
you know the same thing happens as before,
and maybe this time we get lucky
and we actually get the operation without any failures.
If you think a little bit careful about this,
that does mean that a client operation might end up twice in the log, right,
because actually may be the case that the first time it succeeded,
but just didn't get the response
and so it doesn't know that it succeeded,
it will retry,
you know this new leader will put the log, the new retry operation also in the log
and it will pop out at some point in at kv key-value servers
and actually be a duplicate
and so as you will see later in the lab 3,
actually it turns out that the you know what,
you need to do duplication, detect duplicates.
But that's mostly an issue for lab 3,
so it's not going to be a main issue for now,
but it's important to know you know that this is the sort of general style
in which you know one would actually use raft to build a replicated state machine.
Any questions about sort of how to use raft for replicated state machines?
We have a question in the chat.
Yeah.
What is typical number of clients contacting the leader?
Well, there could be many,
there's no real limit on it,
what you'll see you know it could be the case that a single machine can [mean],
maybe that's implicitly, but the question is,
it could be the case that a single leader can not tolerate, the is not capable of handling that many clients
and so, what happens then is that
basically the servers gets sharded,
you know shard key-value servers in multiple raft groups,
so for example shard one would be one raft instance,
shard two is one raft instance,
shard three is one raft instance
and the clients to talk to the appropriate shard to to apply their operations
and in that way we can scale the server to many clients
and in fact that is what lab 4 does.
How does the client know how to communicate with the new leader after the old leader fails?
The client basically has a list of all the servers that are in the system,
so in this case,
we're running with three servers,
everybody agrees there only three servers in the world,
clients know about the three servers
and did they try one randomly,
if that is not the client, it will redirect, that's not the leader,
it will redirect the client to the appropriate one, the actual leader.
Yeah the answer is quite clear.
But do we assume the servers are like in geographically close,
like close to each other or they are.
They could in principle be far apart,
there's no real restriction on that side,
the only issue of course if it serves a fair spread around the world,
the delays to actually get in a log record append,
you know will take a little while,
and so the delays will be long.
What is the log entry being executed in the kv storage?
When, once it's committed in by raft,
so once raft has decided that they're all there enough replicates have received it
and it's now no way possible that one has to back out of that operation,
then, it's headed to the key-value server.
So the leader will first like execute this command
and the leader will tell the followers that this command is committed
and then the follower called.
The leader knows, well as soon as the operations committed
actually get handed off the key-value server.
Let me, let's talk about it right now,
I'll go in more detail as we go,
so like more of an overview of the protocol.
So previous board was sort of an overview of how you use raft to build a replicated state machine,
now let's look at the raft itself a little bit more detail.
So we here some timelines, got a leader, we got two followers.
So we're running three, the client to talk to the leader,
the leader has a log,
you know all the put and get operations,
you know when it gets a new one,
you know appends it you know to the end of the log,
then it actually sends it,
you know sends the log entries to the new log entries to the followers.
And you know let's say you know that follower 2,
here follower 1, here follower 2,
follower 1 actually received this log entry,
everything is okay,
appends at the end of the log,
it sends basically an act back, saying yes you know I appended it.
And at this point in the raft the world two servers actually have the log entry
and so raft actually the leader can actually commit the log entry
and so at this point you know the the the leader can actually hand off that request just received,
that can actually hand it off to the kv server.
And the way actually the lab does this or this lab infrastructure does this is
that basically we have a channel Go channel,
one single Go channel were basically Raft Goroutines
and the Raft Goroutine actually decide that a particular operation is committed,
it just sends that operation on the apply channel,
so that the key-value server can actually apply it.
You know some point later, so notice at this point,
the leader basically has committed the operation,
and it's perfectly safe for the leader to commit this operation,
because the majority of the servers, actually majority of the peers actually have received the operation, correct,
so there even if there was a failure
and we elect a new leader,
that's the case that that leader are one of the servers,
that is remaining actually has the last operation,
that was appended to the log by the previous leader.
So everything is good,
of course the last guy, the first follower also at some point respond and you know said yes.
So this point, basically from the point of view of the leader,
the operations committed, except the followers don't really know it yet,
because the followers you know, they only know that they got it
and that the leader probably has it,
but they you know they don't really know,
and so what actually happens is that,
the subsequent operation, when another client request comes in,
the leader will append another log entry
and basically sends you know a new operation or new append entry to the followers
and that append entry, does basically two things,
it you know provides the new log entry for the new operation,
but it also confirms that all the preceding operations order
tells us which operations actually have committed so far.
And so when F1 and F2 receive you know this this operation, this RPC,
they know that the operation has been committed by the leader
and therefore at that point, they can also deliver it to their key-value instance,
and know that this operation is committed.
I I had a quick question,
so, so when the leader sends an operation over and server replies,
does that mean, that means it's in the log, right,
but what happens if you get a majority like a slight majority
and then one of those logs like one of those servers crash,
like our logs, the logs have to be in storage, like in disk.
Yep, so that's a very good question, correct,
the every change to the log,
so you look at the Raft paper in detail,
the some state is must be stable,
and the log is one of those pieces of information, that must be stable,
as well as the term number and a bunch of other things.
And so if a server crashes,
no big, no big deal really,
because you know the majority of the servers does have that entry on their disk,
and when they come back up, they'll find it.
I have a question?
Yeah.
So what happens if for example follower one replies with yes and later commits,
just before it sends the next command to the remaining followers to also commit, it crashes,
now there are many followers don't know that they need to commit,
because the leader has crashed,
so wouldn't this cause problems?
They will commit,
because one follower will have it in its log
and as we'll see in the leader election rules,
it will become the leader,
and it will propagate that append entry you know to the other servers
and then they will apply too.
Okay, I see, okay, thanks.
OK, so that brings me maybe this is a good segue to the next topic,
why logs, last three questions are all about that.
Yeah.
I actually as a follow-up to the last question,
so the server crashing after it has like consensus crashing,
right, like right before committing,
it could delay committing, right?
What do you mean with committed?
So so, like after it has consensus on a change right after it has a majority,
and it can like the paper said, you [] you essentially tell other ones, like other servers,
you tell them okay, this is ready for,
or sorry it's committed it's ready for like, like execution right into the state machine.
So if it crashes before it tells all the servers that it's ready for execution,
it could delay execution, right.
It could delay execution,
okay, first of all, if the leader fails at that point, nothing happens, right,
at least the clients can't proceed with any other more operations
and so basically the if you want to think about, at that point raft reconfigure itself,
elects a new leader,
and that's going to be you know F1 or F2,
one of the two is going to be the new leader
and the other one is going to be the follower, right
and one of the two actually has received you know the append entry,
that the leader might already have committed,
in fact it's kv might already have executed,
no problem correct, because one of them has it,
that one will become the leader as we'll see later with the leader election rules,
and that one will submit to its kv server
and will replicate it to the other follower
and then it will apply to each kv server,
in the end all will apply all the operations in the same order.
I I I agree, like eventually it'll happen,
but it could be delayed right?
Yeah could be delayed absolutely,
[] a complete lot to all the followers,
it will you stay, the way it works is actually,
it will try to send the end of his log,
if one of the followers doesn't recognize the end of the log, go back off
and you know send more and more you know earlier entries,
we'll talk about it later.
But, in the end it could be the case
that the leader will replay its complete log to one of the followers,
if one of the followers has missed all the log entries.
I gotta get me back to logs.
So one reason you might wonder why you have logs at all
is because like kv server, it has a database too,
you know have some table with all the information
and so why do we need actually you know sort of this information twice,
once in the logs and ones in the kv table.
And so a couple reasons for that,
one, a couple that already came up in the questions basically,
one for retransmission,
so when the leader sends one of these append entries you know to one of the followers that message might get lost
and so the leader must be able to retransmit,
so we need to keep a record of all the log entries,
that, that are sort of being in flight.
Second reason that's probably the prime reason,
first is like we need order,
and every append operation or every commands must be delivered in the same order at the same and all the replicas
and the log is a very convenient way for us to actually maintain that order,
so the second reason retransmission.
The third reason is we need persistence,
you know one of the followers might crash
or actually all of them might crash
and then they come up again
and we still need to be in a position that we can basically retransmit log entries to bring everybody up to date
and so log must also be persistent.
And finally we need sort of space for tentative operations or tentatively commits tentative commands,
so as we noted earlier,
if it came up in the earlier questions,
when the leader sent an operation to a follower,
the follower doesn't really know at that point where that operation will be committed,
so just stick around for a little while
until it actually learns that operation is committed
and so we need some space for [] operations
the log is convenient place to actually do that.
In the end, you know what will happen correct is that the logs are identical on all servers,
you know there may be out of sync during periods of time,
you know, one might have more entries than other logs,
but like if you keep running the system,
and then stop the clients,
then at some point in time,
all the logs will be completely identical,
and that means that basically those since they all have the same order,
all the operations all the operations will be fit to decline the kv servers in the same order
and then kv server well end up in the same state.
Okay?
Okay, let me talk a little bit about an individual log entry.
So really, yeah whatever, we're gonna draw many pictures like this,
where there's a bunch of log log entries,
you're starting 0 1 2 blah blah,
and if we look inside of one of these log entries,
there's gonna be a command,
which we're mostly going to sort of ignore,
we're gonna really think about much about it at all,
and that's the thing that's actually being delivered to the application,
so that's an example to put or get operation with its arguments.
And then the second thing that's in there is term,
and this is basically the leader's term,
so the term in which this particular command actually was appended to the log,
one way you can think about this is that
basically the term identifies uniquely the leader that appended the operation to the log,
during every term, there's only one single leader,
and so the term id really basically implicitly signals who leader was actually appended to to that log entry.
The number that goes along here,
so if this is n or maybe like me use i here,
you know that's the log index,
so the combination of the log index was a term number,
basically uniquely identifies the content of that particular entry,
there could be no two log entries that have the same index, the same term and have different commands,
because only a single leader you know could have been in charge, in that particular term
and leader commits appends operations,
will uncommit log entries will be overwritten,
yeah they might get overwritten,
we'll talk about it later,
but that's certainly possible.
Okay, so if we look at this picture,
so there are two things that in this part of it,
I guess my answer to this question
and there are two things that need to happen,
we need to elect leader for a particular term,
and we need to actually ensure that the,
ensure logs become identical,
and we have failures and we have leader changes,
and so we're going to talk about both of these topics,
and we're gonna start with leader election
and then talk about the making logs identical a little bit later.
Okay, election,
election is really the topic of lab 2a,
and you know really the story is some way straightforward,
you know we have you know,
say here we are, system with three entries,
we have a leader in you know term 10,
we have the following term 10,
so we're sort of stable situation,
another following term 10
and let's say the leader crashes or gets partitions you know from network,
so you know can't talk anymore,
what will happen is that,
the followers will start an election.
And the reason they start an election is because,
they're missing heartbeats from the leader,
you know the job of the leader is to periodically,
it's sort of fixed interval send append entry to the followers,
you know normally you know that might be happen,
because a lot of clients are active
and so the followers continuously get append entries,
but if the leader doesn't receive any commands from the clients,
then it's actually supposed to send in heartbeat periodically
and telling the basically to inform the followers that actually still the leader,
and the heartbeat basically takes form of normal append entry except no new log entries,
and so the leader tells leader to tells in the heartbeat,
like my log is you know this long,
this is my last entry,
if you know those match and then everything is good.
So if the leader fails,
then after a couple of heartbeats
and we'll talk a little bit more in detail about this,
there will be an election time out.
So the followers have a timer running,
and they reset the timer every time they get a heartbeat or append entry,
but if they don't receive any heartbeats or append entries,
then at some point of time, after this election timeout, the timer goes off,
and at that point follower starts an election
and just let's assume that the first follower reaches that point first
and what it will do, it will send, it will increase its term number,
so we'll set the term number to 11,
it will, you know talk to itself, if you will
and be part of the and will vote for itself
and then you know we'll contact you know the other follower also tried to contact the leader,
presumably the leader, let's say the leader is down,
so the leader doesn't respond, but the second follower does respond,
and so at that point, it gets two votes,
one for himself and one from the follower
and at that point, actually it becomes the new leader,
it becomes the leader for term 11,
and then you know start doing basic clients fall over to that leader
and you know the things you just proceed as before.
Okay?
Now maybe it's slightly there's a couple problems and you might worry about,
one of them could be the following situation,
we it turns out there was a network partition between leader 10,
where the leader for term 10 and the followers for term 10.
And so at some point that network you know partition heals
and so maybe the applied request came in still to leader, for leader for term 10,
and now of course, now it looks like oops, we might have actually two leaders
and we're back into the split syndrome problem,
that turns out not to be the case,
because when the leader tries to actually you know send append entries to the followers,
to followers that are now in term 11,
they will just reject those append entries
and they will tell the old leader,
that you know too bad you know he's not the leader anymore,
in fact they'll send a message back saying, no I cannot do the append,
and here is my current term number 11,
the leader receives that sees the term number 11 is bigger than this term number 10
and basically steps down as leader and becomes a follower.
And they take up another election,
or to basically become part of term that has all three of them,
but basically there's no chance of split brain problem,
because you just can't actually get any operations through,
so no split brain.
And the reason that we avoid split brain is,
because of this majority rule as well as these term numbers.
Okay, that's of course not the only problem,
that we might have another challenge is,
we might end up with split vote.
So like it was a particular picture,
we had a leader,
maybe here was leader in 10,
is partition of the network,
here are two followers in 10,
and if we're not careful,
you know, maybe they will actually start you know elections very close to each other,
and so you F10 you know vote for itself,
first leader follower votes itself,
the second leader, second follower of votes itself,
then you know they sent you know vote request with each other
and the rule is that you know you can vote, one vote per term.
So when you know the first followers voted for itself
and it has voted for itself,
when it receives a second vote request,it actually cannot vote for that request,because it already voted for itself,
and so at this point, we're gonna have split votes,
like this guy is going to have one vote
and this guy is going to have one vote,
it won't do anything,
in but at some point again later,
there will be timeout,
and then this process starts again,
and of course you know part of that process,
you know this is election 11, 11 result in 12,
if you want to go to election number 12,
and you start trying to trying to do this again,
now if you not care for correct,
this could just happen over over and over endlessly.
Basically every time you know the two followers roughly at the same time start this election
and we're not going to make forward progress.
And so we need to avoid this problem is that the election timers are randomized.
And so when the followers you know set the election timer in the paper,
they talk about picking a value between 150 milliseconds and 300 milliseconds,
random number in that interval,
and every time you know these followers basically reset their election timeout,
they pick a new number, random number in that involved
and only when that timer goes off, they run the election,
and, if basically you know,
if this interval is wide enough,
that it's unlikely that's like the first person or the first follower that actually gets the,
the first follower whose election timer runs out,
you know the interval is wide enough that you know,
there's a good chance that actual succeed complete, complete election,
before the second timer grows up,
before had another follower,
so this avoids you know the sort of endless split votes,
you know we might get unlucky
and we get maybe one or two split votes,
but over time you know that has to be the case, that in the end we will succeed.
There are a couple sort of,
this is important maybe for the lab 2,
there's a couple pressures on these election time outs,
you don't want to make an election timeout is too short, right,
because if it's too short
and for example short than heartbeat,
you know you might lose one message
and immediately you start running an election,
and nothing bad happens,
because you know we'll elect a new leader,
you will go through a new term and all that kind of stuff,
but basically you know during this an election,
this system is actually not usable, the clients are actually blocked.
So you don't want unnecessarily cause elections,
and so one of the things you want to actually basically probably spit take value at least bigger than a few time out, a few heartbeats,
perhaps in a, maybe a data center will take a few milliseconds to do an rpc
and we may want to wait at least you know so maybe three four rpc around [good] times,
so that we get a chance to a retry rpc,
without actually having election timer go off,
so we can cover from temporary network fails.
Then you know we want to presumely add some random value to that,
random value to avoid you know the split votes,
and so one hand we want to make the random values big as possible,
because we make it big,
then a very little chance that actually we run into a split vote problem.
But the other hand if we do that,
then there's a chance that you know the system may be down for a longer period of time,
we might take a big value for the election time out,
and that means down time from the point of view of the clients,
so we want to keep this short enough,
the down time is short,
in the paper in [] election does quite a bit of work on sort of validating,
in order for reasonable values for their particular setting
and then that's how they got 250 to 300 milliseconds,
in the lab, we're going to be original generous,
basically if you recover within a second,
you're more or less going to be good,
with for our test cases.
Okay, I want to make one more point about the, about the elections,
so another scenario that is important to consider is
you know we have a follower
we have the leader,
leader goes down,
so this is 10, this is 10, here's follower 10.
And we already talked a little bit about it,
when let's say this guy goes first, vote for itself,
and you know we the protocol records you know unstable storage, why who we voted for,
so the record records on the this follower one, this follower two, will record voted for in term 11,
you know for follower one, why is it recorded on stable storage,
and why does you know follower need to remember that,
that is voted in term 11 for itself.
This way doesn't vote twice, if it fails.
Yeah, it might crash, right here, and come backup,
and it should remember that and something might have been,
let's say it was actually referred one guy in here, follower whatever 3,
and already voted for follower 3,
then, it can actually not change in mind, right,
and so because in the end, we at the end of the term,
we need to have have to be in a position,
that per term there's only one leader and never never two,
and so to ensure that every follower must remember for which candidate voted and never change its mind.
Okay, I guess all discussion in the chat about a timeout numbers in relation to the lab,
so people can look there are confused about this,
otherwise we can talk about elections a bit more,
because this is the last thing I want to say about elections.
Any questions about the elections?
Have a bit more general question,
so, in like the figure two of the lab,
that says that for each server storing like the current term and then who voted for,
but not the like current state of the server like if its candidate or follower or leader.
So I'm wondering how they like,
is that implied or is there another way to figure that out,
I guess when you come back up
and you come back up as a follower,
and you're starting an election,
and then that will in the end, at the end of the election,
you know what you are,
you either a follower or the leader.
I see, okay, thank you.
That makes sense?
One warning about figure two mostly positive
and then there's maybe negative statement.
Anywhere in the figure two when it says like you know you should do this,
you should really do it,
so you cannot admit any detail that actually is in figure two,
if you do that,
then undoubtedly going to fail some of the test cases,
unfortunately figure two is not complete,
and so you still have to do something,
so particularly figure two doesn't really say not much about how the replies are handled,
the vote rpc and append rpc
and so, you will have to do something to fill in the missing details,
and so, so there's two points here like figure two,
anything that's in there you better deal with it
and but there still might be things missing that you will have to resolve for yourself,x
you'll be looking at figure two a lot.
So from the description of the election process,
there seems to be, even for lab 2a, which deals only with election,
there seems to be some state that we need to store on persistence,
look for example like who you voted for and the term number.
Yeah.
But, when you look at the code of lab 2,
all of the code that has to do with saving the persistent state,
it says above it lab 2c,
so is it that it's not that crucial,
maybe to care about persistent storage,
or should we absolutely start [].
Yeah, I think the first couple tests, we don't actually crash machines,
and so therefore it's not important
and in 2c were definitely crashing machines.
Okay, awesome, thank you.
Okay, how are you doing, everybody on board?
Okay, here we go, next step.
Okay, so one important thing to realize
and this came up earlier in the questions
and when I hit that now that topic hard
is that logs may diverge diverge.
And now they can be quite dramatic,
but just let's get into it, for basic understanding
and then discuss in more detail,
so let's do a couple simple examples,
so I'm going to write things and using the following notation,
we're going to have three servers as before,
but I'm going to cut all the timeline business
and just like draw the logs.
And you know we have indexes,
so let's say these are indexes you know there's preceding part to it,
when we're talking about 10 11 12,
and so you know there is an term entry in each one of them,
so let's say all three servers committed or appended an operation in term 3 to index 10,
and you know and same thing happens in with index for 11,
so one way to think, one way you could get this correct,
that server one would be the leader,
server one appended to its own log,
then replicates it to S2 and S3,
same thing happens for index 11,
then the next 12, maybe also successful appends,
one operation in that index for each term,
so that's term 3,
but then it crashes.
Okay, so now we're in a situation,
where one server actually has an extra log entry in its log
and the other ones don't or maybe that one of them has two,
but they are definitely not identical.
But that's a simple case correctly,
not merely particular step we're going on,
but there's much more interesting cases going on.
So, another case could be one server, again S1 here we go,
same scenarios S2 S3.
And, let's say we have the following logs,
so this is the situation we have in index 10,
we have entries and all servers for term 3,
index 11, the first server has no entry,
the other two have an entry for term 3
and then last one number 12 you know we have entries in index 4 at servers 2 and 3 with term numbers 4 and 5.
So the first question that we need to ask ourselves is this possible,
can raft end up producing logs in this way,
were they in the same log entry,
we have two different term numbers and same log index.
Yeah, that's possible.
So basically,
it looks like.
So it like scenario that produced.
Yeah, so it looks like server two or server three was leader for term 3
and then got some logs out to server one
and then shared another log with only one of the two servers,
after which point it went down,
and then S2 got elected as leader for term 2,
which is still possible,
because its log is like up to date as as up to date as others, and then.
And then again to make sure,
so S2 got elected for term 4.
Yes.
Okay, not term 2.
Okay, so S2 get elected for term 4
and using S1 as a backup, correct,
basically as the follower?
Yes, I think, and then S3 gets elected for term 5 before S2 can put anything in the logs.
Yeah, another way of saying it's like maybe S2 crashed, right away, right after I got elected to term 4
and so then there's a timeout,
then let's say S3 is partition but now is back,
in that point, it will become,
it will, it come into a term 5, right.
Yeah.
Okay, good,
so that's possible,
so turns out there are quite a bit of wild variations possible,
so we'll look at the,
so here's the figure six or figure seven sorry from the homework,
and oops, in and the homework, ask basic questions about the form,
like well what happens like this guy in the figure six itself, figure seven whatever it is,
I think figure seven,
the scenarios being discussed,
is like this guy becomes, the top one becomes new leader
and in the homework, we ask the question,
what happens if this leader just goes away,
and what are the possible outcomes
you know and the possible outcomes like for every log index
and the question is which one gets rejected,
which one will be accepted for sure,
and which ones depends.
And I think there's an important thing exercise to do,
because once we have to understand what all log entries are possible,
they're possible outcomes gonna do a whole really firm up,
like our understanding about how raft actually supposed to be operating,
what I'd like to do is like do a quick breakout room
and I'd like you to identify the two possible outcomes, that not guaranteed,
and in the corresponding scenario,
so let me let's take a quick break out room session here
and let's try to figure out the answer to the homework question in five minutes.
Lily you're able to.
You want me to.
Yeah, oh, yeah.
Yeah yup, let me actually make you participants host, now you're host.
Hey, ones.
Okay, can everybody hear me again?
Can I get a positive signal.
Yes, okay sure,
okay, so hope everybody gotta have a good time discussing this
and so let's this is really a discussion about log divergence
and we see here correcting this figure,
there are pretty wild variations,
in what can happen
and these are all possible as the caption of the figure explains,
they're all possible scenarios,
so the question in the homework and just to quickly review that I'm sure most of you already.
I don't think, we can see your screen.
Oh, how'd you do that,
that's because I forgot to click yes,
okay, let me fix that right,
appreciate that.
Okay, do you see much of it on the screen.
Yeah, okay okay, thank you sorry,
but okay, so go so going back to this caption of figure seven,
figure seven explains like these all possible situations
and what we want to figure out, you know before talking about the details about how the logs gets repaired
you know what actually is possible,
so soon actually this top guy did not get elected leader,
so the caption of the figure,
but basically what outcomes are possible
and they're going to be,
what I mean with that is like for example we look at f,
you know it has 2 an index of an entry from term 2 index 4.
And the question that we want to ask and understand is
the clear this is possible,
because this could have happened,
you know what will happen next,
you know, is it possible that this entry will survive,
so we reconfigured like the leader,
basically you know logs get being you know put together in synchronized
where you know the leaders force logs could be identical,
is there a scenario in which actually the log entry, the entry from term 2 will survive.
No.
No, correct,
this will definitely be rejected, correct
and why is that the case?
There are entries from term 6 that are already committed,
so f will never be elected.
Yeah, f will never be elected
and so somebody else will be elected
and nobody has 2 in term 2 index 4,
so it will be overwritten, with what value will be overwritten.
There will be a 4 overwritten.
There will be, this will become a 4,
so when later on when we talk about sort of log,
you know synchronization were forcing logs on the followers,
it has to be the case that these 2 turns into 4 at f.
Good, so, so, this also answers the second question,
like the entry from the index 4 from term 4 is definitely going to be accepted.
Okay, then maybe more interesting is discussion about depends,
you know, so we know at least one entry term that's definitely going to reject it,
we know one term that's definitely going to accept it,
and you know are there any sort of in terms and indexes that maybe possibly accepted.
Oh, the 7s maybe.
Yeah, 7s.
So when would this 7s not be accepted.
Okay, so the easy scenarios,
the 7s will be accepted correct,
because d gets elected leader
and then it will force it log on everybody else.
So that's the case where 7s gets appected,
when I get this 7 getting rejected.
If c gets elected leader and then d is down,
it is all overwritten.
Yeah, so d goes down, c becomes leader,
and then c's log entries are being pushed on everybody else entries
and then whenever d and so we're going to be term 7, correct,
at some point it will be longer and every d comes back up,
you know it's you know entries are going to be overwritten, right.
Is a possible.
So 7 is definitely possible, but not guaranteed.
In the other case.
I had a question, a could become leader too, right.
a? Yeah.
Yeah, a could be a leader if c and d are down.
Well d don't even have to be down for a to be elected leader right,
it just goes to [].
The first one.
Is a longer longer if two terms equal at the end,
then you pick the longest log.
But, I think if a is the first one to call for an election, right,
like potentially be.
Yeah, if c and d are down and a could win the election.
But if they're alive, can it also still win the election?
Ah, so let's say c,
okay let's d is down,
let's do that for sure, correct,
because we know that d will win the election period, d done.
Does it have to, like we know we know we know it won't get a vote from d right for sure,
but, but what does it have to win.
Why, what do you think?
What if a received the vote from b e and f first
and then received the vote from.
Yeah, you can get a majority without actually d participating.
Even if d participated in the election,
it's possible for a to get the majority votes, right.
Yes, I think we just answered that.
Isn't isn't there a mechanism though where, if the candidate sees a message from another server of the higher term number like stands down.
From a higher term number, but a has, if d is down.
It doesn't have to be down, right,
we just have to get them first, just.
Yeah.
Exactly.
But it will step down when it gets to vote from 7 for d.
Wait, are you sure about that,
because I don't think so.
Well, what okay, if d at some point,
well, it depends, they're gonna start racing, correct,
the, okay, let me ask this very important topic
and so I don't want to do it in ten seconds
and let me come back to this,
at the start of the next lecture,
okay, this is a great point to stop.
I think the state machine in figure four clarifies or like a candidate goes back to follower,
if discovers a higher terms,
so if d wasn't down it will go back to follower at once trying to elect its own.
Wait, but I thought that it would only go back to a follower state,
if it received an append entries from a current leader,
like a request vote, is not the same.
So it is worth worth and there's a difference between the term number the servers at
and the term of the most recent entry in the log.
Oh yeah.
Like server a, it has most recent entries the log be 6, the term 6,
but have its current term number be 7.
And current term can actually be arbitrarily high.
Yes.
Correct, that's correct
and so a could start term 8,
and then get elected in term 8
and that and whatever these tells it doesn't matter,
because if these most recent terms 7,
it won't go back to follow,
because it's a higher term than 7.
I see, so it could be a higher term arbitrary.
Wait, could could a going to into terms 7,
its own term 7 if d was like partition,
like if there was a network partition
and it didn't know about d.
I think confused is,
like even if it does know about d,
why does that matter, it shouldn't matter.
If a promotes itself to candidate
and then sends out a request, a vote request,
then, like d could come back and say like,
oh well my latest log entry was at this index for term 7,
but I don't think that a,
wait, actually, it doesn't even see that, right,
in in their response to a request for rpc,
basically says like its current term which would be 7, which matches a's,
because that way that's our hypothesis and then.
Yeah a started the election in turn 7,
with a and d would not vote for a.
Yes, that's true,
but I don't know I think it's totally fine,
if d is alive and gives it a response to a's vote request,
I don't think that deters a from being a candidate.
Someone just put in the chat, I think the answer to that,
so I grant said that,
as soon as d rejects the vote,
a will revert to being a follower,
because it will realize that it has a lower term number.
But, okay.
Not necessarily, because again the remember that the most recent term on their log is not the same thing as the most recent term that the server keep track of,
you can have a higher current term than the most recent thing on the log
and so if a tries to elect itself in term 7,
yes when it tries to contact d,
it will give up,
but if a tries elect itself in term 8,
which it would if it's already seen that the has reached term 7,
then, like a can get elected.
Wait, but. if d if we assume that d is in term 7,
like if a tries to elect itself for term seven,
then the we don't actually have this case,
because if the rpc request response contains a term
which is strictly greater than the current term, you give up,
but if they're the same,
then it doesn't matter,
it will just proceed as normal.
That's great.
Yes.
The d's entris get replaced by whatever a telling it.
So, at the end of section,
like the election restriction section 5.4.1,
if the raft determines which of the two logs is more up to date by comparing the index in terms of the last entries in the log,
so wouldn't that mean that d has to become the leader,
if we're comparing.
No, because d just vote no,
but other people might vote yes.
Yeah.
So.
What, what about the case where e runs for election in term 5 [] 5,
yeah and then it gets a vote from d saying no,
it would then update its term right and stop running.
Hold on, like so you're thinking about e starting the election for 5.
Yeah, and if it gets a response from almost anybody,
it's going to see that it's behind a term, right,
so, it does update its term in that case, right,
to append.
So another way to ask this question, who can become leader,
correct,
this you know from this, you know whatever from these 6 a b c to f who can become leader.
Can what f become leader?
No.
Can e become leader?
Also no, the only ones that can become leader are a c and d.
That's correct, possible leaders.
But can, can a become a leader, if d is alive,
because the because the safety section says that the rpc, the request for rpc implements the restriction,
that it compares the last log entries
and the one with the highest log entry should become the leader.
I I only think it doesn't vote for someone.
Exactly.
So like they will never vote for a, right for anything else.
That's exactly right.
I mean it's also not true, that like if you have an entry in a higher term than another node,
like you're actually sort of like better right,
because I mean you can be like becoming leader
and trying to append entries into the log what they like don't go through, so.
Well,d is like when you go through,
okay, d is like, correct, d voted again, a becomes leader,
d actually tries to,
well, a won't contact d, if actually didn't vote for it.
And so they would just proceed.
So why could they have logs in terms 7,
if it's not a leader in terms 7?
d must have been the leader in term 7, right.
Yeah, I agree.
Otherwise, you would have no log entries.
When you have log [] I think I forgot.
So in this case, was d was d a leader in term 7,
who got disconnected
and then the new leader got elected the one at the top.
Yeah I think so.
Actually, let me take that back,
I don't really remember exactly sequence,
I didn't really pay attention much to the top guy,
but I presume that is the case,
it does say that it's neither for term 8 and [] a log.
I think the case we're looking at
the one where a has a higher term number than d is,
the contradiction case in the safety argument, they mentioned,
like I think they proved that this is not possible.
What one is not possible?
Like that, a could be elected, b missing an entry and have a higher term than d,
which is the case here,
I think there's like step proof that this is a contradiction.
I I don't think so,
I think it's totally fine for [it] to be elected leader.
Yeah, I think the, I think the safety proof says that a future leader cannot have, needs to have all of the log commited.
Commited, yeah.
And 7 is not committed.
Exactly.
I could use a whole bunch of operations here,
they're not committed right,
they're just tentative
and so anything can happen to them,
then nothing wrong will happen in the end.
And the reason that the whole committed thing works is,
because if it's committed then more than the majority have,
those entries and so someone who doesn't have the committed entries could never become elected, right.
Yes.
That's exactly right.
Yeah, they they discussed like,
yeah, like in terms of only someone who has older committed entries can get elected,
I think it gets more complicated with you know within the people who have all committed entries which ones can get elected,
that's.
Yeah, some ways it doesn't matter.
Yeah.
So all.
All the commits after term 4 are not committed then here, right.
So these two 4s, those are not.
The first, the first two 4s.
Those are, where your question,
they will be committed.
Yeah, those would be committed,
but done everything after wouldn't be?
5 will be committed.
Two 6.
And two 6 also be commited.
Okay, you only need exactly,
it's okay,
exactly how it's okay, okay.
No, another one.
Over 4.
Yeah, so the 5 and 6 wouldn't be committed,
oh, but you have another leader right.
Yeah yeah.
Okay, well let's not forget about those right, I got it.
Okay, okay, I'll come back to this, at the beginning of next lecture,
because some some of you probably have to run to another class,
but, I'll come back to this,
if you have more questions feel free to stick around,
you know we'll resume this.
Oh, can you see the log duplication, again,
why, when could there be log duplication.
What, what I mean is that the leader at some point forces its log on the followers.
I think I think you meant it on some of the previous slides.
Okay, so maybe, yeah maybe I I can't remember I said.
It is a little more, maybe a little more.
Oh, is there is there deleted duplicates.
Detect duplicates.
Yeah, it's difficult.
Yeah, this is, this is not a raft issue correct,
this is really a kv, a key-value service issue.
Where a client request,
you might be reaching a client may,
client might not get a response,
even though you know that request actually went through raft,
because what happened is that the leader may be applied to operation to its state,
before responding to the client, it crashed,
so the client will retry,
and we will send this request to the new leader,
the new lender will run it through raft
and it will pop out of raft again.
And so it has to be the case,
that the kv server does duplicate detection.
Oh, this is like only if the client didn't get the response.
Yeah, exactly.
Okay, okay I see, thank you.
You will do this in lab 3.
I think I also ask questions during the lecture,
but I don't think I fully understood the answers,
so I just repeat the question,
the question is that,
you said that a way commits work is that,
once the leader commits, it waits for a new client message
and then it just appends that message to the log entry
and send append entry to the remaining followers
with an additional message saying that they should also commit all the previous entries, correct.
Yeah, there's indirectly the protocol the staff correct.
Right, so my question is that,
what if a the leader commits all the entries,
and right before it is able to send this message to the remaining followers,
the leader crashes.
It cannot commit until have a majority response from majority of the followers.
I see, so it at first like even.
It sticks to a log,
but it doesn't actually deliver to the kv servers yet.
I see, so it waits from a reply of commit, from all the remaining followers
and then it commits its own.
Okay okay.
So there's the basic, there's a variable last applied commited index, right,
that is actually maintaining,
it only increases the commited index
and once it receives a response from the majority of the followers.
And all of the followers say that they have committed their own,
like they have committed the log entries on their own servers.
They will commit their log entries once they know that the leader actually has committed it.
Right, so that's my question, like how would they know if the leaders unable to send that message to the remaining.
Well, yeah, so then we basically we end in situations that we just saw in this figure 7,
there's going to be tentative log entries in their logs
and depending who becomes new leader
and what the log situation is,
in that operation may get committed or may not get committed.
I see.
Okay, yeah.
I get it.
Hi, I had a follow-up question on this,
so if says a leader pushes a log entry,
it's accepted by majority,
but it crashes,
then later on, this log entry can be committed, right, by some other leader.
It can also may not.
Yeah, but say if it's get committed,
then, how does the new leader know who was the client,
who requested for this log entry or the client be qualified.
The, the, what okay,
so there's really a question about actually how the kv serves actually store information with raft,
so the scenario is,
client talk to the leader,
the the client, leader actually committed,
did executive this operation or not,
they did not know,
they did not know with,
so then one of the followers later will get this operation,
maybe apply it,
won't send a response because it doesn't know about the client,
but the client will retry right,
because it actually haven't gotten response,
it will contact the new leader
and basically enter the same operation in the, in the raft again
and will pop out again
and then the server will send, as we'll see in the lab 3,
will send the last response, right,
in fact, servers remember the last value that they send back.
Okay.
If get request, you know the first get request is executed,
there's no response to be sent back
and get request actually will store the response in the in the kv server, will remember the response.
So when it sees you do duplicate, then will send a response,
so there will be duplicate detection table,
that includes the response.
Okay, yeah, makes sense, thanks.
You're welcome.
I I was a little curious,
I think I asked roughly this is my question like pre lecture questions well,
like how raft compares to other like consensus algorithm in terms of like optimization you could do
and as an example I was thinking the only thing I could think of was batching.
Yeah.
It seemed like raft is like perfect for batching,
because the leader could just like put more than one entry on its log,
wait a little before sending its next entries,
then send up entries with whatever batch set of operations
or whatever it wants the replicas to do,
just trying to figure out what what the deficiencies are raft,
like from performance point of view.
Well, raft does not do that [shape], right
and you know maybe it could,
but it would make protocol more complicated
and so they decide nothing.
I guess, okay, I guess the way I happen to have written my raft lab code,
like I sort of did batching implicitly,
because I'll just wait a little bit sometimes before sending append entry,
so I guess I felt like you don't really need to do anything other than just like maybe wait if you feel like it before.
Yeah you can have.
So yeah like.
Yeah, yeah, I I think it all comes down to performance,
so you know there's a whole bunch of optimization that raft doesn't do,
you know that some other systems do,
you know for example you might be able to communicate your operations,
because doesn't matter in what order you do them,
so there's a slew of optimizations
and in raft basically do none of it.
Okay, thanks.
It might be perfectly fine for like use case, right.
Right.
You mentioned something a couple minutes ago,
that log entry could be lost,
so is it possible that a client request could never be executed,
but raft guarantees that, all the servers will execute the same set of block entries in the same sequence.
And so that means raft does not cannot be usable for all applications,
we can only afford the some lost requests.
Well, you know we have to assume that you know the responses from the from the raft servers as a whole correct kv servers plus raft,
may get lost anyway,
because the network gets lost,
network network may lost responses,
so the client has to be able to repeat,
they call it must be recent, must retry.
I see, so like when it actually commits log entry
and excuses it replies to the client,
that it did actually do.
Yeah, so this is like we're a little bit earlier we talked about the duplicate detection table,
the duplicate detection table has the response that was sent
or was constructed in response to executing that operation.
Okay.
Any further questions?
Okay, thank you so much.
Alright, welcome, it's great to ask so many questions.