Good afternoon, good evening, good night, good morning, wherever you are
or whenever you're watching this.
So today I wanna talk about Spanner,
is a paper from 2012,
but the Spanner system is in active use
and also still continuously under development,
so it's a real system.
The main topic and why you Spanner is really interesting,
is supports wide-area transactions,
and this is a really powerful programming model,
so even though the data, maybe the data shared across multiple servers
and the servers being in different data centers
and different pieces on on the planet,
you can just run transactions
and they have ACID semantics
and their atomic you know respect failure,
that all the writes happen or none of them
and they provide serializability.
And so that's an incredibly powerful programming abstraction
and of course the challenge is to implement it efficiently,
and one big challenge is like a law of physics you know the speed of light,
you know sending a packet from one end
in one part of the US to the other part of the US
or to another continent
and it takes a lot of time,
you know we're talking about tens of milliseconds.
So, what we see in this paper is that
read-write transactions are actually, are indeed quite expensive,
but they work very hard to make read-only transactions very inexpensive.
And so the read-write transactions are are implemented using two-phase commit,
as we talked about last week
and two-phase locking
and one of the things that is interesting about it is that,
the participants in this protocol are just basically Paxos groups.
The read-only transactions can execute at any data center,
and they're going to run very fast,
in fact you look at the table six in the back of the paper,
you'll see that read-only transaction somewhere like ten times faster read-write transactions.
And there are two key ideas there,
and we'll talk about this lecture,
one is snapshot isolation,
which actually is a standard database idea,
but I use it here to make the read fast,
in particular you know to make it actually work well in a distributed wide-area setting,
they rely on synchronized clocks or [],
you know those clocks are perfectly synchronized
and so, their transaction scheme must deal with a little bit of [] or drift or error margin
in exactly know what the true time is.
As I said is widely used, both in internal Google,
but also as a Google customer, you can use it,
spanner is basically a cloud service that you can use as a Google customer,
if you use gmail, probably your email or parts of the email system actually go through Spanner.
Maybe before diving into a more detail,
I want to make one logistic comment,
not related to Spanner,
as you may already have seen,
we made some adjustments for the long weekend, long upcoming weekend, first of all, lab 4a is not as heavy duty as the other labs
and hopefully take them less time,
we also cancelled next week's lecture,
so that you can actually use that as time to work on 4a
and we made the deadline for 4a more flexible,
so your next Friday is now convenient for you,
you can actually choose to have another extra late hours to submit it later.
And hopefully that will allow you to enjoy the long weekend
and perhaps get some sleep and maybe do something else than debugging your labs.
The second point I want to make is directly related to Spanner,
you know some of you noticed this and came through the questions,
this paper is quite complicated
and there are many reasons why it's complicated,
but one reason is that
actually there's a lot of things going on,
that's a powerful system,
has a lot of different components to it,
and you know the interaction between different components is important,
and so there's a lot of material in this paper,
and so although I'll try to do in this lecture
is try to to make that more clear
by focusing on a couple aspects of the paper
and I'm not going to do a full treatment of the paper,
but you know, of course I think what are the most important ideas
and why we're reading it in 6.824.
That took me actually a little bit of time
or few years to figure out actually how to present this paper
or explain it in a way that I think it's a maybe easier to understand
you know if you are for the concept of 6.824.
Okay, but ask questions as always.
Okay, so let's dive in and talk a little bit of the high-level organization.
And more from the point of view
from the way I want to talk about this Spanner in this lecture.
So there's multiple data centers
and you know for convenience for simplicity,
you know, just think about there 3 data centers, A B and C,
I mean it can be anywhere in the world,
and the goal is that basically you know data will be like,
we have a data like like a shard,
you know that you know contains some database rows or some key value pairs,
so after shard,
maybe it has the keys a to you know m,
and the basic idea is actually going to replicate that shard across data centers,
and with the goal that like even if complete data center goes down,
then you know we can proceed
you know the way we're going to arrange,
that we're going to be able to proceed is that
basically these shards you're going to form these replicas,
that are sitting in different data center will form one paxos group,
so if you're thinking about this,
we're trying to think about this in terms of lab 3,
then you can think about that,
you know we have a key value store
where the key value servers are spread around different data centers
and the keys are updated,
the [] raft writes,
you know through the raft log
and then we go to the individual key kvs,
you know update their state,
and so you can think about you know lab 3 being here
instead of running you know 3 kv servers on your machine,
you're going to run one kv server in different data centers.
Okay?
So we, then look there's gonna be a paxos group per shard,
so there, it might be other shards
that hold other parts of the, the key-value space or database rows,
so let's say you know we have only two shards,
you know for this particular database, you know shards containing a to m,
and then the shard containing n to z,
then they have form their own access group,
and the reason we want to get multiple shards is to get parallelism.
So that we can you know transactions involve different shards,
you know disjoint set of shards,
you know they can be used disjoint can actually proceed completely in parallel.
So, as mentioned earlier,
we have paxos group shard you know for replication,
but you know paxos actually provides us you know an additional sort of benefit,
you know the communication costs right for a to b or from b to c might be very expensive,
and seems you know paxos allows to proceed,
where raft allows us to proceed with just majority,
you know the slow machine might actually have not that much performance impact
and so we can sort of easily tolerate either slow machines
or actually one you know data center being down.
So, the majority rule helps us in two ways,
you know we get data center fault tolerance,
and through slowness.
The final goal as we'll see in a little bit more detail is that,
a client of Spanner,
so let's say here's some server that uses Spanner,
would like it to be the case
that you know this server can actually use a close replica,
and so the replica you know typically are placed closed, close to the clients that actually use them.
In fact, we'll see that read-only transactions can be executed basically by the local replica
without any communication to the other data centers.
And when I talk about client,
here, this is typically sort of the backend servers of some Google servers,
for example, this might be the Gmail server,
that's sitting also in some data center
and maybe the same data center
and talks to the replica in that particular data centers
and of course outside our real clients like users you know you read or write email.
Okay, any sort of questions about this high-level organization?
Okay, let me sort of layout the challenges,
that I wanna focus on in this lecture,
I mean, we're going to sort of three main challenges.
One is, the way is it like I said,
we want to actually read-only transactions without actually having to communicate with any other server,
but you know we got to make sure that the reads sees the latest write,
this sort of classic challenge that we've seen before,
you know zookeeper, zookeeper sort of avoid, doesn't really address the challenge direct head on
and just like weaken consistency,
but here in this design,
we'd like to arrange in a way that actually we still keep linearizability,
in fact you know Spanner shoot for [] stronger property than linearizability.
Second thing is when you want to support,
Spanner wants to support transactions across shards,
so even this is actually like we do a bank transfer
and one account in one shard,
the other account, the destination account, there's another shard,
we want to arrange you know it still can be executed like a introduction and have ACID semantics.
Finally, you know the transactions both read-only ones
and read-write ones must be serializable,
in fact a little bit stronger than serializable.
And you know we'll see that,
you know for this, you know for basically for the read-write transactions,
we're going to use two-phase locking, two-phase commit
and basically two [] that we talked about in the last lecture.
And so what I'd like to do first is
talk about read-write transactions
and then talk in more detail how read-only transactions are executed,
so that they can run very efficiently.
Okay, so read-write transactions you know basically two-phase locking and two-phase commit.
So hopefully this is pretty easy to understand,
and there going to involve these sort of complex timing diagrams, that we looked at last week
and so the way it's set up
and I'm going to simplify a bit,
looking at the way it's set up in Spanner,
is we have the client
and the client is sort of in charge of really running the transaction
and user transaction manager transaction library,
actually runs on the client machine
and in charge of basically you know orchestrate this transaction
and again the client here is not you know the user web browser or gmail,
but basically the servers server on, the gmail server in the data center,
that's the client of Spanner.
And so let's make the picture reasonable simple,
so we have two shards instead of three four five,
so we have shard a and we have shard b.
And let's assume we're going to just execute the transfer transaction, the same one as before,
we're going to deduct some money from one account, then add it to another account.
And initially, I'm going to talk about this [without] the timestamps,
in some ways you know the one reason to do so is that,
actually for the read-write transaction timestamps are not very important,
the timestamps actually are mostly there for read-only transactions
and they need a little tweaking to the read-write transactions to support,
that we don't need transactions
and therefore the timestamps are sort of in drifting to read-write transactions too,
but in essence you know the read-write transactions are basically straight two-phase locking and two-phase commit.
So the client is going to reads these accounts,
for example let's assume that you know read x,
so we just gonna do the transfer transaction from moving money, form adding 1 to x,
you know subtracting subtracting 1 dollar from x
and adding a dollar to y,
it's going to be x,
and let's assume that x sits in one shard,
so it's going to be a cross shard transaction
and and you have to read of y,
and, there's gonna be,
when the client executes these read operations,
they go to the shards and shards actually keep lock table,
and so they record basically this transaction,
you know so let's say this is transaction whatever TID,
and they're gonna record that you know the x is owned you know,
lock table actually owned by the clients,
you know and here is y owned by the client
and that sort of a very standards you know we've seen before.
You know the thing that is slightly different here
and not fully drawing it out here is that,
when we're talking to one shard a,
shard a is really one of these paxos groups,
and so it has you know three in this case, you know a group of three peers
and so SA really replicated servers consisting of multiple peers,
in when executing read-only transaction,
we're gonna be talking to the leader of that peers,
so if you think in terms raft style,
you can just think about it,
the read request goes to the leader of the paxos group.
And, another, so every time I sort of draw this one single arrow here for SA or for SB,
you know it's a much more complicated story,
particularly when writes get involved,
because writes actually going to go through the paxos of raft group.
The read-only or lock tables actually not replicated,
it is stored at the leader of the paxos group,
and if the leader goes down during the transaction,
then you know basically the transaction has to be restarted,
where the transaction will be aborted,
because the lock information is lost.
The reason that these lock table is not, -} is not the replica,
this is may read operation fast.
Okay, so once you know the client actually has gotten the values of x and y
and it's taken out the locks you know sort of two-phase locking style,
the it's gonna subtract one from x, you know add one you know y,
and then basically going to submit a transaction.
So basically all the writes are done locally at the client,
again so this is the gmail server
and one [] thing is, when the client is done with transaction,
it submits transaction to to Spanner,
and, it submits to a transaction coordinator,
so some you know set of servers you know or some machines you pick as the transaction coordinator
and again the transaction coordinator is paxos group,
as I said it's multiple appears in a different data centers.
And one reason we want this to be a paxos group is,
so that as we've seen before,
in two-phase protocol or the two-phase commit,
that if the coordinator fails,
it might actually block the participants, right,
if participants have prepared and agreed to go along with the transaction,
but then the coordinate fails you knwo this petition to have to hold on to their locks
and have to wait until the coordinator comes back
by replicating the coordinator using paxos
and we make the coordinate highly available
and so basically avoid that particular sort of disaster scenario.
Okay?
So the transaction coordinators then basically in charge of running the two-phase commit protocol
and so it will send you know the updates for x and y to the leader of shard a,
x y to the leaders of a shard b,
the they you know grab the logs
you know in this case, you know, you know the already hold the locks,
or promote locks write, read-write locks
and basically prepare you know transaction,
so they don't really execute it yet,
but just make the you know typically using write ahead logging,
you know prepared to changes
and if everything is okay,
then they basically commit to the transaction by entering sort of this prepared state,
and this is sort of a big moment,
because at this point,
the transaction is what appears, when participants are committed to this transaction
and we know from last lecture,
you know the participants do actually have to record state,
so that if they fail and they come back up,
they can recover and pick up from where they left off,
so, at the prepared state,
basically this results into a paxos write,
you know recording the state of the transaction,
and 2PC state the logs that participate holding etc etc
and so this paxos write,
so the leader of this particular shard,
there's a push paxos write across you know the different peers in the group
to ensure that state is replicated fault tolerant.
So once you know the, the participants have prepared and agreed to prepared,
then you know they sent back okay,
you know, okay,
this is very similar two-phase protocol that we talked before
and at this point you know the coordinator can commit,
and of course the point to commit, the coordinated, these records actually made the commit decision,
because when our participants may come back later,
and want to know and find out about it
and we might have failures,
so again the paxos state with PC two-phase commit state is written to using paxos and replicated using paxos.
And from this whole presentation,
you can just think about paxos as being complete substitute or equivalent to raft,
you know spanner predates raft,
but like you know for perceptually and you know through first order,
you know for this paper is basically the same.
So this point is actually commits,
this you know is really commit point,
which ones transaction coordinator,
has written down the transaction is committed,
that is actual commit point
and then informs you know their participants,
you know that has happened.
And you know they're going to respond back, if okay,
great transaction is committed
and the transaction coordinator can clean up its state
and at some point later the shards can also clean up their state,
and that at the point of commit and the participants release their locks.
Okay, so that is sort of the basic story for read-write transactions
and so any questions about this?
And I think the simple way to think about is,
this is two-phase commit, two-phase locking,
with the main difference between what we talked about last week
and this week is that the participant, the transaction coordinator,
the participants are all paxos groups,
or they replicated their highly available,
and some of the problems that we talked about the two-phase commit last time are less, less relevant here,
because the participants are much more highly available.
So the each shard is replicating the lock table or not?
Yeah well, it's not replicating the lock table,
it's replicating the lock that's holding when it does the prepare.
So only the lock when it's that it's holding during.
Yeah the state that it needs to do two-phase commit.
So then they like the current locks for some transaction that hasn't reach the prepared stage,
it will they just lost.
They will be lost and then the transaction will abort,
participant does not participate,
and tell the coordinator hey I lost my locks to that, can't do it.
Thank you.
Okay, so that the rest of this lecture is about the read-only transactions,
and, so these transactions are only do reads no writes,
and they are common
and so one of the goals is to actually make them very fast.
And the way you're, there, the way they achieve you know high performance
is the range that the reads,
Spanner makes high performance because reads are only for local shards,
and they have no locks,
and no lock is good,
because it means that read-write transactions can block the read-write transactions
or another way saying is read-only transactions can't block read-write transactions,
and no no two-phase commit
and so that means also no wide-area communication necessary
and so that the reads can definitely execute from a local replica.
And you know also see of course you know this is the read from a local shards,
the the real challenge here is like how to still get consistency or you know serializability,
but it's important to point out
you know, but for a moment you know assume
that we know how to do this, you know we could,
then reading from only local shard, holding no locks, not doing two-phase commit
means that all the communication is local within within that particular data center
and it can be very fast,
then if you look at the end in table 3 and 6 in the paper,
you basically see that,
basically you know read-only transactions are ten times faster than read-write transactions,
read-write transactions are in the order of hundreds of milliseconds,
which sort of makes sense,
because they have to communicate long distance
and but read-only transactions on a new order of a 5 to 10 milliseconds.
Okay, so the key challenge of course is always going to be
we've executed local replica, how to get correctness.
So let me talk a little bit about it,
because it's slightly different than what we've seen before,
so correctness means two things here,
one you know that transactions are serializable,
so they must execute in some serial order,
so if you think about it,
we have a read-write transaction,
we, and we have another read-write transaction,
then we have a read-only transaction,
you know the read-only transaction has to sort of fit between the two read-write transactions
and read-only transaction should not observe some part of the read-write transaction,
so the read-write transactions does multiple writes like the first one,
then the read-only transaction you know see all those writes with none of them,
and similarly for the one that actually is past them.
Okay?
So the second, this is a standard thing that we talked about last week, serializability
and then would they go for something stronger?
And what they call external consistency,
and external consistency means that if a transaction 2 start after transaction 1 has committed,
then you know t2 must see t1's write.
So we'll go back into this previous picture,
like if read-only transaction, this one started after the first transaction committed,
then is read-only transaction must see the reads the writes of that transaction t1,
and, and so the idea is if you think about this,
basically this sort of external consistency means serializability plus this real-time requirement
and in fact you know it is very similar to linearizability.
Except you know the one way to contrast external consistency for transactions,
with linearizability is that external consistency really transaction level property
and the way we've been talking about linearizability so far
and always has been sort of individual reads and writes.
And but to the first order,
you know I think you should think about exactly the same way.
And like linearizability, external consistency is pleasant for programs,
is very strong consistency to require property.
Okay, any questions about the correctness definition there or the correctness goal that the Spanner has.
Okay.
Okay, let's then talk about how to actually achieve this correctness for read-only transactions,
and let me start out by explaining that plan that actually doesn't work
and then we're going to talk about a better plan.
So the bad plan is,
we're going to read the range that we read always the latest committed value,
that seems about write, right,
because we have to arrange that if t2 starts after t1 committed,
we'll see, you have to see it's right,
so why not read the latest committed value,
then we should be maybe we're good.
So here is the,
the problem case of course it doesn't actually work,
so t1 namely t1 does a write of x, does write of y,
as transfer commits,
then you know we have another t transaction,
we have transaction t3
or t3 is the read-only action,
it actually does a read of x,
so this is sort of real time
and then after t2,
then after t1 t3 starts,
t2 runs runs quickly,
[] the write of x, the write of y,
commits and then you know t3 got a little bit delayed
and then actually does secondary read read of y,
sort of time you know as usual going that way.
And you know if you're following a release the latest committed value,
then what is this really going to return,
it's going to return the value from this transaction t1,
and this read is going to return,
the value from y and that objection,
because you know that's why this commited value.
And that would be wrong, right,
because now we're actually in a situation where basically you know t3 observes the writes you know from different transactions
and not get a consistent [].
So, so this rule is not good enough,
and to avoid this problem and not use this bad plan,
Spanner uses a different plan.
And that's plan is called snapshot isolation,
this actually is a standard database idea,
and mostly sort of local databases
and not actually across the wide-area.
And so we'll talk about in the sort of white-area aspect in a second,
but just let me first explain what's snapshot isolation is.
And so what snapshot isolation does is,
we're going to assign a timestamp to a transaction,
and you know there's two different points,
we're gonna assign this timestamps for read-write transactions,
it's gonna be you know the commit started to commit.
And for read-only transactions,
it is going to be the start of the transactions.
And then we're gonna execute all operations,
transaction in timestamp order.
I will explain in a second, but whatever I mean that.
And be able to execute all the operation in timestamp order, you know each replica,
this is store one value for a particular key,
replica actually stores multiple values for key namely with their timestamp.
So, for example at a particular replica,
we can ask, please give me the value of x at time 10
or give me the value of timestamp x at 20
and so sometimes this is called multi version databases or multi version storage,
you know what basically keep for every update,
you basically keep a version of the data item,
so you can go back in time.
And, so this fixes you know the problem that I showed in the first case,
because basically what's going to happen,
let's look at the three transaction again,
so we got T1, we've got T2, we got T3,
T1 just write one,
you know there's a write, write of x, write of y,
let's commit,
let's say the commit actually happens at you know 10,
so this transaction basically runs at timestamp 10,
then you know at some point,
we're going to get our read of x,
we'll talk about that in a second,
and here we have this other transaction,
we get the write of y,
the write sort of write x, write y, the commit,
let's say this transaction commit at timestamp 20,
just run basically at that timestamp
and then we have to read of x
and we have the read of y,
now when the read of x happens,
it's going to be assigned to timestamp starting type type of transaction,
so starting times,
let's say the starting time of this transaction is 15,
so T2 runs at 15,
and so when the read of x is executed,
it needs basically to read the latest value of x,
after, after, before 15,
and you know we do that you know the latest committed value for timestamp 15,
before timestamp 15 is going to be times the the values from this transaction.
So read x, reads the value of transaction one,
but of course, read y also will execute at the timestamp of the start of the transaction,
so it's going to also read y at that time at 15
and you know there's going to be only one value for y 15,
namely that is the one produced by the transaction T1
and so read one, read y will also reads from T1
and so we avoid this problem that we had before,
where we read from different transactions.
And so this gives the linearizability or serializability that we're looking for,
all the transactions are executed in a global timestamp order.
Does that make sense?
So what you can think about is that every replica basically keeps a table,
write of values and timestamps
and so we're gonna have like x at value 9 at 10
and x at value 8 at 20.
And so when the read comes in you know at a particular replica,
reads 15 comes in,
I can just pick out you know the latest write,
you know preceding its timestamp.
So I have a question,
so when we do the read x,
let's say, so let's just focus on read x,
so x itself exists on some shard,
which is replicated on a paxos group,
which let's say you know there are like three servers that replicate x
and when you read from x,
because we want to read-only transactions to be very fast,
we just read from the local replica,
which need not necessarily be the leader,
so like how do we guarantee that we don't read the stale,
how do that we don't make a [].
You know brilliant question
and that's exactly the topic I want to talk about next.
The problem as you point out,
you know there's a challenge that maybe the replica hasn't seen,
as in seeing the write to x at timestamp whatever 10, right.
And so the way you know this problem solved in the Spanner,
the solution they called something that's called "safe time".
And, so the way this result is that,
basically paxos or raft you know sends all writes also in timestamp order,
so there's not you know you can think about the total order is not a counter as usual for example maybe in lab, lab 3,
but it actually is literally a timestamp
and since the timestamp also form global order, that global order of timestamps,
you know sufficient to order all the writes.
And then there's a rule,
there's an additional rule for read,
before you do read,
so before read of x at you know timestamp 15,
the replica has to wait for write,
that is with timestamp bigger than 15,
this C write with timestamp bigger than 15,
it knows that there's certainly no writes anymore before 15,
and so therefore for safe to execute the read at timestamp 15,
and know what value actually needs to be returned.
And so for services that are,
so this means that the read action may have to get a delayed a little bit until the next write,
now of course for busy servers,
these writes will come along all the time
and so that wait probably non-existence or almost non-existence.
Okay?
But this is the rule that needs to be followed
to make sure that indeed this problem of replica actually have not seen the write yet,
returning the wrong value.
The real slightly more complicated,
you also have to wait,
also wait for transactions that have prepared but not committed,
for example, this action might have been prepared,
basically you know timestamp 14,
but it hasn't maybe committed write yet,
you know to the key value store
and so we got to make sure that you know any transaction that was going to prepare it,
before our read timestamp that actually commits before we actually return the value of the read.
Okay?
Does this make sense?
Would this also be the case for different shards,
do we consider different shards separately.
The read just hit a local shard,
right, the local replica, and,
so I'm not hundred percent sure what the question you ask me.
I think I think the question I'm asking is,
the correctness guarantees do they apply across shards.
Yes, you know they apply the level of transactions right,
so so if a read-only read a local replica,
we still have to make sure that the transactions are extremely consistent,
and by following these rules we achieved that goal.
Okay, make sense, thank you.
Okay, now what you know, we're going to sort of the core part of the Spanner paper,
which is really,
what we want to reason about time like timestamps in this case,
then you know the clocks, you know different servers must be,
clock must be good,
it must be perfect,
people must have, different participants must agree on the timestamp order
and if the transaction takes a particular timestamp,
you know that timestamp must be the sort of same timestamp everywhere in the system,
so, and so the way I've described it in his previous slides,
you know whatever participant data picks the the read transaction,
assigns a timestamp to like 15,
which maybe go back a little bit,
you know here you know we're just assigning timestamp to these transactions
and it better be the case that like actually t1 and t2 t3 agree on these timestamps,
and that they are comparable
and so as we'll see in a, in a second,
this only matters really for read-only transactions,
and we can you know consider the two cases,
like what happens,
here's a question that we want to ask is,
what happens is like one replica or one server just has the wrong time right,
and so it doesn't agree with the time that the other servers,
what kind of problems could introduce,
so let's first think about the case,
what the timestamp is too large.
So, for example you know, let's go back to our version here, with this case,
so let's say the read-only transaction starts reading
and it reads actually instead of you know 15,
maybe whatever the value returns actually is 25,
and what would I do,
or let make it a little simpler, you know 18,
to get less confusion,
you know what, what is the outcome of actually having timestamp that is off,
but often in the direction of being too large.
It's still less than 25,
doesn't it still read further than 20,
doesn't it still read from the first one,
but if it's later,
it'll read from the second one.
Yeah, which if either one is fine, correct,
the real key issue here is that,
you know before reading, remember you have to wait until you see a write, right,
so if you are, so what happens if your timestamp is too large,
we're often from the too large side.
You have to wait for.
Yeah,you have to wait, a little longer maybe,
nothing goes wrong.
So now the other question is,
what if the timestamp is too small,
so for example the read,
when the t3 the machine that executes t3 you know ask for the time,
instead of time 10,
actually gets back you know say 9,
then this is a variation of the lecture question,
so basically like t3 runs at 9.
And maybe this is a good time for actually so take a break out room
and you can think and argue,
what, what is the outcome,
what is the potential outcomes
you know or what could go wrong,
if actually the timestamp that got assigned at t3 is 9 instead of 10.
So maybe we can do a breakout here,
Lily would be possible,
okay, I think Lily is back soon,
hold on a second here.
Okay, anybody else getting that noise?
Okay, everybody back and everybody can hear me again?
Yep.
We're all good?
Assume we're all good.
Yes yes, we're good.
We're all good.
Okay, okay, so back, you know so this question here,
usual we're investigating, we're relying on scheme where the clocks on different machines are perfectly synchronized,
as I mentioned, matters only for read-only transactions,
because read-write transactions you know grab logs and use two-phase locking to get a total order,
so they were executing some serializable external consistent order,
where we see that for read-only transactions, the timestamps crucial,
at least, we think it's crucial for if they're too large,
you know not maybe just affect performance negatively,
but the question is what happens if the timestamp is too small
and so the particular question we're asking is
like what, what would happen if in the scenario that we looked at a second,
where we have transactions you know t1 actually I wrote this wrong,
you know t2 and t3
or t3 is doing the read
and this read instead of actually happening maybe at 15
and it actually happens you know because the clock you know 3 wrong,
it actually happens at 9,
and you know how bad would that be?
Break our serializability?
Anybody?
Okay, looks like,
okay, sorry, I didn't hear you,
because I actually had some problem on my side tonight,
I can hear you I think,
can you repeat the answer.
Sorry, I said it would break serializability.
Yeah, why?
Because then you're you're read would happen,
would you assume to be happening after your latest write,
would then happen before which you wouldn't yield the the write.
Yeah, so just make the story complete,
you know t3 really is executing at time 15, right,
which is after t2 t1 committed,
so, t3 must see t1's write,
but if the clock is wrong
and timestamp 9 got assigned to to t3
and t3 will actually read the value of x before transaction t1 executed,
and that will be wrong,
that will break external consistency.
Okay?
Everybody clear on that?
Okay, so clearly we'd like to avoid this
and and sort of the central problems,
the [] is how do we get clocks,
how do we keep clocks synchronized.
Oh, wait, I just have one more question about.
So this scenario basically can happen,
because it's always the coordinator for read-write transaction that assigns the timestamp,
so even if the read is local and it happens on,
so it's possible for the machine that was running behind to have a version, that's in the future of its local clock.
Yeah, or in the past, that in the future, yeah.
Okay, and that can happen,
because it's not at machine who decided the timestamp.
No, okay, so forget about which machine it is,
like t3 is going to decide on the timestamp for transaction, right.
We go back here to this picture,
so here we got t3,
so t3 starts and t3 starts in principle a absolute time in true time after 10, right,
because t3 starts after t1 as we can see from this picture.
So this particular read x you know
and so we assign the timestamp to read-only transaction,
we start, we assign the timestamp for read-only transactions,
at the point of the start of transaction,
so the read of the x is the start of the transaction for t3,
t3 basically needs to get the timestamp,
so it asks you know please give me the current value of its clock.
And you know if you know the clock is reliable and correct
you know it will give back the time,
sometime after 10 for sure,
because t3 started after 10.
But let's you know we were hypothesizes that the clock of t3 is not,
you know clear [] synchronized
and the clock actually return 9.
And so now transaction 3 will execute timestamp 9
and that will cause you to read the value from before t1
and that will break external consistency.
Okay, but if, if the,
if the replication which we execute the t3 had the,
it may have the version 10 of variable x, right.
It might,but you know it's executing transaction at time 9,
so we'll get the value for before 10, this version memory.
Yeah yeah.
Yep?
Yeah.
Just making sure this is a very good question,
I think this very important point to get crystal clear what's going on here.
Okay, so so I think we're now hopefully on the same page,
you know it's very important that these clocks, these different machines are perfectly synchronized
and of course you know it's not possible to get perfect clock synchronization
and sort of a couple of difficulties,
it's difficult to get clocks synchronization,
because of clocks naturally drift.
And so you know when you think it's you know whatever 10pm and plus one microsecond
you know my machine might think it's you know 10pm and two plus two microseconds.
And just basically because you know they're sort of in your machine or in the servers,
that oscillators you know that keep track of time,
they are supposed to run at a particular frequency,
but the frequency you know it's not perfect,
you know and better clocks you know atom clocks you know have better oscillators that are much more precise
and as sort of the kind of clocks that Spanner is sort of relying on,
that you know pretty high precision,
but there's still, they need to synchronize once in a while with common you know global time
and so to avoid the problem of drift,
you know pretty precise clocks, they use atomic clocks,
which are more precise than like the clocks in your computer
and then they synchronize with global time,
so to make sure like all clocks sort of agree on the global time
and then they sort of keep ticking ticking ticking and then resynchronized periodically,
synchronized clocks and with global time
and they use GPS global position system that broadcast time,
as a way to synchronize these different atom clocks
and then keep them running in sync.
And so it looks like, the paper doesn't really say too much about actually how the true time system works,
but it looks like they have maybe few or one atomic clock per data center,
servers you know synchronize you know without time server to regularly synchronize their local clocks with that time master
and different time master, in the different data centers,
you know synchronize themselves through the GPS system.
But and so as a result,
the clocks are actually on the different servers are pretty close,
in terms of you know they talk about the  you know what the error rate is
and so it seems like the  for their clocks,
you can look at one of the tables at the end of the paper
is in the order of a few microseconds,
to you know a few milliseconds.
And so when a machine reach,
you know ask the operating system, please give me what the current time is,
the current time that gets returned maybe a few microseconds off from ture time
or even a few milliseconds off from true time.
Okay?
So there's a bit of [].
Yeah, go ahead before.
Yeah so, so like the paper,
I mean as you mentioned, we did not really go into that,
but just like the process of synchronizing the clocks or even measuring how different they are.
Yeah.
I mean shouldn't we also account for the time of the message travel, I mean.
Yeah, yeah, I think that's what they mean,
I'm sorry I didn't say much about this,
but that's what they mean,
so they sort of keep a running estimate about what they think,
you know the for example to synchronize with the time master,
the presumably the time library on the local machine keeps track of the start to make an estimate
of what is the average delay or normal delay
for sending or receiving a message to the time master
and basically use that to correct for any small mistakes,
then they also the protocol clearly have support for outliers
and so your outliers,
I mean something bad happened in the network,
and therefore a your timestamp got delayed in a lot,
so you should not include those,
and I guess there's a third problem,
which is you know sometimes these oscillators go [kaput],
you know just are not correct anymore
and so they may return incorrect values
and so you know again the, they don't talk about the great amount of detail,
but it seems those just use similar techniques like ntp
to deal with those kinds of problems.
I see, thank you.
So if you're interested in this kind of stuff,
there's protocol called ntp,
that actually when your computer and [] uses to actually synchronize its clock with you know global time,
and ntp has all these kind of mechanism built into it,
but ntp is not, it doesn't have the same position or the same small margins,
that actually true time has.
And so I think ntp could be you know you should be thinking that these error rates are in order of you know milliseconds to ten milliseconds,
basically it has to do mostly with the roundtrip time.
And you further questions about this?
Okay, so clocks are not perfectly synchronized,
you know there's basically, there's a margin of error
and what basically the true time does is
actually giving true time gives an answer,
you know gives you certain best estimated guess of what the current absolute timer or true time is
plus you know what the machine things is the margin of error.
And so, and and so the solution or to solve to deal with this clock drift,
is to not use timestamps you know true time
or just just pure timestamps,
but basically timestamps are intervals.
And so every value return from now, from the current time,
basically has the earliest and the latest.
And so, for example we ask for the current time,
and it is true time is 10 am or 2 pm,
it might return interval,
saying well the earliest it could be is you know 1 pm 1:59, and you know 59 seconds and you know whatever 20 microseconds
you know and latest might be you know 2 pm and plus you know two microseconds.
And some machines might be more than a couple of microseconds,
some machine might even milliseconds
and I guess some things in the paper,
the margin sometimes are in order of 10 milliseconds or multiple milliseconds,
but it gives an interval
and it's guaranteed that the true time is within that interval.
It's a, it's a interval epsilon to epsilon?
The paper doesn't really talk about it,
in that sense, it is just an estimate about what the margin of error is.
And I think if you look at the details of the protocol,
often that margin area boils down to two epsilon.
Okay?
Now to deal,
so now we need to adjust our protocols right,
because our protocols have some rules that setting the start time for timestamp
or sending the start time for transaction using a timestamp
and in a rule for you know reach the way to the next write,
and we'll see you know basically there's a couple of rules that need to be changed
to deal with intervals as opposed to with a true time.
So, first of all the start rule is different,
so start rule is the current time,
you know we asked the computer, please tell me the current time is,
get some info back
and then the start time that we pick is the latest.
And so that just means correct, whatever timestamp their start rule actually is [science] is guaranteed to be after true time.
So we know that true times in the past.
And if for read-only transactions you know this is assign to the start of the transaction,
and for read-write transaction before,
it actually has at the point that the commit starts.
So that part doesn't change,
the only part that really changes is that,
you get the end point of the interval,
and we can get the end point of the interval,
so that at least true time past, has past.
Okay, then there's a second rule that we didn't have before,
which is to commit wait rule.
And we're gonna delay in transaction,
so if that is actually got some timestamp at the commit time,
with the start to commit
and then we get to the end of the commit,
then we're going to delay that commit,
delay commit until the timestamp that was assigned at the starting of the commit,
is is the past.
Oh, my notes are wrong here, for one second.
We're going to delay until the timestamp is before now earliest,
so we know that actually is definitely before true time.
Okay, so so that's sort of the modifications to the protocol,
and let's see how that works,
with a simple example,
they get a little more feel for it.
So, for example, I'm going to use a slightly simpler than the previous one,
I'm just gonna focus on the transaction, but just writes x.
And we still have 3 transactions,
so here's t1,
and t1 does write to x and then commits
and just you know, let's you know we don't really care too much about these transactions,
so let's see the commit at 1,
so true time 1,
so now we're gonna run transaction t2
and it's gonna write,
yeah, so transaction t2 of course runs after t1,
and it writes you know say x2,
so here write x1, writes 2 to x,
it starts to prepare which was the beginning of the commit,
and so, at the beginning of the commit to ask for a time,
and so it's going to get an interval back.
And you know we know that a true time that's going to get back as some goal line that interval,
but somewhere in that interval,
so the interval in fact you might you know start well before you are a true time,
let's say you know interval starts even at you know one
which overlaps with the transaction t1
and you know maybe the latest value of true times is interval 10,
so that's what it gets back
and what we're going to pick as the timestamp is going to pick this value 10,
and we want to pick the latest value,
because we want to be absolutely sure that,
you know if there's a transaction that started before you know the true time,
that you know we pick a time that is definitely after that transaction,
that's the true time,
so we're gonna pick 10, which is definitely beyond one
and so we'll never get confused about this previous transactions.
Then, at some point,
you know, so this transaction you know takes timestamp 10,
and the 10 you know might be a little bit further in the future of true time, right,
so transaction doesn't prepare all whatever necessary work,
you know the two-phase commit actually hits the real commit point,
and there and may have to wait, right,
because this is a commit rule,
we have to wait a little while,
until we're actually sure that 10 exactly in the past.
And so, this basically the commit time,
what you know just actually coordinate will do is look at commit time,
just keep reading his local clock
and we'll keep reading his local clock until it gets an interval back,
where the earliest time is past 10.
So maybe at some point you know reading boom boom reading,
read gets actual interval back
and then interval and the interval starts to say at 9 or 7,
it keeps reading until it actually gets a value that's bigger than 10
and then we know for sure that true time has passed,
and so it save actually to commit transaction.
And so any transaction that now runs after t3 will have must run after true time 10.
So let's say you know transaction 3 start at some point
and transaction 3 starts after t2,
so we have to now make absolutely sure that we read you know x is 2 is going to read,
so it's gonna read x,
and and so we will ask for the current time,
it's gonna get maybe an interval back,
interval might overlap a little bit t2,
but you know the true time maybe from this clock is pretty precise
and true time be interval get back is from 10 to 12,
so true time is somewhere between 10 to 12.
We know which are basically has to be past you know 10,
because you know we're going t3 reads by definition after t2,
and that's gonna work out,
because basically t t3 is gonna pick us its timestamp the end of the interval by the latest rule,
so t3 is actually going to run timestamp you know true time 12, if you will,
and that will guarantee correct that you know this interval we know for sure pass the true time 10
and so when t3 reach you know is going to read x is 2,
because it will observe you know the value of transaction 2,
because you know the, it's reading well beyond true time,
and this must cost a little bit of delay,
but hopefully if the clocks are pretty precise,
as we talked a little bit earlier,
that delay is actually going to be small.
Does this make sense?
Sorry, I had a question,
so if t2 is saying that it's going to start a transaction at time 10,
then when we read something do,
like in the same transaction,
do we also need to make sure that 10 is outside,
like before the now interval.
The question is,
let's say t2 does more than writes
and does reads or writes,
you know t2 should observe its own write,
is that the question you're asking?
T2, like when when we reads, for example is going to read y.
Yep, so let's add this to it.
Yeah, or yeah after that.
Yeah, you're way I really care before to prepare actually reads y.
Okay, let me, yep.
And then, oh,
okay, this may be.
The reason read write actually don't really matter that much,
because if you go back at the very beginning,
at this picture you know the,
if a read-write transaction reads right,
the reads will go to the shard masters or shard leaders,
that will take if you take read locks out,
and the reads are basically declined executes all the operations locally, right,
and so it gets read values
and we'll read the most recent read value that we got after it was,
you know the the lock variable,
so basically in read-write transactions,
the locks really do all the global ordering,
here's the two-phase locking ensures global ordering.
And so really the interaction that is interesting is
the interaction between you know the read-only transaction, which is t3,
and the read-write transactions.
One is t2 actually commit
and we're reading it before it commits.
Yeah, so the protocol in read-write transaction is,
we're reading right early on refers to all the work,
and then we go to the commit phase,
so here's like, here's the commit point or here's where the clients like please commit transaction
and sends it to the transaction coordinator
and then the transaction coordinator runs the two-phase commit protocol.
But you know the old shards,
you know you need to have locks,
the values that actually that transaction is actually using.
Okay?
Okay.
Alright, so let's try to summarize a little bit.
So read-write transactions you know are basically global ordered,
or serializable external consistency serializability plus external consistency
due to the fact that they basically do two-phase commit plus two-phase locking.
The read-only transactions are the ones that are special,
because they are only contact a local replica
and the reason they actually see you know the correct value is,
because of snapshot isolation,
each data item is actually versioned
and stamped with the timestamp which actually was modified
and so, you know you can read in the past using snapshot isolation
and then to ensure that,
so this snapshot isolation really gives us extra serializability.
But you know Spanner actually shoots for something stronger,
namely it actually shoots for this external consistency property,
which is like linearizability,
so there's real-time component to it.
And to actually ensure that we got actually external consistency,
we execute the read-only operations in timestamp order,
and you know because you know timestamp order,
it requires on perfectly synchronized clocks,
the Spanner relies the rules a little bit
by actually using time intervals.
And the whole goal correctly, the whole,
by using the set of techniques,
it turns out that read-only transactions are very fast,
so read-write transactions are basically you know not actually particularly fast,
if you look at the table 6,
you know it's you know 100 milliseconds for read-write transaction,
that means basically you can only do 10 transactions per second, right,
this is really not much,
but the read-only transactions are fast.
Now, this is the case though like you know,
you know the although the read-write transactions are maybe not that fast,
they they are very powerful,
you're basically doing transactional operations across multiple shards,
that is sitting in different data centers in different parts of the world,
and that just for programmers incredibly convenient and powerful tool,
that you can ACID semantics across shards in replicated in all over the world.
So, this is all I wanted to say actually about Spanner,
I hope this actually was helpful
and that you're not maybe less confused and more confused,
because of this lecture,
but, if you have questions, feel free to hang around
and I'll be happy to discuss this or any other aspect of Spanner.
And good luck finishing 3b,
and I hope you get time to enjoy the long weekend.
Thank you.
So I have a question, maybe early in the slides,
so when you have diagram for the two-phase commit,
for the read-write transaction,
so before we communicate with the, with the, with the TC,
the TC stands for the coordinator?
Yeah, stands for coordinator, yeah.
Okay, so before we communicate with the transaction coordinator,
when we read x and read y initially,
we don't do any communication with TC,
so my question is what is the nature of these reads,
do we treat them as read-only,
so we read from the replica that is closest to us
or do we actually do like majority type of communication.
You know we we go actually to go to the participants leader,
goes to the paxos leader.
I see, so it goes the,
okay, so it goes like in lab 3.
Sorry?
So it's basically so the read x here basically was the same thing as in lab 3,
so it goes through the leader
and it gets replicated through the whole.
No, it actually doesn't,
there's no, I believe there's no actually reads go inside running through paxos,
but you know and go through the transaction leader,
oh sorry the paxos leader and the paxos leader of course knows what the last write was.
But what if the, for example we have some failure
and the leader thinks that it's the leader,
but it's in some partition,
and it actually has updated information.
I don't know exactly,
you know how they deal with this case.
I I think their leases make that impossible.
Yeah yeah, so they have the,
so every leader is leader for a period of time,
and you become during that period of time,
no other leader can be leader.
Okay, I see, awesome, thank you.
Thank you remind you.
Hey, I had a question with the last diagram with time interval,
yeah, I was wondering if like if the read for t3
or let's say the write at t2 time intervals from one to 12,
also such that the write happens at 12 for t2,
and t3 reads also happens at 12,
what happens in that scenario.
Okay, you gotta like what if you want more.
Yeah, so for t2 in t2 the write right now,
it's from one to 10 right.
Then what happens at like 12,
so that it's like the same as the transition 3.
12 not 2.
I think 12, sorry, meaning both, interested.
So if the,
so it's P correct transaction 2 would take 12 as start time,
of the of the read-write transaction,
it would wait correct until 12 shows up in the interval before it commits,
so true time is somewhere between one and 12
and wait until at least 13, right,
and so true time is now beyond twelve for sure.
Yeah.
And now we know that t3 starts after t2 right,
you know it could never got this interval back,
because the true time is already definitely pass 13
or you know you know past 12.
So when this guy now reads its clock,
we know there's going to be some interval,
you know, maybe it still includes 10,
but you know and will include 14 or 13,
and we'll pick the latest value, right,
so let's say pick 14,
and so it will do timestamp actually at 14.
Actually, so basically like that scenario wouldn't have happened,
because the time interval thing would have guaranteed the earliest and latest.
Yes, and that is the case that the t3 definitely started after t2,
by definition, that's the way we set up the example.
And then also then like if if,
instead like the read was happening around the same time as committed not necessarily strictly after,
as in this case like what is there any guaranteed on that,
like does it have a.
Great question,
so remember what the definition of linearizability right,
if t2 and t3 basically run roughly concurrently, like run truly concurrent,
then it doesn't matter,
you know t3 can go for t2 or after.
Okay.
But then what about serializability aspects,
if they execute again,
like it might not necessarily be in the same order,
the [] executed some total order
and t3 go to before t2 or after t2,
but either order is fine,
which both are allowed by serializability or linearizability,
because the execution is truly concurrent,
t3 starts before t2 committed.
Gotcha, and then for the t3 like the if the commit and read happens at the same time,
the t what t3 is actually gonna read,
just gonna depend on if the replica is reading from has that commit.
Yeah.
Thank you so much.
You're welcome good questions.
I had a question about,
like if, if I saw this in this picture
and they when it tries to commit 12 is not there,
it's just gonna retry and wait again.
Okay.
it's just good reading the clock until it gets interval back
where the earliest it's past its timestamp.
Okay, I also have just clear just to make sure the guarantee that it provides is that,
if if designs in timestamp x,
and by the time where x is like before the now interval,
this machine orders or paxos group will have seen everything worked,
I guess machine will have seen everything that has happened,
at like before x, is that right.
Yeah, I think more or less yes,
I've not heard of since you're what you're asking,
but you know we we get an interval back,
what we know is that,
the true time is somewhere in this interval,
so here's true time,
and so when we start this prepare,
you know true time is not past 12,
but it's somewhere between one and 12
and so when we do commit,
we gotta make sure that the commit actually happens really after true time,
and so we're gonna wait a little bit,
you know, so we know we got big 12
and we're going to wait until actually our clock gives an interval
where true time is definitely past 12.
I think I think what I was asking was more like,
if you pick 12
and then your interval is returned to be 13 to 20,
do you know that anything that,
like with timestamp less than or equal to 12,
that the changes for those transactions
that you're gonna be able to see them.
Yes.
Okay.
Okay, that makes sense.
Thank you.
So I don't totally understand what the point of commit wait actually is,
because it seems like commit wait will happen after you've already selected the timestamp for the transaction that you're interested in
and you simply delay the actual absolute time at which the thing will let you get committed just to make sure that extra.
I know, no but the commit time, you really start updating the database.
Aha.
And so at commit time, you have to commit,
you return like t3 didn't run until after of the C.
Right.
Because that was our definition like t3 started after t2 committed.
Right, right right, but like what would happen if you didn't,
like what do you lose,
if you don't have.
Then t3 would run concurrently with t2.
Okay.
I see.
I I'm not sure which scenario you want to explore,
but, if you know we allow t3 to start before C,
then you know we have completely different story, correct,
because there's nothing to discuss,
because t3 runs concurrently t2
and it could observe to t or not, then over.
Okay, I see.
And so the timestamp for C,
we are waiting those,
yeah we pass true time of you know the signing of the prepared number that we get back,
so we know that the true time really has passed.
And this is.
T3 could never pick a time true time that actually would be would be before t2 committed on.
I see, I see, okay.
I guess it seemed like everything was already version,
that if you modify the data,
you physically modified this or like that would be okay,
because everything has a timestamp attached to it,
so no one would,
you know from far away it seemed like no do the wrong thing,
like looking more at what they actually define as external consistency,
I don't really understand how it is similar to linearizability,
because it just says that,
if a transaction actually commits before another one starts,
then they'll have the first will have a smaller timestamp the latter one,
is also sort of implicit in that transactions execute in the order of their timestamps for sure.
Yeah, maybe my short rotation was not so brilliant,
but but yeah absolutely,
the real requirement is that,
if a transaction start after,
if t2 starts after t1 committed,
t2 must observe all the writes from t1.
Aha, right, right, right.
I see, I guess the,
I guess the time knowing that the timestamp of t2 larger than t1 will tell you
that you're going to have observed everything t1.
Okay I see, makes sense.
Yeah.
Okay, thanks.
You're welcome.
Any other questions, if there's still anybody there.
I had a question about part 4.2.3,
section of schema-change transactions.
Yeah, I didn't talk about it all.
I was just curious about like,
because essentially there they talk about like predicting the time of the commit.
Well, you may be,
let me see,
I'll tell you whatever way I think about it
and then you can say me, you can tell me where where where the confusion is,
so schema change correct that means basically adding column to a table or delete a column of a table or something along those lines,
so it really changes you know the layout of the database.
And, and so schema changes are generally expensive
and the way they make sure that their atomic they're running in far in the future,
so they run over the timestamp,
you know well beyond the current time.
And so I guess that's actually usually do its stuff, correct,
because every other is actually reading or writing using this version memory
and you know they're creating version memory way farther in the future.
And so it can't affect any of the current transaction is running.
Now communicate you know you know this takes so long,
by the time they actually want to commit the schema migration part,
there, there are actually transactions,
they're starting to [encroach] on the time that migration transaction started.
So those you know, those transactions actually times marches on,
you know we're doing transactions
and then the rule is that basically any read-write transaction
or any read-only or any transaction basically have to stop,
until basically the transfer, the migration transaction was completed.
Because the migration transaction is timestamping is a new values,
you know with its timestamp.
So when when there's a request essentially for this migration,
it chooses a commit time far into the future, and.
You know basically, you hope basically the that transaction also commits you know not.
Yeah, by then.
So any reads that come at a time up until then are served from the current.
Local replicas from at all, correct,
because they could have even seen that, right.
Okay, and it's a cool trick,
if you have version memory,
you can you schedule things in the future.
Yeah, it's a cool trick,
I was just wondering how they actually like figure out that point in the future.
Yeah, it's probably some some [] stick or something, okay.
So, but essentially so if you don't choose a time, that's far enough in the future,
then you run the risk of.
Exactly.
Okay, so then you have incorrect results.
To avoid risk of incorrect results, which actually block.
Yeah, I see, okay.
Awesome, thanks so much.
You're welcome.
Bye.