Okay, good afternoon, can everybody hear me?
Yep.
Okay, thank you,
yes I will post the lecture notes at the end of lecture,
response to the chat.
Okay, so, today basically I want to start a new topic in in 6.824,
and sort of last topic that will be discussing,
the topic is really decentralized systems.
And these are typically decentralized really refers to the fact,
that there's no single authority that is in control of the system,
a lot of the systems that we've seen so far,
all the machines and servers sort of cooperate
and on the under control of a single institution or any single authority.
And systems are a lot of you ask questions,
about like how would it work,
if there's no central point of trust.
And so, from now on, the three systems or three papers were going to be discussing,
all sit in this form of decentralized systems
and decentralized systems are harder to build than the sort of single trust systems,
because you know you might have to account for byzantine failures or byzantine participants.
And these are participants that you know sometimes follow the protocol
and sometimes they don't follow the protocol,
so again they really they think about it,
they are basically adversaries,
and they may try to abuse or trick other participants in systems,
you know for their own goods, but not maybe for others.
And so that makes actually system design,
which distributed system designs much more challenging
and much more difficult to reason about,
[] feel like in the last you know 18 whatever lectures,
mostly when we talk about, when we design protocol or we thought about raft,
and we just assume that actually every participant in the protocol follows the rules
and in the byzantine with byzantine participants, that is not the case anymore,
you know the participants can cook up new messages,
you know send messages out of order,
trick other participants
and so the we thinking about those kind of protocols is much more difficult,
because we have to consider what, what the adversary could do,
to sort of make our life to break basically the properties of the protocols, that we're shooting for,
so this tends to be made the problem much harder.
And really you know where what this sort of topic is,
so sits on the intersection of distributed systems and security.
And as we'll see in the next this the next three papers,
you know cryptography or security ideas,
like signing and hashing
and are going to play a crucial role to actually make [forward] progress.
In fact, you know the paper actually that we're reading for today is also
is a paper that we use in the 6.858,
taking maybe 6.858 last Spring,
we talked about this paper too,
although then for mostly from the perspective of security
and today I'm going to mostly focuses on the perspective of distributed systems,
the SUNDR itself, a lot of people ask,
a lot of you ask you know SUNDR being used,
and as far as I know,
there's actually no systems that actually implement SUNDR directly or based directly based SUNDR,
other than lab 4 in 6.858,
in lab 4, what if you do lab 4, the default project,
lab 4 at 6.858,
then you actually implement SUNDR.
Now, the reason, so you might wonder why we are studying this paper at all,
the reason we're studying it,
because it actually proposes a number of very powerful, techniques are powerful ideas.
and so particularly the signed log,
even though is a strong design conceptual design,
is incredibly powerful
and you see back same idea appear in lots of other decentralized systems,
you know ranging from systems like git to you know systems like Bitcoin
or any other sort of cryptographic ledger,
we're gonna be talking about Monday or next Tuesday,
I know one system actually is directly influenced by SUNDR,
which is a system called keybase,
I mean keybase uses SUNDR techniques,
and and many more,
if you're not familiar with keybase,
actually was originally acquired by zoom,
which was only all familiar with.
Okay, so that's sort of for the quick intro to this paper,
before I dive into more of the setting,
any sort of questions before diving a little bit deeper in the paper.
Okay.
So let's talk a little bit about the setting of this paper or the motivation of this paper.
So the setting in the [hour] that the [officer] set forward is a network file system,
and, you can think about this a little bit in the style of earlier paper,
that we've read Frangipani,
where the topic also was to implement and consistent network file system.
So we have a file server,
we have clients that interact with the file server,
somebody might actually create a file f,
and maybe read f on another client.
And you know the setting we're in,
is that basically the file server as opposed to in the Frangipani,
the file server are actually can be Byzantine.
And Byzantine really increasing extremely powerful threat model
or you know gives the attacker an incredible amount of power.
So in Byzantine you know the server might send different RPCs back,
you cook up its own RPCs, the the, takeover the machine,
you know bribe the administrator
and for everything is basically the way to think about is that,
the adversary gets complete control of the file server.
And so this covers sort of wide range of you know sort of more common attacks
or like the typical attacks you might see in a real system,
so real attacks one bug in software,
so if you know there's a bug in the software,
then you know the adversary can exploit,
that [] maybe to obtain privileges and you know that Byzantine model,
you know completely compasses that organise system,
administrator might have a weak, with weak password,
if the attacker compromises and then they take control over the system,
you know that's also covered by Byzantine physical breaking,
maybe the attacker rangers you know get access to the physical machine,
and you know can therefore control the physical part of the machine,
again it's all covered by this you know Byzantine threat model
or even you know, maybe you know the the attacker bribes an operator
or colludes you know with a malicious client,
you know that is also covered by this model,
so this is a threat model,
that is a very very gives a lot of power to the adversary,
it covers a lot of standard attacks.
And and you know the first thing sort of observed,
you know again that SUNDR place is that,
instead of actually you know sort of maintaining the whole file system on the file server,
the file server is as simple as possible,
and in fact you know the file servers very much like almost like Pedal,
it's almost like a block device with a little bit more.
So there's a central place where all the blocks are stored
and but the clients really implement the file system,
so it's not really, you know that the client sends, create for file actually,
you know sends blocks and reads blocks, from the block server
and basically constructs you know from the blocks with reads or writes,
you know its own view of the file system
and serve a file system operations,
basically on the straight on the client
and so here really, we create you know f, read f etc.
So very very similar to the Frangipani,
except the big difference of Frangipani is that Pedal and all clients were completely trusted.
And in this setting,
the clients are not trusted
and the file servers, it can be also, is also not trusted.
Okay?
Okay, so the paper focused on a particular set of security properties,
and focus is really on, the focus is on what's called integrity properties.
And in contrast to confidentiality,
confidentiality about protecting data from them,
so that nobody else can read it,
integrity is just ensuring that the system structure is correct
and the modifications, illegal modifications to the data are being detected
and whether the data is public or not public,
you know that sort of besides the point here.
To make a little bit more concrete,
you know there sort of, the thing that happens in our minds is,
we have a set of, we have developers,
you know we have dev1, you know dev2,
they may share some machine,
that contains the source code repository of some source of project,
the developers you know are collaborating on that project,
and and so think about this as a example,
the paper mentions is,
in the paper maybe this is the development machines
and the server for a debian Linux
and what they want to again, defend against is trap or trapdoor,
you know trapdoor in the software.
So the you know the attacker, you know takes over control,
breaks into the machine, that contains the source repo,
modifies the software [noticed]
and then it's going out of that software gets deployed,
you know for example debian Linux gets deployed to lots of machines
and now the attacker has control over those machines,
because it's gonna exploit the trapdoor.
The the paper talks about this attack,
this particular instance in debian Linux in 2003,
where the attack was able to compromise you know the development server or cluster,
in recovering from these kinds of attacks very painful,
in fact in 2003 you know they report,
that the debian Linux which froze development for a couple days,
and while they were trying to sort out which parts of their source repo was still correct
and which parts were actually modified by the attacker
and these attacks happens periodically,
I think last year you know Ubuntu had a similar type of problem in in 2018 or 2019,
I can't remember exactly,
and it was a similar case,
where one of the core development servers was broken into,
you know they have to sort out,
what we're see which software which files got infected and affected by that breaking.
Okay, so that's sort of the setting of the paper,
and I'm going to make a little bit more concrete,
a little bit of a toy example,
to help us, you know go through the techniques, that this paper actually uses.
So the example that I'm gonna use,
partially inspired by 6.858,
is, let's say you know we have a file system,
there's, you're doing the,
and the file system contains you know the source code for this application of using 6.858 zoobar
and zoobar is a sort of a virtual bank type application,
where users of the system, registered users of the system can transfer zoobars to each other
and so it has a file called auth.py, you know does authentication
and that's a file that basically you know influence bank, bank.py.
And, so, let's consider the case where a you have a new set of developers, A B and C
and they decided that they wanted to increase the usability of zoobar,
actually deployed for real and make it real,
basically you know they decide to divide the work as follows,
A, is gonna modify auth.py to support MIT certificates or MIT certs,
kerberos tickets or certificates,
and with the idea that, what we're gonna do is,
we're gonna auth.py is going to be modified,
so that only legit MIT community members actually can log into the file server,
file server or into zoobar,
instead we actually know who it actually really is,
that is associated with that particular MIT certificate
and then you have to make a little bit more useful.
You know B can actually modify the bank.py to actually link it you know to cash tag for techcash.
And so, you know the idea that basically we can actually use this zoobar system do that,
like we can use the zoobar system to actually transfer money,
you know real money instead of zoobars,
between users that are registered with this servers,
that this sounds of course like a crazy idea,
you don't really do it,
but it's not completely ridiculous,
you know, because you know the auth.py really checks who would actually is
based on the MIT certificate
and so maybe it's not unreasonable that we could connect you know bank.py to actually techcash.
And then basically C in our scenario is going to be that person,
that's actually going to deploy the software,
find machine takes software installs it and runs it
and it opens it up to the MIT community.
Now, in the case,
now let's consider what you know what could happen, what could go wrong,
if actually the file server was compromised
and so was byzantine.
Well, the obvious you know problems, a couple of obvious problems, you know bad outcomes possible,
let's consider them,
you know that outcome one which is the one thing we should be talking about
and also in the previous examples,
it is basically the adversary gives arbitrary code to C,
adversary provides own code to C.
And you know that sort of maybe that adversary slightly subtle about it or clever about it,
you know whatever makes it a little bit hard to spot,
then actually modified auth.py for example to delete the MIT certificates,
but they're basically you know there's really no way for C to check,
that actually got the software that A and B produced
and without any modifications from the adversary.
So that's sort of the obvious problem we're going to talk a lot about,
it there's a second sort of that outcome which may be a little more subtle,
which is that the adversary provides the changes you know to bank.py,
without changes to auth.py.
And so at this point,this is pretty problematic, correct,
because you know bank.py link to techcash now,
but we actually don't have appropriate authentication to users anymore,
in fact anybody that actually creates zoobar account can now actually interact with the techcash,
and so you know clearly very very undesirable, and harder to spot,
because basically the adversary actually doesn't really modify any software,
just selectively you know presents you take pieces of it
and present that to see who then actually goes off and deployed.
And so it's really you know the attacks the paper considers of course the attack number one to two,
but there are a lot of some of the subtle issues actually are brought out by the second case,
that will be talking about.
Any questions so far,
you know about the setting by the motivation,
before we're going to try to discuss solutions.
So the problem with the second case is that
the user that the authentication does not authenticate.
Yeah, it doesn't use MIT certificates anymore
and so we don't really know actually who logs in.
Thank you.
What about the case where A like B won't see is like the fork.
Let's assume for a second that A and B actually I have talked to each other and divide up the work,
so they know they're supposed to be doing it together.
Right.
May form a team, they're in close collaboration in contact,
you know and they've divided up the work
and so they know you know B tells A,
when B done, tells A,
when they done and then they tell C go ahead, we all done.
Okay?
Okay, so, let's start with considering a simple design,
that is too simple, meaning it doesn't work,
but it gives us some starting points for more sophisticated design,
hopefully might work
and so the simple point is that
A and b or any,
all the files are going to be signed with person who modified,
so when like A modifies you know auth.py,
A actually produces a signature,
and signed with the public key,
which signature signed to the public key of A,
and you know that signature covers the data of the file.
And so when C downloads, you know the auth.py,
you know check the signature,
and if the signature checks out,
you know then that C knows that actually this file was produced,
you know this file was produced by A
and you know might all believe that things are good.
And that's the basic plan
and we'll talk a little bit about where the keys are coming from,
although you know the issue of public key distribution is really an 6.858 topics,
so I'm not going to talk too much about it,
but just assume for now,
that every user has a key, public private key pair
and the private keys are secret and the public keys are public,
and every user knows whose public key belongs to who.
So now let's consider attacks and see which one sort of you know fail,
which ones you know work.
So, of course the obvious attack was number one,
that we talked about on the previous slide,
this S modifies file,
and that's not a little bit,
that's not directly S modified auth.py,
that's not really going to be possible anymore,
because when C downloads you know the file and the signature,
and checks it and it will see that the signature rejection check,
because the data that actually was signed is different than the data that actually the server produced
and so it's not really possible for the server really to modify auth.py,
without actually being attacked or without actually being detected.
So you know this is we're sort of in good shape here on this attacks
and that's sort of the core attack, right.
But there's a lot of other things that S still could do,
so let's consider some of the other things,
S you know could actually, we describe S send another file,
and pretends to be auth.py,
and because the signature doesn't really say
you know which actually file the data belongs to
and so S you know produce some other files,
like oh yeah see this is actually auth.py,
you can believe me in here,
the sign the signature which of course produced by S,
so of course this could be fixed,
you know maybe the signature should not only include data,
but also probably should include the file name,
so you know maybe not too, too bad in something that you could be addressed.
Third, you know another yet another possibility is
to for S to basically send the contents of old files, old content,
maybe some new.
And it does a bit more difficult now
for us to handle correct this to simple plan,
because you know there there's no way you know basically the files individually authenticated, but not together
and it's not C, gets a consistent picture of the file system,
it just gets like sign files,
and how do sign files relate to each other in terms of their histories,
is completely not covered in these two simple design.
This is exactly of course gonna issue,
there's more subtle attack that now could just completely work out, correct,
because you know S could send the,
could send the old version of auth.py,
it will completely check out,
and then send the new version of the of the bank.py,
which actually talks is linked to techcash,
and now exactly back in there's a worse some case,
were you know with an old version of auth.py
or not to change to auth.py,
not the certificate changes to auth.py,
and the new version that actually link to techcash.
And so this is not so good,
so and the simple point that we have here, just doesn't deal with this.
There's a similar sort of another version of this,
that where you know of course you know S can also just claim that the file doesn't exist,
and C doesn't really have any way of checking whether that's actually true or not,
because again they should have a global picture where it's a consistent view of the file system,
nobody knows about signatures for each file.
And so you see that the simple design may be a good starting point,
but we need something more, more complete
and I think we need something that really ties all the file systems, all the files together,
that ties directories together, the content of the directories together,
and and we have to be able to decide in some way,
what is the latest version of the file system,
so that C can't be tricked into in this sort of problematic case,
where one file is installed and the other file is not installed.
So that's really what the SUNDR paper tries to address
and the big idea in the in the paper,
and it just turns out to be just a big idea in general,
and it's a conceptual idea,
even though the paper actually doesn't really implement this big idea directly,
implement it in a more indirect way,
it is an incredibly powerful idea.
So the big idea is to have signed log of operations.
And of course you're well familiar with logs of operations,
and you and you know you can
and this is basically a sort of [beefed] up version of it,
where there signatures on log entries,
that both consider cover the entry as well as preceding entries.
And this turns out to be as we've seen in all the previous distributed systems and failure recovery protocols,
we talk about the log is actually very powerful idea to think about the correctness of the system
and in the same way that idea is carried for here in this Byzantine context.
And so let me draw a simple log,
so captures this in the paper,
so log whatever have some entries
and let's say you know we're coming up we are talking about,
so it's modification, a mod, you know auth.py,
by A, signed by A,
you know there's a mod,
if everything goes well, you know there's a mod of the bank.py signed by B.
And as we'll talk about in a second
you know it turns out that not only are the modifications in the log,
but also the fetch of the read operations.
So fetch fetch the log you know signed by C, auth.py,
and then fetch of bank.py, singed by C.
We'll talk about those operations, so the fetch operations, a little bit,
I first want to talk about how to operate the preceding operations for modifications.
So, first of all, the what's important to realize is that,
this signature that is in the record not only covers the current records,
but it also covers all the records before.
Let me stop for a second here,
because I'm not a hundred percent sure if can everybody still hear me.
Yeah.
Yes.
Okay, I got my ipad and I walked out of the zoom session,
I always walking twice and my ipad logged out,
so I just want to make sure I'm still talking to you and you can hear me,
and start that is the case.
Okay, so let's just proceed the.
So, actually.
I think we lost Frans.
Can people hear me now, Does anybody hear me.
Yes.
Okay.
Okay, I don't know if anything weird happens on your end,
but my end, I got logged out of Zoom and log back in.
Maybe there's a Byzantine server at work.
Okay, let me hold on one second, and get myself in.
And let me see, that video goes off.
Camera, okay, let me know if I'm good.
Okay, good.
No screen sharing yet, but yeah.
Okay, I hope this works better,
okay, so it was at this very important point,
where the signature just not cover the log entry itself,
but also covers all the preceding log entries.
And so when you know A as this modification to auth.py to the log,
it signs the log records itself plus the preceding log record,
so you can think about this,
that the preceding log is may be represented by,
the content of the preceding log is cryptographic hash,
and a in the record, basically modification to auth.py,
you know the the cryptographic hash the preceding part of the log
is included and covered by the signature.
Just to be clear, we still can't see the screen.
You can't see the screen, screen hasn't changed,
but, let me see if I can do something about that.
And [] I guess,
Zoom still thinks there's actually sharing the screen,
but it doesn't look like actually is.
How about this?
Yep, I can see now.
Okay, thank you.
Okay, so I didn't change anything yet,
other than I think I was going to draw the next arrow,
which basically when these signs you know it's actually covered all the preceding entries too.
And this is a good, correct,
because when client you know C actually receives you know or gets actually sees the log entry for B,
then it's impossible for the server to drop the log entry of A,
because you know that will be detected when C actually detect signature on the log entry of B.
And so we really made a big step forward,
in the sense that it's much harder for the server now to selectively drop log entries.
So that's so we're pretty good pretty good, you know the servers cannot drop A,
and keep these modifications.
So that's actually a big big step forward,
so let's look a little bit more in detail,
how this actually is going to play out,
so we're a client C and you know we're fetching the log to basically pull out you know the distribution of the software
to install on a particular machine,
the first thing the client does,
you know it actually check all the signatures.
And you know always the question of course is like,
when you know you want to check the signature log entry you know which public key do you use,
and because you want to make sure that,
you're not being tricked in accepting [] modification by A,
but it turns out that actually A was not the person actually signed it.
And it turns out basically to figure out which key to use to actually verify the signature,
the key uses the owner of the file,
so the public key need to correspond to the owner of the file
and ignoring groups for now,
you know basically only the owner of the file was allowed to modify a file.
So for simple for slightly simplified,
we can think about it auth.py is owned by A
and the id of the file is basically the public key of A
and so we know which public key to use and can verify the signature with it,
and so if somebody else makes a modification that pretends to be A,
that actually is not going to check out.
So it's really only A can connects and make modifications similar for B.
So that's part of the you know one thing that's actually clever about SUNDR,
I'm not really going to be talking about,
some since the file system is actually doubling both as a file system,
as a public key public key infrastructure or distribution infrastructure,
and so it's actually possible to something basically why we determine like which user has which public key.
But I'm not really gonna talk about this,
I really want to focus on the consistency aspects
and the more distributed systems aspects.
The second thing that the client does is check its own last entry.
And this is to protect clients from actually being rolled back by the server in time,
so the server can actually by the client checks always last entry,
if its last entries in the log steal,
then you know the only way forward for the attacker is to actually roll the file system for A can roll backwards,
so C will check whether the [] of its previous operations are in it
and confirm that they're still in it,
actually it's last entries still in it.
Is the question here,
this only I think this attack from the server to rollback,
would only work if no other client wrote to the log,
like after this client's last entry, right,
because otherwise checking signatures would figure that out.
Yeah, although you know let's talk about in a second,
maybe I mean you could always play a fork attack,
so you can always split you know the use of the file system in multiple users,
but you can at least not roll back the client,
once the client saw a particular file system,
you can't go backwards in time.
The client could, the server it can present different file systems in future,
but you can't roll back.
Third part, the first place with the [] industry is a [constructive] file system.
So after you know, it knows actually it's not rolled past version of the file system,
it basically applies all the modifications,
basically builds a file system tree you know on the client
and and then before whatever operation it is,
it wants to perform,
so let's say in the case of C,
what it will do is,
you know it will read you know auth.py and append an entry to the log and sign it.
So in the case when it reads auth.py,
it will, it produce basically a signature or an entry for this log entry.
And basically then and then the final step in this protocol is,
it uploads the log to the file server.
And you know clearly this protocol is completely in practical,
and and really what it is,
it's sort of more conceptual protocol
to help us understand why eventually we might even be successful in achieving security
in the context of Byzantine server.
Because if we're ridiculous correct to download the log for every operation
and the log contains the history of all the operations ever happened to the file system,
in step three, you know the client actually constructs file system at all the, all operations ever performance since the beginning of time,
and then finally in step five,
upload the whole log back to the server, seems completely ridiculous
and it is ridiculous,
in terms of performance,
but it will help us understand
you know when we look at the implementation of the scheme,
when it actually has the same set of properties,
that they sort of conceptual design has
and we'll see later example, in the case of Bitcoin,
that literally does actually have a log
and since the beginning of time, with all operations in it
and so, maybe it was a crazy idea,
maybe in the context of 2004,
but you know people actually do have these sign logs and really maintained it.
And so in that sense,
you know it's not only a big conceptual idea,
that some people do it in practice.
Any questions so far?
Okay.
The one thing you know that you're probably wondering about,
it was proposed as question for the reading today,
is what is up with these fetches,
you know why are the fetches in the log too,
and and the because you might think,
well you know the only thing I really care about,
if we think about, we care about is only the modifications,
you have to be in the log,
because there are actually things, actually modify the file system,
reads don't really modify this file system,
so what's the what's the problem.
And so I think I wanna do a quick breakout here
and I'm sure if you can bring some of each other,
but what you thought the answer to this particular question was
and hopefully maybe this initial coverage like SUNDR you know maybe how to improve your understanding
and you know you can sort of figure out what the answer is,
or talking about something else,
so I would like to take, maybe do a five minutes breakout room.
Okay, just double checking everybody back.
Looks like it.
Good, thank you.
Okay, so what,
I guess, let's start with the homework questions,
with no more question why, why are the fetches in the log.
Anybody?
If you have a read-only server,
if there are no fetches,
this file system can give it anything.
Can it?
Can give it, because it,
because there are no fetches in the log,
that would mean that there are, there be read-only servers would not be doing a lot of the checks,
that we talked about before,
so they they go back in time,
for example might maybe not work,
because, it did not put anything in the log,
because it only fetches.
Yeah, okay good,
okay, so I think you're totally on the right track,
it was like trying to make it a little bit more precise or make more concrete
and I think you know that is correct.
So let's assume this is the log looks like
and the C's fetches are not in it.
And let's you know,
so this is the log before actually C downloads log,
so let's say you know where C fetches fetches auth.py, correct,
the file that was modified by A
and basically what the server does,
the server instead of actually providing both the modifications A and B,
because it has it,
which A and B were done with its modifications,
it sends the C basically prefix,
since the prefix that excludes the modifications to A and B,
so we have mods A and B right,
and so C you know fetches this file,
it fetches the log
and so this basically is this part of the log prefix,
you know the C checks you know the signature,
checks whether it's proceeding operations are in it,
you know and they're all there,
because C hasn't done any other operation yet
and so basically it will accept the log
and the log as it is or the prefix as it is,
and basically returns you know auth.py to whatever application,
that is copying this software into the machine,
that actually run the installed software.
So then C fetches bank.py,
and this time around, the server sends the whole log.
And you know the C, C looks at these entries
and it's a valid log,
in the operations are presumably the prefix,
since we didn't care about fetches,
you know its all caught in the log
and so everything looks you know good,
you know these are valid modifications,
the nothing has been changed
and and so you know C, you know without the fetches in the log,
C will actually accept this log
and basically build a file system,
that has, that deploy includes modifications to A and B
and returns the results you know to the application for bank.py.
So that it can install the machine,
that actually is going to run the servers
and as you can see you know we're sort of in a bad situation, right,
because we took the old version of auth.py
and the new version of bank.py,
and the one way you can think about this is that,
you know from you know C's perspective,
what really seemed to have happened is that,
while you know it was reading auth.py,
you know there were concurrent modifications to A and B,
and just happened basically at the same time
or at least the server is pretending,
it happened at the same time
and so and so it gets confused,
or can't detect the fact, that these applications were did happen before any time.
So this is the, this is the problem,
that you know basically putting the fetches in the log source,
is like let's make that actually just also concrete,
and so see why actually this problem is solved in that case.
Professor, I I had a question.
Yeah, so I I'm having a little trouble understand,
like understanding what the, like sort of like the interface,
for like for fetch and modify is like what,
I I thought you fetched pretty much like the whole tree
and had to rebuild the whole file system,
basic example,
but this slide before you're fetching specific files.
The server is the one that returns the log correct,
so the server can decide what entries to include.
Yeah, and we're already seeing that it can't really delete anything out in the middle of the log
and that's not really possible,
it's always send a prefix of the log,
because the prefix is always consistent with itself.
And so in this first case, correct,
it sends the prefix
and in the second case, sends the whole log.
Yeah.
So the server can decide to do that,
but there's nothing that the client can or at least it like so far,
you know, discuss there's nothing that the client,
how the client could detect,
that it didn't get like the whole log.
Right, I I my question is more towards,
like what the interface is for clients to use,
like fetch and modify, like,
because I thought, initially I thought,
okay fetch fetch is like the whole file system.
No, no, fetch is a single file.
Okay.
And and so basically what the fetch does,
it get to the log, like modifications,
modifications are all the operations that modify a file,
and like if you go back to a slide a little bit earlier,
you know in the modification record,
it says explicitly which file is being modified
and you know what's being said is,
similarly in the fetch, it says which file like this client saw.
Okay.
And then, so so, so for fetch like a client goes through the log,
but only looks at.
Yeah, feath a thing that does actually read the file that actually is looking for.
Okay, but does it check every single entry in the log anyways for the signature.
Yeah, okay, the first step is always check the whole log,
go for and make sure that your last you know operations in it,
whether it's a [] or modify,
although in this broken scheme, you know we drop the fetches,
it applies all the checks, all the signatures
and then it builds up the file system,
by replaying the log from the beginning of time,
get a file system
and then it does its operation,
and so in this case, the operation is certainly fetched auth.py, is basically reading it.
Okay.
The reason you know basically that we talk about fetch and modify is,
because all operations are basically following one or two [catch], either to fetch or it is a modification operation,
like writing a file, creating a file,
there's all modification operations,
the fetch operations are reading a file,
maybe [] directory status file, that kind of thing.
Okay, and then the modify is also,
like a modify, like doesn't fetch the, okay also fetches the log,
but then builds the file system.
Yeah, so maybe the fetches here I'm using fetch I guess in two ways,
one describe read-only operations
and actually to obtain or receive the log from the server.
Okay, but then modified, modifies also one single file.
Yes, yeah, for every modification in the file system,
you're gonna have a log entry.
Okay thanks.
Sorry, I also have a question,
I I don't really understand why this scenario is a problem,
because as you said,
it's it's possible,
like from the perspective of the client,
it may well be that A and B got created or modified, for the last fetch.
Yeah, in principle, it could have happened, correct,
that was recovering modification,
we do know, because like we were sort of look from the top
and we know that basically C you read the file after A and B modified,
but the server can pretend as if it actually happened concurrently
and in the second, we'll see that, if we stick the fetches in the log,
server can not pretend to do that.
Okay, but even if the server pretends that,
does it, is that even a problem,
does it break anything,
because.
Yeah, this is a example where it shows how to break something, correct,
like step one, you know C fetches auth.py,
the server gave it one you know as far as the fetch,
it gave the prefix.
And so the client constructed file system,
executing the operation returned auth.py to the application
and install the software on the machine,
just to make it very [],
so now the first, you're reading auth.py that operation is done,
finished already executed
and has installed the old version of auth.py on the machine.
Then the client you know can fetch is bank.py,
now the server actually the client the application want to read bank.py,
so the client fetches the log from the server or ask the server,
please give me the log,
the server this time around, gives the whole log,
and not just the prefix.
Yeah but.
The [] that builds up the whole file system
and returns bank.py to the application.
But in like, I wouldn't this happen in an incorrect implementation of the client,
because if the client finds that receives the log
and it sees an additional modification on A,
if the client knows that its logic depends on A and B being in sync,
it would also fetch A again.
Okay, so there's a question,
C doesn't know, correct,
that is C,
okay, in this particular scenario,
the we're trying to establish whether actually,
you know C can determine whether actually modification happens concurrently or in the past, before reading.
You know we want to be in the case,
that actually happened in the past,
because actually really happened in the past.
But you know what this you know server does,
it just pretends that the modification actually happened concurrently,
we've actually sees operations,
and C doesn't really have any way to detect that,
other than a new you know maybe A you know there should have been a modification for A and B together.
But that only could have known,
if there were sort of communication between C and A and B,
and second, let's talk about that in a second,
but if C had not talked to A and B
and you know yeah it could have gotten, could end up in this scenario,
where it installed the old version in auth.py, the new version of bank.py.
And we'll see in the second,
if we stick the fetches in,
then this probably cannot happen.
Somebody asked if we timestamp everything,
then we could detect things all that thought for a second.
Okay, let's look at the with fetches scenario, right,
so see what actually happens in that case,
so client fetches, what is the fetches of auth.py.
Oops, what happened now.
Hold on a second, something wrong.
I presumably nobody can see my screen yet.
It's black.
Yeah yeah coming back hold on a second.
I definitely feel today, there's a Byzantine component to 6.824.
Okay, I need to stop sharing screen for a second.
Allright, we're back hopefully.
Okay.
Okay, so back to this example,
we're now the features are in the log,
C fetches the auth.py.
So let me continue, right then,
save this for just,
it fetches auth.py,
the server since the prefix,
so basically sends you know these modifications, correct,
the server can just return whatever it likes,
then, you know, in this new plan, correct,
where the fetches are being log,
then, C constructs file system, using A and B,
and then returns of course you know auth.py to the client, to the client or to the application
and then it adds a fetch to the log,
and uploads that log to the server,
and then you know the, that does a fetch of you know bank.py,
and you know the server, you know in previous example,
first it sends just a prefix,
so here's like prefix,
now you know sends, now the client sends the whole thing, right,
so sends the whole log
and it, but if modifications are not in it,
so and we'll have to send the whole log,
well to send the whole log
and must include the fetch from C, right,
and so, if it doesn't, you know sends [] to see,
it actually, sees C is actually not there, the read operation
and basically the client will reject the log,
because actually it's own fetch operation is actually not in it,
so it's not possible for the server to pretend
you know that to send the log later on,
because actually the new log should have included that fetch operation,
that was in it and update the C
or the server cannot twice that fetch operation into here,
to make it consistent what actually happened before,
because that would be detected,
because you know the modifications on the records of A and B are not, wouldn't check out.
Okay, so basically what this really does is to sort of step back,
is that you can think about this attack,
that the server sort of pretends that the modification of A and B happen concurrently,
with the C reading it,
even though we know that actually it's not the case
and by speaking the fetches in it,
that attack cannot happen.
I have two questions,
maybe first just, if you could like define fork consistency and the fetch modify consistency,
and then the second is,
in this example, so what exactly is stopping the server from placing the fetch in the right place of the log.
Because remember every log entry covers all its proceeding entries.
Okay, so if.
The server could not [slice] that, you know fetch you know after the prefix before the modification of A and B.
So let's say it only wants to send the modification of A,
it knows the hash of the modification of A and everything preceding it,
and then it could insert the fetch to C there,
because it knows that,
it's a hash of that, and.
Then they couldn't send that.
Yeah but then they couldn't send the modification to B,
because the modification would B you know is directly after A
and so any must yeah and so it can't [splice] it between A and B either.
I see, okay.
Sorry, what was a problem with having it where it is in the picture?
Well, where it is, now the picture is perfect,
that's fine right,
in fact you know this basically suggests you know that the fetch of C actually included the modification of A and B,
like the blue was the real log.
And we have the fetch to C in it
and you know the everything to be perfect.
So just to clarify the definition of fork consistent.
Yeah, hold on, hold on a second because,I haven't talked this slide,
I haven't talked about the definition of fork consistency,
I'm gonna do that right now.
Okay?
So we're talking about fork consistency.
So, so what we've seen so far is that,
the server cannot really manipulate the log,
it can only send prefixes or can hide parts,
you can hide, it can send prefix back to the client,
but it can't really modify the log,
so just basically have an opportunity to you know sort of show different logs to different clients,
and that is basically what fork consistency is.
And so it cannot provide you know the kind of,
the server cannot provide the type of persistence that we've seen so far in the past,
name likely linearizability and external persistency and things like that,
that's just not possible,
but it can provide this,
what this what the paper calls or introduces is fork consistency.
And let me abstract a little bit away and to explain what that is.
So let's say we have client A,
we have the server S,
and it has a log,
and let's say I'm just gonna extract everything away,
it has entries A B C and D and E,
and, you know A you know whatever maybe you know [] entry to the log
and you know, and that's basically [].
And maybe we have another client B,
and, what the server can do is sort of give the other client a completely different view of the world,
by basically have another copy of the log or its own copy
or give a different copy of the log,
for example, maybe that log contains the record A,
but then every operation of B does,
goes into this log you know B1 B2,
maybe even some operations from other clients, that also get this view
and end up in this log,
but they're not actually shown to A,
you know A basically A may actually also add more entries to log,
like maybe it had B C and E,
and those are not actually shown to D,
so these two logs to the [] view of A,
you know it's completely consistent,
because it's unaware of any of these changes,
and to B you know this log looks completely consistent,
because they're really aware of any A changes right,
in this model of the world,
the only sure shared communication place that is, there is the server,
you know that is sort of the,
you know the thing that you know shows you know what actually is the state of the system.
And one way you can think about is,
like in terms that we've talked about before,
this is sort of like a split brain,
you know basically you know A gets C1 view of the world,
you know cooked up by by log that's consistent with A view
and you know B you know it's another view of the world.
And basically the servers sort of keeps them to carefully separate
and and therefore can pretend that you know A is looking one,
sees the left side of split brain,
B is actually the right side of split brain.
Okay? Does that make sense.
So that's sort of what you know basically they're saying is,
like you know we can't really do better than fork consistency,
because it's always possible for the server to to basically make a copy of the log
and then from then on, you know present different views for these clients.
Now, S could not merge the two logs again, correct,
these logs have to be separate,
you know for A and B,
because it could be,
it's impossible for S to sort of take you know the logs,
let them grow for a while
and then basically splice these two logs together again.
Because you know the, because these entries should protect all these preceding entries,
these entries protect all the preceding entries with those
and so you can't put them back together.
And because the signatures wouldn't check out,
because the signatures always covered the current entry for all the preceding entries.
And so the only thing they are basically do,
the server can do basically split the world, fork the world into different into two different logs,
they might have a common log at the beginning,
then to sort of fork them,
now that you know A and B basically operate in different worlds.
So, and that's sort of the definition fork consistency
and that's basically the best you know this particular file system, this particular system can do,
if there's, the only communication actually happens between S.
Notice is actually by the way,
that's sort of fork consistency is good enough for our particular applications zookeeper correct,
because the, either the server shows the old version, you know without A B,
or you know the server shows the S,
you know the modification with A and B.
Okay, so what do you do,
it seems like you know maybe this is actually [],
how do you detect forks and how could you.
So how do you detect fork,
well there's two schemes, that paper mentions,
one is out-of-band communication,
it is pretty straightforward,
you know if you know A and B ever talk to each other,
for example ask each other,
hey, what did your last entry in the log
and they get different answers,
they know you know that they have been fork,
because either they could have different answers,
but at least then one should be the prefix of the other,
and if that's not the case,
then they know that they're actually being exactly fork.
So, that's one possible scenario, that they discussed in the paper,
basically share the clients periodically exchange during the last log entries,
the last entry in their log.
Another solution which actually has mentioned in the chat is,
you know introduce what they call sort of trusted machine,
that is time stamp box
and basically like every few seconds,
you know it actually ends adds a time stamp to the log
and in every client, knows that you know, basically it's a file,
in the file system that contains you know the current time,
everytime the time stamp box,
you know every couple seconds time stamp box updates that file,
the clients read that file
and they know there should be a new modification like every couple seconds.
And that basically you know that that fork that contains the time stamp box is sort of the fork the the clients,
the server actually has to present to the clients.
Okay?
So that's the two things that actually the paper discusses
and what's sort of interesting and we'll see on Tuesday,
is this, this whole fork detection in fork resolution approach
is sort of a key problem basically in Bitcoin,
and we will talking Tuesday,
but Bitcoin you know we see a way basically to settle on a fork.
So even if the file system or the servers,
the Byzantine servers actually have created a fork,
you know Bitcoin basically has a way of deciding,
well we're gonna reads the [consensus] on like which fork we're going to actually proceed with.
So we'll leave that up to Tuesday,
but here sort of a connection between you know SUNDR and actually Bitcoin.
Any questions about this?
Okay.
Okay, I want to talk very quickly,
because I got three minutes left,
about the other,
so I think the key thing I'll get the paper is actually this log conceptual view of the world,
of course the impractical as I mentioned earlier
and so some directly has a proposal for how to do better,
even though like other systems like going actually do maintain the whole log
and so what does somebody do things better,
instead of actually maintaining a log,
you know that's actually snapshots.
That's similar to sort of snapshots,
that we've seen before, in a raft,
where we construct the part of the world based on log,
we take a snapshot
and that actually forms the the current state,
in fact, really what the SUNDR does,
it actually doesn't really literally [take] snapshot,
it really maintains a snapshot view of the file system
and does it per user.
So one way to think about it is that,
that file systems is sharded by user,
every user has its own view snapshot of the world
and you know there's a little bit of protocol
to make sure that these different snapshots and different users are actually consistent.
And let me, talk a little bit about,
how actually SUNDR actually has makes the snapshot.
Basically in SUNDR,
and SUNDR basically there's something that's called the user i-handle,
and the user i-handle basically uniquely identifies snapshot in the file system
and basically is a cryptographic hash of the i-table,
which completes all the inodes in the system,
and you know and for every inode,
there's a hash inode,
it would basically covers all the data, all the blocks belong to that particular inode.
So, for example, when say A modifies auth.py in my write one block,
the client re-computes the hash of this block,
updates the entry here, updates the entry here, updates the entry here
and that's basically a new handle,
that describes basically the the capture you know the complete file system,
we're going to ignore the group in the directory block for a second,
so this basically gives you complete checkpoint,
where a snapshot of user to view of the file system,
now and then to deal with this issue,
of how to get a sort of consistency across users,
they have this notion of version vectors.
What version vector is pretty straightforward,
every version vector has, an i-handle,
like A has i-handle is in it after it modified, say auth.py
and then for every user in the system,
the version vector has a counter for the number of modifications, that were made by that user,
so if A made updated auth.py, that counter is set to one,
you know B didn't make any modifications,
you know C didn't make any modifications, zero zero,
and this whole thing is silent.
And so when B makes modifications,
so we use the version vector for B, A version vector, B version vector,
it creates a new handle,
that includes of course, all the modification, represents all the medications
and in its version handle,
it actually opened its version vector,
it includes which how many operations are read by [] user,
so it will record the fact, for example that it actually saw A's modification,
it updates B is to be 1, C is 0,
and basically signed to this whole thing.
You know C, when C actually does an operation,
want to read you know auth.py
and fetch you know and bank.py,
it basically downloads all the version vectors from every user,
you know and in this case,
it will get the first version vector for A and B,
takes the latest one, which in this case is B,
because actually it includes all the operations of A in it
and that's basically represented version of the file system,
from that version it reads you know auth.py and bank.py.
Note, you know that basically it's impossible for the server to basically present bank.py, not auth.py,
because you know it cannot,
you know it can only to sort of version factors can return is,
this version vector or this version vector,
version vector A doesn't include actually the changes of bank.py,
if C actually does get versions of bank.py,
it must actually have the versions, the modification A is made,
because the version vectors are constructed in that way.
And so that's basically the way for using version vectors
to detect the S doesn't drop changes,
as we as the same way that the logging system is done.
Okay, so that's the essence of the version vector plan.
So, in summary.
Okay, Byzantine participants you know sort of a problem you have to handle in decentralized systems,
because there's no single institution that sort of,
it can be source of trust
and we've seen this notion of signed logs,
it's a very powerful tool to deal with malicious servers.
And, as I said, on on Tuesday,
we're going to continue this discussion
and you'll see how this design logs are used in Bitcoin,
in particular like how fork consistency,
where how the fact that forks are sort of being created,
are being resolved in the case of Bitcoin.
Okay, so that was it for an introduction to the decentralized systems,
and I hope the paper a little bit more understandable
than maybe when before you start reading it earlier this week or today.
Okay, see you on Tuesday.
And of course, there's questions, feel free, please feel free to hang around,
if you need to go somewhere else, absolutely go somewhere else.
I have a question about the data structure,
that they use the B+ tree or whatever,
like what's the difference between that and like,
yeah, like the [] log, for example.
Using a [] data structure,
you know I think the person who sort of credited with his id is [],
and that's why it called the miracle data tree.
So this is the same thing?
Okay.
SUNDR basically uses a [] tree.
Sorry, when when you are verifying the the signatures,
doesn't mean you have to,
like, basically, as you go,
if you're a hundred entries into the log,
you have to compute the hash of all the 100 entries concatenated and then compute, and.
Yeah, you need to keep a running hash,
okay, let's go back to verify,
okay, so here is probably a good place to talk about it.
So, so here, so let's say, let's take the last entry, correct,
the last century will have a hash of the preceding entries,
so everything you know from the like whatever records,
let's say this is zero one and two 0 1 and 2, where basically has the hash of the previous entry number 2 in it,
and that needs to be, that needs to be checked.
And the way now this being checked is,
you know in principle, if you start really from the beginning of the world
and you would have to compute the hash with record 0,
you find out what the hash is
and double check that corresponds to the entry, that's in here
and that the signature is valid, etc, etc.
Of course, you know in the real system,
you can remember most of the log
and just double check that,
like whatever and start from there.
Oh, it's inefficient, okay.
Yeah, you have to replay from the beginning of time,
you basically have to really validate the whole log from the beginning of time.
Thank you, it makes sense.
You'll see this in the Bitcoin paper.
So are the hash is like,
almost like a [merkle] chain, like.
Yes.
Okay, same idea.
So, are they, like if like leaf in the sort of tree or chain,
like an entire file or like blocks of a file.
This is a block, one block,
so this 4096 bytes,
and all the other hashes don't change, correct,
so it's actually not that efficient inefficient.
Because if you only change part of the file,
that only rehashes that part.
Yeah you just have to rehash that one
and then you have to re-compute the hash of the tree,
all the way to the users i-handle.
The paper talks about, there's a sort of optimization to make this more efficient,
but hashing is generally not that expensive,
signing is a more expensive operation.
I had a question about version vectors,
so we use version vectors to make sure that the system can't return like an old state,
why can't the, why can't the system just return the old state and the old version vector,
if it keeps a second copy.
Yeah, got fork, right?
So we only have fork consistency, then.
Yeah, your version vectors only fork consistent, SUNDR fork consistent, no more.
So fork consistency, you need the timestamp?
The fork consistency, I mean, you know, the server can fork the log at any particular point in time,
present a consistent view of the what they can merge logs back together.
So, really this picture, that the server can actually construct you know different views of the world
and split you know the world, the multiple world,
but can emerge the world back together undetectably.
So, the best we can do is fork consistency,
which allows for forking,
but we can detect forking.
So if we detect forking,
can we then get something stronger than fork consistency?
Well, yep, well, we can settle on a fork,
we're gonna have forks,
we can try to settle like pick one forks one to go forward with.
Okay,
but SUNDR doesn't have a way to do that.
I mean SUNDR does propose some some methods now?
Methods to detect and basically you know basically proposes like you use the timestamp box to use that one.
Thanks.
You're welcome.
The timestamp timestamp box just a server that appends entries.
And is trusted, it was not under control of the adversary.
Thank you.
Can I also ask one final question about the debian example, you set up in beginning,
can you say again what happened there.
Yeah, sure,
so basically the this is the source repo or develop machines for debian Linux in 2003,
an attacker compromised broke into this machines and modified files,
and this is the distribution that has been sort of handed off you know which you know if you're on debian Linux,
you know you're you're,
anybody who got like the debian linux after attack,
you've got maybe a compromise debian Linux.
And so when they soon as they discovered this,
they didn't do any further development
and they were refer to distributions,
sorted out like they went to backups,
you know started comparing files from backups, with files that they have,
and you know basically double check that all the changes that were in the repo are actually legit.
Okay.
Rollback and rollback any changes are not legit.
That's pretty bad.
Yeah, that's pretty bad,
it occasionally happens,
this is a real problem,
that's a real problem in practice.
Thank you so much that was very interesting lecture, thank you.
You're welcome.
Thank you.