We'll talking about is spark
and so this goes back to almost the beginning of the semester,
where you know we talked quite a bit about mapreduce,
in fact you know lab 1 that you implemented mapreduce.
So, and really what's you know sort of informally you know the spark is basically the successor you know to hadoop,
and hadoop is the open source version of mapreduce.
So I think today, you know people typically will use spark instead of hadoop,
and so it's really widely used.
And it's widely used for data science computation,
so people that you know have lots of data that need to run some computation over it,
require a ton of machines,
you know spark is designed for that particular case,
it is commercialized by a company called databricks,
you know Matei Zaharia who is the author, of the main author of this paper, his PhD thesis,
started with a number of other people,
this company databricks which commercializes spark,
but it also supports the Apache open source spark version,
it's been a pretty popular open source project or very popular open source project.
It is one reason I sort of replaced you know the use of hadoop is,
because it actually supports wider range, wider range of applications than mapreduce can,
in particular, was very good at these iterative.
Oops what happened there,
let me see something maybe external crash, hold on a second.
Okay, fortunately, we're in good shape,
okay, so it supports a wide range of applications,
in particular is good at these iterative applications,
so applications where multiple rounds of mapreduce operations,
so if you have an application that requires one set of mapreduce followed by another set of mapreduce followed by another mapreduce computation,
spark is really good at it
and the reason is so good at it is,
because basically it keeps the intermediate results in memory
and that's really good support, programming support for doing so.
In some ways, you know, so if there's any connection at all between the previous paper and this paper,
which basically is not but you know they're all both targeted to sort in memory computations,
you know for datasets that basically fit in memory,
in the previous paper and FaRM paper is all about you know the database filling in memory,
here's the data set the data science computation,
for data science computation that you want to do.
Of course, you know since 2012 when this paper was published,
a lot of things have happened,
the, spark is not really tied to scala, sort of described in the paper,
but there are other language front ends,
for example but probably more importantly you know the rdd has defined in this paper,
slightly deprecated,
and replace by dataframes,
but dataframes the way to think about it,
the way I think about it,
this is basically column is rdd with [explicit] columns
and all the good ideas of rdds are also true for dataframes.
And so from the rest of the lecture,
I'm just gonna talk about rdds
and think about them as equivalently as to dataframes.
Any questions before I proceed?
And then quick other point,
maybe this research is really quite successful, widely used,
also [] you know received the ACM doctoral thesis award,
for this for this thesis that basically is all about spark.
So it's quite unusual actually for a doctoral thesis,
that to have that kind of impact.
Okay?
So the way I want to talk about spark by just looking at the so many examples,
because I think you get the best,
you, you understand the programming model,
but that is based on rdds
best by this I think looking at examples,
and you get the best idea of what actually in RDD is.
And so let me pull up some of the examples, that were in the paper,
then we'll walk through those.
Look this one, so let's start here, a very simple example.
And so you know the idea is that,
in this example is that,
you know first of all, you can sort of, use spark interactively,
so you can see that startup spark at the workstation or laptop
and start interacting with spark you know the way you you type in commands like this.
And so now what does this command do,
you know this basically creates an RDD,
you know called this RDDs, lines is an RDD
and I just represents the RDD that actually stored in hdfs
and you know the hdfs you know might be have many partitions you know for this particular file,
so for example the first thousand or a million records list on like partition one,
there's next million live in partition two,
and the next million live to partition three,
then this RDD lines basically represents you know that that set of partitions.
When you run this line or you type in this line in return,
return basically nothing really happens,
and so this is what the paper refers to as lazy computations,
in fact computations executed somewhat later
and we'll see in a second line,
but at this particular point to line,
the only thing that's actually happened is that
there is a line lines object that happens to be in RDD.
And, RDD you know supports a wide range of operations,
we can actually look a little bit with some operations that it supports.
Yeah, so it's used as an RDD has an API
and it turns out that the methods of the API
or the methods on RDD fail in two classes,
one are the, are Actions,
and actions are really the operations that will actually cause computation to happen,
so all the lazily sort of build up computation really happens at the point, that you're run an action
and as an example, you run count or collect,
then, the spark computation actually is executed.
All the other API or methods are Transformations,
and they basically take one RDD and turn it into another RDD,
it turns out that every RDD is actually read-only or immutable,
so you can't modify an RDD,
can only basically generate new RDDs form an existing one.
And so if we look at the second line,
this basically creates a second RDD RDD errors,
and that one is created by running a filter on the lines RDD,
so the lines RDD read only, read only you can run this method to filter on it,
which in this case, basically filters out all the record [] start with all the lines that start with the message error or string error,
and that represents a new RDD
and again at this point nothing actually really being computed
is usually a recipe or a built over almost a data flow
or what the paper calls iterative graph of the computation.
Also, when the computation actually starts running,
it hasn't run yet,
but when it will start running,
these operations are pipelined with that they mean,
so for example in stage one you know the this computation of the lines,
the stage one will read some set of records,
you know from for example this first partition,
and then, do its processing on it,
if there's anything and then handed off to stage two,
you know which stage two basically you know doing this filter,
and so in stage two you know the, the, this filter will run
and sort of grab the lines that actually are match.
And you know basically produce with that new RDD,
that just contains you know the lines,
you know strings, that start with lines,
that start with the string error.
And while this sort of secondary RDD,
second stage runs you know the first stage you know grab the next set of records from the file system,
and then you know fetch them again to stage two
and so as you go further, you have more and more stages in your pipeline,
where your iterative graph and all those stages are going to be running sort of parallel,
and that's what I mean with lecture pipelining the transformations.
Okay, so,x so here this this you know this line basically describes
how to create RDD error,
RDD errors RDD and then this lines basically like,
tells spark to basically keep a copy of this RDD in memory.
So if subsequent computation run that you do more stuff with errors,
spark will actually keep the original RDD actually in memory,
so that, it can be shared with later computation,
so for example if you wanted to reuse the error file,
then that error file will be in memory,
doesn't have to be reconstructed from the files,
directly represent the hdfs and allows you to run the second computation.
And here for example one already know even in this simple example,
you'll see there's a big difference between this and mapreduce,
where can the mapreduce job and you run the computation, it ends,
and then, if you want to redo something with the data,
you have to reread it in from the file system in using this sort of persistent method,
spark can avoid, you know having to reread that data from the disk,
and you know save a lot of time.
Any questions so far?
And so when the error file gets extracted from P1 let's say
and then there's another error file that gets extracted from P2,
so my understanding is that, this happened in parallel?
Yes, so you can think about it,
like you know they're going to be many worker, like in mapreduce
and the workers work on each partition,
basically, you know the scheduler will sent a job you know to each of the workers,
and a job is a task you know pertains to a particular partition,
and workers start working on get one of these tasks
and basically start running.
So you get parallelism between the partitions
and you get parallelism between the stages in the pipeline.
I see, thank you.
That's awesome.
What's the.
Sorry.
Can you hear me.
What's the difference between lineage and the like just the log of transactions, that we've seen before,
like is it just the granularity of the operations.
As we'll see lineage log is strictly linear, right
and the examples that we've seen so far,
the lineage is also linear,
but we'll see later examples where we have forks,
where one stage depends on multiple different RDDs
and you know that's not representative in the log.
You know there share some similarities in the sense,
that like you're starting the beginning state,
all the operations are deterministic
and then you'll end up in some if you apply all those operations,
will end in some deterministic end state,
so in that sense, there's some similarity,
but you know I think they're quite different.
I also have a question, in this case filter,
so it works by just applying filter on each partition,
but sometimes like I see the transformation also contained join or sort.
Yeah,let's talk about a little bit,I will talk about sort and join in a second,
they're clearly much more complicated.
So is do we, but like this persist is when we start computing.
No, nothing has been computed yet, still all [descriptions],
so let's talk a little bit further.
Let's look at actually something that actually generates the computation.
So, here are two commands that actually result in computation,
so this command will result in computation,
because it contains count, which is an action
and this command will result in a computation collect is an action.
And so yeah and so you can,
so we look like,
so the reason that they show two commands,
because they demonstrate that basically you can reuse errors,
and so if you look at you know this computation,
yeah, then you can draw the lineage graph,
right, so start with lines,
there was a filter that we ran,
oops, sorry,
let me just read slightly differently,
there was a filter on lines, that we just saw that produces errors,
or that's a description, how to get errors,
then there's in this case, there's another filter,
it's the filter of hdfs,
and that basically produces another RDD,
you know that RDD is not explicitly named here,
but it does produce another RDD,
so I was going to call it hdfs,
because the filter on hdfs.
And then, we see there's a map,
and that produces yet another RDD,
again this RDD doesn't really have a name here, but so it's anonymous,
I'm just gonna give it a name, that's time,
because basically splits the one your line into three pieces
and grabs the [third] piece out of that line
and that happens to be the time,
and then, there's a final you know operation and that's collect,
which actually comes up all the number of times, that time actually appears
or the number of entries basically result of the in the RDD produced, in the time RDD.
Okay?
So this, so this is actually this point,
when you know the return you hit return here
in the user interface or in the interactive user interface it is
and at that point basically spark you know will collect you know a lot of a set of workers,
split you know send them the jobs
or basically inform the scheduler that job needs to be executed
and the description of the task that needs to be executed this lineage graph.
And so we can sort of think a little bit about exactly how the execution happens,
so let me draw a picture,
so the pictures follows we got there's what's called the driver, that's the usual thing,
you know what is the program that the user typed into,
it start of collecting a bunch of workers,
you know in a bunch of machines,
all over the same way like as in mapreduce.
And you know there's gonna be a hdfs,
there's lines file, that actually has partitions are P1, P2 whatever, blah blah blah.
And typically the number of partitions is larger than the number of workers,
sorry, number of, yes number of partitions is larger than the number of workers,
you know you get load balance is, like one partition is small and the other one is big
and you don't want to have workers are relying sitting around idle.
And basically the scheduler, you know there's a scheduler runs you know basically the computation
and it has you know the information that has the lineage graphs
And so worker is basically check in you know the driver exercising the code, spark program
and we just constructed
and the worker should go basically to the scheduler,
say please you know which partition should I work.
And, then they run basically part of the pipeline,
and so we look at this,
let me actually draw this slightly different,
so I have a little bit more space here.
So we saw there was a whole bunch of stages
and then the last stage was the last operate was to collect stage.
So in this, in this scenario that we just looked at,
the collect stage, of course needs to collect data from older partitions, right,
so in principle, now let's draw a green line,
basically everything of this, it was executed on an independent partition,
so every worker gets one of these tasks from the scheduler,
runs you know the thing and produces in the end on time RDD,
and when the scheduler you know determines that basically all the time,
you know, like all these stages, this is called the stage,
if all the stages have completed
and so all the time partitions have been produced,
then it actually will run you know the collect action to basically do the addition
and retrieve information from every partition,
to actually compute the collect
or actually this is not collect, it was a count, sorry about that.
And so one sort of way to think about this is
that this is sort of like almost like a mapreduce
where you have the map phase,
and then you have a shuffle
and then you run the reduce phase
and the count is almost similar in that fashion,
and in the paper, the way they refer to this is,
this dependency if although there's a wide dependency,
because the action or the transformation is dependent on a number of partitions
and these are called narrow, narrow dependencies,
because, this RDD,
to make that RDD is only dependent on one another,
only at the, only dependent on the parent partition,
only one parent partition to actually be able to compute it.
So generally you you would prefer computation have narrow dependencies,
because they can just run locally without any communication, before wide dependency,
you might have to collect, you might have to collect partitions from the parent
or you may have to collect partitions from the parent RDD from all the machines.
Professor.
Yeah.
I had a question,
so in the paper, it says narrow dependencies,
where each partition of the parent RDD is used by at most one partition of the child RDD,
but it doesn't say anything about the the control,
the [] is like, it doesn't say like a child partition needs to use at most one, one parent.
Yeah, that's correct, because then.
Yeah, if a child uses multiple parent partition,
then it's a wide dependency.
If a parent, sorry.
If, if the child meets the partition,
if the partition for multiple parent partitions,
then it's a wide dependency.
So, for example in the count case, correct,
you know you have time, time partitions.
Right.
And the count operation is going to collect data from all of them.
So if count where at RDD,
it isn't like, it's just an action,
but even we're in RDD,
then basically you know that would require interaction with all the parents.
What I'm saying is,
I think I think it's just the opposite, right.
I I think this might like,
I mean I I I I was actually confused,
like with the paper.
On this specific issue.
But as it says,
like each partition of the parent RDD is used by at most one partition of the child,
but it doesn't say one partition of the child uses it most.
I'm not actually sure you know exactly why you're confused with this,
so let me know when we can postpone this and come back to it.
Sure.
I think the key thing observers basically two types of dependency,
wide ones and narrow ones
and wide ones basically you know basically involve communication,
because they have to talk to the,
collecting the information from the from the parent partitions.
Okay?
Thanks.
I actually have a question on interface,
like the previous one or two slides,
what happens if we don't call errors.persist.
If you do not, then,
the you were the second computation,
like this computation would re-compute errors from the beginning.
So if you run this workload,
the spark you know computation would re-compute errors,
you know from a the starting file.
Got it, thank you.
So I actually have a question about this point,
so for the partitions that we don't call persist on,
in the mapreduce case,
we basically stored them in intermediate files,
but we nonetheless stored them in a local file system,
let's say in the case of mapreduce,
do we actually store intermediate files here,
that we don't persist in some persistent storage
or we just keep the whole flow in memory, rather.
By default, the whole flow is in memory,
except you can provide to,
there's one exception that we'll talk about a little bit more in detail in a second, hopefully,
which is you see this persist here,
this persist here take another flag, I think it's called reliable,
and then, that a set is actually stored in hdfs, basically called this a checkpoint.
I see, thank you.
I have a quick question about the partitioning,
that with partitioning, the RDDs initially,
is it initially hdfs who partitions them for each worker to operate on is spark handling.
This lines are in hdfs,
you know the partition is defined basically by the files directly in hdfs,
you can repetition,
and you'll see in a second that actually it might be the stages to do so,
for example using this hash partition trick,
and you can define also your own partitioner,
there's a partitioner object or abstraction that you can supply.
So, it's already handled by hdfs,
but if you want to do it again to spark,
then you can.
Of course files are also created by this files,
presumably, you're created by logging system that sits on the side
and just produce different partitions
or you know you can reshuffle if you want to.
Makes sense, thank you.
Okay, so,
and so let me,
so that's the execution model,
and I want to talk a little bit about fault tolerance.
And so let's go back to this, this sort of fault tolerance
and the thing that we worry about fault tolerance is that,
maybe one of these workers you know might crash, right,
then the worker had is computing some partition
and so we need to re-execute that
and as basically this plans are the same as mapreduce, right,
were if a worker crashes,
we need to, in mapreduce and the map tasks need to be re-executed
and perhaps maybe reduce task has to be re-executed,
now in here, the task is slightly more complicated,
because they're basically like these stages
and so it means that if one worker fails,
we may have to re-compute the stage.
So, let's talk a little bit more about that,
that sort of perspective from fault tolerance, right,
that's what we're trying to achieve.
This is really different than like the fail tolerance that were you implemented in lab 2 or 3 or paxos
and stable storage and all that kind of stuff,
and here really what we're we're worried about is crash of a worker,
the worker loses its memory, lost memory,
and that means losses partition. And you know later part of the competition are probably dependent on that partition
and so we need to reread or re-compute this partition.
And so the solution is exactly like in mapreduce,
you know basically the scheduler notice at some point that doesn't get an answer,
and then reruns the stage for that partition.
And you know and what is the cool part,
like exactly as it in mapreduce all if we look at all these transformations that are sitting here in the API,
all these transformations are functional.
So they basically take one input,
they take an RDD as an input,
they produce another RDD as output,
and just completely deterministic.
And so like you know in mapreduce you know these maps and reduce for functional operations,
if you restart a stage where a sequence of transformations from the same input,
then you'll produce the same output
and so you recreate the same partition,
recreate partitions [].
Okay?
Sorry, is this why they are immutable?
There's also the reason, I think they're [] immutable, yes.
Okay, there's one tricky case though, which I want to talk about,
so this the fault tolerance is basically for the narrow case,
it's the same as sort of as we saw before in mapreduce,
but you know the tricky case is actually the wide dependencies.
So let's say you know we have you know some transformations,
and, one of these transformations is dependent on
a you know this is like sort of here is one worker, here is another worker,
and another worker.
And one of these stages is actually dependent on a number of parent partitions,
so let's say whatever maybe this is a join
or we'll see later other operations,
where you know we're actually collecting information for lots of partitions,
and you know create a RDD from that,
from that RDD that might be used again by a map or whatever keep going
and so now let's say you know we're we're worker and we crash here,
then we need to reconstruct this RDD,
and you know we sort of followed,
that means that we have to, we could also recompute this RDD,
to recompute this RDD on this worker,
that means we also need the partitions on the other workers.
And, so, the and reconstruction the execution of a competition on a particular worker, a particular partition
may actually result that actually these ones also need to be recomputed.
Of course, you can do this partially in parallel,
you can just ask you know please, you know start to repeat this guy,
we can see that guy,
and you know produce then the final RDD again,
but you know certainly you know failure, one worker going to result in the recomputation of many many partitions,
and that sort of slightly, it could be slightly costly,
and so the solution is that as a programmer,
you can say you can actually checkpoint or persist RDDs on stable storage.
And so you might decide,
for example, this is an RDD that,
then you don't want to recompute in the case of a failure,
because it requires you know recomputing all the different partitions,
you may want to checkpoint this RDD.
And then we know this stage,
when actually when this you know computation needs to be reexecuted,
gonna actually read you know the results of the partitions from the checkpoint
instead of actually having to recompute them from scratch.
And so this is why spark supports checkpoints
and that's sort of their fault tolerance story for wide dependencies.
Any questions about this?
I I had one question.
So there was, so you persist right just in general,
but they, they also mentioned a reliable flag.
Hmm.
So I was wondering,
like what's the difference between just persisting and using a reliable flag.
Persist just means you're gonna keep that RDD in memory
and you're not going to throw it away,
so you can reuse it in later competitions in and use in memory,
the checkpoint or reliability flag basically means,
you actually write a copy of the whole RDD to hdfs.
And hdfs is a persistent or a stable storage file system.
Is there a way to tell spark to unpersist something,
because otherwise like for example if you persist in RDD
and you do a lot of computations,
but like those later computations number use the RDD,
you might just have it sticking around in memory forever.
Yeah, oh yeah, so we,
I I presume you can or there's a general strategy that spark uses,
they talk a little bit about this
is that they have there's really no space anymore,
they might spill some RDDs to hdfs or remove them,
the the paper slightly vague on exactly you know what their plan for that is.
Thank you.
Of course, when the competition ends and a user you logout, or you stop your driver,
then I think you know those RDDs definitely gone from memory.
Okay?
Okay, so that is almost you know the story of spark,
the you know we've seen what a RDD is,
we've seen how the execution works
and we've seen how the fault tolerance plan works,
the thing that I want to talk about is another example
to really show off where spark shines
and that is an iterative example.
So in competition that has an iterative structure,
and the particular one I want to talk about the PageRank.
I assume most of you are familiar with page rank in some form,
basically it's a plan to algorithm to give weight or important to web pages,
and this dependent on the number of links that point to a particular web page,
so for example if you have a web page U1, main points to itself,
you have maybe a web page U3,
so I'll use an example and web page U2,
U2 has a link to itself and to U3
and maybe you know U3 has a link to U1.
And basically page rank is an algorithm based on these connectivities,
computers you know the importance of a web page
and page rank for sort of the early one of the algorithms,
that really drove the Google search machine,
in the sense that if you had a search result,
the way you rank search result is that,
if search result appears on a more important web page,
you know that results gets promoted to higher in the list,
and that was one of the reasons early days,
Google search machine actually produce better search results,
were the more important information actually order more important webpages were on top.
And so the paper talks about shows off the implementation of page rank in spark.
So here's the implementation of the spark implementation of the page rank
and as before you know this is just a description,
so we look at the individual lines,
you know, these are just the recipe to actually how do compute page rank
and only when like you know in this particular case,
if you do say ranks collect at the very end,
and then actually competition would run on you know the cluster of machines
and using sort of execution pattern that we've seen so far.
And so I want to walk through this example a little bit more detail,
to get a sense you know what, to get a better sense,
why spark are shines in the iterative case.
So, there are two RDDs here,
I'm also going to talk about some optimizations that are cool in spark,
one of these links RDDs
and links is basically represents the connection of the graphs
and so precisely it probably has a line,
I'm going to write it like that, as a line per url,
so here U1, it has two outgoing links,
U1 U3,
actually, I missed one link here.
And then, you know the U2, entry for U2 which has now going to U2 and U3,
and there is an entry, you know U3 going to U1.
So this is basically a description of, you will the world wide web,
and of course you know my tiny little example, I have three web pages,
but if you know were running this at the scale of Google,
you would have a billion web pages, right,
and so this file is gigantic and it's partitioned in partitions.
So that's links,
and then ranks is a similar file
that contains the current ranks for these web pages
and so you can think about these as a U1, you know comma you know it's rank,
and let's assume the ranks initialized 1.0
and then you know here's 1.0,
then U2 you know 1.0,
U3 1.0.
And we see actually that the links,
the links are these is actually persisted in memory,
that presumably in the same way as the error file that we saw before, the error RDD.
And then ranks, it's initialized to something
and then basically there's sort of description of number of iterations to produce new ranks RDD.
You can see a little bit how this actually plays out,
and one of the things we notice is
that links gets reused in every iteration,
and length actually gets joined with ranks,
what means what does it mean,
to actually do this join up this this,
this operation, this operation basically creates an RDD
and we wonder how does the RDD look like,
well that RDD is going to look like U1,
you know, and then the joining of the ranks in the, and the link file,
so it's gonna be U1 U1 U2,
because those are U3 outgoing links plus the rank for U1,
which I'm going to go write as R1.
And that's sort of the RDD that's being produced here
and so same thing for you know whatever U2,
and the one for U3 is whatever U1 and you know R3 rank for 3,
basically merges these two, as literally joins the two files based on key.
Okay?
And then you know it runs a computation of flatMap on this
and that flatMap itself internally has a map over links,
so basically it's going to run over,
like the screen is going to run over these lists
and basically partition or divide up the rank you know to the outgoing urls.
And so it will you know create triples of the form,
let me write this in green then,
U1 R1 divided by 2,
and U1 or U3 over the outgoing links,
so give 1 to U1, 1 to U3,
here's U3, R1, divided over 2, etc,
it creates triples of this kind of form,
so basically it computers the way divides that rank across the outgoing edges
and gives you know the values of these ranks you know to the outgoing edges,
so the outgoing edges, so we got a big RDD that has you know this form,
that's produced basically, that is the contributions RDD.
Then there's a final step in the,
I think it first has to be reduced by key,
so basically grabs all the U1's you know together and then sums them,
so basically this will result is that,
you know all the weights or the fractional weights,
you know that U1 is going to receive are being added up.
So, U1 of course is going to receive weight from itself,
this one is going to relate from U3,
and so you will sum up,
there's going to be R1 divided by 2
and R3 divided by 1,
and that was basically the sum, that's been created.
And so that gives us a list of sums
and then that's when they are added up
and computed into a final value.
It produces the new ranks RDD,
which has the same shape as the one that we saw before, namely this shape,
for every web page, there is a number.
Does this makes sense?
And so, it's interesting to know that sort of description,
so first of all, you can see that,
actually the description of page rank quite precise
and there's one examples,
this is like if you had to run this in a mapreduce style,
then that would mean that every iteration of this loop,
at the end of the iteration,
you would store the results in the file system,
and then you reread you know the iteration from the result for the next iteration
and in in this spark system, uses every iteration runs straight out of memory, leaves results in memory,
so that the next iteration could pick it up right there,
and furthermore you know these links file is shared among all the iterations.
Okay, so to get a little bit more sense,
like you know why, there's also a cool,
the way to look at is to actually look at the lineage graph for this particular competition.
So let's look at the lineage graph for,
so here's the lineage graph for the for page rank.
And so a couple things I want to point out,
first of all, so the lineage graphs like dynamic,
almost it looks,
you know just keep growing you know with the number of iterations,
and so as the schedule you know basically computes does new stages,
then, it keeps going,
and you know we can see what the stages are gonna be, correct,
because, you know sort of, you know every iteration of a loop is one stage
and will basically append you know parts of transformations to the lineage graph.
So we see here's the input file, here's links
and as we saw the links actually created ones,
then persisted in memory,
we're not on this, persist in memory
and is being reused many many times,
like every loop iteration basically the ranks being reused
and so again, we're compared to mapreduce,
if you have to write this to mapreduce style,
you don't get that we use
and so that's of course going to tremendously performance,
because links you know as we said before,
it's like just gigantic file,
that basically corresponds to one line for every web page in the in the universe.
Another interesting thing to observe here is that
we see a wide dependencies here, right,
this is a wide dependency,
could be the wide dependency,
will be a little bit more sophisticated about this in a second,
because basically these contributions you know when we contribute to the intermediate result,
it is a join across ranks and links,
and so it needs the partitions from links,
and it needs partitions from ranks to basically to compute partition for contribute, contrib RDD, sorry.
So that might require you know from from a network communication.
But it turns out they have sort of a clever optimization,
and this is in response to an earlier question about partitioning
the you can specify you want to partition and RDD, using a hash partition.
And what does that mean is that,
the links and ranks file, these two RDDs are going to be partitioned in the same way
and they're actually partition by key or by the hash key.
So we look back at our previous picture,
the keys for ranks, you know, are U1 U2 U3,
the keys for links.
Okay, so the key for ranks U1 U2 U3,
keys for links are also U1 U2 U3.
And basically, the client for optimization,
this is a standard optimization from the database literature,
is that if you partition links and ranks by key,
then you know this one is going to have U1 on one machine,
now, maybe this is U2 on one machine,
and ranks just going to have the same thing,
just gonna have U1 on one machine
and in fact you know it's going to have U1 on the same machine,
as links one saying for U2 and U3.
So even though this join is [perceptually] wide dependency,
it can be executed like a narrow dependency,
because basically to compute you know the join of these two,
for the U1 for the first partition, for P1,
you only have to look at the partition P1 of links
and P1 P1 of ranks,
because you know the keys are hashed in the same way to the same machine.
And so the scheduler or the programmer can actually specify these hash partitions,
scheduler sees, ha, you know the join actually uses hash partitions,
the hash partitions that are the same,
and therefore actually don't have to do this wide dependency,
I don't have to do a complete barrier as mapreduce,
but I can just treat this as an narrow dependency.
So, that's pretty cool,
then you know again,
if a machine fails, right,
we talked a little bit about it earlier,
that might be a painful,
because you may have to reexecute many loops or one iterations
and so, you know if you would probably write this for real,
then, the programmer would probably say,
like maybe every you know 10 iterations you know basically checkpoint,
so that you don't have to recompute computation all the way from from the beginning.
Oh, so we don't actually recompute links or anything each time, right,
like we don't persist, sorry.
We don't persist, no, not at all,
the only thing that was persist with only one was links, right,
this is the only thing that was kind of persist call.
Oh, we do persistent.
Links, we do.
Okay.
But not the intermediate RDDs,
because they're basically new RDD every time,
like ranks one is a new RDD,
ranks 2 is a new RDD.
But you may want to persist them, you know occasionally and stored in hdfs,
so that if you have to a failure, you don't have to go back to iteration loop, iteration zero to compute everything.
Okay, does this make sense?
Oh, sorry, the different contribs, can they be computed in parallel?
On different partitions, yes.
Because there's like this line that goes vertically down.
That vertically down, it's pipelines, right,
there's just two types of parallelism,
there stage parallelism,
and there is sort of parallelism between different partitions,
and we could think about this thing, you know this whole thing,
like running many many times on different partitions.
So in this case, the collect at the very end will be the only place where we have a wide.
Yeah, exactly exactly,
the collect is the only one that's gonna,
yeah whatever we're we have more partitions correct,
I making a mess of this picture,
but that is gonna have to get it from everyone.
Okay, I hope that everyone sees this is actually pretty cool, right.
You know just by expressing these computations
and sort of lineage graph or data flow computation,
the scheduler has a bit of room for organizations like this,
it's exploding hash partitions,
the you know we get a lot of parallelism,
we can also reuse, you know we can keep the results of one RDD in memory,
so that we can reuse it for the next iteration
and you can sort of see,
that you know these techniques combined
you know going to give you significant performance optimization,
and allows you to express more powerful or more interesting computations.
So maybe with that I was like summarize this lecture.
So a couple things,
you know so RDDs are made by functional transformations,
they're group together in sort of lineage graph,
you can think about as a data flow graph,
and this gives the, this allows reuse,
it also allows some clever organizations by the scheduler.
And basically it was also more extra,
it's more expressiveness than you know mapreduce by itself,
and which results basically in good performance,
because a lot of the data stays in memory.
So if you actually if you're excited about this,
you can try it out,
you can download you know spark play around and write some programs,
or you know go to databricks.com
and you're creating accounts
and then you can run spark computations on their on their clusters.
So we're excited about this and want to try it out,
you know it's pretty easy to do so,
unlike FaRM, you can just like not play with,
but this actually you can actually go out and try out.
Okay, with that, I want to stop for today
and and the people that want to hang around and ask more questions,
please feel free to do so,
the only thing I want to remind people of is that
you know the deadline of for 4b is a little bit away,
but I just want to remind people the 4b is pretty tricky,
requires a bit of design,
so, don't don't start too late.
And with that I'll see you on Tuesday.
And again questions, I'm happy to answer them.
Thank you.
I had a question about the checkpoints,
I think if they mention automatic checkpoints,
using data about how long each computation took.
I wasn't really sure what they mean by this,
but what, what are they going to be optimizing for.
I'm gonna build a whole checkpoints is correct,
there's an optimization between,
you know taking checkpoint is expensive,
and so you know takes time,
in but in reexecution, if there's a machine failure,
also takes a lot of time.
And so for example if you take never checkpoint,
then you basically have to reexecute the competition from the beginning, right,
but if you take periodically checkpoints,
you know you don't have to repeat you know the computation that you did before the checkpoint,
but checking the checkpoint takes time.
So if you take very frequent checkpoints,
you don't have to recompute a lot,
but you spend all your time taking checkpoints.
And so there's sort of you know an optimization problem here,
you know you want to take the checkpoints
and some regular interval you're willing to take to recompute.
Okay, so maybe like compute checkpoints only for very large computations.
Yeah, or like for example in the case of page rank,
you know maybe you know do it ever 10 iterations.
Thank you.
It depends, of course, if decides to checkpoint,
but decides to check which follow you can check out more frequently.
But in the case of this page rank,
you know that checkpoint is going to be pretty big,
there is going to be a line or record you know per a web page.
That makes sense, thank you.
You're welcome.
I have a question about the driver,
does the application, is like does the driver, is the driver on the client side,
or is it.
Okay.
Yeah.
If it crashes, we lose like the the whole graph and that's fine,
because that's the application.
Yeah, I don't actually know what happens,
because the scheduler has a [],
and the scheduler fault tolerance,
so I don't know exactly when you know what happens,
maybe you could reconnect I I don't know.
I had a question about the why dependency optimization,
you mentioned that they do the hash partitioning,
how does that work.
Okay, I say a little bit more,
so this is not,
hasing is not something today,
then there is actually something that's is a standard database, partitioning scheme,
and it is cool,
because if you need computer join,
you don't have to do a lot of communication,
so let me just start a new slide,
it's because it's a little hard to read.
So hash partition,
so if you have two datasets,
here's dataset one, here's dataset two,
they have keys, right, key one, key two,
so they have the same set of keys,
then what you do by hash partitioning your partition the dataset and number of partitions,
so boom boom boom and you have to keep,
so you have K1, you has K2 and that actually determines the partition ends up.
And so all the keys that actually have the same hash went up in the same place,
so like this machine 1, machine 2, machine 3,
so you take whatever you hash K1, that goes in here,
you know you hash whatever K2, may be somewhere else in the file, who knows where it is
and you hash to partition.
You do the same thing here, for the other datasets,
so here's dataset one,
here's dataset two,
like links and ranks
and what will happen is that,
all the records in this dataset,
that have the same keys as records in the other dataset,
those keys or those records will end up in the same machine, right,
so you're gonna partition,
this guy and basically K1 will end up here too, on the same machine,
correct and same for the other keys,
because you basically use the same hash function,
and you have the same set of keys
and so this allows you to take a dataset you know partition that both in the same way
using this hashing trick.
And this is cool,
because now if you need to do a join over these two datasets,
like if you need to join these two datasets,
that basically you can just join the partitions,
and you don't have to communicate,
you know each of these machines doesn't have to communicate with any other machine,
because it knows it has all the keys you know the other dataset has
and they're all on the same machine.
Gotcha, so basically it's just trying sort, not sort,
but like bucket the different objects in the same machine,
so that it doesn't communicate.
Okay great, thank you so much.
So this means the hash function has to make sure that,
there are no links that would have to be like using the computation on another machine.
Yeah, well, they're good since they use the same hash function
and they have the same keys, you know that will happen.
yeah.
I had a question,
I actually wanted to come back to the question I asked before.
Yeah, good.
So let me open up. Yeah, let me also open the paper, I guess.
Any other people that have questions,
because maybe this will take a little bit of time.
Yeah, actually, I had a quick question on the fault tolerance, fault tolerance of FaRM,
so so just to clarify what happens,
so if a failure occurs before the decision point,
then the entire thing is aborted,
but it occurs after the decision point,
then after the failed computers come back up,
they have to reask the coordinator for whether or not they should commit.
They don't really reask right,
like what happens is there after failure there's a recovery process runs,
and the recovery process looks basically all the logs are drained
and then the recovery process looks at the state of the system,
and based on the state of system
and decides what to do with transaction,
either aborted or commits it,
and the key aspect here in this protocol is
to ensure that at the point when the transaction coordinator actually have reported to the application
that the transaction succeeded committed,
it has to be the case,
that there are enough pieces of evidence left around in the system,
so that during the recovery process,
that transaction is definitely committed,
and, that's, that's sort of the plan.
And the reason that there's enough evidence is,
because there's these large records lying around,
there's commands background records right lying around
and there's this one commit record.
I see, so if something,
for example if a failure occurs on a primary, before against commit primary.
Yep.
What happens there?
So that's interesting,
so there's enough backup record, correct,
to basically decide you know that every backup that every shard actually has committed,
and, and so that's enough information for the recovery process to say
I am going to run for that transaction,
because it could have committed.
Got it, so it doesn't need the primary in that case,
can use the backups because the backups have.
Yeah exactly.
Got it, thank you,
and what happens if the backup fails.
Well then one of the backup fails
and presumably that means that the commit record to still there,
and then again there's enough information to decide
that actual transaction needs to commit,
and there's enough backups around to actually know what the new values
or there's also the log entries which actually contains,
so if a primary is up,
it will have a log entry,
there will be a committed entry plus there are not backups actually finish the transaction.
Thank you.
Oh, sorry to follow up on that,
if you said that if the primary failed,
then you could use the backups to complete the action,
if there's enough of them,
so we need to elect a new primary?
I I think this is all happened during the,
basically you can think of the recovery process as a primary
and that just finishes everything off.
Oh, so whoever does the recovery is the primary.
Yeah.
Okay, make sense, thank you.
I think explicitly they you know promote primary,
just like go ahead and do it.
And what is like enough backups.
Well, we have f+1, right,
and so it means that, you know so long as one is left,
you know we were good,
so we can have more than f one failures,
we can only have f failures in this particular drawing f is 1.
So there has to be per shard, you know one machine left.
Okay, that makes sense, thank you.
You're welcome.
Okay, Felipe, it just me and you.
Well, unless anyone else ask questions I think.
Yeah, I and you.
So it's page, page they explain on page 6.
Yeah yeah.
That below table 3.
Yep.
Some [bare] ground starts the most interesting question right,
it goes on to define.
Both sufficient usual to classify dependencies in two types,
narrow where parent partition, the parent RDD is used by most one partition of the child RDD right,
so this is.
Right.
So let me, so let's draw this correct,
so here we have a parent partition.
Right.
And let's say there's a map,
and here we have the child partition.
Okay?
Right.
Good, so that's the narrow, this is the narrow case.
Right, but I think like the the example of I was thinking of is you know each parent is used by at most one partition of the child,
but the child right,
that doesn't say anything about,
like it says right like it doesn't necessarily mean it's a one-to-one relationship, right.
Well, because more or less have to correct,
let's say, let's say we have a wide one, correct,
so then here we have parent partition one.
Here we have maybe it has any of them correct,
here, here's n in the wide one, the child is.
Right, what what what I what I was saying is
I I think you know based on the definition given in the paper,
this could be a narrow partition,
and in fact, I mean like if you look at,
like a join with input co-partition, like you have.
The hash partition that actually the wide one turns into a narrow one.
Right, but you still have like a partition, a child partition
getting like like being computed from several parent partitions, right.
Explicitly mention that right,
I think that's the only example.
Yeah, but like I think there's a typo in that sentence, right.
I I mean I'm not sure it's,
yeah I I'm not sure if it's,
what they meant to like writer.
Alright, well, we know we conclude this is the two cases, like I got.
Yeah.
I guess and there are no other cases,
oh, and so then we can go for every operation correct
and then we can see when it's narrow wide one.
Right right.
So once the job of the programmer that defines these operations
to actually indicate whether it's a wide partition or a narrow, wide dependency or a narrow dependency,
that's what, for figure table 3 about.
Yeah, like what I'm saying is like,
usually like like the way I saw it through paper,
like like, your example on the wide would be,
could would be a narrow dependency,
unless right like you have several child
and the parent partitions are like.
Okay, so in general,
okay, it is the case of course,
if there's another child partition here,
okay so maybe that's why we're trying to get,
so let's separate, the real picture actually draws this,
so it has another child partition
and basically operations, the transformations are.
Exactly, yeah and that's narrow for sure, like.
This on the right side, this is wide.
Sorry, that's wide, yeah.
That's what I meant, that for sure is wide.
Another I drew is also wide I believe.
Look if you do join,
if you do an action like collect the very end, you know wide dependency.
Yeah, okay.
It doesn't say, it doesn't say, it has to come from different RDDs,
it just says like it has to come from different partitions.
And so this is narrow, so I think narrow is only the case where is one-to-one.
Okay.
Narrow is like, narrow means no communication.
Right, okay, yep.
Yeah, I think I think the case where I was confused
was like like many-to-one,
like I think based on the definition of the,
like of the of the paper,
like the many-to-one relation is still, still narrow.
No, I think they mean it to be.
Yeah yeah, but like strictly like if you really,
like yeah I I think maybe like an implementation you'll see like,
yeah what are you saying right like it's wide.
I was just like,
I think if you read like.
[] confusing.
Paper actually yeah you can get confused like many-to-one relationship,
now the one-to-many is clearly wide, yeah,
but, yeah okay, sounds good.
Okay.
Yeah, I think the paper easier to understand in general.
Good okay.
There's that easier than the paper for FaRM.
Oh yeah, sure.
Yeah, I think so I think those were probably the most two heavy-duty paper,
so a lot will see in this term.
Okay, nice.
The part it's hard to stay there,
I think the remaining was a little bit more you know more,
I'm going to say straightforward,
perhaps fewer moving pieces.
Nice.
Okay, awesome, thanks professor.
Can I ask one last question,
I just realized that I have,
it was about the conversation, you can paralyze it,
if if it's a different partitions,
but if it's also you said if it's in.
The stage stages right,
you know there's sort of what is it like streaming parallelism, if you will or pipeline parallelism.
Let me see if I can find a picture, there's one of them.
I gotta find lineage graph, no, no,
right here whenever this graph,
great now maybe here's one picture that we can modify.
Do you see?
Yes.
Okay, so basically this is the lineage graph here to collect
and so this is like one stage right,
the scheduler runs one of the stages of each worker, for each partition, right,
so each worker runs a stage on the partition,
so basically all these partitions, are all these stages running parallel on different workers,
then within a stage, there's also parallelism,
because you know every filter is pipelined,
without you know they mean like you read,
maybe like the first and records,
and then you apply the filter operation,
and then a it produces you know whatever fewer n records,
and you know then the next you know filter you know process those n records,
the [] crossing those records,
the first filter reads the next n,
and you know produces them and then pass them on
and then you know making results in some number records,
again, and it goes on and on,
so basically all these all these, oops, like these all these transformations are pipelined,
and so they're always running concurrently
or running not truly concurrently, they're running in a pipeline fashion.
Oh, I just said this is a batch thing, they were talking about.
Yeah, so things are past and batches,
and basically every stage the pipeline processes batch.
Okay, okay, yeah makes for clear,
yeah, thank you so much,
that was it was an interesting lecture, thank you.
Okay, you're welcome, glad you enjoy it,
it's a cool system.
Sorry, sorry, can you hear me now.
Yeah yeah, wondering what did yeah.
No problem, I'm sorry about that,
I yeah sorry I was listening,
I I I realized we'd be going late,
I'm going to try to make this question very quick,
I've gotten to use spark before.
Thank you, thank you so much.
So yeah yeah I really, really appreciate this lecture,
spark is actually something that I'm gonna use in my future job,
so I appreciate you teaching this me,
just one.
Probably, probably I'm not sure this will really help your writing spark programs.
No, I mean I did it as an intern really not knowing what I was doing,
but like this has helped me give give more context with it.
So I guess the the quick question with a spark programs that,
the way that I've understood spark jobs is
how spark constructs a directed a directed acyclic graph of all the tasks, and.
Yep, and this is what you talked about with the wide partitions and narrow partitions.
I think they're called dependencies, not partitions.
Oh yep, okay, okay. okay, sorry,
that with our RDDs and I guess like,
okay, this is different terminology between,
the dependencies are like these tasks in the directed acyclic graph of all the tasks,
but the RDDs that's like each task in this graph is not represented by this RDD.
Let me actually go back,
maybe these pictures are right.
And oh gosh I appreciate you staying here,
please let me know if you have to go to.
No no no no no that's right I have more time.
So, okay, so this is sort of a RDD correct,
let me draw another color, so we can [agree],
this is an RDD, RDD has a bunch of partitions,
and here's another RDD.
Okay, yep and the arrows are basically as sort of like the same story,
when we actually finish this picture too,
on the side here more partitions,
here's the RDDs, boom RDD, boom RDD,
those transformations basically between RDDs, right,
so the arrows,
let me pick another color,
you know these errors, those are transformations.
Got you, and this is this is like part of the directed cyclical graph of the smart job,
every single transformation leads to creating another RDD,
that makes sense, that makes sense.
Okay and then the only thing is like some of these arrows are wide and some of them are narrow,
and the graph, from the graph, you can't really tell whether which ones are narrow or which ones are,
which transformations are narrow transformations or wide transformations.
You're talking about the graph that's the spark program actually shows you in there.
Yeah, this linear graph, you can't.
Gotcha, okay, okay.
Yeah, that's here, so here look at this lineage graph a bit,
like this transformation transformation transformation, all that transformation narrow, would like narrow,
because it's a single arrow,
but it's not really true right,
like the last one, for example, must be a wide one,
because it will collect information from all.
Gotcha.
Okay, then I I guess I was wondering
like do you have recommendations on resources for things,
that can show me how spark figures out how to construct the directed acyclic graph to do all these tasks.
Yeah, look at scheduler that's all.
Right and yeah I read in the paper,
like I I you know I was trying to comprehend the paper as best as I could,
but it's you know it's difficult, but.
It will always be difficult to read,
so the scheduler I think I would go back first to thesis [] thesis,
I'm sure it has a [] on the scheduler.
Gotcha gotcha, oh okay
and that'll show me just how spark figures out how to make this graph.