Okay good afternoon, good morning, good evening, good night, wherever you are.
Let's get started again.
So, today we have a guest lecture,
probably speaker needs a little introduction,
Russ Cox, was one of the co-leads on the Go project
and we'll talk a lot more about it.
Let me say a couple words, not trying to embarrass Russ too much,
Russ has a long experience with distributed systems,
he was a developer and contributor to a plan9 when he was a high school student undergrad at Harvard,
he joined the PHD program at MIT, which where we met up
and probably if you've taken any sort of pdos class, if you will,
there's gonna be, you will see Russ's touches on it
and certainly in 6.824 you know the Go, switch to Go for us has been a wonderful thing
and but if you differ in opinion, of course feel free to ask Russ questions and make suggestions,
he's always welcome to entertain any ideas.
So with that, Russ, it's yours.
Great, thanks, can you still see the slides, is that working.
Okay great, so so we build Go to support writing the sort of distributed systems that we were building at Google
and that may Go a great fit for, what came next which is now called cloud software
and also a great fit for 6.824.
So in this lecture, I'm going to try to explain how I think about writing programs in Go.
I'm going to walk through the sort of design and implementation of programs for four different patterns that I see come up often.
And along the way I'm going to try to highlight some hints or rules of thumb that you can keep in mind when designing your own Go programs.
And I know the syllabus links to an older version of the slide,
so you might have seen them already,
I hope that the lecture form is a bit more intelligible than just sort of looking at the slides.
and I hope that in general these patterns are common enough
that maybe they'll be helpful by themselves,
but also that you know you'll hints will help you prepare for whatever it is, you need to implement.
So to start, it's important to distinguish between concurrency and parallelism.
And concurrency is about how you write your programs about being able to compose independently executing control flows
whether you want to call them processes or threads or Go routines,
so that your program can be dealing with lots of things at once without turning into a giant mess.
On the other hand parallelism is about how the programs get executed about allowing multiple computations to run simultaneously,
so that the program can be doing lots of things at once,
not just dealing with lots of things at once.
And so concurrency lends itself naturally to parallel execution,
but today the focus is on how to use Go's concurrency support to make your programs clearer, not to make them faster,
if they do get faster that's wonderful, but that's not the point today.
So I said I'd walked through the design and implementation of some programs for four common, excuse me concurrency patterns that I see often,
but before we get to those,
I want to start with what seems like a really trivial problem,
but that illustrates one of the most important points about what it means to use concurrency to structure programs.
A decision that comes up over and over, when you design concurrent programs
is whether to represent states as code or as data.
And by as code, I mean the control flow in the program.
So suppose a reading characters from a file,
and we need to scan over a C style quoted string.
Oh hello the slides aren't changing.
Yeah, it will, can you see prologue goroutines for state right now.
No, we see the title slide.
Oh, no yeah I was wondering about that,
because there was a border around this thing, when I started and then it went away.
So let me let me just unshare and reshare.
I had to figure out how to do that in zoom.
Unfortunately keynote menu wants to be up
and I don't know how to get to the zoom menu.
Ah, my screen sharing is paused, why is my screen sharing paused.
Can I resume.
Here we go.
Alright, I don't know the zoom box says you're screen sharing is paused, so that,
now the borders back, so I'll watch that.
Alright so, see I was back here,
so so you're reading a string,
it's not a parallel program is reading one character at a time,
so there's no opportunity for parallelism,
but there is a good opportunity for concurrency.
So we don't actually care about the exact escape sequences in the string,
that we need to do is match this regular expression.
And we don't have to worry about understanding exactly,
we'll come back to what it means,
but that's basically all you have to do is implement this regular expression
and so you know you probably all know you can turn a regular expression into a state machine.
And so we might use a tool that generates this code,
and in this code, there's a single variable state that's the state of the machine
and the loop goes over the state one character at a time,
reads the character depending on the state
and the character changes to a different state until it gets to the end,
and so this is a completely unreadable program,
but it's the kind of thing that you know an auto generated program might look like.
And the important point is that the program state is stored in data, in this variable, that's called state
and if you can change it to store the state in code that's often clearer.
So here's what I mean,
suppose we duplicate the readChar calls into each case of the switch,
so we haven't made any semantic changes here,
we just took the readChar that was at the top and we moved it into the middle.
Now instead of setting state and then immediately doing the switch again,
we can change those into gotos.
And then we can simplify a little bit further,
there's a goto state1 that's right before the state1 label, we can get rid of that.
Then there's, I guess, yeah, so then there's you know there's only one way to get the state2,
so we might as well pull the state2 code up and put it inside the if where the goto appears
and then both sides of that if now end in goto state1,
so we can hoist that out.
And now what's left is actually a pretty simple program,
you know state0 is never jumped too,
so it just begins there,
and then state1 is just a regular loop,
so we might as well make that look like a regular loop.
And now like this is you know looking like a program
and then finally we can get rid of some variables and simplify a little bit further.
And, and we can rotate the loop,
so that you know we don't do a return true in the middle of the loop,
we do the return true at the end.
And so now we've got this program that is actually you know reasonably nice
and it's worth mentioning that it's possible to clean up much less egregious examples,
you know if you had tried to write this by hand,
your first attempt might have been the thing on the left, where you've got this extra piece of state
and then you can apply the same kinds of transformations to move that state into the actual control flow
and end up at the same program that we have on the right that's cleaner.
So this is a useful transformation to keep in mind anytime you have state,
that kind of looks like it might be just reiterating,
what's what's happening in the program counter.
And so you can see this if the the original state,
like if state equals zero, the program counter is at the beginning of the function,
and if state equals one or if inEscape equals false and the other version,
the program counter is just inside the for loop,
and state equals two is further down in the for loop.
And the benefit of writing it this way instead of with the states is that it's much easier to understand
like I can actually just walk through the code and explain it to you,
you know if you just read through the code,
you read an opening quote and then you start looping
and then until you find the closing quote, you read a character
and if it's a backslash you ski[]p the next character,
and that's it right, you can just read that off the page,
which you couldn't do in the original.
This version also happens to run faster,
although that doesn't really matter for us.
But as I mentioned, I'm going to highlight what I think are kind of important lessons as hints for designing your own Go programs
and this is the first one, to convert data state into code state when it makes your programs clearer.
And again like these are all hints,
you should you should you know for all of these, you should consider it as, only if it helps you can decide.
So one problem with this hint is that not all programs have the luxury of having complete control over their control flow,
so you know here's a different example instead of having a readChar function that can be called,
this code is written to have a ProcessChar method that you have to hand the character to one at a time.
And then ProcessChar has no choice really, but to you know encoded state in an explicit state variable,
because after every character, it has to return back out
and so it can't save the state at the program counter and stack,
it has to have the state in an actual variable.
But in Go, we have another choice right,
because we can't save the state on that stack and in that program counter,
but we can make another goroutine to hold that state for us,
so supposing we already have this debug readString function},
that we really don't want to rewrite in this other way,
we just want to reuse it,
it works, maybe it's really big and hairy,
it's much more complicated than anything we saw,
we just want to reuse it.
And so the way we can do that in Go is
we can start a new goroutine that does the readString part,
it's the same readString code as before we pass in the character reader.
And now here you know the Init method makes this goroutine to do the character reading
and then every time the ProcessChar method is called,
we send a message to the goroutine on the char channel,
that says here's the next character
and then we receive a message back that says tell me the current status
and the current status is always either I need more input
or you know basically you know, was it okay or not.
And so, you know, this lets us move the the program counter that we couldn't do on the first stack into the other stack of the goroutine.
And so using additional goroutines is a great way to hold additional code state
and give you the ability to do these kinds of cleanups,
even if the original structure of the problem makes it look like you can't.
Russ.
Go ahead.
I assume you're fine with people asking questions.
Yeah, absolutely.
I just wanted to make sure that.
Yeah, definitely, please interrupt.
So,so the hint here is to use additional goroutines to hold additional code state
and there's there's one caveat to this,
and then it's not free to just make goroutines right,
you have to actually make sure that they exit,
because otherwise you'll just accumulate them.
And so you have to think about,
you know why does the goroutine exit,
like you know, is it going to get cleaned up.
And in this case, we know that you know q.parse is going to return,
where q.parse go.
Sorry that's not right.
Oh, sorry, the readString here,
readString is going to return, anytime it sends a message, that says need more input.
Where it go, there's something missing from this slide.
Sorry, I went through this last night.
So so as we go in, we go into Init,
we kick off this goroutine that's gonna call readChar a bunch of times
and then we read the status once and that first status is going to happen,
because the the first call to readChar from readString is going to saying I need more input,
and then we're going to send a character back.
We're going to send the character back in ProcessChar
and then every time ProcessChar gets called, it returns a status
and so up until you get, you know need more input,
you're going to get the.
Sorry, this is not working, you're going to get any more input for every time you want to read a character.
And then when it's done reading characters,
what I haven't shown you here, what seems to be missing,
somehow is when things exit and when things exit.
Let's see if it's on this slide.
Yeah, so there's a return Success and a return BadInput, that I'd forgotten about.
And so, you know these returning different status and then they're done,
so when ProcessChar in in the readString version,
when it returns BadInput or Success,
we say that you know it's done.
And so as long as the caller is going through,
and you know calling until it gets something that's not need more input,
then the goroutine will finish,
but maybe if we stop early, if the caller hits an EOF and stops on its own,
without telling us that it's done,
there's a goroutine leftover
and so that could be a problem.
And so you just you need to make sure that you know when and why each goroutine will exit
and the nice thing is that if you do make a mistake
and you leave goroutine stuck,
they just sit there,
it's like the best possible bug in the world,
because they just sit around, waiting for you to look at them
and all you have to do is remember to look for them.
And so here's a very simple program,
at this, goroutines and it runs an http server,
and so if we run this, it kicks off a whole bunch of f goroutines
and they all block trying to send to a channel
and then it makes the http server.
And so if I run this program, it just sits there
and if I type control backslash on a Unix system,
I get a SIGQUIT which makes it crash and dump all the stacks on the goroutines.
And you can see on the slide, that it's going to print over and over again,
here's a goroutine and h call from g call from f,
and in the channel send.
And if you look at the line numbers,
you can see exactly where they are.
Another option is that since we're in an http server.
and the http server imports the net http pprof package,
you can actually just visit the http servers, debug pprof goroutine url,
which gives you the stacks of all the running goroutines,
and unlike the crash dump,
it takes a little more effort and it duplicates the goroutines based on their stacks
and so and then it sorts them by how many there are of each stack.
And so if you have a goroutine leak,
the leak shows up at the very top.
So in this case, you've got a hundred goroutines stack in h called from g called from f
and then we can see there's one of a couple other goroutines
and we don't really care about them.
And so you know this is a new hint that,
it just it's really really useful to look for stuff goroutines by just going to this endpoint.
Alright, so that was kind of the warm up.
Now I want to look at the first real concurrency pattern,
which is a publish subscribe server.
So publish subscribe is a way of structuring a program,
that you decouple the parts that are publishing interesting events from the things that are subscribing to them
and there's a publish subscribe or pub sub server in the middle that connects those,
so the individual publishers and the individual subscribers don't have to be aware of exactly who the other ones are.
So you know on your android phone, an app might publish or make a phone call event
and then the dial might subscribe to that
and actually start you know help dial.
And so in a real pub sub server,
there are ways to filter events based on what kind they are,
so that when you publish and make a phone call event,
it doesn't go to your email program.
But for now we're just going to assume that the filtering is taken care of separately
and we're just worried about the actual publish and subscribe,
and the concurrency of that.
So here's an API, we want to implement,
with any number of clients that can call subscribe with a channel
and afterwards events that are published will be sent on that channel.
And then when a client is no longer interested,
it can call cancel and passing the same channel,
to say stop sending the events on that channel
and the way that cancel will signal that it really is done sending events on that channel, is it will close the channel,
so that the receiver caller can keep receiving events until it sees the channel get closed,
then it knows that the cancel has taken effect.
So notice that the information is only flowing one way on the channel right,
you can send to the channel
and then the receiver can receive from it
and the information flows from the sender to the receiver,
and it never goes the other way,
so closing is also a signal from the sender to the receiver, but all the sending is over,
the receiver cannot close the channel to tell the sender I don't want you to send anymore,
because that's information going in the opposite direction.
And it's just a lot easier to reason about if the information only goes one way
and of course if you need communication in both directions, you can use a pair of channels
and it often turns out to be the case that those different directions may have different types of data flowing,
like before we saw that there were [rooms] going in one direction and status updates going in the other direction.
So how do we implement this API,
here's a pretty basic implementation that you know could be good enough.
We have a server and the server state is a map of registered subscriber channels, protected by a lock,
we initialize the server by just allocating the map,
and then to publish the event, we just send it to every register channel,
to subscribe to new channel, we just added to the map
and to cancel we take it out of the map.
And then, because these are all, these are all methods that might be called from multiple goroutines,
we need to call lock and unlock around these to protect the map.
And notice that I wrote defer unlock right after the lock,
so I don't have to remember to unlock it later.
You've probably all seen this,
you know sort of a nice idiom to just do the lock unlock
and then you know I have a blank line and have that be its own paragraph in the code.
One thing I want to point out is that,
using defer makes sure that the mutexes gets unlocked,
even if you have multiple returns from the function,
so you can't forget,
but it also makes sure that it gets unlocked if you have a panic,
like in Subscribe and Cancel where there's panic for misuse.
And there is a subtlety here about,
if you might not want to unlock the mutex,
if the panic happened while the thing that was locked is in some inconsistent state,
but I'm gonna ignore that for now,
in general you try to avoid having the things that might panic happen,
while you're potentially inconsistent state.
And I should also point out that the use of panic at all in subscribe and cancel,
implies that you really trust your clients not to misuse the interface
that it is a program error worth tearing down the entire program potentially for that to happen.
And in a bigger program where other clients were using this API,
you probably want to return an error instead,
and not have the possibility of taking down the whole program,
but panic is simplifies things for now.
And you know error handling in general is kind of not the topic today.
A more important concern with this code than panics is
what happens if a goroutine is slow to receive events.
So all the operations here are done holding the mutex,
which means all the clients kind of have to proceed in lockstep.
So during publish, there's a loop that's sending, on the channels sending the event to every channel,
and if one subscriber falls behind,
the next subscriber doesn't get the event,
until that slow subscriber wakes up and actually get the event off of that channel.
And so one slow subscriber can slow down everyone else
and you know forcing them to proceed in lockstep this way is not always a problem,
if you document the restriction and for whatever reason you know how the clients are written
and you know that they won't ever fall too far behind,
this could be totally fine,
it's a really simple implementation.
And it has nice properties,
like on return from publish you know that the event has actually been handed off to each of the other goroutines,
you don't know that they've started processing it,
but you know it's been handed off.
And so, maybe that's good enough and you could stop here.
A second option is that if you need to tolerate just a little bit of slowness on the subscribers,
then you could say that they need to give you a buffered channel with room for a couple of events in the buffer,
so that you know when you're publishing,
now, as long as they're not too far behind there always be room for the new event to go into the channel buffer,
and then the actual published won't block for too long.
And again, maybe that's good enough,
if you're sure that they won't ever fall too far behind, you get to stop there.
But in a really big program,
you do want to cope more gracefully with arbitrarily slow subscribers
and so then the question is what do you do.
And so in general you have three options,
you can slow down the event generator, which is what the previous solutions implicitly do,
because publish stops until the subscribers catch up.
Or you can drop events or you can queue an arbitrary number of past events,
those are pretty much your only options.
So we talked about you know publish and slowing down the event generator.
There's a middle ground where you coalesce the events or you drop them,
so that you know the subscriber might find out that,
oh hey you missed some events and I can't tell you what they were, because I didn't save them,
but I'm at least going to tell you, you missed five events.
And then maybe it can do something else to try to catch up.
And this is the kind of approach, that we take in the profiler,
so in the profiler if you've used it,
if there's a goroutine that fills the profile on a signal handler actually with profiling events
and then there's a separate goroutine whose job is to read the data back out
and write it to disk or send it to an http request
or whatever it is you're doing with profile data.
And there's a buffer in the middle and if the receiver from the profile data falls behind,
when the buffer fills up, we start adding entries to a final profile entry,
that just has a single entry that's that's a function called runtime last profile data
and so if you look at the profile,
you see hey the program spent 5% of its time in last profile data,
that just means you know the profile reader was too slow and it didn't catch up,
and we lost some of the profile,
but we're clear about exactly what the error rate is in the profile
and you pretty much never see that,
because all the readers actually do keep up,
but just in case they didn't,
you have a pretty clear signal.
An example of purely dropping the events is the OS signal package,
where you have to pass in a channel,
that will be ready to receive the signal,
a signal like SIGHUP or SIGQUIT,
and when the signal comes in,
the runtime tries to send to each of the channels that subscribe to that signal,
and if it can't send to it, it just doesn't, it's just gone,
because we're in a signal handler, we can't wait
and so what the callers have to do is they have to pass in a buffered channel,
and if they pass in a buffer channel that has length at least one, buffer length at least one
and they only register that channel to a single signal,
then you know that if a signal comes in,
you're definitely gonna get told about it,
if it comes in twice you might only get told about it once,
but that's actually the same semantics that Unix gives to processes for signals anyway,
so that's fine.
So those are both examples of dropping a coalescing events.
And then the third choice is that you might actually just really not want to lose any events,
it might just be really important that you never lose anything,
in which case you know you can queue an arbitrary number of events,
you can somehow arrange for the program to just save all the events that the slow subscriber hasn't seen yet somewhere
and give them to the subscriber later.
And it's really important to think carefully before you do that,
because in a distributed system, you know there's always slow computers,
always computers that have fallen off line or whatever,
and they might be gone for a while
and so you don't want to introduce unbounded queuing,
in general you want to think very carefully before you do that
and think well you know how unbounded is really and can I tolerate that.
And so like that's a reason why channels don't have just an unbounded buffering,
it's really almost never the right choice,
and if it is the right choice,
you probably want to build it very carefully.
And so but we're going to build one just to see what it would look like.
And before we do that, I just want to adjust the program a little bit,
so we have this mutex in the code
and the mutex is an example of of keeping the state whether you're locked or not in a state variable,
but we can also move that into a program counter variable,
by putting it in a different goroutine.
And so, in this case, we can start a new goroutine that runs a program function called s.loop.
And it handles requests sent on three new channels publish subscribe and cancel.
And so in Init, we make the channels and then we kick off s.loop.
And s.loop is sort of the amalgamation of the previous method bodies
and it just receives from any of the three channels,
a request a publisher subscriber or cancel request
and it does whatever was asked
and now that map, the subscriber map, can be just a local variable in s.loop.
And and so it's the same code.
But now that data is clearly owned by s.loop,
nothing else could even get to it,
because it's a local variable.
And then we just need to change the original methods to send the work over to the loop goroutine
and so uppercase Publish now sends on lower case publish the channel the event that it wants to publish
and similarly subscribe and cancel.
They create a request that has a channel,
that we want to subscribe and also a channel to get the answer back
and they send that into the loop and the loop sends back the answer.
And so I referred to transforming the program this way as converting the mutex into a goroutine,
because we took the data state of the mutex,
there's a lock bit inside it
and now that lock bit is implicit in the program counter of the loop.
It's very clear that you can't ever have a publish and subscribe happening at the same time,
because it's just single thread code and just you know executed sequence.
On the other hand, the original version had a kind of like clarity of state,
where you could sort of inspect it
and reason about well this is the important state
and it's harder in the the goroutine version to see what's important state
and what's kind of incidental state from just having a goroutine.
And in a given situation, one might be more important than the other,
so a couple years ago I did all the labs for the class, when it first switched to go
and raft is a good example of where you probably prefer the state with the mutex,
because raft is so different from most concurrent programs
and that each replica is just kind of profoundly uncertain of its state right,
like the state transitions.
You know, one moment you think you're the leader
and the next moment you've been deposed,
like one moment your log has ten entries
and next moment to, actually know it only has two entries
and so being able to manipulate that state directly
rather than having to somehow get in and out of the program counter,
makes a lot more sense for raft.
But that's pretty unique in most situations,
it cleans things up to put the state in the program counter.
Alright, so in order to deal with the slow subscribers,
now we're gonna add some helper goroutines
and their job is to manage a particular subscribers backlog and keep the overall program from blocking.
And so this is the helper goroutine,
and the the main loop goroutine will send the events to the helper which we then trust,
because we wrote it, not to fall arbitrarily behind
and then the helper's job is to queue events if needed and send them off to the subscriber.
Alright, so this actually has two problems.
The first is that if there's nothing in the queue,
then the select is actually wrong to try to offer queue of zero
and in fact just evaluating queue of zero at the start of the select will panic,
because the queue is empty
and so we can fix these by setting up the arguments separately from the select
and in particular we need to make a channel send out, that's going to be nil,
which is never able to proceed in a select,
as we know when we don't want to send
and it's going to be the actual out channel when we do want to send
and then we have to have a separate variable that holds the event that we're going to send,
it will actually read from queue zero, if there's something in the queue.
The second thing that's wrong is that
we need to handle closing of the channel, of the input channel,
because when the input channel closes,
we need to flush the rest of the queue,
and then we need to close the output channel.
So to check for that, we change the select from just doing e equals received from in to e comma ok,
equals received from in the comma ok,
will be told whether or not the channel is actually sending real data, or else it's closed.
And so when ok is false,
we can set in to nil, to say let's stop trying to receive from him,
there's nothing there we're just gonna keep getting told that it's closed.
And then when the loop is fine, when the queue is finally empty, we can exit the loop
and so we change the for condition to say we want to keep acting the loop as long as there actually still is an input channel
and there's something to write back to the output channel
and then once both of those are not true anymore,
it's time to exit the loop and we close the output channel
and we're done.
And so now we've correctly propagated the closing of the input channel to the output channel,
so that was the helper.
And the server loop used to look like this.
And to update it, we just changed the subscription map,
before it was a map from subscribe channels to bolls,
it was just basically a set
and now it's a map from subscribe channel to helper channel
and every time we get a new subscription,
we make a helper channel, we kickoff a helper goroutine,
and we record the helper channel in the subscription map instead of the actual channel.
And then the rest of, the rest of the loop actually barely changes at all.
So I do want to point out that
if you wanted to have a different strategy for what you do with a clients that fall too far behind,
that can all go in the helper goroutine,
the code on the screen right now is completely unchanged,
so we've completely separated the publish subscribe maintaining the actual list of subscribers map
from the what do you do when things get too slow map problem
and so it's really nice that you've got this clean separation of concerns into completely different goroutines
and that can help you keep your programs similar.
And so that's the general hint is that you can use goroutines a lot of the time to separate independent concerns.
Alright, so, the second pattern for today is work scheduler
and you did one of these in lab one for mapreduce
and I'm just going to build up to that
and this doesn't do all the RPC stuff,
it just kind of assumes that there's kind of channel channel based interfaces to all the servers.
So you know we have this function schedule,
it takes a fixed list of servers,
has a number of tasks run
and it has just this abstracted function call that you call to run the task on a specific server,
you can imagine, it was doing the RPCs underneath.
So we're gonna need some way to keep track of which servers are available to execute tasks.
And so, one option is to use our own stack or queue implementation,
but another option is to use a channel,
because it's a good synchronized queue.
And so we can send into the channel to add to the queue
and receive from it to pop something off.
And in this case, we'll make the queue be a queue of servers
and we'll start off its a queue of idle servers,
servers that aren't doing any work for us right now.
We'll start off by just initializing it by sending all the known servers into the idle list.
And then we can loop over the tasks
and for every task we kickoff a goroutine
and its job is to pull a server off the idle list,
run the task, and then put the server back on.
And this loop body is another example of the earlier hint to use goroutines,
like independent things run independently,
because each task is running as a separate concern,
they're all running in parallel.
Unfortunately, there are two problems with this program.
The first one is that the closure that's running as a new goroutine refers to the loop iteration variable, which is task
and so by the time the goroutine starts exiting,
the loop has probably continued and done a task++
and so it's actually getting the wrong value of task.
You've probably seen this by now,
and of course the best way to catch this is to run the race detector.
And at Google, we even encourage teams to set up canary servers that run the race detector
and split off something like point 1% of their traffic to it,
just to catch you know races that might be in the production system.
And you know finding a bug with the race detector is way better than having to debug some corruption later.
So there are two ways to fix this race,
the first way is to give the closure an explicit parameter and pass it in
and Go statement requires a function call specifically for this reason,
so that you can set specific arguments that get evaluated in the context of the original goroutine
and then get copied to the new goroutine.
And so in this case, we can declare a new argument task2,
we can past task to it.
And then inside the goroutine task2 is a completely different copy of task.
And I only named it task2 to make it easier to talk about.
But of course there's a bug here
and the bug is that I forgot to update task inside the function to refer to task2 instead of task,
and so we basically never do that,
what we do instead is, we just give it the same name,
so that it's impossible now for the code inside the goroutine to refer to the wrong copy of task.
That was the first way to fix the race,
there's a second way which is you know sort of cryptic the first time you see it,
but it amounts to the same thing,
and that is that you just make a copy of the variable inside the loop body.
So every time colon equals happens,
that creates a new variable,
so in the for loop, in the outer for loop,
there's a colon equals at the beginning
and there's not one the rest of the loop,
so that's all just one variable for the entire loop,
whereas if we put a colon equals inside the body,
every time we run an iteration of the loop, that's a different variable,
so if if the Go function closure captures that variable,
those will all be distinct.
So we can do the same thing we do task2
and this time I remember to update the body,
but you just like before it's too easy to forget to update the body
and so typically you write task colon equals task,
which looks kind of magical the first time you see it,
but that's what it's for.
Alright, so I said there were two bugs in the program,
the first one was this race on task.
And the second one is that, we didn't actually do anything after we've kicked off all the tasks,
we're not waiting for them to be done.
And and in particular, we're kicking them off way too fast,
because you know if there's a million tasks are going to kick off a million goroutines
and they're all just going to sit waiting for one of the five servers,
which is kind of beneficial.
And so what we can do is we can pull the fetching of the next idle server up out of the goroutine.
And, we pull it up out of the goroutine,
now we'll only kick off a goroutine when there is an idle server to use.
And then we can kick it off
and and you know use that server and put it back
and using the server and put it back runs concurrently,
but doing the fetch of the idle server inside the loop slows things down,
so that there's only ever now number of servers goroutines running instead of number of tasks.
And that receive is essentially creating some back pressure to slow down the loop,
so it doesn't get too far ahead.
And then I mentioned we have to wait for the task to finish.
And so we can do that by just at the end of the loop,
going over the list again and pulling all the servers out
and we've pulled the right number of servers out of the idle list,
that means they're all done.
And so that's that's the full program.
Now to me the most important part of this is that,
you still get to write a for loop to iterate over the tasks,
there's lots of other languages where you have to do this with state machines or some sort of callbacks.
And you don't get the luxury of encoding this in the control flow
and so this is a much cleaner way where you can just use a regular loop.
But there are some some changes we could make some improvements
and so one improvement is to notice that, there's only one goroutine that makes requests of a server at a particular time,
so instead of having one goroutine for task,
maybe we should have one goroutine per server,
because there are probably going to be fewer servers than tasks.
And to do that we have to change from having a channel of idle servers to a channel of yet to be done tasks
and so we've renamed the idle channel to work.
And then we also need a done channel to count you know how many tasks are done,
so we know when we're completely finished.
And so here there's a new function run tasks,
and that's going to be the per server function,
and we kick off one of them for each server.
And runTasks, his job is just to loop over the work channel, run the tasks
and when the server is done, we send true to done
and you know the server tells us that you know it's done
and the server exits when the work channel gets closed,
that's what makes that for loop actually stop.
So then you having kicked off the servers,
we can then just sit there in a loop
and send each task to the work channel,
close the work channel and say hey there's no more work coming,
all the servers, you should finish and then and then exit
and then wait for all the servers to tell us that they're done.
So in the lab, there were a couple complications,
one was that you might get new servers at any given time
and so we could change that by saying the servers come in on a channel of strings.
And that actually fits pretty well into the current structure,
where when you get a new server, you just kick off a new runTasks goroutine
and so the only thing we have to change here is to put that loop into its own goroutine,
so that while we're sending tasks to servers,
we can still accept new servers and kickoff the helper goroutines.
But now we have this problem,
that we don't really have a good way to tell when all the servers are done,
because we don't know how many servers there are,
and so we could try to maintain that number as servers come in,
but it's a little tricky
and instead we can count the number of tasks that have finished,
so we just moved the done sending true done up align,
so that instead of doing it per server,
we now do it per task,
and at the end of the loop, at the end of the function,
we just have to wait for the right number of tasks to be done.
And so, so now again we sort of know why these are going to finish,
there's actually a deadlock still
and that is that if the number of tasks is is too big,
actually I think always,
you'll get a deadlock
and if you run this,
you know you get this nice thing where it tells you like hey your goroutines are stuck.
And the problem is that we have this runTasks server loop,
and the server loop is trying to say hey I'm done
and you're trying to say hey like here's some more work,
so if you have more than one task, you'll run into this deadlock,
where you're trying to send the next task to a server,
I guess it's a few more tasks than servers,
you're trying to send the next task to a server
and all the servers are trying to say hey I'm done with the previous task,
but you're not there to receive from the done channel.
And so again you know it's really nice that the goroutine just hang around
and wait for you to look at them
and we can fix this.
One way to fix this would be to add a separate loop,
that actually does a select that either sends some work or a counts for some of the work being done,
that's fine,
but a cleaner way to do this,
is to take the work sending loop that task sending loop
and put it in its own goroutine,
so now it's running independently of the counting loop
and the counting loop can can run and you know unblocked servers
that are done with certain tasks, while other tasks are still being sent.
But the simplest possible fix for this is
to just make the work channel big enough,
that you're never gonna run out of space.
Because we might decide that you know having a goroutine for task is
you know a couple kilobytes per task,
but you know an extra int in the channel is eight bytes,
so probably you can spend eight bytes per task.
And so if you can, you just make the work channel big enough,
that you know that all the sends on work are going to never block
and you'll always get down to the counting loop at the end pretty quickly.
And so doing that actually sets us up pretty well for the other wrinkle in the lab,
which is that sometimes calls can timeout
and here I've modeled it by the call of returning a false,
so just say it didn't work.
And so you know in runTasks is really easy to say,
like if it's really easy to say like if the call fails, then,
sorry if the call succeeds then you're done,
but if it fails, just put the task back on the work list,
and because it's a queue not a stack,
putting it back on the work list is very likely to hand it to some other server.
And so that will probably succeed,
because it's some other server, and this is all hypothetical,
but it's a really, you know it fits really well into the structure that we've created.
Alright, and the final change is that
because the server goroutines are sending on work,
we do have to wait to close it until we know that they're done sending.
And, because again you can't close before they finish sending.
And so we just have to move the close until after we've counted that all the tasks done
and sometimes we get to this point
and people ask why can't you just kill goroutines
like why not just be able to say look hey kill all the server goroutines at this point,
we know that they're not needed anymore.
And the answer is that the goroutines has state
and it's interacting with the rest of the program,
and if it all of a sudden just stops,
it's sort of like it hung, right
and maybe it was holding a lock,
maybe it was in the middle of some sort of communication with some other goroutines that was kind of expecting an answer.
So we need to find some way to tear them down more gracefully
and that's by telling them explicitly hey you know you're done, you can go away
and then they can clean up however they need to clean up.
You know, speaking of cleaning up,
there's there's actually one more thing we have to do,
which is to shut down the loop that's watching for new servers
and so we do have to put a select in here,
where you know the thing that's waiting for new servers on the server channel,
we have to go tell it, okay we're done just like stop watching new servers,
all the servers are gone.
And we could make this the caller's problem,
but this is actually fairly easy to do.
Alright, so here pattern number three, which is a client for a replicated server of service.
So here's the interface that we want to implement,
we have some service that, we want that is replicated for reliability
and it's okay for a client to talk to any one of these servers
and so the replicated client is given a list of servers,
the arguments to Init is a list of servers
and a function that lets you call one of the servers with a particular argument set and get a reply.
And then being given that during Init,
the replicated client then provides a call method that doesn't tell you what server it's going to use,
it just finds a good server to use
and it keeps the same, keeps using the same server for as long as it can
until it finds out that that server is no good.
So in this situation, there's almost no shared state that you need to
and so like the only state that persists from one call to next is what server did I use last time,
because I'm going to try to use that again.
So in this case that's totally fine for mutex,
I'm just going to leave it there,
it's always okay to use mutex,
if that's the cleanest way to write the code.
You know, some people get the wrong impression from how much we talk about channels,
but it's always okay to use mutex, if that's all you need.
So now we need to implement this replicated call method,
whose job is to try sending to lots of different servers.
But first to try the the original server.
So, so what does it mean if the try fails,
well there's no clear way for it to fail above,
it just always returns a reply
and so the only way it can fail is if it's taking too long,
so we'll assume that if it takes too long, that means it failed.
So in order to deal with timeouts,
we have to run that code in the background in a different goroutine.
So we can do something like this,
where we set a timeout,
we create a timer and then we use goroutine to send in the background
and then at the end, we wait and either we get the timeout or we get the actual reply,
if we get the actual reply, we return it
and if we get the timeout, we have to do something,
we have to figure out what to do.
It's worth pointing out that you have to call t.stop,
because otherwise the timer sits in a timer queue,
that's going to go off in one second
and so you know if this call took a millisecond
and you have this timer that's going to sit there for the next second
and then you do this on a loop
and you get a thousand timers sitting in that that queue
before they start actually you know a disappearing.
And so, this is kind of a work in the API,
but it's been there forever and we've never fixed it
and and so you just have to remember to call stop.
And then now we have to figure out what do we do in the case of the timeout.
And so in the case of the timeout,
we're going to need to try a different server,
so we'll write a loop.
And we'll start at the id, that id zero it says
and you know if a reply comes in, that's great
and otherwise we'll reset the timeout and go around the loop again
and try sending to a different server.
And notice, there's only one done channel in this program
and so on the third iteration of the loop, we might be waiting
and then finally the first server gives us a reply,
that's totally fine, we'll take that reply, that's great.
And so then we'll stop and return it.
And, but if we get all the way through the loop,
it means that we've sent the request to every single server,
in which case there's no more timeouts,
we just have to wait for one of them to come back
and so that's the plain receive and return at the end.
And then it's important to notice that the done channel is buffered now,
so that if you've sent the result to three different servers,
you're going to take the first reply and return,
but the others are going to want to send responses to.
And we don't want those goroutines just sit around forever, trying to send to a channel that we're not reading from,
so we make the buffer big enough that they can send into the buffer and then go away
and the channel just gets garbage collected.
We've got a question in the chat,
that says, why can't the timer, just be garbage collected when nobody's referencing it
instead of having to wait when it goes off
when you said that you have multiple waiting if he goes off in one millisecond.
The problem is that timer is referenced by the runtime,
it's in the list of active timers.
And so calling stop takes it out of the list of active timers.
And and so like that's arguably kind of a work in that,
like in the specific case of a timer,
that's like only gonna ever get used in this channel way
like we could have special case that by having the channel,
because inside the timer is this t.C channel right,
so we could have like a different kind of channel implementation that inside
had a bit that said hey I'm a timer channel right
and and and then like the select on it would like no to just wait,
but if you just let go of it, it would just disappear.
We've kind of thought about doing that for a while, but we never did,
so this is like the state of the world.
But but you know the garbage collector can't distinguish
between the reference inside the runtime and the reference and the rest of the program,
it's all just references,
and so until we special case that channel,
in some way we can't actually get rid of that.
Thank you.
Sure, so, so the only thing we have left is
to have this preference where we try to use the same id that we did the previous time.
And so to do that preference,
we you know had the server id coming back in the reply anyway in the result channel.
And so you know we do the same sort of loop,
but we loop over an offset from the actual id,
we're going to use which is the preferred one
and then we get an answer,
we set the preferred one to where we got the answer from and then we reply
and you'll notice that I used a goto statement,
that's okay if you need to goto it's fine,
it's not sort of there's no [zealotry] here.
Alright, so, the fourth one and then we'll do some questions is protocol multiplexer.
And this is the logic of a core of any RPC system
and this comes up a lot,
I feel like I wrote a lot of these in grad school
and sort of years after that.
And so the basic API of a protocol multiplexer is that
it's in from some service, which we're going to pass to the Init method.
And then having been initialized with the service,
you can call and you can call Call and give a message a request message
and then it'll give you back the reply message at some point
and the things it needs from the service to do multiflexing, is that given a message it has to be able to pull out the tag that uniquely identifies the message
and will identify the reply,
because it will come back in with a matching tag
and then it needs to be able to send a message out and to receive a message,
but they send and receive are arbitrary messages are not matched.
It's the multiplex job to actually match them.
So, to start with, we'll have a goroutine that's in charge of calling send
and another goroutine that's in charge of calling receive,
both in just a simple loop.
And so to initialize the service will set up the structure
and it will kick off the send loop and the receive loop
and then we also have a map of pending requests
and the maps from the tag that we saw the id number in the messages
to a channel where the reply is supposed to go.
The send loop is fairly simple,
you just range over the things that need to be sent and you send them
and this just has the effect of serializing the calls to send,
because we're not going to force the service implementation to deal with us sending you know from multiple goroutines at once,
we're serializing it, so that it can just be thinking of you sending one packet at a time.
And then the receive loop is a little bit more complicated,
it pulls a reply off the service
and again they're serialized or only reading one at a time
and then it pulls the tag out of the reply.
And then it says oh I need to find the channel to send this to,
so it pulls the channel out of the pending map,
it takes it out of the pending map,
so that you know if we accidentally get another one,
we won't try to send it.
And then it sends the reply.
And then to do a call,
you just have to set yourself up in the map,
and then hand it to send and wait for the reply,
so we start off, we get the tag out,
we make our own done channel,
we insert the tag into the map,
after first checking for bugs.
And then, we send the argument message to Send
and then we wait for the reply to come in on done,
it's very very simple,
I mean like I used to write these sort of things in C
and it was it was much much worse.
So that was all the patterns that I wanted to show
and I hope that those end up being useful for you in whatever future program yo're writing
and I hope that they're you know just sort of good ideas, even in non Go programs,
but that you know thinking about them
and Go can help you when you go to do other things as well.
So I'm going to put them all back up.
And then I have some questions that Frans sent, that were from all of you.
And, we'll probably have some time for questions from the chat as well.
I have no idea in zoom where the chat window is,
so when we get to that, people can just speak up,
just I don't use zoom on a daily basis, unfortunately.
So, and and normally I know how to use zoom regularly,
but with with the presentation, it's zooms in this minimized thing, that doesn't have half the things I'm used to.
Anyway, someone asked how long Go took.
And so far it's been about thirteen and a half years,
we started discussions in late september 2007,
I joined full time in august 2008 when I finished at MIT.
We did the initial open-source launch november 2009.
We released Go one the sort of first stable version in October 2011,
sorry the plan was October 2011, Go one itself was march 2012.
And then we've just been on a regular schedule since then,
the next major change of course is going to be generics
and adding generics and that's probably gonna be go one eighteen,
which is going to be next in February.
Someone asks you how big a team does it take to build a language like Go.
And you know for those first two years, there were just five of us
and that was enough to get us to
you know something that we release that actually could run in production.
But it was fairly primitive,
you know it was a good prototype, it was a solid working prototype,
but it wasn't like what it is today
and over time we've expanded a fair amount,
now we're up to something like fifty people employed directly, employed by Google to work directly on Go.
And then there's tons of open source contributors,
I mean there's literal cast of thousands that have helped us over the last thirteen years
and there's absolutely no way we could have done it even with fifty people,
without all the different contributions from the outside.
Someone asked about design priorities and motivations.
And you know we built it for us right,
the priority was to build something that was going to help Google
and it just turned out that Google was a couple years ahead,
we were just in a really lucky spot where Google was a couple years ahead of the rest of the industry,
on having to write distributed systems right now,
everyone using cloud software is writing programs that talk to other programs and sending messages
and you know there's hardly any single machine programs anymore.
And so you know we sort of locked into at some level
you know building the language that we the rest of the world needed a couple years later.
And then the other thing that was really a priority
was making it work for large numbers of programmers
and because Google had a very large number of programmers working in one codebase
and now we have open source
where you know even if you're a small team,
you're depending on code that's written by a ton of other people usually.
And so a lot of the issues that come up with just having many programmers still come up in that context,
so those were really the things we were trying to solve.
And you know for all of these things we took a long time
before we were willing to actually commit to putting something in the language
like everyone basically had to agree in the core original group
and and so that meant that it took us a while to get the pieces exactly the way we wanted them,
but once we got them there, they've actually been very stable and solid and really nice and they work together well.
And the same thing is kind of happening with generics now,
where we actually feel I feel personally really good about generics,
I feel like it feels like the rest of Go,
and that just wasn't the case for the proposals that we had,
you know even a couple years ago,
much less the early ones.
Someone said they really liked defer, which is unique to language,
and I do too, thank you,
but I wanted to point out that we did absolutely you know create defer for Go,
but Swift has adopted it
and I think there's a proposal for C++ to adopt it as well,
so you know hopefully it kind of moves out a little bit.
There was a question about Go is using capitalization for exporting.
And which I know is like something that you know sort of is jarring when you first see it
and the story behind that is that, well we needed something and we knew that we would need something,
but at the beginning, we just said look everything's export everything publicly visible,
we'll deal with it later.
And after about a year, it was clear that we needed some way to you know let programmers hide things from other programmers
and you know C++ has this public colon and private colon
and in a large structure it's actually really annoying that you're looking you're looking at definitions
and you have to scroll backwards and try to find where the most recent public colon or private colon was
and if it's really big, it can be hard to find one
and so it's hard to tell whether a particular definition is public or private.
And then in Java, of course it's at the beginning of every single field
and that seemed kind of excessive too, just too much typing.
And so we looked around some more
and and someone pointed out to us that while python has this convention
where you put an underscore in front to make something hidden
and that seemed interesting,
but you probably don't want the default to be not hidden,
you want the default to be hidden.
And then we thought about well we could put a plus in front of names.
And then someone suggested well what about uppercase could be exported,
and it seemed like a dumb terrible idea, it really did,
but as you think about it,
like I really didn't like this idea,
and I have a very clear memory of sitting in the room
and what I was staring at as we discussed this,
but I had no logical argument against it
and it turned out, it was fantastic,
it was like it seemed bad just like aesthetically,
but it is one of my favorite things now about Go
that when you look at a use of something,
you can see immediately, you get that bit of is this something that other people can access or not at every use,
because if you see code calling a function to do you know whatever it is that it doesn't think,
oh wow can other people do that,
and you know your brain sort of takes care of that,
but now I go to C++ and I see calls like that
and I get really worried about is that is that something other classes can get at
and having that bit actually turns out to be really useful for reading code.
A couple people ask about generics.
If you don't know, we have an active proposal for generics,
we're actively working on implementing it,
we hope that the released later in the year,
towards the end of the year, we'll actually have a full version of generics, you can, you can actually use,
the that'll be a preview release,
the real release that we hope it will be in is Go on eighteen,
which is February of next year,
so maybe next class, we'll actually get to use generics, we'll see.
But I'm certainly looking forward to having a generic min and max,
the reason we don't have those is that,
we have to pick which type they were for
or you have a whole suite of them
and it just seems silly,
it seems like we should wait for generics.
Someone asked, is there any area of programming, where Go may not be the best language, but it's still used.
And and the answer is absolutely,
like that happens all the time with every language.
I think Go is actually really good all-around language,
but you know you might use it for something that's not perfect for,
just because the rest of your program is written in Go,
and you want to inter operate with the rest of the program,
so there's this website called the online encyclopedia of integer sequences,
it's a search engine you type in like two three five seven eleven
and it tells you those are the primes
and it turns out that the backend for that is all written in Go.
And if you type in a sequence,
it doesn't no it actually does some pretty sophisticated math,
on the numbers all with big numbers and things like that
and all of that is written in Go too,
because it was too annoying to shell out to maple and mathematic
and sort of do that cross language thing,
even though you'd much rather implement in those languages,
so you run into those sorts of compromises all the time and that's fine.
Someone asked about, go is supposed to be simple,
so that's why there's no generics and no sets,
but isn't it also for software developers and don't software developers need all this stuff
and it's silly to reconstruct it.
And I think that it's true that there's someone intention,
but but simplicity in the sense of leaving things out was not ever the goal,
so like for sets, it just seemed like maps are so close to sets,
you just have a map where the value is empty or a boolean, that's a set,
and for generics, like you have to remember that when we started going 2007,
Java was like just finishing a true fiasco of a rollout of generics
and so like we were really scared of that,
we knew that if we just tried to do it, you know we would get it wrong
and we knew that we could write a lot of useful programs without generics.
And so that was what we did.
And then we came back to it,
when we felt like okay we've spent enough time writing other programs,
we kind of know a lot more about what we need from from generics for Go
and we can take the time to talk to real experts
and I think that you know it would have been nice to have them five or ten years ago,
but we wouldn't have had the really nice ones that we're going to have now,
so I think it was probably the right decision.
So there was a question about goroutines and the relation to the plan9 thread library,
which was all cooperatively scheduled,
and whether goroutines were ever properly scheduled and if that caused problems.
And it is absolutely the case, that like Go and the goroutine runtime were sort of inspired by previous experience on plan9,
there was actually a different language called Alef on an early version plan9
that was compiled, it had channels, it had select,
it had things we called tasks which were a little bit like goroutines,
but it didn't have a garbage collector and that made things really annoying in a lot of cases,
and also the way that tasks work,
they were tied to a specific thread,
so you might have three tasks in one thread and two tasks in another thread,
and in the three tasks in the first thread,
they only one ever ran at a time
and they could only rescheduled during a channel operation
and so you would write code where those three tasks were all operating on the same data structure,
and you just knew because it was in your head when you wrote it.
That you know it was okay for these two different tasks to be scribbling over the same data structure,
because they could never be running at the same time.
And, meanwhile in the other thread you've got the same situation going on with different data and different tasks
and then you come back to the same program like six months later,
you totally forget which task could write to different pieces of data
and I'm sure that we had tons of races,
I mean it was just it was a nice model for small programs
and it was a terrible model for programming over a long period of time
or having a big program that other people had to work on.
So, so that was never the model for Go,
the model for Go was always it's good to have these lightweight goroutines,
but they're gonna all be running independently
and if they're going to share anything they need to use locks,
then they need to use channels to communicate and coordinate explicitly.
And that that has definitely scaled a lot better than any of the plain line stuff ever did,
you know sometimes people hear that goroutines are cooperatively scheduled
and they they think you know something more like that,
it's it's true that early on, the goroutines were not as preemptively scheduled as you would like,
so in the very very early days,
the only preemption points when you called into the runtime,
shortly after that, the preemption points where any time you entered a function,
but if you were in a tight loop for a very long time,
that would never preempt and that would cause garbage collector delays,
because the garbage collector need to stop all the goroutines
and there be some goroutines stuck in a tight loop
and it would take forever to finish the loop.
And so actually in the last couple releases,
we've finally started we figured out
how to get a unique signals to deliver to threads in just the right way,
so that and we can have the right bookkeeping to actually be able to use that as a preemption mechanism.
And so now things are I think the preemption delays for garbage collection are actually bounded finally,
but from the start, the model has been that you know they're running preemptively
and they don't get control over when they get preempted.
As a sort of following question,
someone else asked where they can look in the source tree to learn more about goroutines and goroutine scheduler.
And the answer is that, this is basically a little operating system,
like it's a little operating system that sits on top of the other operating system,
instead of on top of CPUs.
And so the first thing to do is take 6.828,
which is like I I mean I I worked on 6.828 and xv6
like literally like the year or two before I went and did the Go runtime
and so there's a huge amount of situate in the go runtime.
And in the actual go runtime directory, there's a file called proc.go,
which is you know proc stands process,
because that's what it is in the operating systems
and I would start there that's the file to start with and then sort of pull on strings.
Someone asked about Python, sort of negative indexing,
where you can write x minus one
and that comes up a lot especially from Python programmers
and and it seems like a really great idea you write these really nice elegant programs,
where you want to get the last element, you just say x minus one.
But the real problem is that you have x of i,
and you have a loop that's like counting down from from you know n to zero
and you have an off by one somewhere and now x of minus one
instead of being x of i, when i is minus one,
instead of being an error where you immediately say hey, there's a bug I need to find that,
it just silently grabs the element off the other end of the array
and that's where you know the sort of Python,
you know, simplicity makes things worse
and so that was why we left it out,
because it was going to hide bugs too much, we bought.
You know you could imagine something where you say like x of dollar minus one, len minus one, not line of x, but just len.
But you know it seemed like too much of a special case
and really it doesn't come up enough.
Someone asked about you know what aspect of Go was hardest to implement.
And honestly like a lot of this is not very hard,
we've done most of this before, we've written operating systems
and reading libraries and channel implementations,
and so doing all that again was fairly straightforward,
the hardest thing was probably the garbage collector.
Go is unique among garbage collected languages
and that it gives programmers a lot more control over memory layout,
so if you want to have a structure with two different other structures inside it,
that's just one big chunk of memory,
it's not a struct with pointers to to other chunks of memory.
And because of that, and you can take the address of the second field in struct and pass that around
and that means the garbage collector has to be able to deal with a pointer
that could point into the middle of an allocated object
and that's just something that Java and Lisp and other things just don't do.
And so that makes the garbage collector a lot more complicated in how it maintains its data structures.
And we also knew from the start, that you really want low latency,
because if you're handling network requests,
you can't, you just pause for 200 milliseconds while
and block all of those in progress request to do a garbage collection,
it really needs to be you know low latency and not stop things
and we thought that multi-core would be a good good opportunity there,
because we could have the garbage collector doing one core
and the Go program using the other cores
and that might work really well
and that actually did turn out to work really well,
but it required hiring a real expert in garbage collection
to like figure out how to do it, and make it work,
but now it's really great.
I I have a quick question,
you said like if it's struct,
like it's declared inside another struct,
it actually is a big chunk of memory.
Yeah.
Why, why did you implement it like that,
what's the reason behind that.
Well, so there's a couple reasons,
one is for a garbage collector, it's a service
and the load on the garbage collector is proportional to the number of objects you allocate
and so if you have a structure of five things in it,
you can make that one allocation,
that's a fifth of the load on the garbage collector
and that turns out to be really important.
But the other thing that's really important is cache locality right,
like if you have the processor is pulling in chunks of memory in 64 byte chunks or whatever it is
and it's much better reading memory that's altogether than reading memory that's scattered.
And so you know we have a git server at Google called Gerrit,
that is written in Java,
and it was just starting at the time that Go was just coming out
and we just missed like Gerrit being written and Go I think by a year,
we talked to the guy who had written Gerrit
and he said that one of the biggest problems in Gerrit was like you have only shot one hashes
and just having the idea of twenty bytes.
It is impossible to have in Java,
you can't just have twenty bytes in struct,
you have to have a pointer to an object
and the object like you, you can't even have twenty bytes in the object,
you have to declare five different insert something like that to get twenty bytes
and there's just no good way to do it
and it's just the overhead of just a simple thing like that,
really adds up.
And so you know we thought giving programmers control over memory was really important.
So, another question was was about automatic parallelization,
like for loops and things like that,
we don't do anything like that,
and the standard Go tool chain,
there are go compilers for Go frontend for GCC and llvm
and so to the extent that those do those kind of loop optimization in C,
I think you know we get the same from the Go friends for those,
but it's not the kind of parallelization that we typically need at Google,
it's it's more, you know lots of servers running different things
and and so you know that sort of you know, like the sort of big vector math kind of stuff,
doesn't come up as much,
so it just hasn't been that important to us.
And then the last question I have right now,
is that someone asked about how do you decide when to acquire release locks
and why don't you have re-entered locks.
And for that I want to go back a slide,
let me see, yeah here,
so like during the lecture, I said things like the lock, like new protects the map or it protects the data,
but what we really mean at that point is that we're saying that a lot protects some collection of invariance
that apply to the data that are true of the data
and the reason we have a lock is to protect the operations that depend on the invariance
and that sometimes temporarily invalidate the invariance from each other.
And so when you call lock, what you're saying is I need to make use of the invariance that this lock protects
and when you call unlock what you're saying is I don't need them anymore,
and if I temporarily invalidated them,
I've put them back, so that the next person who calls lock will see correct invariance.
So in the Mux, you know we want the invariant that each registered pending channel gets at most one reply.
And so to do that when we take done out of the map,
we also delete it from the map before we unlock it,
and if there was some separate cancel operation that was directly manipulating the map as well,
it could lock the, it could call lock it could take the thing out call unlock.
And then, if it actually found one it would know,
no one is going to send to that anymore,
because I took it out,
whereas if you know we had written this code to have an extra unlock and relock between the done equals pending of tag and the delete,
then you wouldn't have that protection of the invariance anymore,
because you would have put things back, you've unlocked and relocked,
while the invariance were broken.
And so it's really important to correctness to think about locks is protecting invariance.
And and so if you have reentrant locks,
all that goes out the window,
without the reentrant lock, when you call lock on the next line,
you know, okay, the lock just got acquired all the environments are true,
if you have a reentrant lock,
all you know is well all the variants were true for whoever locked this the first time we might be way up here on my call stack.
And you really know nothing,
and so that makes it a lot harder to reason about what can you assume
and so I think the reentrant locks are really unfortunate part of Java's legacy.
Another big problem with reentrant locks is that
if you have code where you know you call something and it is depending on a reentrant lock
for something where you've acquired the lock up above.
And then, at some point you say you know what,
actually I want to have a timeout on this or I want to do it,
you know in some other goroutine while I wait for something else,
when you move that code to a different goroutine,
reentrant always means locked on the same stack,
that's the only plausible thing it could possibly mean
and so if you move the code that was doing the reentrant lock onto a different stack,
then it's going to deadlock,
because deadlock is now actually going to be a real lock acquire
and it's going to be waiting for you to let Go of the lock,
you're not going to let Go of it,
because you think that code needs to finish running.
So it's actually completely fundamentally incompatible with restructurings where you take code
and run it in different threads or different goroutines.
And so anyway, my advice, there is to just think about locks protecting variants
and then you know just avoid depending on reentrant locks,
it it really just doesn't scale well to real programs.
So I'll put this list back up,
actually we have that up long enough I can try to figure out how to stop presenting.
And then I can take a few more questions.
Anyone has.
I had a question,
I mean I I think coming from Python gets very useful right,
it's very common to use like standard functional operations like map or filter stuff like that,
like, like list comprehension,
and when you know I switched over to Go and started programming,
it's used, I I looked it up and people say you shouldn't do this, do this with Go.
Right.
I was wondering why.
Um, well, I mean one is that you can't do it the other way,
so you might just do the way you can do it,
but a bigger a bigger issue is that.
Well, there's, that one answer.
The other answer is that,
you know if you do it that way,
you actually end up creating a lot of garbage,
and if you care about not putting too much load on the garbage collector,
that kind of is another way to avoid that,
you know, so if you've got a map and then a filter and then another map,
like you can make that one loop over the data instead of three loops over the data,
each of which generate a new piece of garbage.
But you know now that we have generics coming,
you'll actually be able to write those functions,
like you couldn't actually write what the type signature of those functions were before,
and so you literally couldn't write them.
And python gets away with this, because there's no static types.
But now we're actually going to have a way to do that
and I totally expect that once new generics go in there,
will be a package slices and if you import slices,
you can do slices.map and slices.filter and slices.unique or something like that
and I think those will all happen,
and you know if if that's the right thing, then that's great.
Thanks.
Sure.
I have, that one of the hints that you had,
it was about running goroutines that are independent like concurrently,
and some of the examples of the code, I think I could understand,
it seems to me like you can just like call the function in the same thread rather than a different thread.
And I was not sure why you would call it in a different thread.
So, usually it's because you want them to proceed independently,
so so in one of the one of the examples, we had,
like the there was a loop that was sending you know tasks to the work queue,
but there was the servers were running in different goroutines
and reading from the work queue and doing work,
but then when they were done,
they would send a you know hey I'm done now to the done channel,
but ascending Go doesn't complete until the receive actually matches with it.
And so if the thing that's sending on the work queue
is not going to start receiving from the done channel
until it's done sending to all the work queues
are sending all the work in all the tasks in the work queue,
then now you have a deadlock,
because the main thread, the main goroutine is trying to send new work to the servers,
the servers are not taking new work, they're trying to tell the main thread that they're done,
but the main thread not going to actually start at like reading from the done channel
until it finishes giving out all the work
and so there's just staring at each other, waiting for different things to happen,
whereas if we take that loop, that if we just put the little goroutine around the loop that's sending the work,
then that can go somewhere else,
and then it can proceed independently,
and while it's stuck, waiting for the servers to to take more work,
the servers are stuck waiting for the main goroutine to acknowledge that it finished some work
and now the main goroutine actually gets down to the loop,
that pulls it finishes that actually acknowledges that finish the work that reads from the done channel
and so it's just a way to separate out,
you know these are two different things that logically,
they didn't have to happen one after the other
and because they were happening one after the other that caused a deadlock
and by taking one out and moving, it let it run independently
that removes the deadlock.
Thank you so much.
Sure.
Could you talk a little bit about how Go's race detector is implemented?
Sure, it is the llvm race detector,
and so that probably doesn't help,
but it is exactly the thing that llvm calls thread sanitizer. And, and so we actually have a little binary blob that we link against,
because we don't want to depend on all of llvm,
but it's the llvm race detector
and the way the llvm race detector works is that it allocates a ton of extra virtual memory
and then based on the address of of the thing being read or written,
it has this other you know spot in virtual memory
where it records information about like the last thread,
you know it thinks of threads, but they're goroutines,
has where the last thread that did a read or write
and then also every time a synchronizing event happens,
like you know a communication from one goroutine to another,
that counts as establishing it happens before edge between two different goroutines,
and if you ever get something where you have a read or write
and they're not properly sequence right,
like so if you have a read and then it happens before something in another goroutine which then later does the write, that's fine,
but if you have a read to write and there's no happens before sequence that connects them, then that's a race,
and it actually you know has some pretty clever ways to dynamically figure out quickly,
you know, did this read happen, is there happens before path between this read and write as they happen
and it slows down the program by maybe 10x,
but you know if you just divert a small amount of traffic there, that's probably fine,
if its for testing, that's also probably fine,
it's way better than not finding out about the races,
so it's totally worth it.
And honestly ten or twenty x is fantastic,
the original thread sanitize or was more like a hundred a thousand x,
and that was not good enough.
Well, what's the race detector called, llvm?
It's called thread sanitizer, but it's part of llvm,
which is the clang C compiler,
the one that almost everyone uses now,
is part of the llvm project.
Can you talk about slices and the design choices,
having them as views on arrays,
which like confused me at first.
Yeah, it is a little confusing at first.
The main thing is that you want it to be efficient to kind of walk through an array
or like if you can quick sort or merge sort or something where you have an array of things
and now you want to say well now sort this half and sort the other half,
you want to be able to efficiently say like here, this is half of the previous one like you know sort that
and so, in C the way you do that is,
you just pass in you know the pointer to the first element and the number of elements
and that's basically all the slices
and then the other pattern that comes up a lot when you're trying to be efficient with arrays
is you have to grow them
and and so you don't want to recall reallocation every single new element,
you want to amortize that
and so the way you do that in C again is that
you have a base pointer, you have the length that you're using right now
and you have the length that you allocated
and then to add one, you check and see if the length is bigger than the amount you allocate,
if so you reallocate and otherwise you just keep bumping it forward
and and slices are really just an encoding of those idioms,
because those are the most efficient way to manage the memory.
And so in any kind of like C++ vector or something like that,
that's what's going on underneath,
but it makes it a lot harder to like the C++ vector,
because of ownership reasons,
the vector is tied to the actual underlying memory,
it's a lot harder to get like a sub vector,
that's just the view onto the second half for merge sort.
So that's sort of the idea
is that just like there are all these patterns for accessing memory officially that came from C
and we tried to make them fit into Go in an idiomatic way, in a safe way.
Can you talk about how you decided to implement the Go like remote module system,
where you import directly from a url, which is like.
Yeah, I mean I just didn't want to run a service
and like like you know a lot of the things like ruby gems
and those were not as for at the front of my mind at the time,
just because they were newer,
but I had used Perl for a while and like CPAN
and I just thought it was insane
that like everyone was fighting over these short names like db,
you know there probably shouldn't be an argument over who gets to make the db package.
And so putting domain names in the front, seemed like a good way to decentralize it
and it was also a good way for us not to run any server,
because you know we could just say well we'll recognize the hostname
and then Go grab it from source control, from someone else's server,
and that turned out to be a really great idea I think,
because we just don't have that kind of same infrastructure, that other things depend on.
But in the Java world, it's actually really problematic,
there are multiple, there's no sort of standard registry,
but they all use these short names
and so like maven can be configured to build from multiple different registries
and if you're an open-source software package provider,
you actually have to go around and be sure that you upload it to all the different registries,
because if you miss one and it becomes popular,
someone else will upload different code to that one
and then like maven actually just takes whichever one comes back first,
it just sends a request to all of them and whatever comes back first,
so you know if someone wants to make a malicious copy of your package,
always do is find some register other people use that you forgot to upload it to
and like you know they get to win the race sometimes,
so it's a real problem, I think having domain there really helps split up the ownership in a really important way.
Thank you. Sure.
What the, maybe take a quick pause here,
most people that have to go can go,
I'm sure Russ is willing to stick around for a bit longer and answer any questions,
but I do want to thank Russ for giving this lecture,
hopefully this will help you running more good Go programs, these patterns
and so thank you Russ.
You're welcome, it's nice to be here.
And then more questions, feel free to ask questions.
Yeah.
Oh just a little logistical thing,
the slides that are on the 6.824 website are not exactly the same as Russ's slides.
I'll get Franz a new PDF.
A more general question about when is writing a new language, the like the best solution to a problem.
That's a great question, it's almost never the best solution.
But you know at the time we had just an enormous number of programmers
like thousands of programmers working in one codebase
and the compilations were just taking forever,
because C++ was just not meant for efficient incremental compilation.
And so it, and furthermore at the time like threading libraries were really awful
like people just didn't use threads,
I remember like one of the first days I was at MIT and talking to Robert
and Robert said to me, like in 2001 he said to me,
like we don't use threads here, because threads are slow.
And and that was like totally normal,
that was just the way the world at the time.
And at Google we're having a lot of trouble,
because it was all event based little callbacks and C++
and there were these multi-core machines and we actually didn't know how to get things to work on them,
because like Linux threads were not something you could rely on to work
and so we ended up like if you had a four core machine,
you just run four different process in completely independent processes of the web server
and just treat it as like four machines,
and that was clearly not very efficient,
so there were a lot of good reasons to try something.
But you know it's a huge amount of work to get to the point where Go is today
and I think that, so much is not the language right,
there were important things that we made in the language that enabled other considerations,
but so much of the successful languages,
the ecosystem that built up around it and the tooling that we built in the Go command,
and like all these like not the language things.
So, you know primary language a people who are focused on the language itself,
I think sometimes get distracted by all the stuff around,
like they miss all the stuff around it.
Oh, can I ask a lot from that.
Yeah.
I was wondering how I was working on Go different now,
since it's more mature than it was before.
Oh, that's a great question,
you know in the early days, it was so easy to make changes
and now it's really hard to make changes,
I think that's the number one thing.
You know, in the early days, like everything was in one source code repository,
literally all the Go code in the world was one source code repository,
and so there were days where we changed the syntax,
used to have a star before chan everytime you set a channel,
because it was a pointer underneath,
and it was all kind of exposed,
so you'd always say star chan int instead of chan int
and similarly for maps
and at some point we realize like this is dumb,
like you have to say the star, let's just take it out
and so like we made the change to the compiler
and I opened up literally like the couple hundred Go source files in the world in my editor
and like the entire team stood behind me
and I typed some regular expressions and we looked at the effect on the files,
yep, that looks right, save it, you know compile it, we're done
and like today you know we can't make backwards incompatible changes at all.
And even making new changes like it.
It affects a lot of people
and so, you know you sort of propose something
and you know put all this won't work for me
and you try to adjust that maybe.
It's a lot harder we estimate there's at least a million, maybe two million Go programmers in the world
and is very different from when they were four or five.
Not sure if this is a valid question,
but what languages Go written, is written in Go also or no.
Now it is, now it is, the original compiler runtime write written in C,
but a few years ago we went through a big,
we actually wrote a program to translate C to Go,
and it only worked for our C code, but still was good enough.
So that we wouldn't lose all the encoded knowledge in that code,
about why things were the way they were and how things work,
so we've got to start from scratch,
but now it's all written in Go and a little bit of assembly.
And that means that people can,
you know people who know Go can help on the Go project,
whereas before like if you wanted to work on the compiler or the runtime,
you had to know C really well
and like we weren't getting a lot of people know C really well,
there's not actually that many of them proportionately,
and furthermore like our entire user bases Go programmers, not C programmers,
so moving to Go was a really big deal.
I was wondering how do you prioritize what features to add to the language at this point,
I know genetics like we're asking for that,
like did you all know like how you choose what to work on.
I mean we've considered language mostly frozen for a while
and so we haven't been adding much,
there was a long period, we said we weren't adding anything
and then we added a little bit of things in the last couple years
to lead up to generics just kind of shake the Rust off,
like all the what breaks when you change something in the language,
so you can put underscores between digits and long numbers now
and things like that.
But you know generics has clearly been the next thing that needed to happen
and we just have to figure out how.
In general, we try to only add things that don't have weird kind of interference with other features
and we try to add things that are really important that will help a lot of people for the kinds of programs,
that we're trying to target with Go,
which is like distributed systems and that sort of thing.
Cool, thank you.
Oh, I had a question actually,
so, for I noticed that like you know Go doesn't have like basic functions like min or max for like,
yeah, so is that like something that you're considering like say adding with the generic stuff,
maybe is that why you didn't.
Exactly right, because you can't have a min, you have min_int [],
but those have different names and that was kind of annoying.
So now we can write just a generic name,
over any type that has a less than operator.
Yeah.
That'll be good.
And you know honestly like for the specific case of min and max.
It's not that hard to code, I know.
I was gonna say, I'm starting to feel like we should just make them buildings,
like you know print and things like that,
so that you can just always have them,
but even if we don't,
you'll be math.min and that'll be there at least.
Yeah.
We really didn't want to make them buildings until we could express their types
and we couldn't do that until generics happened.
Because there is actually a min for floating points actually.
Yeah, I know it's kind of weird,
because the math library is basically copied from the C math.h, set of things.
Yeah.
That's a good point,
we can't actually put them in math,
because they're already there.
Okay. But.
Yeah.
We'll figure it out,
like I think we should probably just put them in the language,
but we have to get generics through first.
And another thing,
actually I noticed that you did USACO like competitive programming,
I did it too, actually.
Cool.
Yeah, so how did you, so actually I included this in one of the questions that I submitted,
let me pull it up,
so my question was like,
how did how was like how did you, go from doing competitive programming
to like doing what you you're doing now at Google working on Go
and how is the transition between like competitive programming to systems,
also finally what made you decide to go into system,
so how did it relate to programming code.
I mean competitive programming at the time that I did,
it was not as all consuming as I gather it is now,
like, like you know you could just like be able to implement a simple dynamic programming
like little two for loops, and that was fine
and now you have to go with complex algorithms and all that stuff that I can't do,
so at some point like somehow like it was different.
But you know I was actually more interested in the sort of systems you kind of start from the start
and the program contests were just something fun to do on the side.
Oh.
It wasn't a huge transition there,
I was never into implementing complex algorithms
and max flow and all those sorts of things.
On the other hand, like when you start a new language,
you actually do get to write a lot of core things right,
like someone has to write the sort function,
and it has to be a good general sort function,
like I spent a while last month, like looking into [dip] algorithms
and that's like matches that background pretty well,
so it does come up.
But you know it's just it's just a different kind of program.
Oh so, you thought of it as more of a side thing, back then, no.
Yeah, it was definitely not the sort of main thing I did when I was writing programs.
Yeah, because like today it's effectively like the main thing.
I know, if if you don't do it full time, like there's just no way you can.
Okay, they just want that many people who cared in 1995.
Well, yeah twenty years later.
I'm gonna ask a related question to that,
so how do you decide to go from like academic work into,
I mean your work is still a little bit more different than like the usual like software anything, but still.
Yeah, you know I got lucky,
I I grew up near Bell Labs in new Jersey
and so that was how I ended up working on plan a little bit in high school and college.
And so you know I I sort of knew I was going to go to grad school
and you know the plan was to go back to Bell Labs,
but it kind of imploded, while I was in grad school,
with the dot-com bubble, and the dot-com crash
and and so like you know Google was was sort of just vacuuming up PhDs, systems PhD at the time,
and and and doing really interesting things,
I mean you probably there's,
I don't know I haven't looked at syllabus for this year,
but you know there's things like spanner and bigtable and chubby and and things like that
and you know they they had a whole host of good distributed systems kind of stuff going on.
And so it was sort of lucky to be able to go to that, too.
And you know at the time I graduated,
I was also looking at you know industrial research labs,
like Microsoft research and places like that,
so you know there's definitely an opportunity there for researching things,
but not in academia, if that's what you want.
It's a little harder to find, now,
I mean most of the places I have like Microsoft research imploded too, a couple years later.
But, you know it's, it's still an option
and and you know just a slightly different path,
you end up,
the differences I see from academia is like you end up caring a ton more about actually making things work a hundred percent time
and supporting them for a decade or more
where as you finish your paper and you kind of get to put it off to the side
and that's really nice actually at some level.
It's, it's definitely strange to me to be you know editing source files that I wrote,
you know in some cases actually twenty years ago,
because I used a bunch of code that I've already written when we start to go.
And it's very weird to think that I've been keeping this program running for twenty years.
Think you.